Living a life that is not as hard, nor should... not a very difficult life.
Tua-llu?
Maa-i-rpak elitnautuukut, elitnaurvigluteng-llu.
Elitnauriyaraq tang cimilria, ayuqenrilria.
Elitnauqerraallemni tayima Kass’atun qanerciigatellruunga.
Tau͡gken Kass’acetun qanerciigalnge’rma qanrucimalallruunga
Elitnaurviim-gguq nunautiini wall’u avatiini uitakuma Kass’aturrlainaq qalareskilii.
Tamana tuaten ayuqenrirtuq.
Maa-i village-aanun ayagaaqamta
School-ani-llu piaqama waten murilkurnaurtua elitnauristet elitnauriaqluteng tayima something called "bilingual education."
Taringumatacimtun-llu tayima tuaten elitnaurvigni tamakunek elitnauritulini pitangqerraqan Yugtun-llu qaneryaramek tayima elitnauritulliniut.
Cumikarnaqsaaqvaa-llu tuaten pilliniata.
What about the schools today?
So much have changed since I first stepped into a classroom.
At one point, although some of us are not able to speak English
We were actually prohibited in some instances from speaking our language.
Yet, we didn’t know how to speak English.
Like I stated, so much have changed since that time.
Today, throughout my travels throughout the region, I’ve seen something called "bilingual education."
It’s my understanding that in these instances, that Yup’ik is taught
And that Yup’ik, in some instances, is actually encouraged to be spoken on school grounds under those circumstances.
This is very encouraging because one of the basis of our society is our language.
Tua-llu?
Umyuangcaqaqernaurtukut.
Ca pininrua piniqapiggluni?
Atam.
Aperyarat, wall’u qaneryaraq. Waten wangkuta qaneryaraput piniqapigtuq.
Elitnauristeḿa iliit angutngurtellruuq.
Waten-llu qanruartelallruanga:
"Kitaki, camek ilavet aperyaranek aturluni qalaruskaten niicugniurqina."
One of the strongest sources of force known to mankind is words.
This source of force is known to all the societies, although they may not be able to communicate with each other.
Yet, it’s the very words, that is one of the strongest sources of force in the universe.
Primarily because of the fact, when you say something using words
What you have stated forever escapes through your mouth to the people.
That’s why I think one must be very careful in their use of words
Because at some point, what you stated using words at some point may come back and haunt you.
Tuamta-llu
Wangkuta ayagyualriani arcaqerluta makut ciuliaput iliini takaqeksaitaput.
Takarnaqsaaqut. Takarnaqeqapigcaaqut.
Yuuyaram-wa qaillun-llu yuullerkaa, yuukumta pillerkamteńek qanrutetuyaaqaitkut.
Atam.
Camek qanrutetuitkut ikayuryugyaaqngamegtekut cakviussiyaagluta yuusqumanrilamegtekut.
Qanellrit-llu tayima takarnaqeqapiggluteng.
Ciumuassiyaagluta piksailkumta, iliini-llu umyuaqeqa’aqluki alerquuteput yuukumta cakviussiyaagngaicugnarqukut.
What about respect?
We must respect our elders.
They alone are the people who can speak about life based on experiences of life.
When they’re speaking about life based on experience of life, you cannot be any stronger.
If we respect and listen to what they have to say
And perhaps remember a very little portion of what they have to say to us
We might find that living this life will be a little bit easier to cope with.
Remember, when they are giving us an advice
That advice is based on the very basis of their experience, and they want to share that with us.
We should be thankful for what they have to tell us.
Tayima waten alerquagaqamegtekut ukut ciuliamta
Alerqualaraakut ikuuyuryuumiamegtekut.
Alerquagaqamegtekut alerqualaraitkut yuullerteng tangerrluku, allat-llu yuullrat tangerrluku ikayuryugyaaqngamegtekut.
Tua-llu?
Ava-i au͡gkut qanellrenka amllenricaaqut, tau͡gaam wangkutnun ayagyuanrulrianun ataurtut.
Wangkuta-wa ayagyualriani, ayagyuarturalrianun ataut.
Tua-llu?
Ciuliarurtellriit-mi wall’u taqnerurtellriit?
Cauga caliarkaat wall’u ikayuutekaat?
Umyuartequrallemni ellaita-llu ikayuryugngaitkut.
Tayima qanruqu’urqatkut assirciquq.
Qaillun yuuyaramta ayagturallerkaa pitekluku qalaruskatkut assiryartuq.
Tua-llu?
Qanqainarcetevkenaki camek qanrutaqatkut quyavikaqluki pikumteki assirciquq.
Maa-i alerquutait eliqu’rqumteki piyuumiutait-llu assiryaryugnarquq.
Thus far, I have been talking about the responsibilities of those of us who are young, maybe relatively young
And lastly, maybe for those of us who are young in mind, heart, and soul.
What about the elderly, or the elders?
What is their responsibility? Or, better yet, do they have any responsibility?
Yes, in my very humble opinion, they also have some responsibility to us.
They must speak out as a group about our cultural values
Before what is left of our values is gone.
I believe, again very humbly, that it is the responsibility of our elders
To teach us what we must do to continue with our values.
But again, it is the responsibility of those of us who are young, relatively young, and young in mind
To hear and listen what they have to share with us.
I think when they’re talking about values, Yup’ik values
They’re talking about something that sometimes is hard to grab.
Yupiit piciryaraitnek yuut qalartaqata iliini taringesciigatnarqeńgalngurnek qalartelartut, tau͡gken tuancaaqluteng.
Ayagyuanrullemni imumi avani apa’urluma pissuryaramek elitnaullruanga.
Qaillun angutem yuullerkaanek elitnautullruanga.
Ayuqucirtuutai ilii tayima aturluku piaqama cakviussiyaaksaitua.
Maurluma-llu
Tayima qanrucimalartua, maurluma-gguq arnam qaillun yuullerkaanek neviarcaq qalarut’lallrua.
When I was a young man, one of the things that my grandfather taught me was how to go after game.
I was quite fortunate in that I had that privilege, I had the opportunity to be taught those skills.
Whenever I have an opportunity, I try to share that, share what was taught to me.
But sometimes I don’t. That’s my fault
Although I was raised by my parents, I spent a lot of my time with my grandfather.
In looking back, I understand
That my grandmother used to teach values that should be respected and gained by the young ladies on how to be a lady.
Tayima ciuliamta qaillun yuuyaramek qalarutaqa’tkut wall’u elitnauraqatekut
Quyavikaqluki pikumta assirciquq.
Atauciq, atauciumek ciuliamta qanrutetuitkut, tamalkumta-llu nalluvkenaki.
Yup’ut Yupiit qaneryaramek waten ayuqellriamek qanlartut:
Yuk-gguq unguvaqallermini taktaciatun eliqurciquq.
Piciuguq.
Qaillun-llu wangkuta yuuyararput, Yupiit-llu piciryarait, Yupiit-llu piyuumiutait piyukumteki
Wangkutnek eliskumta ciuliamteńek wall’u Yuullgutemteńek assirciquq.
What was taught to us by our elders is something that we should be sharing with others.
They taught us values of life, hoping that we’re going to be learning something in life.
I think in turn, we must, we should and must teach the children what was taught to us by our elders.
There is a saying within the Yup’ik society that goes something like this:
"A person will not stop learning as long as they can breathe."
This is very true, because as I travel throughout the region, I’ve been adviced, or given advice by our elders
And I’ve learned on a daily basis what our way of life is.
I think if we are to continue with Yup’ik values
We must seek to learn all that we can from our elders, from others
As long as the Creator is generous enough to allow us to continue to breathe.
Ava-i au͡gkut qanrutkurallrenka amllenricaaqut.
Tau͡gaam piyunartacirramtun qalarqu’rtua
Cikiutellemnek-wa ciuliamteggun.
Qaillun-wa Yupiit piciryarait piugurluteng piarkaukata
Tayima ciuliamteńek eliskumta, tua-i-llu elitelput waten ilamteńun qalarutkaqluki.
Tuamta-llu ayagyualrianun qalarutkaqluki pikumteki assirciqsugnarquq.
In closing, I would like to say that what I had to say was not very much, however, I did the best that I could under the circumstances.
What I shared with you this morning was what was shared with me, or, what I had learned from our elders.
I would like to take this opportunity to thank the Kuskokwim Community College
For giving me an opportunity to share what little knowledge I have gained from our elders, from others
Over the last several, over the last couple decades.
Nangnermek-llu ukut Kuskokwim Community College-aat quyaviksuganka
Waten ilagarluci au͡gkunek-wa tua-i capeqluki
Caliaqesqellra caperqengramku tayima qalarutkuraranka.
Tau͡gaam cali waten elitellemteńun kinguliamteńun au͡gkunun ayagarkat pitekluki quyavikanka.
At this point, I would, I’ll turn the show back to...
[?] pilii.
Ii-i.
Taqsukluten-wa.
Ii-i, taqua.