Yaa, ciumek quyaviksugaaci taillerpeceńek.
Cali-llu at’minek, atranek apertuulluku.
Fred Ollie-ruuq una wani. Maani wani elitnaurvigmi atanruuq.
Arcaqakluki ukut wani taqneret, imkut-llu ayagyuat Yugtun qantulit
Taukut, taukunun-wa tunumalun’ pillruuq.
Tua-i-llu-gguq waniw’ tuacetun piyugyaaqluni man’a...
...rurtellriani arcaqakluci piyugyaaqluni piuq.
Twelve years ago, I came to Alaska and went to the village of St. Mary’s to begin teaching.
And needless to say, I didn’t know much about Alaska.
I didn’t know much about Western Alaska.
And I met, one of the first people I met was a nun, was a Catholic nun by the name of Sister Scholastica.
And some of you in this room know Sister Scholastica.
She’s still doing the laundry at St. Mary’s.
And she gave me the best advice that anyone ever gave me.
She said, "You’re new to Alaska. You don’t know anything about these people.
"So what I want you to do is to say very little and to listen, because there’s a lot you need to learn."
And it was very, very good advice, because even now, twelve years later, I still find that I do too much talking and not enough listening
Because there’s still a lot that the elders of this area can teach us.
Nun-at im’ canek pilaqait?
Manassenkaamek-gguq tuani nallunrilkengangellruuq aterluni Sister Scholastica.
When I was at St. Mary’s, I met students from all over, all over the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta in the coast.
And in 1974, I had a class of students who I was particulary fond of.
And those are these students here.
And I promised them when I left St. Mary’s
That no matter where I went, I would always keep a picture of that class in my office, and I always have.
I lived in Juneau for a while, and I kept a picture of these students on my wall in Juneau. And now here in Bethel, I keep them on my wall.
And one of the reasons I do that, is because I look at these various individuals and I still keep in contact with them.
And it makes me realize how much things have changed in this area
Because I can see the change in these students as they grow up.
Cali maavet tekicimi, calivimini-gguq maani qelkurluku.
Waniwa una wani atularaa, tua-i-wa tangvalaamiki cat cimilriit.
Tangerrsugngaluki imumicetun ayuqenrilameng...
Pass this around. Some people want to see it.
When I look at the pictures of those students, and I think about what they’re doing now
One thought comes to mind...
...being happy, living at home, or living somewhere else, but happy with themselves.
Students who feel good about who they are are the students who did exactly what I think this conference is all about.
They’re the students who took time...
...people in their villages, and I really mean that.
When I look back, and I see the students again who are happy and successful...
...to learn from people who have lived a long time and have had many rich and wonderful experiences.
Tua-i-ll’...
I want to conclude by again welcoming you to this week.
I want to thank you for taking the time to be with us.
I’m very excited about it because this week, I get to be a student too.
I’m going to try to sit in on as many of the talks as possible so I can learn just along with everyone else.
So once again, I want to thank you for coming to Bethel, for sharing your experiences with us.
And if there’s anything I can do to make your stay happier and more enjoyable, please let me know.
Quyanaqvaa.
Uumi icivaq uum Nastashia-m qayagaullranga una qalrutkesqelluku
Qaillun-wa tua-i man’a yuuyaraq wall’u wangkuta piciryaraput ayagturallerkaa pitekluku qalarutesqelluci pillranga
Caperrsullruunga.
Cumigteng’e’rma capperrsullruunga.
Umyuarteqlua-wa waten:
Wii ayagyuanruama una makunun ciuliamteńun aulukekaku assinrunayukluku umyuarteqellruunga.
Tau͡gaam tayima piyunartacirramtun una caliaqeciqaqa
Tau͡gaam cali ak’anun pivkenii.
Tayima icivaq nallunrituci elpeci ilaci tayima pikani Kassiglurmi quyurtellruut
Ciuliaput-wa maani Kusquqvagmi Kuigpagmi-llu.
Tuantellrunritua. Pitsaqevkenii-wa tua-i tuantellrunritua.
Tuancuumillruyaaqua tau͡gaam tayima iliini caliarkat umyuaq aturluku piksailata tuantellrunritua.
Qanrucimallruunga tau͡gaam tuani quyurtellerpeceńi
Qaillun-wa tua-i mat’um yuucimta ayuqucia, ayuqucianek tua-i-w’ taun’ caliaqellrulliniarci.
For the benefit of those of you who have some limited understanding of the English language, let me paraphrase the main points.
Very recently, when Nastashia Martin called me to speak on the issue of how you could continue with the Yup’ik language
I’m sorry, Yup’ik values
Although I was enthusiastic about it, I also had some reservations
Primarily because of the fact that I feel that it’s an issue that can best be addressed by our elders.
I am young, and because I am young, I feel that I have a lot to learn.
But I’m going to try my best under the circumstances.
Very recently, there was a conference at Kassigluq where the elders of the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta were the prime people who attended the conference.
Although I did not have the privilege of attending this conference
I understand that the main focus of the conference dealt with the issue of preserving our way of life.
I would like to have been there, however, circumstances sometimes relating with job prevents that.
Tua-llu ava-i qanqallruunga una qalrutkarkaqa
Elluatuunruluku makunun taqnemteńun auluknayukluku pillruyaaqua.
Ukut-wa tegganemta tayima ayuqucirtualaraakut
CIunerkaput-llu nasvagaqluku.
Nallunrilameng-wa qaillun ciunerkaput ayuqucia yuullruameng.
Atam yuvriqaqernaurput.
Kass’atun elitnaurpailemta ukut ciuliamta tangellruat.
Tayima nallunaituq waten Kass’atun piurangllerkarput.
Tayima, tayima ilavci nallrunritaa, nallunritliarci-wa imna Qinarmiulleq Pavila.
Apa’urluqa.
Taum qanrut’lallruanga waten:
Ayagyuallermini-gguq pektaqami ikamrakun iliini pitsaqa’artevkenani Kass’agnek malrugnek tanglartuq.
Tua-llu pivakarluni pianga
Tau͡gken maa-i iliini nunami-llu ataucimi malruunaurtuk Kass’ak.
Maa-i taum date-aa tayim’ late 1950’s.
Waten qanqallruuq: "Amlleriinartut alungutiit.
"Qaneryarait-llu eliskuvki maa-i assinruciqsugnarquq."
Umyuartutacia, Kass’atun tau͡gken qanyuunani.
Ciuliamta umyuartutacia, umyuartutaciteng-llu tuaggun apa’urlumkun pugellruuq.
Taum nalliini camek qalarucia taringumallrunritaqa, camek-llu picia.
Tau͡gken maa-i caliurangllemkun murilkurangua qanellra picia piciupiallinilria.
I somehow feel that the main speaker this morning on this subject, how you could continue with Yup’ik values, should be one of the elders
Because in my opinion, they are the real people who should be giving us this guidance on the issue.
It is them who have given us guidance so that what is left of our values can be preserved.
It is them who had the wisdom to push for a Western type of education
So that we could be able to at least see and hopefully understand what is happening today.
For example, my grandfather Pavila who is from Qinaq was telling me that in his youth, when he was traveling throughout the region with a sled
That sometimes, he saw more than one white man in the whole region.
He said, however, in the late 1950’s, he said there are more and more of them in the region.
And sometimes, there are even more than one white person in a village.
He said at the time that you should learn their tongue, you should learn their language
So that you could at least understand what is it that you want.
It was through him that the wisdom of our elders was brought forth.
He saw much in advance, what was going to happen today.
I’m very thankful that through his wisdom that they pushed us for education.
Tua-llu.
Caliarkamnun piqaqernaurtukut.
Qaillun ayagturallerkaa Yupiit piciryarait.
Nallunrituci maa-i-rpak wani Calista Corporation-aami nunaliurteńguunga
Nuna-llu qaillun auluklerkaa caliaqaqluku.
Nunam auluklerkaa aulukqainaqumteggu cakviurnarqenricaaquq
Tau͡gaam cakviurnarilartuq wangkuta piciryaraput-llu Kass’at-llu piciryarait atauciurtengnaqluki aulukaqamteggu.
Ciuliaput, wangkuta-llu, kinguliaput-llu kingunengqertut nunamek.
Ciuliamta man’a nuna atulallruat.
Atam ellamun an’aqamta wall’u maa-i aneryaarturalartut aipamta apqiitnek air.
Tua-i-ll’ tamatutailkan epciqukut.
Man’a nuna yumta atutua yuutekluku, yuutekqapiarluki.
Nunamek pitarkanek pissutuukut, estuulumun-llu pitaput elliaqluki ner’aqluki.
Tuamta-llu pissuraqamta pitamta iliini amiit tayima atutullruaput aturaurrluki, piluguurrluki, wall’u pilugullraurrluki.
Tamakunek qanqertua waten umyuarteqlua: nuna man’a unguvatkarput.
Tuamta-llu imarpiim, imarpiim cain unguvacetuakut.
Tayima mat’um nunam camek cikiraqakut piliaqesteput aturluku quyalalta
Ellmikutuaraurtellriatun-llu piaqluta.
Unakek’ngaput-llu tayima ilaput ikayuraqluki pikumteki assiryaryugnarquq.
As most of you may know, one of my major responsibilities with Calista Corporation is to run and manage Land and Natural Resources Department.
Land management in and of itself is not difficult.
But if one were to look at land management strictly from standpoint of Western land management
However, it gets difficult when one begins to look at land from standpoint of Yup’ik values and trying to put Western values into it.
The very basis of our society is land, the Yup’ik society.
Our ancestors looked at land much the same way that we look at air we breathe today.
We need air to breathe so that we may survive.
In the beginning, and even today, the Yup’ik people has always been land users.
We survived with the land and what the land provided us.
Land provided us with clothing.
We needed to dress ourselves so that we can protect, we can be protected from any kind of weather.
Sea also provided us with clothing and food.
My point here being: land is something our society has needed and will probably need for long time to come to survive.
What it has provided us, we must receive thankfully, humbly, and we must share that wealth with others.
Tua-llu.
Qaillun-mi man’a yuuyararput, yuuyaramta-llu piciryaraa ayagturciqa?
Qanrucimalartukut, "Kitaki cumiggluten elitnaura."
Tua-ll’ tuaten ellimeruqaamta wall’u qanrucimaaqamta, "Cumiggluten elitnaura," caularta?
Tuamta-llu kia elitnaurciqakut?
Kitaki wangkutnek ap’arteqernaurtukut, "Kia elitnaurciqakut?"
Atam takuyaqaqerci, caniqlici-llu tangerrluki, wall’u kiarteqaqerci maani.
Elitnauristekaput aqumgaurtut waniwa.
Ellaita-wa yuullruameng qaillun yuuyaramek ellaita qanruskakut, ciuliamta makut
Maligeskumteki tayima cam iliini cakviussiyaaksaunata yuuciqsugnarqukut.
Kitaki.
Ciuliamta camek qanruartaqatkut
Quyanarqelartuq-llu ayuqucirtuagaqatkut
Niicugnilalta.
Niicugniqainarpek’nata-llu qanellrita iliit maliga’rtaqluta pikumta cakviussiyaagluta pingaicugnarqukut.
Just who is to be our teacher?