Maa-i mikelnguut waniw' naanguarturalalriit.
Now, you know how children play with toys.
Ak'allani iciw' inugualallrulriit yaaruilallrulriit maa-i tangerrnailngurmek.
You know in old times, they would play with small dolls, and tell storyknife stories that we don’t see now.
Naliat umyuarteqsit anglananrungacetua:
Which do you think is more fun:
Maa-i mikelnguut yaaruiyuilnguut, inuguayuilnguut, wall'u-qaa inuguatellret wall' yaaruitellret?
The children who do not tell storyknife stories or play with dolls, or the ones who played with dolls and storyknives?
Makut-wa mikelnguut Kass'artarnek naanguarameng naangualaameng
Because these children play with Western toys
Tiiviinek tuaten tangvagluteng ak'a naanguangqelput pinrirluki.
They’ve started watching TV, and stopped playing with the toys that we had back then.
Ak'a atam wangkuta nasaurluullemteńi yaaruiyunqellruukut.
You see, back when we were girls, we liked to tell storyknife stories.
Tua-i yaaruin-llu tegumiaqluku kesianek.
We always had a storyknife with us.
Cakuciullruat yaaruit?
What were the storyknives made of?
Yaaruitengqelallruunga wii tulurrarmek tulurmek.
I had a storyknive made of a little ivory, ivory.
Ivory, kia-ll' tayim piliaqellruagu. Tua-i yaaruilrianga taqsuunii.
Ivory, and I’m not sure who made it. I would never stop telling storyknife stories.
Friend-angqelaamta-llu friend-aput-llu elitnaunritaqamta tua-i yaaruiq tau͡gaam.
Since we had friends, when our friends and we weren’t in school, there was only storyknife stories.
Yaaruinaurtukut, yaaruiyarapuk-llu wangkuk friend-aqa-llu aterluteng taukut nunat. Aterluteng Pingkuunguarluteng
We would tell storyknife stories, and my friend’s and my way of telling stories, those villages had names. We preteneded they were Inlanders.
Tamakut ilait qalartelalci Pingkuunguurluci?
Some of the ones you talked about were the Inlanders?
Cakucimek qalartelallruceci, qanemcilallruceci?
What kinds of things would you tell stories about?
Family-unguartelluki. Ukut-gguq
We made them a family. We said that this village
Aiparnatukat tua-i acirnaurai Pingkuunguartelluki.
She would call the partners Inlanders.
Ukut-wa-gguq Nunapigngiaraankut ukut-wa Ceñaqviuksuunkut yaaqlikacagaugurarcetaqlukek.
These was Nunapigngiar and family, and this was Ceńaqviuksuk and family were always the furthest over there.
Nunapigngiaraankut tua-i acirluki tamakut yuut.
She named those people Nunapigngiar and family.
Family-linguaraqluta-ll' eneliliuki tua-i.
We made up families and made them houses.
Pinqurraungnaqluteng? Assinqurraungnaqluteng?
Did they try to be the greatest? Did they try to be the best?
Cangqerruartelluki tua-i wangkucicetun wangkuta tangvallemcetun. Pilallratun pinguarcequ'urluku
She gave them little things like us that we’ve seen. She would have them do as she did.
Yaaruinritaqamta-llu atakumi airrarluta imkunek string.
And when we didn’t tell storyknife stories, we would play string games with string.
Tau͡gaam inerquraqluta ak'anun airraasqevkenata egacuayagmun iterciqniluta.
But they would admonish us against playing string games for long, saying that a legendary little person would come in on us.
Camun airralriamun. Tua-i ak'anun pivkenata airrarraarluta taq'aqluta.
[It would come in] to those playing string games. We wouldn’t play string games for long, then quit.
Ciin-kiq?
I wonder why?
I dunno. Kiagmi-llu, kiagmi-ll' inuguaraqluta
I don’t know. And in the summer, we would play with small dolls.
Inuguangqerrluta, almost every girl.
We had small dolls, almost every girl.
Inuguangqerraqluteng amllernek inuguanek. Family-cuaraugaqluteng ukut.
They would have a lot of small dolls. This would make up a small family.
Makut-wa cali irniaruat, tamakunek naanguangqelallruukut.
And these dolls, we had those toys too.
Canek cali naanguartangqelallruat?
What other toys were there?
Inuguanek pingqelallrulriakut wangkuta.
We had small dolls.
Irniaruanek-llu tua-i tau͡gaam uksu’rqan qemagtaqluki irniaruat.
And dolls, but when winter set, we would store away the dolls.
Tau͡gaam inuguatuluta enemi irniaruayuunata tau͡gaam anluta ellami.
We only played with small dolls in the house, not dolls, but we went outside [to play with the dolls].
Nutaan tau͡gaam up'nerkami yaqulget tekitaqata nutaan irniaruaryaurtaqluta.
Only when the birds came in the spring would we then start playing with dolls.
Ciin-gguq anucuunaki? Qaill' qanlallruat?
Why wouldn’t you bring them out? What would they say?
Irniaruat, irniaruat tamakut anucuunaki.
We wouldn’t bring those dolls out.
Anuskumteki-gguq' ella-gguq imkuciquq
They said that if we bring them out, the weather will, you know
Kiagciiganani, pircirturluni, allauguurciqniluki. Irniaruat anucuunaki.
Summer would set late, constant blizzards, they said it would be strange. We wouldn’t bring dolls out.
Kenirualallruuci?
Would you pretend to cook?
Calarta?
Do what?
Keniruaq.
Pretend to cook.
Naanguatullruukut, ellami-llu naanguarturatullruukut eneliluta canegnek.
We always played, and we played outside making houses out of grass.
Elagyaliluta tupigluki. Naanguaraqluta irniaruaqluki cat aanakegnguarluki.
We wove grass into caches. We would play, pretending to have children and mothers.
Keniruarluta cat tua-i canguarturluta.
We pretended to cook, pretended to do things.
Uluangqenguaraqluci?
Would you pretend to have women’s knives?
Ii-i.
Yes.
Canek? Canek uluangqaqluci cakucinek?
Out of what? What kinds of women’s knives would you have?
Canek uluangqelallruceta tayima?
What kinds of women’s knives did we have?
Aturalinguaraqluki-ll' quagcinek.
We would also make clothes for them out of sourdock.
Canegnek imkurluki. Anglanitullruukut naanguaraqamta wangkuta.
We used grass for them. We would have fun when we played.
Tamaa-i-llu angliringengllemni inuguarnanringlua yaaruissiyaayuirullua-ll'.
And back when I had grown a little, I stopped playing with small dolls and didn’t tell too many storyknife stories anymore.
Kiagmi tau͡gaam angualgullruunga egelrutkun.
But in the summer, I always paddled with a canoe.
Tua-i yuilqumun ayalrianga arulaiyuunii every day ella-llu assilallruami.
I never stopped going to the wilderness every day because the weather would also be good.
Irniaten-qaa elicallruaten waniw' tamakunek aquinermek, inugualinermek?
Did you teach your children to play like that, to make small dolls?
Inugualillrunrilkenka-wa irnianka irniaruangqelallruut tau͡gaam.
I didn’t make my children small dolls, but they had dolls.
Irniaruanek yaaruivkangnaqaqluki-ll' yaaruiqtaraqluteng quliringuarluteng.
Dolls, and I tried to have them tell storyknife stories, and they would pretend to tell legends.
Maa-i-mi waniw' mikelnguut tuaten piyuurlu(?)
What about the children [?who do not] do that today?
Tut'garaanka maa-i Kass'artarnek tau͡gaam naanguarluteng.
My grandchildren now only play with Western toys.
Naanguanritaqameng tiiviiraqluteng
When they don’t play, they watch TV.
Anglaniciqngatut yaaruiyauruskata?
Do you think they’ll have fun if they tell storyknife stories?
Yaaruilaquneng-wa anglaniciqellriit.
They would have fun if they told storyknife stories.
Anglanarqetullruut-ll’ wangkuta yaaruitullemteni.
It was also fun when we told storyknife stories.
Au͡gkunek angutet ayagaqataratameng waniw’ qaillun neq’litlallruceciu?
When the men were going to travel, how would you prepare food for them?
Qaillun upyut'lallruceciki iciw' ayagyuallerpeni aatan wall'u-q'
How would you prepare things for them, you know, when you were small for your father or
Uingellerpeni uin pissuryaqataqan qavcinek tayim week-ani?
Or when you took a husband, when your husband was going to go for several weeks?
Ataka tua-i ayakataraqan aanama tua-i upnauraa
When my father was going to travel, my mother would prepare for him
Neqkainek, saayunek, saarralamek. Kenircuutaicuunateng.
Food, tea, sugar for him. They always had portable stoves.
Tamaa-i tau͡gaam ella assiraqan ellakun kenituluteng tamakut angutet.
But when the weather was good, those men would cook outside.
Ellmeggnek-qaa neqnek piaqluteng pissuraqluteng?
Would they get their own food by hunting?
Ii-i
Yes.
Maaten-llu pinauranka kuvyinaurtut string-anek pililuteng.
Then I would notice that they would make drift nets out of [a certain type of] string.
Ataka-llu neqsurcuuciaqluni muragnek canaluni taluyaliluni.
My father would also make a fishing tool by carving wood, making fish traps.
Can'giircuutnek pissurcuuciaqluteng-llu taluyanek kapkaananek ilaluku angutet tangvalallrenká
The men I watched would make fish traps for blackfish, and they added steel traps.
Aipaqa-ll' pilallruuq wangkuk aipaqliucamegnuk. Uksuiyalgulunuk up'nerkiyaraqlunuk
My spouse did too when we got married. We always went to winter and spring camp.
Maaten-llu tamaani ilamni uitallemni with my parents angayuqaagemni uitallemni
Then I realized that back when I lived with my family, my parents, when I lived with my parents
Up'nerkallra tamalkuan upatuluta March-ami.
Every spring, we would move in March.
Pelatakaraqluta qanikcaam qainganun.
We would set tents on the snow.
Amta-ll' tang qerruteksaunata. Kaminiaq-llu elliluku qanikcaam qainganun.
And yet we weren’t cold. And we put the stove on the snow.
Pelatekami tua-i uitanaurtukut March-amek ayagluta.
We would live in the tent starting from March.
Upagaqamta qavartaraqluta tua-i-ll' qavartarraarluta call'
When we moved, we would camp, then after we camped
Qaniilarraarluta, qaniilarraarluni ataka
After we took our supplies ahead, after our father took our supplies ahead
Nunakamteńun tekitaqluta nutaan. Nunaniqnaurtuq.
We would then reach where we would stay. It would be wonderful.
Ella-ll' assilaami
And because the weather would be good
Pelatekami uitangramta qerrucuunata.
Even though we stayed in the tent, we wouldn’t be cold.
Elisngaluku tuaten pituamta nutem.
We were used to it since we had always done that.
March-ami pelatekami uitaaqluta.
In March, we would live in a tent.
Anurviilallruuci?
Would you be hit by strong winds?
Iliini sometimes anuqliraqluni.
It would be windy sometimes.
Tau͡gaam aturnaqluni anuqliraqluni.
But we would be able to use [the tent] in the wind.
Kiagyugaqami ellallirluni-ll' piaqluni.
And as summer was approaching, it would be rainy.
Nunanirqaqluni akercirluni-ll' ella.
It would be wonderful with sunny weather.
Elpeci-mi arnani calallruceci ayagaaqavci?
So what would you women do when you traveled?
Ayagaaqamta-qaa?
When we traveled?
Maliggluki iciw' March-aami.
Going with them, you know, in March.
March-ami-qaa?
In March?
Iciw' ava-i qanruskevkuk ayagalallrulriaci right, March-aami?
You know, you just told us that you would travel, right, in March?
Pelatekami uitaurluci, arnani calallruceci?
Living in a tent, what would you women do?
Wiinga atam equgtaryunqellruunga.
You see, I liked to gather wood.
Tua-i unuakuarmi, early morning, erqaararaqan
Early in the morning, right after dawn
Maklua equgtarnaurtua
I would get up and gather wood
’cause I was the oldest one, family-ni wiinga alqaullruama.
’cause I was the oldest one, because I was the eldest sister in the family.
Equgtalgullruunga assikluku equgtaneq
I always gathered wood, enjoying gathering wood.
Aanan-mi calallrua?
So what would your mother do?
Aanaka tua-i arulaiqsaunani upluki cat
My mother never stopped preparing things
Atu’urkai-llu atamta taum, ivrucililuki-llu.
Everyhing my father would need, and she would make them waterproof skin boots.
Tamalkumta-ll' ivrucingqerraqluta, water boots pilianek.
And all of us had waterproof skin boots, handmade water boots.
Up'nerkami tamaa-i tamakunek aturaqluta ivrucinek.
We would use those waterproof skin boots in the spring.
Canek piliaqumaluteng? Canek piliumaaluteng?
What were they made of? What were they made of?
Tuntuvallugnek ivrucingqerraqluta, tunturpallurnek.
We had waterproof moose skin boots, large caribou skins.
Tuntut amlletullruut ak'a.
There used to be a lot of moose a long time ago.
All over, tuntut amllerluteng.
All over, there were a lot of caribou.
Tua-i-llu 1941 tuntut wani tuquluteng amlleq.
And then in 1941, a lot of caribou died.
Keglunret tuaten-gguq nerluki.
They also said wolves ate them.
Tuntut-llu catairulluteng tuntutairulluni.
Then the caribou were gone, no more caribou.
Qessatulit arnat angayuqat ca qaill' pilallruaki, qessamkat arnat?
What would the parents do to lazy women, the lazy women?
Qessamkat-wa arnat ellimelallikait.
They probable told the lazy women to do things.
Qaillun qanruyutengqelallruat qessanqurnun?
What traditional wisdom would they have for lazy people?
Wiinga-wa atama tau͡gaam qanrupallutullruanga.
For me, mostly only my father taught me.
Waten qanrullua: wiinga-gguq qessanqerrukuma-gguq wiinga cam-gguq atam iliini
He told me this: if I am lazy, to see that someday
Yuungnaqniartua wangnek.
I will try to make my own living.
Tua-i-llu-gguq qessanqurrukuma caitelarciqlua.
And then if I am lazy, I won’t have anything.
Qessaksaunii-gguq canek cauralaqilii makut yuut cayarait tangerrluki.
He told me not to be lazy but to continously work, looking at the way these people do things.
Kiagmi-llu cat atsat-llu naukata atsanek iqvarlua.
And when berries grow in the summer, to pick berries.
Pistengqerquma-llu-gguq pisteka neqnek pikan neqet aulukluki.
And he said that if I have a provider, if my provider catches fish, to take care of the fish.
Kenekluki qessalerutevkenaki uqlautevkenaki-llu.
I should treat them with love, not be disinclined to do them, and not make a mess of them.
Au͡gkut yuut tangvallrenka angayuqaagka
The people I saw back, my parents
Neqnek uqlauciyuitut uqlauciyuiteqapiarallruut, neqet kencikluki.
They didn’t make a mess of fish, never made a mess, out of reverence for the fish.
Enrraungraan-llu natermun pisqessuunaki kenekluki.
Even if they’re bones, they told us not to put them on the floor out of love.
Kencikluki. Tua-i-gguq atam kencikenrilkumteki tutmautelaqumteki-ll'
To revere them. He said, you see, that if we do not revere them and tread upon them
Pikaitelarniartukut.
We won’t have things.
Wall' kuvyaput cangyuunateng, wall' taluyat cangyuunateng kenkenrilamteki.
Or our drift nets will not catch anything, or our fish traps will not catch anything because we don’t love them.
Cat tamalkuita kencikiurluki pisqaqluta, aturaqengramteki-llu kenkurluki.
They told us to revere everything, and to even treat our clothes with love.
Maa-i-ll' wii man'a tekilluku canek uqlauciiyuilngua.
And now, to this day, I do not make a mess of anything.
Cat-llu amllengrraata uqlaucuunaki kenkurluki tau͡gaam kenciku’urluki.
And even though there’s a lot of things, I do not make a mess of them out of love, but revere them.
Au͡gkunek neqet iciw' poison-angqellriit neqet poison-angqellriit. Qaill’ nallunritullrusiki?
And you know that fish have poison, fish have poison. How would you tell them apart?
Ak'a tamakut tangvalallrenka yuut neqet kencikluki
The people I watched a long time ago would revere fish
Neqliaqetullruit akercircecuunaki.
They would not let the fish they worked on be exposed to the sun.
Kuvyami-llu kuvyam cangtai akercillret
And on the net, what had been caught in the net that had been exposed to the sun
Qimugteńun tau͡gaam neqkiutuluki qerruqallret qerruqsagtellret.
They would prepare the ones that had bloated to be food only for dogs.
Taumek ilussaqercuitellrulriit. Ilussaqertellriamek-wa tangvallrunrilngua yugmek kitumek.
That’s why they never had food poisining. I’ve never seen any person have food poisoning.
Grow up-aallemni-llu-wa angliyugallemni amlleq yuk tuquksaitellrulria.
And when I had grown up, not many people died.
Once in a great while yuk tuquaqluni. Naulluussiyaayuunateng-llu yuut tangvallrenka.
Once in a great while, a person would die. And the people I saw wouldn’t get sick too often.
Cali-ll' taangiqellriamek tangyuitellruunga.
And I never saw anyone drunk.
Sixteen-aallemni tau͡gaam first time taangiqellriamek tangerrlua.
But when I was 16, I saw someone drunk for the first time.
Maa-i nasaurluut 16-aaraqameng iciw' taqnerurtelalriit.
Now when girls are 16, you know, they become adults.
Arnaurrnaciallruama-ll'-wii 16-aallemni tau͡gaam arnaurtellruama.
I became a woman late because I became a woman when I was 16.
Aipangellrulua-ll' 18-aallemni tau͡gaam au͡g’umek aipamnek. Parents-aagma aiparkarrlua.
And I got married to my spouse when I was 18. My parents chose my spouse.
Mingqiilallernek-mi?
What about those who sewed grass?
Wiinga ellangellruunga mingqiiyuilngurni, tau͡gaam canegnek tupigaqluteng.
I didn’t grow up with those who sewed grass, but they would weave grass.
Arnat-llu arnassagaurtellriit curunek kelugkanek
And then women who had gotten older would make mats out of coarse grass
Tupigluteng mallgulluki. Assipianek tupignaurtut.
They would tightly weave them. They wove great things.
Wiinga maurluqa tamaa-i tuqullruuq. When I was about eight-aarlua tuqullruyugnarquq.
My grandmother died back then. I think she died when I was about eight.
Tamaa-i taumek aquinritaqamta-llu arnassagaat ullagluki.
That why when we weren’t playing, we would go to the old women.
Anglaniuratullrukenka caliaqata tupigluteng.
I would have fun when they worked weaving grass.
Tua-i-llu ukaqvaurtellria Mikelnguut Elitnaurviat ak'allarnek piyugluni.
Then it’s been recently that the Mikelnguut Elitnaurviat wanted old teachings.
Old things. Mother-aaqa unguvallrani mother-aaqa pilisqessaaqluku.
Old things. When my mother was alive, they asked my mother to make things.
Ikaraliitnek, aqlitegnek, uyamignek-llu piyugnarqaat, ak'acetun pilisqelluku.
They asked her to make things in the old way, grass mats for kayaks, earrings, and I think necklaces.
Tua-i-ll' mother-aaqa piuq, ellii-gguq pingaituq. Wii-gguq naspaalii.
Then my mother said that she wouldn’t. She said that I should try.
Tua-i-ll' wii tupiglua arnassagarnek tangvalallrenka ayuqeliluki.
Then I wove grass, replicating the old women that I used to watch.
Ayuquciirluki tupiglua tegunecuayaalirluki kelugkanek.
I wove grass like they did, making small warp strands with course grass.
Ilaitnek yualirluki. Waten tupigait ayuqetullruut tamakut: ukut ukatmun, ukut-llu ukatmun.
I used some of them to thread through. The things they wove would be like this: these going this way, and these going this way.
Tegunecuayaarluteng waten ellegtalrianek. Waten tupigluteng.
They had small warp strands that were this thick. They wove grass like this.
Ika-i tang tupigayagaq issraksuayaaq. Atam taiteqerr'.
Look, the little woven grass bag across there. Give it to me.
Una?
This one?
Tua-i, nuu, tua-i-tang, yaa, tauna-llu.
There, no, there it is, yes, that too.
Waten curulilallruut.
They would make mats like this.
Waten tegunirluku, waten-llu akultutaurluki.
They made warp strands like, and made the gaps this size.
Wiinga tua-i pililrianga ikaraliitnek.
I made grass mats for kayaks.
Tua-i-ll' mother-aama tangvaglua pianga, "Atam-gguq waten-gguq ukatmun-gguq qip'aqluki."
Then my mother watched and said to me, "Look, twist them this way like this."
Tua-i-ll' tuaten pingaarcamteng waten ayuqunga'arluteng.
Then when I started doing that, they started becoming like this.
Pama-i atam ikaraliiksuaraliallrenka Mikelnguut Elitnaurviatni glass-ani ekumaut, atqa-ll' tuanlluni Elena Charles.
You see, the small grass mats for kayaks I made are inland in Mikelnguut Elitnaurviat, and my name is there, Elena Charles.
Tua-ll' call' issracisqeńgatnga, issrat'lilua cali iitallernek.
Then when they asked me to make a woven grass bag, I made a bad out of tall cottongrass.
Waten ayuqluku, ang’urluku tau͡gaam.
I made it like this, but pretty big.
Terr'a tau͡gaam kan'a takliriluni, taqurluku-ll' iqua.
But the bottom down there got long, and I braided the end.
Una assirlun' pimauq.
This is done well.
Acia-llu-q’ man’a?
And the bottom here?
Assipiarluni un' pimauq.
This is made very well.
Tegumiaqluku tuaten usgullukek terr’anek piqerr', acia maniluku.
Please hold it, connecting the bottom parts, showing the bottom.
Canegnek-llu tupignaurtut kalngaliluteng.
They would also weave grass to make fish carrying bags.
Paper box-aanek piitellermeggni neqet assigtarkiurturaraqluki.
When they didn’t have paper boxes, they always made bags for fish.
Dry fish-aarutait-ll' assiraqluteng.
And the dry fish they made would be good.
Canegnek tupigluki waten mallegtanun.
They would weave grass with this close pattern.
Wagg’uq kuusqullugnek.
They called those kuusqulluut.
Paingit-llu naqeqluki can'get tupiumaluteng, ilavkuliluteng.
Their openings would be woven, the grass would be woven to make ropes.
Nin'amayiit-qaa cali iluatni uitalallruut?
Would the aged herring be in them as well?
Wangkuta nin'amayugnek piyuitellruukut. I'm from tundra.
We didn’t have aged herring. I’m from [the] tundra.
Elliviit-llu, elliivingqerraqluteng every family.
And caches, every family would have a cache.
Fish cache, kanagarluni muriit.
Fish cache, and it would have wooden posts.
Pagna umciggluni, wall-aq-ll’ umciggluni.
It was airtight up there, and the wall was airtight.
Natrit tau͡gaam ukinerluteng.
But their floors had holes.
Neqautait-llu imai assiirucuunateng.
And the fish in them wouldn’t spoil.
Kalngiit-ll' imait neqet kumlanret assipiat.
And the frozen fish inside the fish bags would be very good.
Dry fish-aat-llu uquggluyuunaki. Assirnaurtut.
And the dry fish in them wouldn’t get mold. They’d be good.