Ii-i, qaneryullemnek waniw’ qanqatartua makunek
Okay, I’m going to say what I want about these
Waten tan’gaurluullemni, tan’gaurluullemteńi makunek
These things when I was a boy, when we were boys
Makunek-wa tua-i nunam qainganelngurnek neqemteńek, pitarkanek, imarpigmiutaat makut-llu cali yaqulget.
Our food that we hunt on land, sea animals, and these birds.
Maa-i mat’um nalliini nang’ut.
There are no more these days.
Makut waten imarpigmiutaat enurnaringut, makut-llu yaqulget cali enurnaringluteng.
These sea animals are becoming scarce, and these birds are also becoming scarce.
Imumi waten tan’gaurluullemteńi, tan’gaurluullemni-w’ tua-i up’nerkami amllepiatullruut yaqulget.
Back when we were boys, at least when I was a boy, there used to be a great many birds in the spring.
Yuilquq nepaitellruuq. Waten ayuqellrunrituq.
The wilderness was quiet. It wasn’t like this.
Tem’ingelriamek waten niicuunata ertaqan, ellami tem’irtellrianek.
We wouldn’t hear anything rumbling like this at dawn, rumbling outside.
Up’nerkami waten up’nerkiaqameng pavani Akulmi nunanirpak yaqulget ayuqenrilnguut qalrialuteng.
When they went to spring camps in the spring like this inland in the Akula region, it was wonderful with various birds calling.
Makut-llu pissulriit waten atakumi atakuara’rqan, atakuaratullruuq kanaqlagcualriit up’nerkillerni pavani.
And these hunters in the evening when evening was setting, they would spend the evenings hunting muskrats in the spring camps inland.
Tua-i cingqullagangnaurtut nut’galriarurrluni waten tua-i piciatun.
They would make loud pops, the air filled with gunshots like this everywhere.
Makut-wa yaqulget pavani nanvat ceńaitni-ll’ up’nerkitullruameng
And these birds, because they would camp in the spring on the shores of lakes inland
Anglanaqluteng yaqulget kuimalriit qalrialuteng.
It was fun with the swimming birds calling.
Nunaniqluni tua-i piaqluni up’nerkami.
It would be wonderful in the spring.
Qaillun wii umyuarteqaqama pissurnanriiceteng-qaa nang’ut?
For what reason, when I think about it, are they gone since they don’t hunt them anymore?
Wangkuta-llu tan’gaurlucuarni cali waten elitnauruterluni: pissungqerrluta makunek yaquleyagarnek.
We boys also had these lesson: we hunt these little birds.
Amllepiarluteng cali.
There were a great many of them too.
Pitgaquurluki tamakunek yaquleyagarnek pissurnaurtukut.
We would hunt those little birds with arrows.
Tamakut-llu pitaput iciw’ egcuunaki.
And, you know, we wouldn’t discard what we caught.
Makut cali nasaurlullraat meqtayagarluki kenirnaurait.
Also, these girls would pluck their feathers and cook them.
Tau͡gken cali aanamta imum keniraqluki cali pitaput egcuunaki.
However, our mother would also cook what we caught without discarding them.
Waten qigcikluki, makut nunamiutaat neqput kencikluki au͡gkut pitullruit.
The people back then would respect and revere the food we got from the land like this.
Mat’um tau͡gken tua-i nalliini qaillun piat?
Yet what are they doing these days?
Makut-llu yup’ut pissuyuirulluki imkut makut yaquleyagaat pitgaquurluki pitulput.
And our children do not hunt these little birds that we used to shoot arrows at.
Tayima tua-i tangrrunanrirluteng maani nunam qaingani up’nerkami pissulalput.
What we used to hunt on the land here are no more to be seen.
Tuamtellu cali kiagmi tukraqameng napamiutaat amllepiarluteng puyurcivignun it’raluteng.
And then when those in the trees hatched in the summer, there would be very many entering smoke houses.
Wangkuta-wa cali maa-i pitgaquurqeput.
We would also hunt with arrows.
Amiiyaarluki uuggun qat’gaitgun cilla’arrluki kemgit au͡g’arluki, uuggun-llu yaqruita piitgun ayagciqerluki.
We skinned the little things, opened them here on their chests, removed their flesh, and propped them on their wings here.
Nuucirluki-ll’ nutaan napamek agarqurluki.
Then we tied them and hung them in the trees.
Wagg’uq-qaa nakaculiluki. Tuaten pitullruut.
They called that nakaculiluki. That’s what they did.
Amllepiarluteng yaquleyagaat cakaniyuunateng.
There were a great many little birds without any change in population.
Makut-wa cali aulukesteput
Also, our caretakers
Up’nerkami tua-i ayagluteng yaqulget waten cetunatkameggnun ner’aqluki tua-i neqekluki kayanguit-llu.
Starting from the spring until the birds went downriver like this, they would eat them as their food source including their eggs.
Camek niicuunata nangqatalrianek, ikegliinalrianek.
We wouldn’t hear anything about there being no more, or anything depleting.
Tau͡gaam waten pitullruut: allamiaquaqan cat ukut ikgetaqluteng.
But this is what happened: every year, something would have low numbers.
Caaqameng-ll’ amllerrluteng, waten ikgeliqetaarluteng.
And sometimes, there would be a lot, occasionally decreasing.
Tau͡gaam nangyuunateng, cakaniyuunateng.
But they wouldn’t be gone, wouldn’t be affected.
Amllerrlainarluteng yaqulget imarpigmiutaat-llu.
There were always a lot of birds and sea animals.
Tua-i-llu tamakut waten yaqulget up’nerkami nerluki yaavet tua-i neq’ngellerkaanun.
And then, they would eat those birds like this in the spring until there were fish.
Cetuameng tau͡gaam taqluki, ayanqigtevkenateng.
They only stopped when they went downriver, stopped going out to hunt.
Nuna tua-i yugtairulluku waten Akula, imarpigmi, unani tau͡gaam Kusquqvagmi.
There was no one left like this in Akula, but [they were] down on the Kuskokwim.
Neqnun cali cauluteng. Amllepiarluteng call’ neqet.
They turned to the fish. There also a great many fish.
Tamaaggun-wa kencikellratgun, Agayutem cikiutekngamiki kencikellratgun tua-i amllerrlainartelluki.
Through there reverence, because they are God’s gifts and they revered them, he always kept them at high numbers.
Maa-i mat’um nalliini umyuangcarqama tamakut, neqrateng tua-i makut neqteng murilkelluki, mulngakluki.
When I think on that these days, they would watch and be careful about whatever food they had.
Neq’lipiatullruuq agaani waten tan’gaurlullraullemteńi.
There used to be a lot of fish across there when we were boys like this.
Puukaquaqluteng-llu maavet ceńamun.
They would also bump each other to the riverbank here.
Kuimarqamta-llu iliini maaggun naw’un puukaraqluteng neqet.
And sometimes when we were swimming, the fish would bump into us somewhere here.
Tua-i-llu mat’um nalliini tua-i kencikenriamceteng cat nangengluteng.
Then these days, since we don’t revere them, there are no more of some things.
Kencikellruit au͡gkut.
People back then revered them.
Tuamtellu waten wangkutnun tua-i yugnun atalliniut makut neqput.
And then, our food sources are evidently connected to us humans.
Tuamtellu cetuanek makut piaqata inerqurnauraitkut ivraasqevkenata tayim’ cetuarcurqata.
And then during beluga hunting season, they would admonish us against wading in water when they were hunting beluga.
Maavet ukalirnermun agaantaqamta ivraqaasqevkenata inerquanauraitkut.
On this side when we were across there, they would admonish us against wading in water.
Cetuarcurniluki tamakut qaill’ pilriit tuaten inerqutullruitkut.
They would admonish us like that, saying that they were hunting beluga.
Tua-i-llu mat’um nalliini tayim’ nangluteng pissuyuirucamceteng.
And so, there are no more these days because we don’t hunt them anymore.
Makut-llem yaquleyagaat nangluteng tayima pissurnanriimceteng wangkuta pitgaquurluki.
And there are no more of these little birds because we’re not hunting them with arrows anymore.
Tau͡gken makut aipaimta kellutestaita amllericangnaqsaaqluki inerquuteksagulluki pissuyuirutevkarluki yaqulget.
However, our Caucasian counterparts who regulate them are trying to raise bird populations by restricting us from hunting them.
Makut yaqulget arulairucuitellruit au͡gkut anglicartemta.
Those who raised us back then didn’t stop hunting these birds.
Tua-i waten pavani up’nerkami neqkerraarluki
After having them as a food source in the spring inland
Tua-i-ll’ cali neqnek pirraarluteng imkut tengesciigaliata ingcata piyagaat-llu
And then, after they fished, when those birds couldn’t fly anymore as they molt, and the chicks
Irniarit angtateksaguarcata nutaan cali tamakut pissungluki, qayateng imirluki tekirqengnaurtut.
When their young were the same size, they would start hunting them, returning with full kayaks.
Cakaniyuunateng-llu ikegliyuunateng.
And they wouldn’t be affected, wouldn’t deplete.
Mat’um tau͡gken tua-i nalliini cat tamangluteng yaquleyagaat-llu.
Yet these days, there are no more of some things including little birds.
Wall’u-qaa pissurnanriamceteng piut?
Or is it because we don’t hunt them anymore?
Tua-i au͡gna waten qanengssaka pitauq.
Well, that is all I have to say.
Kitak’ im’u, iciw’ ayagalriani, tayim’ iciw’ ak’a ayagatullratni
Then, you know, when traveling, you know back when they traveled
Iciw’ pellaalliaqata wall’u qaill’ piaqata, kaingaqameng canek nertullruat yuilqumi?
You know, should they get lots or something happens, what would they eat in the wilderness when they got hungry?
Kaingaqameng-qaa neqkaunateng?
You mean when they got hungry without food?
Yaa, iciw’ yuilqumi pellaakata qaillun neqkailkata canek neryugngaat?
Yes, you know, if they are lost in the wilderness with no food, what can they eat?
Qaill’ iciw’ uksumi wall’u-q’ kiagmi wall’u-q’ up’nerkami wall’u-q’ uksuarmi?
How would they do it, you know, in the winter or summer or sping or fall?
Yaa.
Okay.
Au͡gkut-wa waten alerqutullruitkut tua-i neqkailkumta, arenqiallugeskumta:
People back then would instruct us like this if we had no food, or were in an unfortunate situation:
Neqkaunata pikumta neqengqerrsugngayaaquq waten:
If we have no food, one can have food like this:
Maa-i makut uugnaraat neqkaugut cailkuni yuilqumi, tau͡gaam kenengqerquni.
These voles are food sources if he has nothing in the wilderness, but only if he has a fire.
Tamakut tamaa-i neqkauyaaqut.
Those can actually be food.
Tau͡gken cali niitetullrulua, makut-gguq qangqiiret anait imkut neqnguut. Tamaa-i tamakut.
However, I also used to hear that ptarmigan feces can also be eaten as food. Those things.
Ava-i apeskevnga qaillun neqkailkuneng nerengnaqlerkait.
You just asked me how they could eat if they had no food.
Makut uugnaraat uksumi tangrruutuut.
We see these voles in the winter.
Tamaa-i tamakut neqkauyaaqut.
Those can actually be food.
Tau͡gaam-am cali nerailkuni angu qassaasqevkenaku.
But also, if he has not eaten in a while, he should never eat raw meat.
Wall’u ayainanermini akaurrluku-w’ tua-i nereksaitellni
Or as he’s traveling, if he hasn’t eaten in a long time
Waten taluyillruarmek tekiskuni, iciw’ imkut can’giicuayagaat alungya’rnek pitullret, angu nerqaasqenritait tamakut.
If he comes upon a fish trap like this, you know the blackfish fries they call alungyaraat, he should never eat those.
Elliinek, elliinek pitaqeciqniluku anrutaanun.
They said that they would kill him through his stomach.
Una neraicaraq, arcaqertuq tau͡gaam una meqsulleq kiimi.
Being without food, but it’s worse to be thirsty.
Arenqiallugeskuni ayakuni neqkailkuni meqsukuni
If one gets into misfortune in his travels and is hungry and thirsty
Inerquumaukut taqsuqluta qanikcarmek neresqevkenata meqsungramta.
We are admonished that if we are tired, not to eat snow even if we’re thirsty.
Qanikcartuaraasqevkenata. Wangkutnek piciqniluta. Ircaqurput pinialiciqniluku tuaten qanikcarmek nerkumta.
They told us not to eat snow. They said we would kill ourselves. They said our heart would weaken if we ate snow like that.
Tau͡gken merkailkuni ca imna plastic-aaq maavet iterrluku.
However, if he does not have water, he should put a plastic bag inside here.
Puqlami urugcirluku. Tuaten tua-i alerqulallruit.
They would melt it in warmth. That’s how they would instruct them.
Unani-llu cali imarpigmi tuaten ayuqluni arenqiallugeskuni, merkailkuni.
That’s also how it is down in the ocean if he gets into misfortune without water.
Pitami anrutaa, iciw’ qilua...
His catch’s stomach, you know, its intestines...
(Piciatun?) Ai? (Piciatun pitani?)
(Anything?) What? (Anything he caught?)
Ii-i, piciatun pitani tua-i maklaarem imarpigmiutaam qilua.
Yes, the intestines of whatever he catches, a seal, a sea animal.
Kepluku qaillun tua-i pitariluku piyugtacimitun maqluku. Un’a imarpik umyuangarrluni mernaituq meq egyungvailgan.
He should cut it to whatever length he wants and drain it. One should not drink at the first thought down in the ocean before water seeps out.
Arenqiallugeskuni tamatumek avaqlingqerquni pitangqerquni
If he gets into misfortune, if there’s one of those around him
Anrutaa wall’ qilua imna takqupak qaill’ tua-i taktariluku kepluku maqluku-llu, nutaan-llu qanikcarmek imirluku.
Cut its stomach or its long intestines into whatever length he wants, drain it, then put snow inside it.
Ayagninqigteqaa.
Please start again.
Ii-i, au͡gna ava-i pilqa
Okay, about what I was just talking about
Imarpigmiutaam qilua maqeqaarluku, tua-i-ll’ qanikcarmek imirluku.
After draining the sea animals intestines, put snow inside it.
Tua-i-llu-gguq maavet iterrluku puqlami, tau͡gaam kememinun pivkenaku.
And then, they said to put it into the warm spot here, but not touching his skin.
Maavet tau͡gaam urugarkauluni waten piluku iquuk qillerrlukek.
It will melt here, tying its ends like this.
Tua-i-gguq tuaten unani merkiutuut arenqiallugeskuneng.
They say that’s how they get water down in the ocean if they get into misfortune.
Maani tau͡gken nunam qaingani tua-i arenqiallugeskuni wall’u kiskuni
However, if he gets to misfortun here on land or sinks into water
Tua-i egmianun nenglliqan aturani nengllingraan piyugngakuni egmian yuuluki kumelqerpailgaki.
If it’s cold, even if it’s cold, he should take off his clothes right away if he can before they freeze.
Makut tua-i aturani ciulaagluki, utumacarluki, all’uki-llu.
He should quickly wring his clothes to make them better, and put them on.
Nutaan-llu askuniki canegtangqerqan maakun ekiarakun piluki imirluku.
And when he puts them on, if there’s grass, he should fill and line them.
Makuk-llu waten unkut.
Including the area down here.
Waten alerquuterluni nenglliqan. Ukuk tau͡gaam waten taptaarturlukek pisqellukuk, ukut-llu waten ukuk.
This is an instruction when it’s cold. But, they are told to continually fold these here, including these like this.
Tau͡gken-gguq-am waten uitaurquni cikuskani tua-i ukuk pektesciigalkagnek amllirasciigatarkauluni.
However, they said that if he stays still and freezes, when these can’t move anymore, he will not be able to walk.
Ukuk-llu cali waten pikagnek tua-i pektesciigatarkauluni.
And if these also freeze, he won’t be able to move.
Alerqulallruitkut tuaten tua-i camek-wa tua-i anirtuuka’rmek nunamteńi piilkumta tuaten pisqelluta.
They would instruct us to do that if we didn’t have anything around us to save us.
Ukuk tua-i waten elliurturaqaqlukek nengelmi, ukuk-llu, ayanrilkumta.
We should keep doing this with these [arms] in the cold, and these [legs], if we’re not moving.
Arenqiallugcaraq amllertuq maani nunam qaingani.
There are many ways to get into misfortune here on land.
Piyunartacirramitun.
He should do whatever he can.
Tuamtellu-gguq cali waten alerqutullruitkut:
And then, they would also instruct us like this:
Nengelvagmi ayainanemteńi tua-i alqunaq igeskumta
If we are traveling in the extreme cold and suddenly fall
Egmian cikum acianun pinrilkumta tangerrluku qamevkenata
If we do not immediately go under the ice, depending on if we do not sink in
Iciw’ tua-i piqarraarluta piyugnganrilkumta
You know, after we do that, if we are unable [to do anything else]
Aliumatvut waten piqerluku nep’artelluku.
Do this with our glove to make it stick [to the ice].
Tauna tua-i nepingaurtelluku waten elliuqaqluku.
Keep that stuck, occassionally doing this.
Tua-i piarkaunriqreskan nutaan tuaggun cayugluku waten nugyugngaarkauluni nugyugngakuni.
If it would not come off, he will be able to get out of the water by pulling that like this if he is able to come out.
Arenqiallugcaraq una amllertuq qanruyutii.
There is a lot of traditional wisdom about getting into misfortune.
Arenqiallugeskumta-gguq iciw’ tavevkenata, alqunaq-wa tua-i anirtuangnaq’laagesqevkenata.
They said that if we get into misfortune, you know, not to panic and try to hastily save ourselves.
Pingnaqkumta-gguq wangkutnek pitaqeciqukut.
They said that if we try [too hastily], we will kill ourselves.
Maani-llu cali mermi, ayagakumta meq man’a murilkelluku anirtuumatkarput.
And in the water here, when we travel, we should observe the water for what can save us.
Qairet-llu makut cali murilkelluki qaill’ atullerkait. Alerqutullruitkut tuaten.
They also told us to observe how to use these waves. That’s how they instructed us.
Tamaaggun tamaa-i murilkellermikun tau͡gaam una temni ayagatarkaugaa.
He must only physically travel through his being observant.
Ava-i-llu tua-i neqkaicaram ayuqucianek apcaaqerpenga.
And, you just asked me about being without food.
Tau͡gaam nalluaqa qaillun cakaunani-w’ tua-i pillerkaq.
But I do not know what to do if one does not have anything.
Tau͡gaam aturangqerquni neryugngalriamek qecigmek
But if he has skin clothes that can be eaten
Tauna tua-i kenengqerquni eleggluku qassarpek’naku.
If he has a fire, he should char it, not eat it raw.
Akaureskan nereksaitellni tauna tua-i anirtuatekarkaugaa.
If he hasn’t eaten in a long time, that will save him.
Makut maa-i alerqutullruitkut qangqiiret-gguq makut anait qanikcarmun waten akuarrluki nerellrit cayuitut.
They would instruct us that it’s safe to put ptarmigan feces into the snow and eat it.
Tan’gaurluullteteńi naspaalaratullruaput tamakut.
We used to try those when we were boys.
Tuaten tua-i ner’aqluki imkut qangqiiret makut anait.
We would eat ptarmigan feces like that.
Qanikcarmun akuarqaarluki ner’aqluki naspaaluki.
After putting them in snow, we would try eating them.
Tuaten qanruyutnguan. Ai?
Because that’s traditional wisdom. What?
Cangateksaunateng?
Were they okay?
Assirluteng, cangateksaunateng napaungameng-wa tua-i makut nunam qaingani nunam qainganek neqengqerrameng
They were good, they were okay, because of these trees, because they eat these trees
Naumalrianek tumaglinek-llu neqengqerrameng, makunek-ll’ ayunek, napat-llu kangritnek.
Because they eat plants, and lowbush cranberries, and Labrador tea, and the top parts of trees.
Cangacuunateng. Inerquutngunritut tamakut. Camek alingnarqellriartaitut qangqiiret anait.
They were okay. Those are not admonished against. There’s nothing dangerous in ptarmigan feces.
Tua-i.
That’s all.
Camek allamek umyuaqengangqertuten?
Do you have any other thoughts?
Ai?
What?
Camek allamek umyuaqengangqertuten?
Do you have any other thoughts?
Kitak’ arulaiqercetqerru.
Can you stop recording for a while?
Ayagnirnariuq? (Yaa.)
Is it time to start? (Yes.)
Ii-i, tua-ll’ waniw’ mat’um nalliini niicugnilriani
Okay, so to you who are listening these days
Umyuaqelallemnek qanqatartua atullemnek-llu.
I’m going to speak about what’s been on my mind and what I’ve experienced.
Waten ukut waniw’: akerta, erenret-ll’ unuakumi akertem ciungani alailallrat, puglallrat
These things: the sun, and what becomes visible, appears, before the sun in the morning
Maa-i mat’um nalliini alairqata pugnilaqeput, igvarqata-llu pug’aqluteng.
When they become visible these days, we say they appear, and they appear when they come into view.
Akerta ikaggun pugtuuq
The sun rises across there
Maani tua-i Kusquqviim kanavalirnerani uitakumta.
If we’re here toward the water on the Kuskokwim.
Una-i un’a Kusquqvak unani caningqauq keggaknerem ping’um waten kepluku.
The Kuskokwim down there is on the side, with the west cutting into it inland.
Arenqiallugeskuni nani maani, wall’u ayuquciireskuni, amirluuskani, pirtunguskani, wall’ taitunguskani
If he gets into misfortune somewhere here, or if he’s lost, if it gets cloudy, if a blizzard sets, or gets foggy
Unukani tua-i, wall’u nanluciitqapiarluni pikuni, nani-ll’ Kusquqvak uitacia nallukuniu
If it’s night, or he has absolutely no idea where he is, and he doesn’t know where the Kuskokwim is
Tua-i ayuquciitkacagarluni.
Being completely lost.
Atullruarput pingayuuluta Negteḿun ayallemteńi.
Three of us experienced that when we were going to Newtok.
Tau͡gaam murilkelallruaqa mat’um ciungani una akerta iraluq-llu.
But before this, I used to observe the sun and moon.
Naw’un picuituq. Ikaggun kiaqvaarkun pit’elartuq Kusquqviim akilirnerakun.
It doesn’t rise anywhere else. It rises across there, a ways upriver across the Kuskokwim.
Tua-i-llu qerturivailegmi, quyigivailegmi Kusquqviim quliikun ayagluni.
And then, before it gets too high, it goes above the Kuskokwim.
Uatmurrluni imarpiim tungiinun.
It goes downriver toward the ocean.
Tua-i-llu nutaan imarpiim quliinun, imarpimteńun unavet, imarpimta tunglirneranun elliami nutaan pagaavet ellirluni.
And then when it goes above the ocean, our ocean odown there, toward our ocean, it finally goes up there.
Quyigikanirviirulluni agluni.
It goes without going any higher.
Tua-i-llu ag’um nunam tunglirneranun piami cali, cali ellurluni nunamun mat’umun ipcarturluni.
And then when it goes across toward the land, it goes down to disappear on the land here.
Iraluq cali-llu akerta.
The moon and the sun.
Tuamtellu iciw’ Qaluuritmek, nallunritarci. Qaluuritmek pillalriaci.
And then, you know, the Big Dipper (Qaluurin), you know it. You talk about the Big Dipper.
Nallunritan?
Do you know it?
Tauna Qaluurin Tunturyugmek pitullruarput wangkuta. Tunturyuk.
We used to refer to the Big Dipper as Tunturyuk. Tunturyuk.
Tauna tua-i cali Erenret Iquata eniumaralriatun, caumauralriatun ayuqelaraat.
It’s like Erenret Iquat [?constellation?] points them to a certain direction, like it faces a direction for them.
Tua-i akerta tevirluni pikan murilkeciquci Erenret Iquat caumaluku.
When the sun sets, you will observe that it faces Erenret Iquat.
Tua-i-llu avaggun ayagluni, agaaggun ayagluni, agaalirnerkun.
And then it goes over there, goes through the area across there on the other side.
Tua-i-ll’ tamaavet imarpilirneq mallgiamiu kanarrluni.
And then when it gets close to the ocean there, it bends down.
Kanarteqanrakun imkut Erenret agkut alairluteng, tanqigiyarturluni agna akertem tunglirnera.
As soon as it bends down, Erenret [Iquat] appear, and the area toward the sun brightens.
Tauna tua-i cali cuqyutraq’lallruaqa.
I also used that to find my bearings.
Tua-ll’ tuani, pim, Negteḿek tailuta kampaassarput assiitelliniluni navgumaluni.
And at that time, you know, as we were coming from Newtok, our compass was bad and broken.
Kiatmurtelliniluta.
We had apparently gone upriver.
Imarpigmun-llu kanaryukluta tan’geriqatarluku.
We thought we were going down to the ocean as it was getting dark.
Imarpigmun kanaryuklemteńi uterrluta tumllemteggun nunamun piluta. Nanluciitkacagarluta.
When we thought we were going to the ocean, we backtracked and went to the land. We had no idea where we were.
Pelatekarluta tua-i inarrluta mecungnaringa’rcan.
We set up a tent and went to bed as it started getting wet.
Tua-i-llu qavainanemteńi uiga’rtua pelatekaq man’a tanqigceterrlugluni nenglaitellruami-llu.
And then as we were sleeping, I opened my eyes, and the tent was a little bright, also because it was warm.
Maaten caugartaqa kumlanaku, pakemna tanqigcesnganan’.
I faced it and found that it was cold, and it seemed bright up there.
Piunga pelatekaq callaneruangqerran tekemnek waten pirraarluku piunga iraluq ingna.
Because the tent had a little hold, after doing this with my forefinger, I saw that the moon was over there.
Tua-i nutaan ayuqucinglua.
I finally understood where we were.
Kusquqvak tua-i una’antelliniluni.
The Kuskokwim was down there.
Uilluta tua-i uisngaluta.
We woke up.
Tua-i-ll’ nanluciicaaqengramta ilagka piagka Kusquqviim tungiinun ayakatarniluta.
And then, even though we didn’t know where we were, I told my companions that we were going to go toward the Kuskokwim.
Tua-i ayagluta Kusquqviim tungiinun.
So, we went toward the Kuskokwim.
Au͡gna-am cali qemini kuik Qurrlurnanek pitulput, umyuarteqluta tamakuukan elitaqciqniluku.
Also, that river among the hills that we called Qurrlurnat, we thought that we would recognize it.
Ayainanemteńi-ll’ tua-i elitaqiluta.
And as we went, we recognized things.
Taumek waten alerqutullrukaitkut murilkerrlainarluku ca maani nunam qaingani pekatesqelluta.
That’s why they would instruct us to observing everything on the land as we went.
Nallunairturrlainarluki.
We should always make them landmarks.
Makut-llu kavirlirraat cuqkurluki.
Also, we should always find our bearings with these [willows with red bark].
Nunat-llu tungiit assi’irqan ca imna kingunemteńun elli’irqan, tauna tua-i cuqyuka’aqluku.
And the things toward land, when it’s good, when it goes to our home villages, use those to find our bearings.
Ca-llu cali maani nanvarra’ar qertuuralria-llu tuanlucia nalluvkenaku.
Also, we should know where ponds or elevated areas are here.
Alerquumatullruukut tuaten.
That’s how we were instructed.
Atam-gguq pitsaqa’artevkenata elitaqkumteggu kingunerput imna assiilengraan tuaggun tua-i tunglirnequcia tuanlucia nalluarkauvkenaku.
They said that if we happen to recognize it, even when the weather’s bad, we will know which direction and where our home villages are.
Taumek murilkerrlainarluta-w’ tua-i au͡gkut anglicartemta waten ayagalaasqellrukaitkut. Ca murilkerrlainarluku.
That’s why those who raised us back then would tell to always be observant as we traveled like this. We should always observe everything.
Avairqan-ll’ unugmi agyat pagkut nallunairturturluki tuanlucia.
And when it gets clear at night, mark where the stars above are.
Wall’u nuna cali tunglirnerani tauna agyaq uitakan, tuani tua-i taukumiut tuantarkauluteng.
Or if a star is in the direction of a village, that village will be [marked as being] there.
Tau͡gaam cali enemeggni uitaurayuunateng.
But, they also wouldn’t stay in their houses all the time.
Cuqluku ayagarkauluni nateqsigikaniraqluni tauna agyat tuaten ayalria cuq’errnguarluku.
They would gauge it when traveling in a certain dirionction, using those stars to get their bearings like that.
Tuaten tua-i wangkuta atullruarput.
We experienced it like that.
Kiituan elitaqillerkamteńun tekilluta.
We eventually reached placed we recognized.
Ayallemteńi-llu cali taiciryaaqluni.
And it was even foggy when we traveled.
Tau͡gaam tuaggun iralukun Kusquqviim tunglirnequcia nalluvkenaku.
But with that moon, I knew which way the Kuskokwim was.
Qanrullukek-ll’ ilagka waten: tua-i uquiruskumta piyuagurluta Kusquqvagmun unavet ayagciqniluta.
And I told my companions this: if we run out of fuel, we will walk down to the Kuskokwim.
Amta-ll’ cataunani Kusquqvak taiciami.
And yet the Kuskowkim was gone because it was foggy.
Tengssuutmun tangerciqniluta unani...
I said a plane would see us down...