Qanqernaurtukuk.
Let’s speak.
Ii-i, tua-i imumi cumigyagutellemni-ll’ wiinga
Well, a long time ago, when I became observant
Ellangamta tua-i maaten ellangukut tamakut-llu au͡g’um ava-i qanrutkellri aiparmi niiskengaqluki.
When we were growing up, we realized that we would hear about what my spouse talked about when we were growing up.
Tau͡gaam tang tua-i wangkutni ayagyuani tua-i alingnaqluteng tamakut Kass’aqarraat.
But for us young people, those first Caucasians were scary.
Qavcin tua-i Kass’at tangerqalaqeput.
We would see several Caucasians.
Tangelguyugnaunani. Caqapkacagaqamta tekitellrianek Kass’anek tangerqaqluta.
We didn’t always see them. Only once in a blue moon, we would see Caucasians who arrived.
Tamakut tamaa-i. Tua-i-ll’ piqerluteng maani Anuuraami uitaluta elitnaurvingluteng maani.
There you have it. Then one day, we were here in Anuuraaq when they built a school here.
Takuk’acagamteńi elitnaurvingluteng, ayumian elitnaungluteng.
They built a school in the middle of us, then they started going to school.
Tua-i-llu tua-i elitnauryassaagyaaqelriakut, tamakut angayuqamta aren qunukekacaarluta.
Then we tried to go to school, oh my, our parents were very reluctant to let us go.
Angurrluk’ elitnauryaasqevkenata.
They told us not to go to school under any circumstances.
Tamakut camek tua-i akusrarrnarqelriamek ayagnirniluki. Maa-i tua-i ungacautnguniluki tamakut elitnaurviit.
They said that those were starting some kind of unacceptable behavior. They said those schools [?made them soft].
Alingnaqkacagarluteng tua-i tuani pillemteńi.
They were very scary when we did it then.
Inerquangraitkut, elitnauryaryaaqerraarlua-ll’ wii ataucirqumek tua-i paq’ercaaqerraarlua...
Though they admonished us, and after I had gone to school, after I had checked them once...
Wait, tauna igtuq.
Wait, that fell.
Aipaqlian?
Are you a couple?
Qastussiyaallemta pillia?
Was it because we were too loud?
Nuu.
No.
Tua-i-llu elitnauryaryaaqerraarluta uitasqeńgatkut uterrluta tua-i.
Then after we had gone to school, we went home since they told us to stay.
Makut-wa tua-i qanerturalriit, makut-gguq elitnaurviit arenqiatut.
These people kept saying that these schools are faulty.
Avani tua-i iqugglungqertut akusrarr[luteng].
Over there, they have a bad mischievous result.
Usviiruciiqut-gguq avani yaaqvaarni tua-i callerkameggnek umyuarteqenrirluteng mat’umek waten akusrarutnek taitengkata tua-i.
They said that they would become foolish far in the future, not thinking about what they should be doing when they start bringing things that cause mischief.
Tua-i elitnaurpek’nata makut tau͡gaam ayagyuarluut tua-i irniaput-llu elitnaungluteng.
We didn’t go to school, but our poor young people and our children are starting to go to school.
Cat nallunringluku tua-i igautaqluta-llu.
They’re finding out about things and they write about us.
Tamakut tamaa-i Kass’at tuaten, qaillun-llu Kass’anek nangciksailnganateng.
The Caucasians have done that, and they didn’t seem to physically abuse any Caucasians.
Tau͡gaam tamakut angalkut-llu caliarit tamakut tuaten ayuqellruluteng.
The work of those shamans were also like that.
Anglanitekluki tamakut piaqluki yuut umyuarrliqngameng tua-i.
People have started having fun about those people they have malicious intent.
Man’a-w’ call’ akuliitni qanruyuterugaita, imkut qanrutestemta akuliitni piyulria qanruyutem tua-i ilakluku ciknayaraq-gguq man’a.
And this, among their many pieces of traditional wisdom, among those who wanted to speak to us, they say that jealousy is part of traditional wisdom.
Yuk-gguq elluarrluni-llu yuungnaqu’urlulria ciknakluku imna angalkum ciknatarlim
They say that a jealous shaman would be jealous of a person who is living a good life
Pinrillugcetaarluku picuirucetaqluku wall’ tukuuyulallrat man’a navgaqluku elluarrluteng yuuqataryaaqellret.
They place curses on them to make them bad hunters, or they destroy the riches of one who had been going to live well.
Umyuarrliqluteng tamakut cakneq.
Those have great malicious intent.
Tua-i-llu cali qanruyutet makut
Then, these pieces of traditional wisdom
Ilameng-gguq akuliit ik’ikengraitkut, tua-i qessamkaukluta-ll’ ayagyuarlurni nasaurlulle’rni maani
They said that though they despise us among our peers, and they say that we poor young people, girls here, are lazy
Unugmi-llu anairucarallruama-ll’ wii, unugmi-llu tan’geriaqan anenermek taq’laama
And because I wouldn’t go out at night, and I would stop going out at night when it got dark
Akeqnerrluggnauraatnga makut qessamkaukuma tua-i waten kaigasteńguciqnilua
They would intimidate me, saying that if I am lazy that I will be a beggar liek this
Picurlautek’larciqniluku-ll’ tamana qessamkaulua pirraarlua ilanka [?] ayuqniam ugaani.
And they said that it would bring me to misfortune after I was lazy, [?] my family because of my desire to [have things].
Tau͡gaam tua-i tuaten qanrutaqluta makut wani qanqegcaarautestema.
But those who taught us well would tell us that.
Ilamta akuliitni-ll’ ellalkartevkenata, imumek [?]tevkenata, murilkevlacagpek’nata, usviitevkenata ilamta akuliitni.
And they told us not to misbehave among our peers, not to [?], not to be inattentive, not to act foolish among our peers.
Maktaqameng tua-i qanruqu’urnauraitkut, "Elpeci-ll’ maa-i ayagyuani irniangekuvci-gguq
When they got up, they would always tell us, "When you young people have children too
"Irniarci-gguq mikelnguungalnge’rmi, wall’ pilukuvceńi camek inerququvciu, ’Kitak’ at’ ilavet piqaqatgen qimagaqluki ingluliuteng.’"
"Even though your child seems like a child, or if you admonish them when you put on their skin boots, ’Now, if your peers do anything to you, run away [?].’"
Atam-gguq cumikeyagatuut.
They say that they pay attention.
Tua-i-gguq maa-i makut maa-i ciulirnemta makut tamana ellangeqarraallermeggni niitellerteng tua-i pikluku tua-i.
They say that what these elders of ours heard when they were growing up are theirs.
Maa-i tua-i tamana umyuaqaqamku qunukelalqa-llu tamana akusrangciqniluki avani
When I remember that now, what I didn’t want, that they would become mischievous in the future
Qitevcuilama-llu qitevtellrit-llu niicuilamki umyuaqluki.
And since I don’t speak English and don’t hear them speaking English, I remember them.
Irniangamegnuk-ll’ aipangamegnuk, aipaput kenekluki pisqessaaqaqluki.
And when we had children and got married, they told us to love our spouses.
Uiput cumikluki, allaliuqsaunata-llu.
We should pay attention to our husbands, and never be unfaithful.
Uimta-llu nalluatni arnaurlulriani wangkuta ayagallerkartuyarrluta
And if we women go to [other men] without our husbands’ knowledge
Kiituani-gguq taum uimta pikenrilkiinek qingangaqluta-gguq.
They said that eventually, we would become pregnant with a child that is not our husbands’.
Imkut maaten tamaani ellangeqarraallemteńi qanrutaqamegtekut ikiu͡kacagarluku ca ikuggluku qanrutnauraitkut.
Back when we were growing up, we realized that when they spoke to us, they would tell us of unacceptable things [?] them.
Tangvagluta-ll’ piaqatkut waten umyuarteqsaaqnaurtukut wangkuta niicugnilriani:
And when they did that watching us, we who were listening would think this:
"Aling ik’um-am cunaw’ nallunrilkiikut. Tangellrukiikut." Tuar tang nallunritkacagarluta ilumun tangellruluta pilaqaitkut.
"Oh my, that person apparently knows us. (S)he saw us." It seemed that they knew us very well, like they had truly seen us.
Cunaw’ tamakut qanruciyupialriit ircaqurteng cairluku ellait atullmeggnek assirluki yuk agesqelluku qanruturlularyaaqellinikaitkut.
It turned out that those who really wanted to speak to us emptied their hearts of what they had experiences, telling us so that a person would do well.
Irniau͡rluput-llu waten makut irniaqsagutaqamteki angurrluk’ tua-i agutevkenaki
And our poor children, when we have children, they said never to bring them [to others’ houses]
Tass’uqluki-ll’ enenun allanun ceńirtaaruqu’ur[pek’naki].
And do not hold their hands to have them visit other houses.
Atam-gguq asriurturlurniartut.
They said they’d become mischievous.
Ikiurlullrat man’a arrsaurlullerput ilalqerluku-gguq atam.
They said that their unacceptable behavior would exacerbate our poverty.
Aanaulriami wani enem nayurtiini, una-wa-gguq aatavut ayagalria pikangengnaqluta
A mother who looks after the house, and the father who travels for what we need
Pitarra’urlui-gguq tekitaqan quyatekluki ciuniurluki arnaulriani.
They said that we women should be thankful for whatever he catches when he arrives.
Wall’ akirrarmek unangekan qenngevkenata wangkuta arnani taqmakegciyugluta, wall’ camek cap’akiqegciyugluta
Or if he earns a little money, we women should not be angry wanting beautiful dresses, or something like beautiful shoes
Aturaqegciamta-gguq tua-i pikarciaritnek maa-i nangerngiimta.
Because, they said, that we stand here with good clothes that they’ve gotten us.
Tamakut-gguq navguutekait taum aipamteńun tamakut unangkengarait, uirlumta unangkengarait.
They say that those destroy our spouses, what they have earned, what our poor husbands have earned.
Munarulluki-gguq munarcallrani tauna aipa’urlurput uqiskirluki.
They said that we should work dextrously with them as our spouse worked dextrously distributing seal.
Tamakut tamaa-i anglatekevkenaki-gguq.
They said not to treat those lightly.
Akingutaurlui tegulerulluta ayagpek’nata.
We should not take his heard earned money and go.
Avani-ll’ ayainanemteńi canun akusrarrnarqelrianun tekiskumta wall’ mer’aluta wall’ canun
And as we go, if we come across things that bring mischief, or we drink, or other things
Inerqurluta tua-i tamalkuitnek tamakunek aarnarqelrianek, irniamta-ll’ takuatni tuaten ayuqesqevkenata. Alerquaciqaput-gguq.
They admonished us against all of those dangerous things, and that we shouldn’t do that in front of our children. They said that we would teach them.
Cunaw’ imna anguyagteńun ayagangaqameng tan’gaurlurugaungameng-ll’ irniapuk tua-i umyuaq una navgurluku yuungaqluta mer’ayullermegteggun maaggun.
it turned out that when they start going into military service, since we have a lot of male children, we start living destroying our mental health because they abuse alcohol.
Tua-i tuaten tau͡gaam ilalqerpek’nani yuk yuurluqili mat’um nalliini.
However, may a person live life without exacerbating things like that in these days.
Tamana-llu tamaa-i akerrneqlugutek’lallrat, akusrangkumta-gguq tamakut angayuqamta qanrutestemta ciulirnemta qanrutaqamegtekut
And their warning of danger, that if we start being mischievous when our parents who teach us, when our elders teach us
Akusrangkumta-gguq camek elpek’ngaarulluta
If we start being mischievous without thought for anything
Qanrutestevut cumikenrirluku alerquastevut, elluarrluta yuusqelluta aviranaunata ilamta akuliitni
Stop paying attention to those who teach and instruct us, telling us to live well without hindering those among us
Tau͡gaam-gguq assirluta tangniqluta enemteńi aqumluta.
Instead, they said that we should be good, pleasant to be seen sitting in our homes.
Enevut-gguq uitanqegcinaqniartuq.
So, they said, that our house would be peaceful.
Allaneruaraam-llu nanikualriim itervikekakut uitanqegcivkangnaqluku, im’uvkenata akusrartevkenata yuukumta.
And if some guest who feels helpless comes in, try to make them feel at east, if we, you know, do not live mischievously.
Tua-i tuaten qanraqata piyugyaaqengramta amta-llu tua-i iliini canun tekitengaqluta tua-i
When they said that, though we wanted to, yet we would sometimes come across things
Assiryugyaaqellerput man’a ukatairluku.
We missed our desire to be good.
Makut-llu maa-i waten makutgun qanruciarkanek kepqengata ayagyuat makut wani kinguqliput maa-i mat’um nalliini yuut amlleriameng
And these days, since these young people, our descendants, are now in great need of teachers these days because there’s not a lot of people
Alerquatmek niicungata, tamana tang tua-i capqerqelaqeka.
Since they want to hear instructions, I find that daunting.
Angliriluta tua-i waten niicugniarkauyaaqekput qanruyutiit elluarrluku
We grew up, needing to listen to their traditional wisdom well like this
Imkut ak’a ayagnengellruyaaqngata ggun KYUK-kun qanelriit, imkut arnat-llu alerquagiluteng.
Because they’ve already strated speaking through KYUK here, and those women instruct.
Tamakut-llu tamaa-i arnat uingit tuar caunrilkellermegteggun ciisqurrilitaqluki tamaaggun
And those women, it seems that through their disregard for their husbands, they’re like knee guards through that
Ayuqenrilngurnek-llu irniangeksaunata, uirlurput-wa una nakmiillarput.
And we didn’t have different children [from different men], with our very own husband here.
Aipamta-gguq tau͡gaam tamakunek irniarinek irniarluta, canek allatarnek ilayuunaki.
They said that we only had children from our spouse, without adding any from others.
Tangniqpiarluteng-gguq.
They said they were beautiful.
Aren ayuqniarluryaaqnaurtua, aling arenqiapaa-ll’.
Oh my, I would want that, oh my goodness.
Waniw’ tua-i nallumteńi-ll’ tua-i tayima tua-i qingircetnayukluta.
Here, we would be scared that we would be impregnated without our knowledge.
Ayagyuarluta-ll’ qingircetlerkaq tua-i alingnaqkacagarluni, mikelngurmek alairillerpuk.
And it was very scary to become pregnant at a young age, to bring forth a child.
Atailnguut tallurnaqkacagarluteng-gguq. Inerquutngullruyaaqluni.
They said illegitimate are embarrassing. It was an admonishment.
Maa-i tamatuullinilria akusrangllerkaatnek qanlallrat imkut au͡gkut ciuliamta.
Apprently, this was the mischief that our elders back then would talk about.
Tamana tamaa-i alerquuterpaksaaqekiit maa-i makut tua-i Kass’at maa-i assipiat. Aling niitniqpiat. Ungaqtarnaqpiat Kass’at.
That import Western instruction these days is very good. Oh my, they’re so nice to hear. Caucasians make us feel nice.
Tangvaqamta tangercetaanek-llu tangvagaqamta canek-llu au͡gkut inerciigalnguut arnat-llu kap’urluraqaceteng qaillurayak elli’irrnaurtut.
When we watch things on TV, when they inject people who are rowdy, including women, they would become very abnormal.
Unaqsaqerrluteng camek tua-i tuar tang eyautairtelalriit wangni.
They become limp [sedated], and it seems they have no more [?] to me.
Cam im’ inerciigalnguum tekiskateng tua-i piningnaqluteng pisciigaciiqnganateng.
If some rowdy person comes upon them, it seems they wouldn’t be able to hold up with their strength.
Inerquutnek makut wani assiitellriit atuqsaileng’erpeciki ayagyuani.
You young people shouldn’t do bad things that are admonished against.
Maligqurassiyaagpek’naki Kass’at makut pisqutait
Do not follow what the West tells you to do too much
Canek tua-i makut puyurtull’e’rnek-llu canek pinglarniitki iqugglugningqeńilaitkit tamakut.
Also because they say these things, including marijuana, have substances and that they do not end well.
Tamakut atuqsailengraata.
You shouldn’t use them.
Waten tau͡gaam yuuqallerput tang tua-i ikgetlinilria.
Our life here is short.
Una wani ayagyuallerput, ellangellerput canimelngat’laryaaqellria, amta-ll’ waten pinialiluta carpagciigaliluta.
Our youth and our time growing up seems close, yet we become weak like this and can’t do strenuous things.
Taumek mulngakluci tuaten tamakut assiiterrlainaat maligtevkenaki.
That’s why you should be careful like that, not following only bad things.
Cavvliurluci yuungnaqluci akingengnaqluci pikuvci tengruluci quyanarqekaca’arciquci.
If you live life doing housework, making money with enthusiasm, it will make us grateful.
But, use your money for yourselves, your houses, to help you with what you need.
Wiinga-ll’ tua-i waniwa qitevvneq-llu nalluamku, qaill’ ucuryagutakevkenaku atuyuilamku tua-i.
And now, since I don’t know how to speak English, I don’t hold it in high regard because I don’t use it.
Pisqeqapigtaqatnga tau͡gaam ik’um-ll’ aiparma maliklua camek, maligglua camek tua-i tegutaqlua una-kiq qaill’ tunllerkaa nalluk’acagaamku.
Only when they really want me to, my spouse across there goes with me, he goes with me and I take something, because I have no idea how to give it.
Quyanaqkacagarluni tua-i quyaaqlua nallucimnek uitanqegcilua uitalaama.
I am thankful that I don’t know because I stay in peace.
Imkut tua-i carrarmek qanlaata tangvak’ngapuk, tayim’ amlleriyaaqellilriit-llu qanelpuk.
Because the ones we watch say little, but we have probably said a lot by now.
Waten-qaa pitakumegnuk amlleriksaitut tayima qanrumallerpuk ava-i?
If this is all for us, have what we said not become a lot?
Tua-i?
Is that all?
Tua-i waten pitayugyaaqelrianga.
This is all I want [to say].