Aren assaliqatallruyaaqlua-ll' assaliarturnaluta taqkuma.
Oh my, I was going to make frybread so that we would have some when I was done.
Maancimaniartukut.
Let's stay here for a while.
Ii-i upcaaqlua, yaa.
Yes, I prepared, yes.
Yaa acaciciqua(?) yuurqerniartukut.
Yes, I'll make (?) so we can drink something hot.
Iciw'-llu Kakianam ellami piyuasqellrukiiten?
And, you know, Kakianaq wanted you to walk outside.
Ii-i aren anyuumiitua.
Yes, oh my, I don't want to go out.
Wall'u-q' keggani patio-mi camek tangvalartuten?
Or do you watch something out from the patio?
Canguapiaraqluten.
You soend leisurely time.
Tua-i-qaa tiiviimeciiqell'.
It'll probably be broadcast on TV.
Iciw' au͡gna Waves-an qanellren mumigcetellruken.
You know, you wanted your Waves of Wisdom recording to be translated?
Qaa?
Really?
Mumigtekan-llu tua-i tauna video-q aturluku piluku.
Then when it's translated, we will use it.
Kituulriaten im’ Yugtun?
What's your Yup'ik name again?
Elena, oh Narull'aq.
Elena, oh, Narull'aq.
Qanemcitqerkut kitak' qaillun akaar miktellerpeni atsanek iqvaryalallrat yuut.
Now, please tell us stories about people would go to pick berries long ago when you were small.
Ii-i, iqvalallrulrianga wii nasaurlullraullemni Nalqiglimi maligarullua.
Okay, I used to go berry picking when I was a little girls in Nalqigliq, going along with them.
Imumek kangiralegmek iciw’ qaltarlua,
I used a square five-gallon gas can as, you know, my berry container,
Kangiralegnek piu͡rlulallruamta.
Because we poor people use square gas cans.
Tua-i-ll' tauna muirluku ut'rulluku.
Then I filled it full and brought it home.
Utercama-llu aanama akulluku tamalkuan yugnun nerevkaritekluku.
Then when I went home, my mother made Yup'ik ice cream with all of it and fed it to people.
Tuaten tua-i iqavaraqluta, tau͡gaam au͡gna aptellren qaillun uksurpak keep-alallrat?
We would pick berries like that, but did you just ask how they would be kept all winter?
Ii-i qaillun qemagtelallruitki imumi kumlivingvailegmeng yuut?
Yes, how did people store them before they had freezers?
Wiinga-w' tanglallrulrianga... tamakut tang wii iqvallrat nallunritenrilkeka.
I used to see... see, I don't know how they picked berries.
Puckami, elaturrametaqluteng.
In barrels, they would be in the porch.
Iciw' elaturrami cat neqkaput-llu uitatullrulriit kumlanateng,
You know, our food would be in the porch and they would be cold.
Elaturrami-w' tua-i tanglallrukeka atsauteput puckami muragmi.
I used to see our store of berries in the porch in a wooden barrel.
Akutaqavci saalartangvailgan camek akuyucilallruceci?
When you made Yup'ik ice cream, before there was shortening, what type of fat would you use?
Aanaka akutelallruuq tunurnek iciw’ imkut, tallow, tunut,
My mother used to make Yup'ik ice cream out of tunut, you know, tallow, tunut.
Reindeer-at tunuit.
Reindeer tallow.
Kinercirluki tua-i-ll’ kinercirraarluki akuteqatarqami uklicuayaarturluki assaalissuutmun ekluki,
She dried them, then after drying them, when she was going to make Yup'ik ice cream, she would them into a frying pan,
Tua-i-ll’ maniluki kaminiamun, iciw’ bacon-aatun.
Then she would heat them on the stove, you know, like bacon.
Tua-i-ll' qallangluteng tzz-aarluteng tua-i-ll' mer’urrluni.
Then they would boil, sizzing, then it would render.
Tamakut-llu qerrluteng ukliqcaarallri.
And those pieces she cut up would bunch.
Tua-i-ll' taumek taggluku tamakut iciw’ ciurluki waten.
Then she removed them and, you know, wrung them like this.
Anlluki tauna-llu tua-i tunuq, iciw' bacon-aat urugarcilalriit uqumek?
She took them out, then that tallow, you know how bacon renders grease?
Uqupiamek add up-aarluku iciw’ uqupiaq tunuq.
She would add the fat, you know, the real fat, tallow.
Qanikcarciluteng iciw’ qancikcaq imna kavtayagaq.
They would get snow, you know, that snow, little hailstones.
Tamakucimek. Tua-i-ll' akulluni iciw' tuaken qanikcamek avuqaqluku.
That kind. Then she would make Yup'ik ice cream, you know, periodically adding in that snow.
Akutaqami-ll'-am nepliqaunrit'laqiikut. Ciin-kiq?
And when she made Yup'ik ice cream, she would tell us not to make any sound. I wonder why?
Nepaunata uitaurnaurtukut.
We would stay quietly.
Tua-i tuaten akutaqluni. Qaillun-wa tua-i elli'irqan qivilartau?
That's how she made Yup'ik ice cream. I'm not sure at what stage she would add berries.
Tua-i tuaten tanglallruaqa tauna.
That's how I used to see that.
Cali-qaa allatgun pilallruat? Uqurrlainarmek-qaa iliini ilaluk' pilallruat?
What else did they use? Would they sometimes add oil/fat?
Tua-i-w' tunurrlainaukuni tegpiarciqell'. Iciw’ tunuq kumlangaqami teggpiatulria?
Well, if it's all [solid] tallow, it would be very hard. You know how hard tallow gets when it's cold?
Tua-i-ll' uqumek avuami mixed-arluni,
Then when it's added and mixed with oil,
Tua-i akucugngayugnarquq. Allamek tang nallulrianga.
It can probably be whipped into Yup'ik ice cream. I don't know of any other.
Nallunritan-qaa qangvaq saalamek atulangellrat?
Do you know when they started using shortening?
Aren wii nallunritaqa. Ukaqvaggun.
Oh my, I do know. It was recent.
Nunapicuarmi wiinga yuungnaqlua.
I was making my own living in Nunapitchuk.
Yuungnaqenglua tua-i. Tua-i-llu au͡gna uicungaqa, au͡gkumiungurtelleq, Iilgayaq, Bristol Bay.
I tried to make my own living. Then my male cross cousin who moved over there, Iilgayaq, Bristol Bay.
Allanrullermini, akutaitnilua wii pilua.
When he came as a guest, I said I had no Yup'ik ice cream.
Kaugamek akutetuunga uqumek add-up-aarluku wii.
I make Yup'ik ice cream out of tallow, adding in oil.
Pitullruunga tua-i saalamek nalluulua.
I used to do that without any knowledge of shortening.
Taum-llu tua-i angutem ayuqucirturlua waten pillemni, "Akutailngua tang wii."
Then that man instructed me when I said this, "See, I don't have any Yup'ik ice cream."
Cukalua-gguq akucukuma saalamek atam piqerlii.
He said that if I want quick Yup'ik ice cream to use shortening.
Tua-i-ll' saalauteka maniamku,
Then when I took out my shortning
Saalarrlainaq miiskaamun waten teguqaulluni
He took nothing but shortning like this into a mixing bowl
Akucesqelluku emiqaqluku.
He told me to whip it into Yup'ik ice cream occassinally adding water.
Wesson-oil-anek-llam avuqaqluk' pituit.
They also add in Wesson oil.
Wiinga-am milegmek piluk' pituaqa.
I personally do it with milk.
Ii-i ayuqenrilngatuq maani nunani.
Yes, it seems to be different in these lands.
Tua-i-ll' tuakenirnek waniw’
Then ever since then
Kaugamek tallow-mek atunqigtevkenii saalarrlainarmek.
I never used kaugaq, tallow, but only shortning.
Cukpiaraqluni.
It's really quick.
Allanek qaa qivilallruit waten anllernek wall’u-q' quagcinek?
Would they add in anything else like this, like tall cottongrass tubers or sourdock?
Ii-i, anllernek, quagcilek. Anllelek, anllerrlainaq,
Yes, tall cottongrass tubers, one with sourdock. The one with nothing but tall cottongrass tubers,
Kiingan-tua-i avuvkenaku wii tangtullruaqa,
By itself, I used to see it with nothing else added.
Quagciq-llu cali una atsanek avuluku, mixed-arluku.
And this sourdock, they would add in berries, mixing them.
Maani-qaa Mamterillrem avatiini wall’ Kusquqviim iluani,
Is it here around Bethel or on the Kuskokwim,
Makut anlleret pilallruaci?
Would you gather tall cottongrass tubers?
Wiinga maani Kusquqvagmi nalluanka tau͡gaam Akulmi pamani Nunapicuaq.
I don't know about them here on the Kuskokwim, but in the Akula region, inland in Nunapitchuk.
Tamaani anllernek anllercurvigluta-llu au͡g'umek iciw' tua-i tuani anlleret pituluteng.
We had a place to gather tall cottongrass tubers over there, you know, there would be some there.
Im'u caulriit im' imkut anlleret epuit.
Well, what were the tubers' plants again?
Tamakutalget anllertangqetuut. Iitaq, iitalget.
Places with those have those tubers. Tall cottongrass, places with tall cottongrass.
Nallunritan-qaa nunat ayuqenrilnguut allarrauluteng akutelallrat?
Do you know how different villages have slightly different ways of making Yup'ik ice cream?
Kuigpagmiut, wall' allamiut?
People from the Yukon, or other places?
Maybe. Wiinga nallunritua tuar tang qagkumiut, Yukon.
Maybe. I know, I think it's people from up there on the Yukon.
Akucunqellriit aren ima tanem akutelalriit-llu kemegnek, iciw' kemget,
They like to make Yup'ik ice cream, I mean, they also make Yup'ik ice cream with meat, you know, meat
White fish meat, kenirrarluku tua-i-ll' enriqcaarluku, amiirluki,
White fish meat, after cooking it, then deboning it, then taking off their skins
Ciurluki-ll' tua-i, tua-i-ll' akulluta.
Then wring them, then make Yup'ik ice cream.
Iciw' tuar tang qanikcaqluki.
You know, it's like they use them as snow.
Tua-i-ll' una calalriit ima? Uleluni, uleluni,
Then this, what does it do? It rises, rises.
Tua-i-ll' wii tamakut tayim' nalluanka.
Well, I don't know those.
Tau͡gaam qagkumiut, Yukon,
Except for the people up there, Yukon.
Ava-i-llam ukaqvaggun au͡g'um keleglua.
Then recently, that person invited me to go eat.
Akutartullruunga kemlek iciw' whitefish-am kemganek avuluku. Pituut.
I had Yup'ik ice cream with meat, you know, with whitefish meat added. They do that.
Qaill'-mi mak'at?
But how do they make aged salmon egg ice cream?
Ciungani-qaa miktellerpeni-qaa mak'ilallruut?
In the past, did they made salmon egg ice cream when you were small?
Mak'ilallruut Kusquqvagmiutarnek iciw' meluk.
They made salmon egg ice cream with, you know, fish roe from the Kuskokwim.
Initukait iciw' half dry?
You know they hang them to half dry?
Tua-i-ll' caquluki. (Taryaqviit-qaa kiimeng?) Piciatun, dog salmon, piciatun meluut iniluki.
Then they encase them. (Only king salmon?) Any kind, dog salmon, they would hang any kind of roe to dry.
Tua-i-llu meluutelilallruukuk aipaqa-llu aipaqa qimugtelilallrani.
Then my spouse and I had a lot of fish roe when he had a lot of dogs.
Qimugtet-am tamakut neq'liaqamiki melugmek tuaken ilaluki kemget pitui.
When he made food for the dogs, he would add in roe from there into the meat.
Tua-i-llu mak'iyugaqamta meluk tauna camna ilua.
Then when we wanted to make salmon egg ice cream, the roe beneath inside.
Tua-i waten teguluni-llu.
He would take some like this.
Ilait-am qanlartut, "Just like cheese-gguq." Cheese-aaq-gguq tua-i.
Some say, "Just like cheese." They say they are cheese.
Kassat-gguq tua-i cheese-aaracetun ayuqluni.
They say it's like Western cheese.
Tamana tua-i unailnguq teggenrilnguq mak'itullruat.
They would make aged salmon egg ice cream out of that soft part that wasn't hard.
Tua-i-ll' cali maa-i whitefish meluk, mak’ituut. Aspiarluni.
And now, they make fish egg ice cream out of whitefish roe. It's very good.
Nutaan tang tamana niiskeka.
That's the first time I heard that.
Whitefish-aat-am meluit aspiaraqluni, iciw' passiluki.
Whitefish roe is very good, you know, crushing them.
Tepengssagauteng. Tamakut atam imkurtut,
They have no odor. Those [others] are, you see,
Meluut Kusquqvagmiut tepengqertut iciw'.
Roe from the Kuskokwim have an odor, you know?
Tua-i-w' caluteng rich-arluteng.
They are, you know, rich.
Makut white fish-aat tua-i aspiat meluit, passirraarluki tau͡gaam.
These whitefish roe is very good, but after crushing them.
Tua-i-ll' imkut nuyarngalnguut iciw' au͡g'arluki.
Then remove those things that look like hair.
Nuyarngalngengqetuut. Caqullrit-wa pillilriit meluut.
They have things that look like hair. It's porbably the membrane from the roe.
Tamakunek-llu mak'ilallruut.
They'd also make fish egg ice cream with those.
Quliranek-qaa nallunritqanrituten akaar akutat quliraitnek?
Do you happen to know any legends from long ago about Yup'ik ice cream?
Nalluunga. Iciw' wiinga qulirat nalluanka.
I don't know. You know, I don't know legends.
Iciw' wii anglaniketaitellruunga.
You know, I didn't find anything fun.
Ceńirtaanqurraama tua-i epsalngutarlua.
Since I'm the one who visits others the most, I get suffocated easily.
Waniw' tua-i quliringuamek-llu nalluunga.
Now, I don't know about any legends.
Qaillun akaar iqvaryalallruceci? Qayatgun-qaa?
How did you go berry picking long ago? With kayaks?
Angyatgun cavluta.
We rowed boats.
Ataucirqumek Nalqiglimek cakma Naparyarrarmiut akiatni nunallret.
One time from Nalqigliq downriver, at the old village sites across Napakiak.
Iciw' tayim' catairutut.
You know, they're all gone now.
Au͡gna-llu friend-aqa-llu Kassiglurmiu-ll' tuqullruuq.
And my friend from Kasigluk died.
Tinker-aam nulirra.
Tinker's wife.
Tauna-ll' atam aipaqelgullruukuk tua-i maligarucunqegglunuk.
She and I always played together, and liked to go with each other.
Maligutukuk-am Nunapicuarmun atsiyalrianun.
We went along with those who went to pick berries in Nunapitchuk.
Cav'urlunuk iciw' waten, row.
We kept rowed, you know, rowing like this.
Tua-i-w' cavluteng.
Well, they rowed.
Cavluta tagluta Nunapicuarmun, yaaqsipiaq.
We rowed up to Nunapitchuk, very far away.
Qavartalallruuci-qaa?
Would you camp?
Qavartaraqluta tau͡gaam, how many days.
But we would camp, how many [several] days.
Tauna-ll' tua-i wangkuk friend-aqa-llu assigtapuk murilkurluraqluki iciw' iqvautepuk.
Then my friend and I would watch over our containers, you know, the berries we picked.
Taukut-wa tua-i au͡gna five gallon-aarullilria-wa.
Those, it was probably a five gallon bucket.
Tua-i taun' wii assigtaqtullrukeka.
That's what I used for a container.
Inglua waten callalluni.
The other had a hole in it.
Iciw' cavignek pitullrulriit im' kaassat.
You know gas had metal [containers]?
Caqurluteng, five gallon. Tamakuciq. Plastic-aanek nalluluta.
They had [those] containers, five gallon. That kind. We didn't know of any plastic.
Qaill'-mi tan'gerpiit iqvarraarluki qemagtelallruceciki aturnatkavceńun?
But after picking crowberries, how did you store them until you used them?
Tanglallruunga imkunun,
I would see them put into those things,
Mukaarutlernun assigtarluki.
They stored them in empty flour bags.
Tua-i-ll' mermun akurrluki. Iciw' tua-i cunaw' tang freezer-aurlurluki tua-i mermun.
Then they submerged them in water. You know, they used the water like a freezer.
Tuani-wa kumlatellriami assirciqngata.
It's because they would be good there where it's cold.
Nallunritaqa-ll' wangkuk pillruukuk aipaqa-llu.
And I know, my husband and I did this.
Akimteńi ikani kit'elluku tauna mermun.
We let that sink across from us in the water.
Kuigmun?
Into the river?
Kuigmun.
Into the river.
Tau͡gaam kuikapiarauvkenani.
But it was a major river.
Agaani camun tuar tang Nanvaryugyaq tumngurngilngurmun, angyat tumekngailkiitnun.
Somewhere across there, I think it was in Nanvaryugyaq where it wasn't a path, where the boats wouldn't go through.
Nenglengan-llu tua-i-ll' mayurrluku, teguluku, assigtarluku.
Then when it got cold, we raised it, took it, and put it in a container.
Surat-mi? Tuaten-llu-qaa surat pilallruat?
What about blueberries? Would they do that with blueberries too?
Curat-wa wiinga tang curautengqellrunrilngua.
Blueberries, well, I didn't have any blueberries, you see.
Tau͡gaam egmian ner'tuluki curatetuyaaqukut.
But we do get blueberries and eat them right away.
Egmian tau͡gaam ner'aqluki.
We only ate them right away.
Piuteksuunaki, assiirrngiata-wa.
We didn't do that with them because they spoil easily.
Kumlivigni tau͡gaam maa-i assiircuitut.
But they don't spoil in freezers now.
Cali-q' allanek akutelallruut? Allanek?
Would they make Yup'ik ice cream with anything else? Other things?
Kavirlit? Kavirliit-llu qerpercilaqait.
Cranberries? They also make crushed whitefish roe ice cream with cranberries.
Qerpertaq. Nallunritan?
Whitefish roe ice cream. Do you know about it?
Qaillun im' qerpercilalriit?
How do they make it again?
Qerpercilallruukut whitefish meluk, cali-am passiluku.
We would make crushed whitefish roe ice cream out of whitefish roe, also crushing it.
Passirraarluku-ll' tua-i kavirliit iciw' cali-ll' passiluki.
Then after crushing it, we would also crush, you know, the cranberries.
Passiurluki tua-i camek avuqangsaarpek'naku.
We crushed them without adding anything.
Mak'aq tau͡gaam caliaqumanaqtuuq. Nallunritan?
But salmon egg ice cream takes a lot of work. Do you know about it?
Avani qerpertaugaqameng ima tanem yogurt-aacetun ayuqelalriit?
When they were made into crushed whitefish roe ice cream back then, wouldn't they be like yogurt?
Ii-i, qerpertaq-llu tua-i tauna camek avungssagaunaku.
Yes, and they wouldn't add anything to that crushed roe ice cream.
Passiluku, passirraarluku-llam tua-i au͡gkut nuyarngalnguut au͡garraarluki.
Crush it, then after crushing it, after taking out those things that look like hair
Tua-i-ll' qivirluk' cali passiluki kavirlit.
Then add berries and crush the cranberries.
Passiurarraarluku akulluku, saarraliraqluku.
After crushing it, mix it, adding sugar.
Qerpertaq-qaa melugmek ilangqertuq?
Does crushed roe ice cream have fish roe?
Meluuguq. Qerpercituut melugnek, whitefish meluk.
It is made of fish roe. They make crushed whitefish roe ice cream out of roe, whitefish roe.
Kiingan tua-i nallunritaqa, tamakunek kiingan qerpercituut.
I only know that they only make crushed whitefish roe ice cream out of those.
Tua-i-ll' iciw' fluffy-rluni. Tua-i-ll' tuaten pian taqluku.
Then, you know, it would be fluffy. Then when it became like that, they finished it.
Ner'aqluku tau͡gaam uqirluku, uqiqerluku.
But they would eat it with seal oil, a little bit of seal oil.
Yaa, quyana qanemciqallerpenek.
Well, thank you for your stories.
Taqsaqlirtukuk.
We're finally done.
Tua-i.
Stop.
Takaryugtua.
I’m shy.
Maaken-qaa makut tan’gerpiit iqvalqaci?
Did you pick these crowberries from here?
Yaa, maani last year iqvallratni.
Yes, when they picked berries here last year.
[?Neqautellruanga]-am tuar two five gallons nangluki.
[?(S)he gave me food], I think two five gallons, all of them.
Iqvaryunqeggami aipaagni piviirucami taitelallrui.
Because she loves to pick berries, she would bring them probably because she had no more room.
[?]aryunqepiartuq mom-an.
Your mom loves to [?].
Nasaurluullrani-llu-qaa tuaten malikluci ayalallruuci? (Ii-i.)
When she was a girl, would go travel together like that? (Yes.)
Tuaten nutem ayuquq [?].
That’s what [?] has always been like.
Ca tamalkuan iciw’ anglanakaa.
She finds everything, you know, enjoyable.
Ava-i-llam Fairbanks...
And recently, in Fairbanks...
Kass’atun-kiq im’uryugngalliuq?
I wonder if she can do it in English?
Kass’at niicugnirkaatnek. Mumigterrlainaryuumiitaqa pilqen.
Something for Caucasians to lsiten to. I don’t want to keep translating what you said.
Yaa, tau͡gaam unuamek [?Napaskiaq].
Yes, but [?Napaskiak] today.
[?Paskiarluteng] cakneq mingeqsartulria. Mingquk sister-aaqa-llu.
They came to sew very [?]. She and my sister sewed.
Camek?
[Sewed] what?
Grant-angelpuk...
The grant we received...