Kass’am taungvaurqai ataucim.
One Caucasian was watching them.
Caknaallratni tua-i au͡gaasqelluki.
When they were struggling, he told them to get off.
Taprarmek waten ikavet pirraarluku muragamek piluku qip’urluki tua-i, waten qip’urluku.
After placing a rope across like this, he twisted a piece of wood, twisting like this.
Caknaatellrit yugyagluteng kassuutellinilukek tau͡gaam nurullukek.
He strung them around through the many people’s [?struggles] but came short.
Amikunek clamp-arlukek Kass’am taum.
That Caucasian clamped them with hide.
Tamakut Yupiit clamp-aitellermeggni ussukcautaitellermeggni-llu.
That was back when Yupiit didn’t have clamps or nails.
Waqaa?
What is it?
Aren, allrakunka-wa... (? ak’allaurte? amllertaritaa?)
Well, my age... (How old are you now?)
Ak’allarpaunrilngua-wa wii.
I am not very old.
Kiugna Johnny Samuelson-aaq Cakayak aptaqa allrakuinek qavciuruciinek, allrakunek-wa wiinga nallunilua.
I asked Johnny Samuelson, Cakayak, his age, saying that I don’t know about counting years.
Tua-i-ll’ tuaten allrakunek amllertaniaki piaqa, "Kitak’ wiinga-ll’ tuaten allrakungqerkilii amllertalrianek."
Then when he said his age, I said to him, "Then let me be that age too."
Allrakumnek qanemcitesciigatamken.
I can’t tell you how old I am.
Nani-mi yuurtellrusit?
So, where were you born?
Yaani-gguq Kuigglugmiuni yuurtellruunga Ceńaqlirni.
They said I was born over in Kwethluk, in Ceńaqliit [Shore/Riverbank].
Qipnermiungulua-llu anglilua.
And I grew up in Kipnuk.
Ik’umek-llu tua-i neviarca’rmek tangrriiqngama Anuuraamun ullagluku aipaqsagulluku, ik’umek ika-i aipa’urlumnek.
And when I had fallen in love with a young lade across there, I went to her in Anuuraaq and married her, my wife across there.
Neviarcaraullerpeni waten ayagyuallerpeni elpetun tangnirqellruuq kegginaa
As you are a young lady, she had a pretty face like you
Aqlikarangqellruami-llu Yugtarnek pilianek.
Also because she hand handmade Yup’ik earrings.
Nutaan-qaa Yugtarnek? (Yaa.)
Should we move on to Yup’ik things? (Yaa.)
Ii-i, kitak’ tua-i nutaan alerquastekma imum Yugtarnek alerquutek’lallemnek qanemciqaqernaurtua.
Okay, let me tell a story about what my instructor taught me about Yup’ik instructions.
Taktuarpassiyaagmek qalarqurallerkaqa qessayagutaqa.
I’ve become disinclined to speak for too long.
Ellangeqarraallemni imkut qanrutetullruatnga umyuartungnaqlua-gguq usvitungnaqlua yuukilii.
When I was growing up, they would tell me to try to live life with an alert and wise mind.
Tua-i-llu angliriama tarricaurcama maani, ikamranun-llu maligucaurcama qanrutnauraatnga waten:
Then when I had grown and started traveling and going with them on sleds, they would tell me this:
Atam-gguq piyaureskuma, unangyaureskuma yuilqurmiutarnek imarpiim-llu unkuum piinek
They said that when I am able, and I start catching animals from the wilderness and down from the ocean
Amirkaq-gguq una atauciq qemangqaurqumku atam-gguq ilangelarniartuq, kiituani-gguq qayangua tua-i.
If I hold on to this one hide, there will be more, until eventually I have a kayak.
Tuamtellu-gguq pavani yuilqumi imarmiutarmek wall’u tevyulimek unangekuma
Then they said that if I catch a mink or muskrat in the wilderness inland
Akia-gguq atam qemangqaurqumku egmianun tunevkenaku
They said that if I hold on to the other side without immediately giving it away
Carrarmun-gguq atam nutaan kinguqvaarni ilakangkan tunkumku piluaqerniartua.
They said that if I have a little bit and there is more later, it will be good if I give it them.
Imkut tang cap’akit makut ayuqniarutkellrukenka
You see, I desired these shoes
Kass’at cap’akiutait qerrulliit-llu makut nutem taqumalriit lumarracuarauluteng.
These Western shoes, and these pants that are pre-made out of fabric.
Tan’gaurluullgutenka au͡gkut aatateng Kass’arqaartelluteng tekitaqata cap’akirluteng, qerrulligluteng lumarracuarnek [?].
When the fathers of my fellow boys returned after going to the city, they would have shoes, and fabric pants [?].
Kamilarma tua-i qerruliyuitellruunga-ll’ kiagmi neqlillerni pikailama.
I would be barefoot, and would not wear pants in the summer at fish camp because I didn’t have any.
Inarteng’e’rma tua-i qavarniiteteullruunga ayuqniarluki tuaten ayuqaitnek pingqeqeryugyaaqlua.
Though I would go to bed, I would not be sleepy because I desired what they had.
Maa-i watuam nalliini ik’um pilugulitullruyaaqekiinga.
Now, [my wife] across there used to make me skin boots.
Qessayagutanka nat’rait tang tua-i makut qurrayirnaqsuata qanikcarmi.
I’ve started rejecting them because their soles are too slippery on snow.
Ukiyugluteng tuaten.
They get holes too.
Tua-i waten kiularaqa:
I respond to her like this:
"Waniw’ tua-i makut cap’akit ayuqniarutkessiyaallruamki cuculuki atungnaq’laranka tua-i cap’akit makut."
"Because I coveted these shoes too much, wanting them too, I try to use these shoes."
Au͡g’um-llu alerquastek’lallma iliita arnam tangvaurarraarlua uluraqkiinga:
And after one of the women who instructed me watched me, she would [?say] to me:
"Umyugailkuvet, umyugailkuvet ilavnek ayuqniallren egmiuciiqan
"If you are mindless, if you are mindless, you will go forward coveting your peers
"Ilaten atu’urkameggnek teguqerrartengraata."
"Though your peers take what they need."
Tua-i umyugaitelliniama ilanka teguqerrartengraata ayuqniarumallruanka.
Since I was mindless, I coveted my peers though they took [what they needed].
Tau͡gaam tang irniama iliitnek au͡g’umek arcaqerlua cangayulalrianga.
But, you see, I feel especially displeased with one of my children.
Makut maa-i akingukarani check-at quyurquranritlinikai.
Apparently, he’s not saving what money he gets through checks.
Akingukarani check-at imarkilengraata quyurqurquniki
If he saves what money he gets through even small checks
Amllerikata tua-i snuukuuq akilicugngariyaryalliniluku.
When they accumulate, he’d be bale to pay for a snow machine.
Massiinaq-llu levaaq akilicugngayalliniluku.
And he’d be able to pay for a boat motor.
Anirtima qanrutaitkut
It’s no wonder they tell us
Akikaar-gguq kiturtelluku egmianun kiturtelluku tun’urluku kipusviit iluatni canek aturanek
They said that passing money by, immediately passing money by to whatever is in the stores
Cucullerput maligtaquurassiyaagluku umyuarput kiturtelluki-gguq akikaaraput tamakut aklungengaitukut.
If we follow our minds whims on whatever we want and pass money by on those, we will not have [important] things.
Angyangengaunata-llu-gguq akitulriamek, massiinangengaunata-llu-gguq akitulriamek.
They said we wouldn’t get an expensive boat, or an expensive motor.
Taangamek-llu-gguq mer’atukumta akitulriamek aklumek aturngaunata.
They also said that if we abuse alcohol, we will not have expensive clothes.
Akusrarutekngamteki-gguq tamakut atu’urkamteńun navrucaryaaqluki.
They said it’s because we use those for mischief, what we would trade for what we need.
Maa-i nutaan waten angukara’urluurcama tangvagaqa tamana qanruyutellerput.
Now that I’m an old man, I’m seeing that traditional wisdom that was passed down to us.
Picimegcetun au͡gkut alerquagiyuitelliniut.
The people back then evidently did not give baseless instruction.
Atullmeggnek tau͡gaam ellaita alerquagitulliniut, ciumteńi atullmeggnek.
Instead, they instruct us on things they’ve experiences, what they’ve experienced before us.
Iliin-llu picurlallerteng aasaqevkenaku, atuusqevkenaku inerquutaqluku picurlallerteng wangkutnun.
And some didn’t keep their mistakes to themselves, but admonished us against committing their mistakes.
Una-am Min’garalria maani qasgimi qanengssaara’rqan niicugniaqamni qanlartuq
When I listen to Min’garalris here in the steam houses, he says
Angutmek-gguq tan’gaurluullermini tangvallruuq, Qinarmiunguuq Min’garalria, wagg’uq uumek Aassitugarmek
He said that he watched a man when he was a boy, Min’garalria is from Qinaq, someone they called Aassitugaq.
Nulirra-wa Marayill’er, qetunraak-wa Nasqunaraankuk, Panigassa’ar, Ayimquutaq-llu.
His wife was Marayill’er, and their sons were Nasquna’ar, Panigassa’ar, and Ayimquutaq.
Tua-i-gguq tang angun tangvallrani ca tua-i picuitkacagaryaaqelria, imarpigmi-ll’ unani piliqsuunani tua-i.
He said that that man he watched was not lucky in hunts, and he wouldn’t catch a lot down in the ocean.
Nunamiuni-gguq tau͡gaam tua-i uitaaqluni. Nunamiunguluni.
Instead, he said that he would be in landlacked places. He lived on the land.
Tevyulit-gguq, imarmiutaat, melqulegtani allrakurtaarluni amllerni qemangqatulliniluki.
He said that every year for a long time, he would keep muskrats, minks, and other fur-bearing animals.
Angyaicuunani-gguq tau͡gken qayaicuunani-ll’ imkunek amirkanek amilegnek, angyat-llu maklagnek amilget.
However, he said that he always had a boat, and always had a kayak made of seal skin, and those seal skin boats.
Angyaicuunani-gguq.
He said he always had a boat.
Tamakut-gguq tamaa-i unangkengarani qemangqalliniamiki pikanrurtaqata angyarkanun tun’aqluni, qayarkanun-llu tun’aqluki.
He said that because he kept whatever he caught, he would sell them for boats and sell them for kayaks when he had enough.
Qanrutetullruitkut, "Yuungnaquralriit-gguq nulirqelriit Kass’artaitellrani imumi, atiita ikamracualleraak makuk taqkunikek
They would tell us, ’Back when a married couple made their own living when there were no Caucasians, if he finished their fathers small sled
"Qanikciurun-llu muragaq taqkuniu, piqertuutacualler-llu qel’kekuniu, cikuliurun-llu
"And if he finishes a wooden shoever, and holds on to a small axe, and an ice chisel
"Tua-i-gguq teguyarangqerciquq tauna family-t ata’urluat arrsaunge’rmi."
"They will be able to have things, even if that family’s poor father is poor."
Neqkarcuun-llu-gguq qalu quarruugnek unangetuli qemangqakuniu
He also said that if he keeps that fishing dipnet that catches sticklebacks
Unarcianek-llu-gguq taluyitukuni neqkanek unangyugngalrianek
And he said that if he makes fish traps out of straight-grained pieces of wood that catch fish
Imarmiutarnek-llu unangyugngalrianek taluyaruanek-gguq civcitukuni
And if he sets fishtrap-like traps to catch minks
Arrsaunge’rmi-gguq tukurlirpagtun ayuqluni family-t atatekaktni
He said that even if he’s poor, if he acts as a rich father of a family
Irniani cirivkarluki aturarrliqengraata aulukciqai pinirillrata yaavet engeliinun.
If he gives his children an abundance of things, even if they have ragged clothes, he will take care of them until they are strong enough [to do so by themseles] in the future.
Kass’artaitellrani makut maa-i qanruyutelput.
This is the traditional wisdom passed down to us before Western contact.
Tangtullruunga-llu wangkuta tua-i arrsagni ayuqemteńek.
I also used to see people who were as poor as we were.
Makut tang tua-i tan’gaurlurnek yulget carraquinermi tau͡gaam iqluluteng arrsaunguaqatullinilriit.
People who have male children and have little mistakenly believe that they are poor.
Qetenrateng makut pissuryaurtaqata melqulegcuryaurtaqata, ata’urluat tuk’uqerrnaurtut patagmek melqulek akikeggillrani.
When their sons started hunting and trapping fur bearing animals, their fathers would suddenly become rich when fur was expensive.
Unaken call’ unguvalrianek tua-i taguquringartaqameng arrsaucillrat imna tua-i nalluyagutnaqluni, ayuqnianarqaqluteng tau͡gaam.
Also, when they start bringing in animals down from the ocean, we forget that they are poor, and instead want to be like them.
Atameggnek aulukestekegciaqameng unangkengait tamakut kiturcetevkenaki amlleriluki tau͡gaam tun’arkauluki piaqameng.
When they have fathers who take care of them well, and they do not pass by what they had caught, but instead sell them.
Tuamtell’ qanernaurtut, "Anngaqelriit-gguq ukut family-t waten nukalpiat tallimauyaaqeciqut
And then they would say, "There may be five brothers in this family who are great hunters
"Una-llu-gguq cali nulirqelriik atauciuyaaqeciquk qetunraak
"And this married couple may only have one son
"Uum-gguq qetunraagnek taukut ayuqniarluki anngaqelriit talliman nukalpiat qessalertevkenani
"If the couple’s son wishes to be like those five brothers who are great hunters and is not lazy
"Nalluatgun inglukluki pingnatukuni ukut-gguq pitacirciqai talliman nukalpiat."
"If he competes without their knowledge by subsisting, he will become as great as those five great hunters."
Talliman-gguq nukalpiat nalluatni inguklerkaat qacignarquq. Nuvkutaagutetuut-gguq ukut anngaqellriit.
They say that it’s easy to compete against great hunters without their knowledge. They say that brothers argue.
"Pi-gguq kuvyayaqili." "Wii kuvyayaryuumiitua." "Pi-gguq muragcuqili." "Wii muragcuryuumiitua."
"Tell him to fish with a drift net." "I don’t want to fish with a gill net." "Tell him to gather wood." "I don’t want to gather wood."
Maa-i-gguq makut qacignarqutiit ayagnerat iquat.
This is what they mean about how it’s easy.
Uum-gguq atauciunge’rmi ayuqeliyugngai ingluliluki.
They say that even one person can compete with them on their level.
Makut maa-i qanruqurauteput ellangyugallemteńi Kass’anek makunek piitellermeggni.
These are what we were told in our early childhoods when there were no Caucasians.
Neviarcaraat-ll’ makut uingeksailnguut angliyartullrat maliggluku ayuqucirtuutnek nutaan patutullruit inerquutnek.
And these young ladies who were not married, as they got older, they gave them a lot of instructions and admonishments.
Agurrluk’-llu yuut tangvanrilkiitni nukalpianun unugmi narukitautesqevkenaki inerquraqluki.
And they would admonish them against ever meeting great hunters at night while people aren’t watching.
Wangkuta-llu unugmi neviarcaraat akuliitnun narukitautesqevkenata.
They also told us not to meet young ladies at night.
Alegyagulluku-gguq nasaurluq yugnek tangvagtaitnitekluta kemga agtuqumteggu wangkutnek-gguq tuquciiqukut.
They said that if we become confident and take a girl because people aren’t watching, we will bring death upon ourselves.
Nulirruarluta tua-i.
We "pretend to have wives."
Tamaa-i tam’ alingnarcarluku qanrutkaat.
They talked about that to have us fear it.
Arnat-llu makut enemi agleraqata qanrutnaurait, "Kitak’ waknirnerk ayagluten tua-i aglertuten.
And when girls had their first menstruations at home, they would tell them, "Now, from here, you menstruate.
"Nulirtuqsailnguq yun’erra’ar tan’gaurluq anuqiin asguakun agurrluk’ kituryaqunaku, waten avaggun tau͡gaam uqrakun.
"Never pass an unmarried young man, a boy, upwind from him, but over there downwind like this.
"Tepen-gguq atam narluku narumangniaraa. Assiiruyutekaa-gguq kiituan."
"If he smells your emanations, he will get addicted to it. Eventually, it will ruin him."
Tuaten-qaa qanrucuitellruatgen? (Qanrutaqluta.)
Would they tell you that? (They would tell us.)
Au͡gna-q’ elitaqenritan?
Don’t you recognize that?
Qang’a, elitaqkacagarluku.
No, I recognize it completely.
Tepii-gguq narluku.
They say he smells her emanations.
Tua-ll’ waniwa mat’umek ak’allarmek-llu ayuqucirtuutmek qanqaasqaqatnga umyuamkun kiulartua
Then now, when they tell me to speak about old traditional instructions, I reply in my mind
"Kingurautuq man’a ayuqucirtuutellerput wangkuta avani Kass’artangvailgan. Kingurautuq."
"Our traditional instruction back before Western contact is late. It’s late."
Makut tang tua-i tangvallrenka makut eyinqigutet ayagyuat Kass’at tau͡gaam mat’umun tua-i yuungnaquciatnun ekelriit.
You see, the young children of the next generation that I see are now getting into the Western way of life.
Man’a-llu Yupiit ellangutait aanameng aatameng-llu qaneryaraat Yugtaq language-aaq man’ Kass’at apqiit temciqutaqluku tua-i.
They also make fun of the Yupik language that Yupiit, their mothers and fathers, grew up with, what they call a language in English.
Qitevterrlainaryaraq tau͡gaam cucuyagulluku tua-i.
Instead, they choose to speak only in English.
Taumek man’a maa-i ayuqucirturillerkaqa ayuqucirtuutellemteńek au͡gkunek qalartellerkaqa
That’s why when I should be instructing on our traditional instructions, and speaking on them
Kingurausngaluku tua-i umyuartequsngakeka. Tengrukevkenaku-llu ayuqucirtuutekelqa.
I started thinking that it’s too late. Neither am I excited to teach what I was instructed.
Yuum iliin niicugnirraarlua uluqunia pegciiqngaku tamana qanemcikelqa qigcikevkenaku.
Because after some people listen to me, if he looks away, he will drop it without respecting my stories.
Kass’aq tau͡gaam tangerquniu nutaan ayuqucilinqiggluni quuyurmi qitevvluni ullagciqaa.
But when he sees a Caucasian, he will change, smile, and go to him speaking English.
Ayuqucirtuutellrenka-ll’ au͡gkut nalluyagulluki tua-i umyuaqevkenaki.
And he forgets what I instructed, does not remember them.
Wangkuta tau͡gken au͡gkut ava-i qanrutkelput egmianun-gguq camek akikuine’rmek melqulegmek tegumiangekumta kiturcequavkenaku.
But what we were told was that if we come into possession of fur that is worth some money, not to let it pass by.
Qemangqauraqaqerlaut-gguq ilangnercirluku.
They said that we should keep it until there’s more.
Atam-gguq ilangekuni nutaan tunkumteggu carrarnek amllernek ikayuutekamtek unangutekniarput.
They said that if there’s more and we sell a lot of even little things, we will get helpful things from them.
Wall’u qanrutaanga au͡g’um caqerlua ap’ama iliita
Or, one time, one of my grandfathers said to me
"Kitak’ maklaarcaureskuvet atam kiturceterrlainarpek’naki atam.
"Now, when you start hunting seals, do not keep letting them pass you by.
"Amirkaq atauciq qemangqaurquvgu atam piinanermini ilangluni, kiituan qayarkanrurciiquq."
"If you keep even one hide, there will come more, until eventually you have enough to make a kayak."
Watuam nalliini imarmiutaat akikeggiameng
Since mink skins are worth less these days
Imarmiutaat tau͡gaam melqulget akiitgun kipusvigmi amirkat tua-i qacignariluteng melqulegnek nav’errluki.
It’s become easy to trade mink skins in stores, trading in fur.
Alqunaq tua-i qayarkanrurpallagaqluteng tua-i.
They suddenly get enough for kayaks.
Mat’umek maa-i qayartangnanrirluteng au͡g’umek ciuliartarmek qalartellerkaqa tengrukenri’rqa.
Since they’ve stopped using kayaks, I am no longer excited to talk about our ancestors’ ways.
Tangvagluku makut, ukut-llu wii ayuqucirtuq’nganka irnianka tua-i
Watching these, including my children whom I instruct
Irniama tuar waniw’ ukut qetunrama ayuqucirtuutet tamakut ayuqucirturiyaaqaqama piksaileng’e’rmeng tailuteng tuar qanqa patulaqiit.
When I teach those traditional instructions, even though my children, my sons, do not [physically] do it, it seems they come and close my mouth.
Au͡gna ayuqucirtuutnek maligtaquingnaqelqa ayuqelinripakaatgu ukut irniama tua-i alerquaqengama.
It’s because my children whom I teach do not follow those traditional teachings.
Tamaa-i tamana puqialutekluku.
That’s why I feel inarticulate.
Ciuliartarmek ayuqucirturiyung’e’rma tua-i mat’umek Kass’at apqiitnek late-aartuq.
Though I want teach our ancestors ways, it is late, as they say in English.
Tutgaraanka-ll’ ukut iliini quyungqaqa’arqata ayuqucirturraarluki aptelaranka, "Au͡gna-qaa ayuqucirtulqa taringarci?"
And sometimes, after I teach my grandchildren when they’re gathered, I ask them, "Do you understand my instruction?"
"Ung’alu," taringenritaatnga-gguq Yugtun qalarulluki ayuqucirtuutelput.
"Ung’alu," they say they didn’t understand what I had been taught when I speak to them in Yup’ik.
Tua-i tang qanelngulrianga. Waten pitaqatartua.
Well, I’m tired of speaking. This is all I’ll say.
KYUK-t kiugkut qanemcilriit cangirnaqluteng qavcirrarnek Yup’igtun qanqalartut.
I want more when they tell a few stories upriver in KYUK in Yup’ik.