Hello, testing. Testing. Are you getting any reading at all?
Tau͡gaam quyanaqluteng taukut.
But we are grateful to them.
Pitarkam unakellerkaakun tamakut cuculuki ayuqniarpegnata ilamteńek nukalpiaruyuumirluta.
We should not be jealous of or envy those around us, wanting to be good hunters who catch a lot.
Umyuarteqerkaugut [?] niisnginarluku.
We must ponder and listen to the [?].
Am I doing the right thing to him?
If we don’t ask questions why he or another or the best of your friends...
...avoided from a good friend or parent or wife or son.
So, we have to ask questions if we are...
...in their mind, to their trial and errors in time of life.
To where a person that scrutinizes the other people and their elders that have...
...can gain that knowledge to where, just lot of these elders just...
You will never know what you’re [?], the trials and errors that you are doing
But you do not understand thinking you’re doing the right thing up until you ask questions.
What led her to [?], then left her on that island to be drowned still remains to be seen.
So, based on that story, you have to...
...want to do to seek the answers.
Only through questions through your elders can you get knowledge and wisdom on how you’re going to lead your own life.
Only through quesionts through your elders can you get knowledge and wisdom on how you’re going to lead your own life.
To take an example, you young people like to hunt.
You just can’t go out there and...
[?] how you have to butcher it, you have to seek knowledge from your elders.
And if you don’t ask any questions, seeing none of it, you just...
And if oyu don’t ask any questions, seeing none of it, you just...
...imkuciuluni, tua-i-wa eneqak’ngaqluku man’a qaneryaraq qulirauguq.
...it’s, you know, I remember this traditional wisdom as a legend.
Mat’um nalliini maa-i eneqak...
Remembering it now...
Waniw’ umyuarteqlemni Agayutem tauna ikayullrua quliraq.
In my opinion, God helped with that legend.
Waten qanllruuq: "Aren atama ima tanem, apa’urluma ima tanem..."
He said this: "Didn’t my father, didn’t my grandfather..."
...naugartesqellrukii.
...wanted it to grow.
Tua-i-ll’ nekevraartuq cugg’agpak naugarrluni, avayai yagglu...
And then the spruce tree with the big [?] grew, its branches raised...
...luni tua-i.
...it [?].
Tua-i tauna Agayutem ikayuraa, ikayullrua.
God helped that.
Maa-i mat’um nalliini, tua-i-wa imumirpak wangkuta...
These days, well, we have always...
Apa’urluan taum umyugaa cagnitaciani tauna nekevraartuq nauguq Agayutem pisqeńgani.
As his grandfather was struggling in his mind, that spruce tree grew as God commanded.
Tua-i tuaten pitaluku iqua nallunayukluku qanenritaqa.
That’s all, and I’ve not said the ending in case you may not know it.
There’s another side to it.
At the very last request.
A thought came to this woman, but her grandfather...
And that’s where Christianity comes in.
If you truly ask from the bottom of your heart, you’ll get the answer of what you requested.
Kituusit camiunguluten-llu?
Who are you and where are you from?
Tununermiunguunga, ategnqerrlua Carl, Carl Flynn.
I’m from Tununak, and my name is Carl, Carl Flynn.
IRA-ni Council-at, IRA Council-aarulua Tununermi.
I’m a part of the IRA Council in Tununak.
Tua-i wanigga...
Now...
Really? IRA Council? (Yes.)
Yaa, kitak’ qanemciyaram ava-i qanrutkellerpetun qaillun ayagnillrua?
Okay, so with telling stories as you’ve said, how did it start?
Cali-llu ava-i-w’ tua-i ciuqlikacaarmek qanllerpenek cali qanrutqerkut.
Also, please tell us the very first thing you said again.
Pulenglluku, pulngarrluku au͡gna qanelqa.
I’m going to repeat what I said.
Una wanigga quliraam ayagnera, ayagneqapiara
The true beginning of this legend
Ukanirpak elluarrluku qanrutkestaitetullruuq avani.
There was never a compeltely accurate telling back then.
Quliraam ayagnillra yaaqsigtuq cakneq waken wanigg’ ernermek.
The beginning of a legend is very far from this day.
Nuna mamkitellruuq ak’a tamaani.
The land was thin a long time ago.
Yucuayagaat-llu tamakut tamaani pitullruluteng ak’a nuna mamkitellrani.
And the little people existed back then when the land was thin a long time ago.
Cali-llu apqait aipait egacuayiit makut cali yugtun ayuqelriit kesianek paivngaluteng
And their companions that they call egacuayiit that look human were always common
Quliraam tamaa-i civuani.
Before the time of that legend.
Wanigga watua qanerturallruunga waten:
Now, I’ve been saying this:
Puqikuvet, puqilriarukuvet, ayuqucin tamalkuan nallunrilkuvgu, yuum-llu ayuqucirkaa assilria nallunrilkuvgu
If you are smart, if you know the entirety of what you’re like, and if you know how a good person should be
Tua-i nerucengaaqngamken qanrutamken.
I’m telling you because you’re my [?great-great-great-grandchild].
Quliramek taqucugngauten yuum elluarrluni egilratkaanek yuk’egciluni.
You can make a legend that will help a person live well as a good person.
Quli’irmek niiskuvet qanerturallran nalliikun akurturyaqunaku.
If you hear a legend, do not accept it as you hear it.
Elpenun tau͡gaam tusnganguarturtelluku kesianek qanerturallra tamalkuan taringengnaqutekekiu taumun elpenun.
Instead, pretend that everything he is talking about is relevent to yourself, and try to understand it as it applies to you.
Umyuartukuvet tua-i waten umyuartequ’urciquten: "Wii qanrutaanga."
If you’re wise, you will think like this: "He is telling it to me."
Uucetun qanerturallratun quliraq tamana cucukekuvgu assilriarukan
If you strive to be like that legend he is talking about if it is good
Qanerturallra elpet ayuquciqsuumirluku elpenun tusnganguartelluku quliraq ayuquskiu.
If you want to be like what he is talking about, treat that legend as if it applies to yourself.
Cali-llu quliraam ilii, quliraam ilii, quliraat ilait yuum ayuqucianun tusngaut.
Also, some legends apply to what people are like.
Anglanaqluteng ucurnaqluteng-llu.
They are fun and amazing.
Tau͡gaam ucurnaqluteng anglanarqelriit yuum ayuqucianun tusnganrilkata
But if the fun and amazing ones are not related to what people are like
Tamakut calliggluki assilriarakun, assilriara tau͡gaam akurtuumakiu kemegpenun ircaqurpenun itertelluku
Discard those and only accept the good things into your flesh and heart
Ayuquciqnaluku elpet piyaureskuvet ukaniku.
So that you will become like that when you are able in the near future.
Piyaureskuvet, allakarpet yuungnaqengkuvet ayuquciqnaluku cucukekiu.
When you are able and you start trying to live your own life, choose to be like that.
Quliraam ilii arcaqalriaruuq yugmun tusngallermini.
Some legends especially apply to people.
Yuum ilii, yuum iliin wii ilama, nakmiin acama qulirillruakut wangkuta anngaqelriani pingayuni quliriarkaqngamikut.
One person, one of my relatives, my own paternal aunt told us three brothers legends because she was to tell us legends.
Anglaniluta niicugniluku. Anglanilua niicugnillruaqa.
We had fun listening to her. I had fun listening to her.
Taqngami-llu, iquklican quliraq tauna
And when she was done, when that legend was over
Atakurrlainarmi tau͡gaam caarkaunrirqameng inartaqameng wanigga qavarpailegmeng quliritullruut.
They only told legends in the evening when they had no more chores to do, before going to sleep when they had gone to bed.
Quliraq-llu tamana qavautekluku unugpak tayima.
And they fell asleep to that legend all night.
Tamaa-i quliritullruut yugmun tut’evkangnaqluku tau͡gaam, yuum ayuqucianun.
They would tell legends only as they applied to people, what people should be like.
Quliraq tauna acagglugairutma qulirikiikut
My late paternal aunt told us that legend
Taqngami-llu, iquklicamiu qanerluni, angu-gguq wangkuta quliraqsaqunata ilamteńun.
When she was done and finished that story, she said that we should never tell those legends to our peers.
Inerqurluta quliraqesqevkenaku ilamteńun.
She admonished us against telling that legend to our peers.
Wangkuta tau͡gaam, pikesqelluku wangkutnun.
Instead, she said that it should be ours.
Tangrriu.
You see?
Quliraq man’a qumlinarqenrituq.
A legend like this is not a cause for irritation.
Qangkun pirpaumiuq. Arcaqalriarumiuq.
It is also something that has always been. It is also important.
Arcaqalriarumiuq quliraq man’a.
A legend like this is also important.
TV-nek tanglartuci. TV-t kesianek atakuneq tamalkuan tangvalaraci.
You watch TV. You watch TV every evening.
Wii TV-t piyaurcata TV-t tangvalaranka anglanilua.
When TVs started to come around, I enjoy watching TV.
Yaatiikun-llu, anglanillma yaatiikun wangnun tusngavkarluki.
And aside from that, aside from having fun, I apply them to myself.
Ayuquciqsunailnguq ayuquciqsuumiinaku calligtellriatun ayuqutek’la’rqa.
I do not want to be like what people should not be like and discard it.
Ayuquciqsunarqelria-llu wiinga teguluku.
And I take upon what a person should be like.
Wangnun ayuqucimnun elliluku ayuqnianarqelria.
I apply what a person should be like to myself.
Qanemcim quliraq niiskuvgu niicugnikiu cakneq, elpenun yuvriutekluku tuaten.
If you hear a story or legend, listen to it completely, and compare yourself to it.
Ayuqucin nallunritan kingunren au͡gna pellulleq.
You know what you were like in the past.
Kingunerpenun elliluku, elpenun elliluku ayuquciqluku niicugniurqiu.
Apply it to your past, apply it to yourself as you listen to it.
Tuani-wa kiimelamegnuk qanrutarkaqngamken makunek ellangcarturarkaqngamken ellangcarturamken.
Since we are alone and I must talk to you and give you lessons, I am giving you lessons.
Camek-llu anuraqutmek caunii.
And I have no such restraints to do so.
Ii-i.
I see.
Is that...
Yaa, amlleriuq qanemcikan.
Yes, you’ve told enough.
Atam quliraam ilakuggaanek niitellrunrilkevnek catailngurmek wani cali ilaqernaurqa.
Look, let me add a missing part of the legend that you haven’t heard.
Quliraq nulirqelriik.
The legend is about a married couple.
Nulirra tauna ellmini canganaunani arnauguq, arnaulliniuq.
The wife is a woman that did not consider herself objectionable.
Irnianglutek-llu mikelngucuarmek.
And they bore a small child.
Arnaq tauna ellmini cangaunani, uiminun angutminun cangakutaunani.
That woman didn’t consider herself objectionable, and had no qualms with her husband.
Angutiin tau͡gken cangayutii amllerrluni taumun nuliaminun.
THe man however, had many qualms with his wife.
Angutiin-llu nalluvkarluku tamana cangakutni nuliaminun, elliin-llu nalluluku canganarqucini.
And the man didn’t let his wife know of his qualms, and she didn’t know that she was objectionable.
Erucim iliini ayautaa qayakun unayaqluku.
At the dawning of one day, he invited her to travel with a kayak.
Qikertamun-llu mermi imarpigmi mer’em patutukiinun elliluku qapilaarrluni, clam-alluni.
And then he left her on an island in the sea that would be covered with water, and she dug for clams, qapilaat.
Anglaniluni tua-i tauna nulirra nunaniryugluni piinanrani piqertuq angutii una ayalria uterrluni.
As the wife was having fun and enjoying herself, she realized that her husband was traveling away going back home.
"Au͡gsuurluuq," alangaallagluni, "au͡gsuuq, waqaa tua-i unitarpenga?"
"Hey you," she was surprised, "hey, are you leaving me?"
"Tua-i canganarqucin qangvaq aipaqsaguqaanerpenek, aipaqsaguqaanemegnuk
"With all of the qualms I’ve had with you since we married some time ago
"Canganarqucin akiliqurarru tuani.
"Pay for all of your objectionable ways there.
"Nangtarpenga umyuamkun. Aipaqsuumiirutamken."
"You are tormenting my mind. I do not want to be married to you anymore."
Unilluku nalitukiinun mer’em.
He left here where the water would cover it.
Tua-i tauna-qaa tua-i cucukluku ayuqucingqerciquten elpet?
Would you envy and choose to be like her?
Canganaqsukluten umyuarteqkuvet elders-aat ullagluki apqauqiki.
Ifyou think you’re objectionable, go to the elders and ask them questions.
Apqaulaqiki. Apqaurutkairupailegpet arnassagarciquten.
Ask them questions. Before you run out of questions, you’ll become an old woman.
Tuaten tua-i pitalii.
Let me stop there.
Quyana.
Thank you.
Quyanaqvaa. (Amllertuq-qaa?)
Thank you so much. (Is that enough?)
Ii-i.
Yes.
Yaa, quyana.
Okay, thank you.