That’ll be useful.
Right, we’re ready.
Okay, for the record, speaking to James Guy, Kuiggluk.
Okay, for the record, speaking to James Guy, Kwethluk.
Imkut-qaa, imkut-qaa qasgimi uitalallret angullrunritaten?
Were you born in time to see those who lived in the community house?
Anguqallruanka.
I was born in time to see them.
Qanengssaaraliyatullrulua-llu maqinerra’arqata.
And I always went to listen to them speaking
right after they took fire baths.
Qanengssaaraitnek angukara’urluut,
wangni tua-i angukara’urluut tan’gaurlucuarama,
niicugniuryarturluki.
I would go listen to the words of the old men
the men I thought of as old because I was a small boy.
Tua-i anglanakluku qanengssaarallrat.
Picirraatun tua-i qanengssaarnaurtut.
I thought it was fun when they spoke.
They would speak as they were.
Imkut tua-i nallunrilnge’rmegteggu-llu qanengssaa
ilameng niicugniurnauraat.
And even when they knew what he was talking about
his peers would listen to him.
Tua-i-llu ala’arcan qanrulluki iqlutun piqerniluku.
And then when he made a small mistake,
they would tell him that he had made a mistake.
Yaa.
Yes.
Canek qalartelallruat?
Whatpl did they used to talk about?
Piciatun imkunek angalkullruarnek, angalkurrarnek.
Various things, those who were shamans, shamans with some power.
Tamakunek qanengssaararaqluteng aqvautaalallritnek tuaten.
They would talk about those, even how they held running races.
Curulallritnek-ll’ anguyiit
anguyangqetulliniameng nutem pitgaqulluteng.
And how warriors attacked,
because there had always been warriors that shot each other with arrows.
Tamakunek qanengsaarnaurtut.
They would talk about those.
Ii-i.
I see.
Atam…
You see…
Tamakut-qaa elitnaurvigtun ayuqelallruut qasgit?
Were those community houses like schools?
Elitnaurvigtun ayuqeksaitut.
They weren’t like schools.
Cali waten unani pinerrluga’artellria
apqemteńek yuut pissuutaitnek teglek’alleq
Also, when someone misbehaved like this down there
what we call those who’ve stolen people’s tools
Maqinermek taq’aqameng ukut tegganret aqvavkarnauraat
tauna tuaten picurlakarniluku nunameggni wani.
When these elders were done taking fire baths, they would get him
telling him that there had been trouble in their village.
Council-aaqeryugluku, tua-i kitugarcugluku.
They wanted to try him, to assuage [the situation].
Tua-i-ll’ aqvaluku tua-i tauna
nutaan quyurmeng inerqurrluku tuaten pinqigtesqevkenaku
And then they brought him, then admonished him together not to do that again.
Tamana teglegyaraq assinritniluku.
Saying that stealing is bad.
Tua-i tuaten takurqautelaraatnga.
That’s what they revealed to me.
Cali wiinga uksuq aipaqa-llu
waten-wa tua-i piniarqaanemnek calirpagciigalama
Also, my wife and I last winter,
because I can’t work very hard ever since I became weak
Sulunaucetellruukuk ukuk yuugka qanruqu’urlukek kiak.
We2 would get salted fish last summer telling my children2.
Tua-i-ll’ uksuq aqvayaaqerpuk pingayuungata sulunat.
And then last winter, we2 went to get it
because there were three [containers of] salted fish.
Malruk tayima, una-llu puckam avga cali,
avga tayima tegulliniluku, tua-i carraq tau͡gaam.
Two of them, and half of this barrel,
someone had taken half, and only a little [was left].
Tua-i ilulliqsaaqua uterrngailata. Qanqaqsaitua.
I was sad because they wouldn’t be returned. I didn’t say anything.
Taumek watua waniw’ qaneryukapigtua yugnun niiciiqngatgu.
That’s why I really want to say something now
because people will hear it.
Waniw’ waten ayuquq,
This is what it’s like,
Nutem-llu imkuni alerquutni imkuni Ten Commandments,
taukuni ekumaluni: “Thou shall not steal,” “Teglegyaqunak.”
It’s also in those ancient commandments, [the] Ten Commandments,
it’s in there: “Thou shall not steal,”
“Teglegyaqunak.”
Yaa, taumek waniw’ nuna tamalkuita yuit inerquranka
Yes, that’s why I’m admonishing all of the people of the land now
Inerquryaaqanka-wa tua-i yuum pianek tangengraata
wall’u neqlillernun tekitengraata pisqevkenaki, tegutesqevkenaki.
I’m admonishing them that even if they see a person’s things
or even if they come upon fish camps not to take anything.
Tau͡gaam waten tegucukata pisqelluki:
But if they want to take anything, do this:
Kalikarrarmek igaqerluku tuaten pitalriamek
tegutniluku yuk tauna tuaken, at’ni-llu elliluku.
Write on a piece of paper that a person is taking that much
and write his name.
Tuaten pikan taum yua quyaciquq.
If [s]he does that, the owner will be grateful.
Waten-llu qanerluni:
“Enulliarturlulliniami-w’ tua-i tuaten nallunaunani pilria.
Quyanarquq tuaten piluni.”
[S]he will also say this:
“[S]he probably let me know because [s]he’s lacking.
I’m thankful that [s]he did that.”
Nalluvkarpek’naku yua kalikarrarkun catailengraan.
Let the owner know with a piece of paper even if [s]he’s gone.
Wiinga-llu tarranqellemni imum…
Pinky nallunritan.
And when I was young and healthy, that person…
You know Pinky.
Ingrini pagaani enullitaqama, enullitelgulaama-ll’ iliini
When I was lacking up in the mountains, because I lacked sometimes
Tekitaqamku camp-aa camek aturyung’e’rma piksaitelallruunga.
When I came upon his camp, even if I wanted to use something, I never did.
Tua-i-ll’ tangrramku qanrulluku enullit’ngerma
camp-anun tekiteng’e’rma qaillukuaqanritnilua.
And then when I saw him, I would tell him that even when I lacked
even though I came upon his camp that I didn’t touch anything.
Waten alerqularaanga:
He would instruct me like this:
Uumiku-gguq kitak’ arcaqalriamek enulliskuma
puckami-gguq taquari ekumalartut.
The next time I am lacking something important
his provisions are put inside the barrel.
Tauna-gguq ikirrluku yuarlua aturyukemnek teguskilii
He said that I should open it, look for what I need, and take it
Atqa-llu-gguq igaulluku,
tuaten-llu-gguq pitalriamek tuaken puckamek aturnilua.
And he said to write my name, and how much I’ve taken from that barrel.
Tau͡gaam wii tuaten piksaitua.
But I never did that.
Arcaqalriamek-wa tua-i enullitqapigteksailngua
I haven’t completely lacked anything important
Tarratelgullruama ayagyuarlua avani yuilqumi.
Because I always traveled in the wilderness over there when I was young.
Cali…
Also...
Makut-mi, angullruaten-qaa, angullruan-qaa imna Aavaaq?
What about these, were you born in time to see Aavaaq?
Yaa, angullruaqa.
Yes, I was born in time to see him.
Niitelartua-am, alartelallilrianga-wa niillua, angalkullraullruniluku.
I’ve heard, I’ve probably heard wrong, that he was a shaman.
Angalkuunrit’urluryaaquq.
The poor guy wasn’t a shaman.
Akleng, ii-i.
Poor guy, I see.
Angalkuunrit’urluryaaquq.
The poor guy wasn’t a shaman.
Tau͡gaam imuullruuq, yuungcarauluni, yaa.
But he was, you know, treated by a shaman [in utero], yes.
Yuungcarauvalallruat-gguq yuut.
People said that he was treated by a shaman [in utero].
Yuungcaravallagniluku tau͡gaam qanengssak’laraat.
They only say that he was treated by a shaman.
Qaillun?
How?
Yuungcaravallagluku.
That he was treated by a shaman.
Yuungnaqevkarpallagluku-wa Taqukamek napacirluku.
(Yuungcatullrullikait-wa ak’a acirluki.)
He was named Taqukaq to keep him clinging to life.
(Shamans used to treat them in utero by giving them names.)
Ellminek-qaa pillrunrituq?
He didn’t [treat] himself?
Yaa, angalkut-wa tua-i tuaten piluku.
Yes, shamans did that to him.
Taumek-gguq aurrlermini imkunek makunek naugaarnek
canegnek waten elliurturluni ner’aqan
They say that that’s why when he was crawling
when he did this, eating plants, grass
Man’a tua-i green-aarurtelalria canegtullra.
This part where he ate grass would turn green.
Aaniin-llu-gguq inerquyuunaku.
And they say that his mother never admonished him [against that].
Angalkuunrit’urlullruyaaquq tau͡gaam tuaten tua-i yuungcarauluni.
The poor guy wasn’t a shaman, but he was treated by one like that.
Makut angullruaten…
Were you born in time to see these…
Yugcetun ima reindeer-at caulalriit?
What are reindeer in Yup’ik again?
Tuntut.
(Yes.)
Yugcetun ima reindeer-at caulalriit?
Were those…
I was born in time to see them.
(Please talk about them.)
Yugcetun ima reindeer-at caulalriit?
Yes, because I liked to go with my father to mark reindeer
Yaa, tuntunek maagiyartulrianun-llu maligucunqeggama atamnun
Tunciuryarturaqata Akiacuarmun maligut’lallruunga.
I used to go with them to herd reindeer in Akiachak.
Tua-i unuakumi taglartut Akiacuarmek maagiyarturqameng.
In the morning, they would go up from Akiachuk to mark reindeer.
Can’gurpatagyugmek yaaken itercivigmun-gguq iterrluki pilarait.
They said that they would corral them from a massive meadow over there.
Tuaken-llu tua-i uss’arulluki wavet paivcivigmun-gguq.
And from there, they said that they would take them to the waiting area
so that they could look around.
Aterluteng-am tua-i casgut.
The fences had names.
Tuaken-llu tua-i paivcivigmek nutegkun iterrluki.
And from the waiting area there, they would bring them in
through the corraling path.
Taksiyaagpek’nani nutek. Iqkunani.
The corraling path wasn’t long. It was narrow.
Tuntut tua-i atauciq tamaagguirturaraqluni.
The reindeer would go through there one at a time.
Cukangnaqellriit-wa [qaill’-qaa] aarnaqluteng.
Those who were fast were dangerous.
Nang’e’rtaqluteng tuaten ilateng tutmarluki piaqluteng.
They would even suddenly stand and tread over the others.
Ataucim-llu naaqurluki.
And one person would count them.
Tua-i alarcuunani waten kalik’vagnek tegumiarluni
qayagpagaurluni.
[S]he never made a mistake, holding large papers, calling out.
Ingkut-llu tua-i cetamauluteng cali callugtet
tuaken nutegmek anelriit.
And over there, there were four wrestlers coming out of that corraling path.
[Amna] pakmaanaaraqan ingkut tua-i callugtet ingcuqernaurtut
waten akiqliqa’arrluku.
When it was overflowing over there,
the wrestlers would wait to catch them across from each other like this.
Tua-i-llu tuntum qamiqurra pugngan egmian teguqerluku,
callugluku, maagluku.
And then when its head appeared, they would take it right away,
wrestle it, and mark it.
Maagumalriit tau͡gken tua-i anevkarturluki.
However, they would let out those that were marked.
Maagumanilnguut tau͡gaam maagaqluki.
They would only mark the ones that weren’t marked.
Qaillun maagluki?
What do you mean maagluki?
Mark-arluki-wa ciutaitgun. Yaa.
Mark them on their ears. Yes.
Nuussikun?
With a knife?
Yaa, nuussikun.
Yes, with a knife.
Atam qayagpagaurtet-llu tuntut elisngaluki.
You see, the callers knew the reindeer.
Taumun, taumun yug[mun]…
[Belonging] to that person…
Avaurilkilartua.
I never forget something.
Qaterpaurpallermek-llam au͡g’umek irrilrianga.
I was amazed at that extremely white one.
Qaillun piluni man’a qaterta tuntu?
How did this reindeer get white?
Piqerluni-am tamaaggun ayagtuq nutegkun
apqiitgun nutegkun.
One day, it went through that corraling path
through what they call the nutek.
Am’um-am tekican qayagpagaa.
When it arrived, someone over there called it.
Nalluyagutenrilkeka-am waniwa qayagpallra:
I’ve never forgotten this, what he said:
“Qayaksuk’s there.”
Qayaksuum pikliniluku tauna tuntu.
That reindeer apparently belonged to Qayaksuk.
Tua-i ciutaitgun nalluyuunaki qayagaurtet.
The callers knew them by their ears.
Tuaken-llu callugvigmek ancamegteggu yaavet
And when they took them out of that wrestling area over there
Casgumun cali anlluku.
They brought it out again to the fence.
Cali-am egmian ayagturtessuunaki.
They wouldn’t let them go about right away either.
Muiqertaqan-am tauna nangneqliq casgu
When that last [area with a] fence was full
Ikirulluki tuntut imkut anevkarnaurait.
They would open them and let those reindeer out.
Nang’ngata-llu patuluku.
And they closed it when they were all through.
Tua-i free-rluki, amkut tau͡gaam taigarkat.
They freed them, except for those that were still to come.
Tua-i anglanaqluteng anglaniurallret.
It was fun watching them have fun.
Calistet calisterluteng cali camani camp-ami pinaurtut.
The workers [on the field] also had workers down in the camp.
Kenirterluteng.
They had cooks.
Kenirteteng-llu-w’ akililallikait tuntumek.
They probably paid their cooks with reindeer.
Atrarqama murilkeńaurtua imna waten tank-am avga egatiit.
When I went down, I would see that
they used half of a tank as a cooking pot.
Tuntuvik tamalkuan ek’lalliat.
They probably put the entire reindeer herd in.
Tua-lli-wa tua-i yugugaat imkut arnartuumarmeng-llu piliyatuameng
And so, because that multitude would go along with women
Utumaumalriit, irniayagiunrilnguut-wa
The [women] with less responsibility who were not taking care of children
Egalvall’er imna tank-am avga nanglaqiit yuut apiatarqameng.
The people would finish that huge pot, half of a tank, when they had lunch.
Tua-i Kass’acetun break time, lunch break time-araqluteng.
In English, they would have break time, lunch break time.
Ayuquciq-wa Kass’artailnguq.
There were no Caucasians.
Twelve kela’agluku nernariniluku.
They would say it’s time to eat at 12 o’clock.
Kiimeng-qaa taukut…
Were they the only ones…
Akiacuarmi pitullruut.
They used to in Akiachak.
Maalirnermun tau͡gaam piaqameng pikani Akulikutaq Corral,
tuani pilallruut.
But when they did it towards here up on Akulikutaq Corral,
that’s where they went.
Tau͡gaam wiinga yaaqsikluku mikcuaraungama maligucuitellruunga.
But because I thought it was far since I was small, I didn’t go with them.
Elitnauraulaama-llu-wa tamatum nalliini.
It was also because I was a student at that time.
Akiacuarmun tau͡gaam piaqata canimelan maligutaqlua.
But when they went to Akiachak, I would go along since it was close.
Tamatum-qaa nalliini tuntuviulallerpeceńi
makut imkut keglunret pilallruut?
Back when youpl herded reindeer, were there wolves?
Keglunertairucuitellruuq.
There always used to be wolves.
Keglunertaicuitellruuq qanengssakaqani old man-ama.
There were always wolves in my old man’s stories.
Tua-i waten-llu pinaurtuq:
He would say this:
“Tuntut-gguq-am ayakaulluki tuqurqilaakalliniuq, tamakut keglunret.”
“It drove the reindeer and killed one, those wolves.”
Tau͡gaam tuntutairut’ngartellrani
wavet-wa nugtartellratni government-aamun
But when the reindeer declined,
when they were taken under the governement
Tamakut tuntut governemnt-aarurtellratni
When those reindeer were taken under the government
Murilkenrillrui, murilkenrillrui.
He stopped herding, he stopped herding.
Caaqameng-llu-gguq tua-i tuntut ayalartut,
qemikun-llu tevluteng, iquani-ll’ cataunateng.
They also said that reindeer would sometimes go,
go over a hill, and they disappeared from the end.
Tamaa-i ircen’e’rnun-wa piyuk’laqait.
They think that the legendary little people took them.
Kiituani-gguq tuntut…
Eventually, they said that the reindeer…
Tuntuurtellruyaaquq all over, pau͡gna maraq, ingrit, agna-llu.
It had become covered in reindeer all over,
up in the marsh, mountains, and across there.
Tau͡gaam tuaten piluteng keglunerrlainaat nangenritait.
But that happened; wolves aren’t the only ones that depleted them.
Tamakut tau͡gaam tuaten paqritaqluteng-gguq patagmek nang’ut.
But that said that they were quickly depleted
when they vanished like that.
Niiteqallruunga-am waten:
This is what I heard:
Anguyagtet-gguq-qaa taukut tuntuviit, tuntut taitellruit maavet.
They said that the government brought those reindeer herding places here.
Tua-llu-gguq elicaryaaqluki amaken
And then they said that they had teachers from outside
Au͡g’umek Lapp-amek tailluteng maavet elicarluki yuut tuntuviuryaramek.
They brought a Saami person here to teach people how to herd reindeer.
Tua-llu-gguq ayiita tamakut yuut aulukluki tuntuviit
aulukcurlaki nangellruvkalarniit.
And then they said that when they left, Yupiit took care of reindeer herds
and they were depleted because they didn’t take care of them well.
Tamana-qaa piciuluni?
Is that true?
Nuu, piciunrituq tamana.
No, that’s not true.
Aulukcurlaumallrunritut.
They weren’t taken care of badly.
Taum tua-i old man-ama qanrutkelallrui tua-i tuaten.
That old man of mine used to talk about them like that.
Keglunerrlainarnun nangenritniluki, tau͡gaam cataitaqluteng.
He said that wolves weren’t the only ones that depleted them,
but they vanished.
Tuaten tua-i iptaqameng qemimun cataitaqluteng.
When they go out of view like that behind hills, they vanished.
Tuaten piluki nangvallurniit.
They say that’s mostly what depleted them.
Urqapiarallruut.
They were extremely dirty.
Governemnt-aarurtellermeng kinguani urqapiarnillruit.
After they were taken under the government,
they say that were extremely dirty.
Tua-i-llu nangluteng.
And then they were depleted.
Piqerluteng nangluteng wii pagaaviqtaaryaurrlua, ayagayaurrlua.
One day when they were depleted, I started traveling up there.
Cali 15 years-aqatarlua wangnek drop out-arlua elitnaumek.
Also, I dropped out of school by my own choice
when I was going to turn 15 years [old].
Yuilqumi akingengnaquralria una ataka ikayuangluku.
I started helping my father make money from the wilderness.
Caliartaitellruami nuna, nunat wani melqulegteggun tau͡gaam.
There were no jobs in the villages, only by [trading] fur.
Akitaunateng-llu elliiganek nunat, apqiitnek grant-anek.
Villages didn’t have donated money, what they call grants.
Melqulegpallurteggun tau͡gaam yuut unangengnaqaqluteng.
People only got [money] mostly through [trading] fur.
Muriurluteng tuaten, equgkiurluteng kiagtuumaan.
They also worked on lumber in the summer.
Akikangengnaqu’urluteng calirpagluteng.
They worked hard to get money.
Quukataarluki tuaten napat iluatnek atrauquriaqluteng.
They would even carry loads of wood down from the trees.
Tau͡gaam daddy-qa una ayagauralallruuq.
But my daddy traveled a lot.
Tua-i neqem kinguani August-aami egmianun ayalallruukuk
pagaavet ingrinun qanganarcuryarturlunuk
We2 would go right after fishing in August
up to the mountains to hunt for squirrels
Akitulaata qanganaat amiit.
Because squirrel skins were expensive.
Tamaani piqarraalallemni $15 akingqelallruuq one coat.
Back when I first started, one coat cost $15.
Tau͡gaam nangliq’laamegnuk qanganarcuryarturaqlunuk.
But because we would be short [on money], we would go hunt squirrels.
Ii-i.
I see.
Tua-ll’ elpeni-qaa mat’um nalliini makut ayagyuat
And so to you, the young people these days
Maaniunrilengraan, allani-llu nunani akusrarteńgut.
Even outside of here,
they’re starting to be mischievous even in other villages.
Yaa, maa-i mat’um nalliini makut ayagyuaput kingum yui akusrartengut.
Yes, the young people, our descendants,these days
are becoming mischievous.
Cali unugmi caarkaituryugluteng, tua-i-w’ tarrangyugluteng.
And they have nothing to do at night, and tend to wander about.
Wangkucicetun pivkenateng.
They’re not like us.
Wangkuta tua-i nallumteńi,
In our time,
Uum-llu wani ciumni qallatellrem yua aiparnikellruamnuk tua-i
nine clock, ten clock-ll’ utercaraqellruarpuk aquirraarlunuk.
And when the child of this one who spoke before me
enjoyed each others’ company,
we went home early at nine [o’]clock and ten [o’]clock after playing.
Mat’um tang nalliini unugmi-llu, unuum-llu qukallran kinguani
These days you see, at night, and after midnight
Tarritessuutengnitekluteng snuukuuraluteng,
fourwheel-araluteng tuaten piyaurtengelriit mat’um nalliini.
Because they have vehicles, they’ve started going around
with snow machines and even fourwheelers these days.
Cali makut ayagyuat, makut tua-i Yupiayagaat
Also, these young people, these little Yupiit
Aanaita picurlagluki wangkucicetun qalarutevkenaki anglicarluki.
Their mothers make the mistake of raising them
without speaking [in our language] as we were.
Elitetuut, mikelnguut elitetuut elitnaumi qitevquryaramek.
They learn, these children learn to speak English in school.
Cat ilaitni maani avani-llu elitnaurviim elatiini
Some days, here and over there outside of the school
Yupiayaarnek makunek inerquilaryaaqua waten Yugtun qallallua.
I admonish these little Yupiit speaking in Yup’ik like this.
Imkuyagaat tanegpayagaat kiugartelaqiitnga,
“I don’t know what you’re talking about.”
Those big boys would answer me,
Piciunrituq man’a qallacaraput cagmarluku, cagmangluku.
It’s not right that we should lose, start to lose our language.
Tuamta-llu iliini kiunauraatnga qalarutaqamki
And then sometimes, they would answer when I speak to them
Tamana-gguq kalikameggni ellimanrituq ukuni high school book-ani.
That that is not written in their high school books.
Ukunun Kass’amteńun ingluangluteng.
They’ve started converting to the Westerne ways in our region.
Tamatum-wa tua-i qitevquraulluki pilallrata pillikait.
It’s probably because they always speak English to them.
Cali man’a cagmangluku ayagayarateng.
They’ve also started losing their traveling ways.
Yaavarraq-llu piyualuteng ayagciiganateng
They can’t walk a little ways over there either
Taungitniluteng qanraqluteng.
Saying that they don’t have that [vehicle].
Wangkuta avani tan’gurralleraullemteńi waten nun’aqertaqan
Back when we were boys, when the land [became walkable] like this
Qimugtengqengramta peggluki tua-i atunrirluki atmagturluta ayagalallruukut.
Even though we had dogs, we left them behind
and traveled with packs on our backs.
Ayarurrangqerturluta tau͡gaam alerquucimcetun.
But we always had walking staffs as we were instructed.
Ayarurraicuunata tua-i nunaungraan-llu maani.
We always had walking staffs even here in the village.
Nunaungraan nunakun ayangramta ayarurraq tegumiaqurluku
Even when we walked through the village, we held a walking staff
Tua-i alerquutekngamteggu.
Because we were instructed to.
Yuut Yupiat alerquutaitni, amllepiartut tayima Yupiat alerquutait,
qanruyutait-llu tayima.
In Yup’ik instructions, Yupiit have a lot of instructions
and traditional wisdom.
Elpeni iliit taukut alerquutet iliit cauga tukninqurrat
For you, what is the most powerful of those instructions
Wall’u-qaa angenqunqerrat qanruyutet yullret qanruyutek’lallrat?
Or the most important traditional wisdom of the people back then?
Angenqurrat ava-i qanrutkaqa: yuum pianek tegucaqunak.
Teglegyaqunak.
I just talked about the most important one: do not take other’s things.
Do not steal.
Angenqurrat tua-i tamamta qivrutuamta.
That’s the most important because we all get disappointed from loss.
Tua-i ava-i angenqurrat.
That's the most important.
Tunglia-wa, ayagakumta ayaruq uitatesqevkenaku nunaungraan.
Next, if we go anywhere, even inside the village,
do not leave the walking staff.
Cikumi-llu piarkaukumta cingileggalegmek pisqelluta.
And if we should go on ice, we should [test it] with a pointed tool.
Nunaungraan muraggaq ayaruliluku tak’urluku tegumiaquraasqelluku.
Even in the village, make a long walking staff out of wood and hold it.
Tua-i nunaungraan, ingrini-llu mayualangramta
Even in the village, and even when we went up mountains
Ayarurraq tegumiaqerrlainarluku tarritetullruluta.
We always walked around holding a walking staff.
Tua-i tunglia.
That's the next [piece of wisdom].
Iliini-llu anirtuqautekaqluku.
And sometimes, it would save us.
Iquyaaqellemteńek aksallagvikluku ayaruq.
When we’re going to fall, we upheld ourselves with a staff.
Iliini-llu kuignayugteggun qeralriani
And sometimes, when we cross streams
Etuuralria nallunritetaqluku tamatum ayarum tuaggun qeraqaunrilucia.
That staff lets us know which parts are deep and should not be crossed.
Allakun tau͡gaam yuaqerluta.
We look for another path instead.
Alingnaqngami cali kuignayuunge’rmi pau͡gna ingrit.
Even streams are dangerous up in the mountains.
Tua-i qanikcaq apqiitnek au͡gkut ciuliamta
pissurpek’naarpek’nata pekeskumta neruiniciiqniluta.
The snow, as our ancestors back then used to say,
if we travel without [?probing], we will fall into hollows in the snow.
Iliini tua-i assirnganani una ayarumek kapellriani camna quutaitelartuq.
Sometimes when we poke what looks good here,
the [hollow] beneath does not close in.
Tamakunun ek’arrnayukluta ayaruitesqessuunata
They told us to always have staffs because we might fall into those
Apeqmeggnek neruinilluta.
What they call neruinilluta.
Camna acia man’a qanikcarrlainaunge’rmi camna acia cagurpagluni.
The area beneath, though this is all snow,
the area beneath [?has a large hollow].
Tamakunun ek’arrnayukluta
nunaungraan tua-i ayarurraq tegumiaquraasqelaraat.
Because we might fall into those,
they told us to always have a staff even in the village.
Qeraqata’arqamta-llu una nequkilengraan tua-i yuvrirrlainarluku.
And when we’re going to cross, always examine it even if it’s narrow.
Cali-qaa…
Was there also…