Tua-ll’ ayagyuallerpeni-qaa qasgimi, qasgimi uitaqallruuten?
So, when you were young, did you live in the community house?
Qaillun-llu ayuqellrua ayagyuallerpeni, miklerpeni, ellangellerpeni tamaani?
And what was it like when you were young, when you were small, in your earliest memories back then?
Qaill’ ayuqellruat tamakut yullret?
What were those people like back then?
Qinarmiuni ellangellruunga.
My earliest memories are in Qinarmiut.
Ellanglua tua-i ellangellemni cataitellruuq Qinaq, mat’umek-ll’ Qaneryaramek pitaunani.
In my earliest memories growing up, there was nothing [Western] in Qinaq, and there was no Bible.
Agayumalriartaunani.
There were no Christians.
Tua-i ellangeqarraallruunga waten kinguqlimnun tuqulriamun tungemnun.
My earliest memories are right after my younger sibling who died.
Tua-i tuaken ayaglua ellanglua. Yuut tua-i nallunrirluki Qinarmi.
I’ve had consistent memories since then. I got to know the people in Qinaq.
Tua-i tuaken ayaglua ellanglua yuut murilkelluki.
I’ve had consistent memories since then, observing the people.
Qinarmiungulua tua-i.
I was a resident of Qinaq.
Tua-i-llu atam pinariama
Then, you see, when I became capable
Kass’at-llu enurnarluteng, ataucirrarmek tau͡gaam Kass’artarluteng, wagg’uq uumek Klondike Johnson, Yugtun piaqluku Parumek.
There were scarcely any Caucasians, but there was only one Caucasian there, whom they called Klondike Johnson, whom they called Paru in Yup’ik.
Irniari-wa cetaman tan’gaurluullgutekluki tua-i.
His four children were our fellow boys.
Malruk tayim’ unguvauk, nuu, pingayun.
Two are alive, no, three.
Alikaqa tau͡gaam tauna Paru. Kass’at alikellruaput.
But I was scared of Paru. We were scared of Caucasians.
Carayakluki tua-i. Tangrraqamki, "Aullu, tarrarrngaitua."
They were strange being to us. When I saw them, "Oh my, I won’t walk about."
Tua-i alingnaqluteng.
They were scary.
Qinarmiut tua-i taukut yuuluteng, elitnaurviinateng-llu.
The people of Qinaq lived there, and they didn’t have a school.
Angliriama-llu qasgimun cali itraqama, qasgiaqama
Then when I went into the community house when I grew up, when I was at the community house
Tauna cunaw’ aiparkama, ug’um aiparkama apa’urlua Akagtaq tua-i alikluku.
I was scared of Akagtaq, the grandfather of the one who ended up being my future spouse, my future spouse downriver.
Maurlurlumnek cali taumek friend-angqelliniami itrumaaqami
When he was in there, since he apparently was friends with my grandmother
Taum maurlurluma egyaqsuani-llu
Also since my grandmother would [?joke about] him
Tua-i alikluku cali ilumun yugnek nertuyukluku.
I was scared of him, thinking that he really did eat people.
Cunaw’ tutgarqelliniamia.
Apparently, it was because I was her grandchild.
Tua-i ukvekpiarluku nevukun-llu ciutengqerrniluni.
And I believed her, and s said that she had ears in the soil.
Amani enemeggni uitaurarqami cauralriit amkut tua-i niirquratuniluku.
When she was in her house, she said that she heard what was going on [in the community house] over there.
Tua-i taumek neqamlinguaqerqamku tua-i cukaqangraan unuamek maa-i qanlalrianga
That’s why when I [?remember] her, however briefly, I say today
"Nutaan-tuq imna tayima nevukun ciutengqerrnilalleq yav’anun phone-arcet’larlaku ingrit aciatgun."
"How I wish I could have that one who said she had ears in the soil make phone calls far away under the mountains."
Tua-i tuaten ayuqluteng Qinarmiut.
That’s what the people of Qinaq were like.
Tua-llu tua-i atam qasgilangama
Then, you see, when I started going to the community house
Yuut, qasgilangvailegma tamaani atam
The people, before I started going to the community house back then, you see
Waten yuut qetunracuarateng wall’u paniteng
People [did] this with their little sons or their daughters
Yuullermeggni camek unangaqata, pitqerriirqata boy-acuarateng, pitgarluki
When they caught something in their lives, when their little boys had their first catches with arrows
Imna tua-i yaquleyagaq kemgirluku, nakaculiluki, ayagcirluku kinertelluku.
They would remove the flesh from their bones, hang them, prop them to dry them.
Tua-i-llu uksuquan kalukarluku.
Then the next winter, they would hold a feast for that.
Tuaten tua-i allamiaqan pituluteng.
They would do that every year.
Tua-i-ll’ wiinga pavani uani neqlillemteńi ak’a
Then inland, downriver at our fish camp back then
Tagyaram uatiini pavani-am tarrarluta pillemteńi, tua-i aqvaqulanglua
When we were wanding downriver from Tagyaraq in land, when I had started running
Atam qangqiiq man’a tengvallagyaaqelria igtellria.
You see, this ptarmigan that had taken off in flight fell.
Malirqerqamni tua-i tengvallaggaarluni igtaq[luni].
As I chased it, it would take off then fall.
Caqerluku tua-i paallaglua teguluku.
Eventualy, I tripped and took it.
Tua-i tengssaangraan tengevkaryugnaunaku tuququaluku.
Though it tried to fly away, I didn’t let it and killed it.
Tayima tua-i qaillun piciinaku.
I didn’t know what became of it.
Cunaw’ tua-i tauma maurlurluma nakaculillinikii tuaten tua-i.
It turned out that my grandmother hung it to dry.
Nalluluku tangeqsaunaku-llu.
I didn’t know about it and never saw it.
Tua-i ugna uksuillerput Iingirayuq
Our winter camp downriver, Iingirayuq
Family-t pingayun waten taluyarpagcutullruut.
Three familes would set large fishtraps like this.
Whitefish-anek, akakiignek, cingikegglinek neqsutuluteng.
They would fish for whitefish, broad whitefish, whitefish with pointed heads.
Tua-i-ll’ aatama taum taluyillra cali kan’a nunat aciat, tauna neqtuluni tayima tua-i.
Them my father’s fish trapping spot down there under the ground would have a lot of fish.
Atam uksuquan Qinarmiut kelelriit.
You see, the next winter, the people of Qinaq sent invitations.
Kelellinilriit Iigmun, Apruka’armun-llu Apruka’armiut yungqellratni, tuaten pitullruameng.
They sent invitations to Eek, and to Apruka’ar when there were people in Apruka’ar, because that’s what they did.
Tua-i allanret tekilluteng.
The guests arrived.
Atam akutetullruut qantav’agteggun
You see, they would make Yup’ik ice cream with huge bowls
Akutapianek tunulegnek, uqunek egcetaarluki tangviarrluut kenirluki, ingqiqcaarluki tamaani akutetullermeggni.
Traditional Yup’ik ice cream with tallow, cooking seal blubber to render their oil, and cutting them up back when they made Yup’ik ice cream [like that].
Tua-i-llu ala pikiitnga, qasgilii-gguq, maligglaki-gguq.
Then, oh my, they told me to go to the community house, to go with [the men].
Maaten anua ikamrak tua-i au͡gkuk atama neqnek tua-i iqukliarrlutek imarlutek.
I went out and found that my father’s sled was filled end to end with fish.
Una-w’ tang miskav’all’er akutamek imarluni.
This huge serving bowl, you see, had Yup’ik ice cream.
Imna-wa tang una qanqiirtalqa kiak ayagterluni akutami kapuyuterluni kapusngalria.
Then, you see, the ptarmigan I’d caught last sumemr had a prop and was stuck to the Yup’ik ice cream with a stake.
Tua-i kalukallinikiinga taum aatama.
Apparently, my father held a feast for me.
Qasginritua. Arenqiatuq taumek imumek yugtutulimek alingua.
I didn’t go to the community house. It was distressing since I was agraid of that cannibal.
Maligtenritaqa alikataqa tauna unguviin tamaani.
I didn’t go with him because the one I was afraid of was alive there.
Tua-i tuaten pitullruut.
That’s what they used to do.
Tua-i-llu au͡gna tua-i kassiyuq iqukliartuq.
That dancing festival was over.
Atam cali nutaan qasgimi, qasgimi qavalangelriakut.
You see, we finally started sleeping in the community house.
Qasgi tua-i imna qasegpall’er qaillun tayima angtaa.
That huge community house, I’m not sure how big it was.
Tua-i ayagyuanek ciulirnemteńek-llu inartaqata piviitnaurtuq.
When young people and our elders lay down for bed, there’d be no room.
Kinguqvaarkun tua-i itellriani, iliini uani tua-i amiigen, acikaitaqama amiigem aciani ciuqerrani qavalartua canirrlua.
When I went in late, sometimes, I would sleep on my side down under the door, in front of it, when I had no bedding.
Tuaten tua-i.
Like that.
Tua-i tau͡gken unuakumi iliini qanerturalrianun tupagnaurtua pak’mumun.
Some mornings, however, I would wake up to someone instructing up there.
Ak’a tua-i angukara’urluut iliit qanerturangellinilria ayuqucirtuutmek, qanruyutmek, yuum yuullerkaanek
One of the old men would already be speaking about instructions, traditional wisdom, how a person should live
Tan’gaurluum yuullerkaanek, uk’umek agiirtellriamek atu’urkamek, piciulriamek.
How a boy should live, what is in store for the future, true things.
Tua-i pekqullagavkenata tua-i maktaqamta tua-i maktaqluta niicugniurluku tauna qanerturalria.
When we got up, we’d get up without sudden movements, listening to the one giving instruction.
Tupaqluta piyuunata.
We wouldn’t [?be forecefully awoken].
Tuaten tua-i unuakut tamaita.
That happened every morning.
Tuamtellu erenrani waten maqillmeng qamanran maqirpatuameng-llu
Then during the day like this, when their fire bath was going out since they had blazing fire baths
Qanerturnaurtut yuullerkamek uk’umek agiirtellriamek.
They would give life instruction about what was in the near future.
Tan’gaurluq arnamun elliqan, aren cayugnailngukut-wa.
If a boy marries a woman, oh my, it was a long way off for us.
Agiirtell[riamek] pellaayairturluta cunaw’.
It turned out, they kept us from being lost in the future.
Tua-i tuaten pinaurtut. Tua-llu tua una nangqe’rtuq.
They would say that. This [topic] is finished.
Tua-ll’ nutaan qalangssalartut.
Then they would tell stories.
Tamaani-gguq ciungani tamatum wangkuta yuurpailemta, tamakut-ll’ angukara’urluut ayagyuarluki nutaan
They said that in the past, before we were born, and when the old men were young
Ayuqucirtuun pinirluku atullruat.
They strongly practiced traditional instruction.
Qasgimi, ayuqucirturiqata’arqameng-gguq qasgimi ugna amiik imumek tua-i cigyagmek.
They said that when they were going to give in struction in the community house, [they would place] a split spruce stick down at the door.
Cigyak-qaa nallunritan?
Do you know split sprice?
Iciw’ taluyat imkut muriit.
You know, wood to make fish traps.
Nauwa? Man’a-ggem pitangqellruuq.
Where is it? Wasn’t there one here?
Taluyanek. Cigyangqelalriit waten iqtutauralrianek.
[To make] fish traps. They have split spruce that are this wide.
Cani’irrvikaqaat qeratmun.
They would put that crosswise on its side [in the door].
Nutaan-llu qanruyutmek qalarrluteng.
Then they’d speak of traditional wisdom.
Tua-lli-wa-gguq tua-i yuut ayuqenritliniameng waten, tan’gaurluut ayuqenritliniameng
Then they said that since people are different like this, since boys are different
Ilii-gguq tan’gaurluum anqertaquq qasgimek, imna tamana tapeqluku asemlluku.
They said that some boy would go out of the community house, even breaking that [split spruce].
Wangliungeqatartut-am, "Aren, arivanrilkii-w’ qaneryaram."
They’d start talking about him, "Oh my, the traditional wisdom doesn’t call to him."
They said that a bad person, a bad person does that.
Tuamtellu qakmani arnat cali allakarmeng eneni arnassagallraat imkut eliperneret ayuqucirtuaguratullruit
Then the women, separate out there in the houses, the [?elderly] old women would always isntruct them
Nasaurluq uingekan tuaten uinganek aulukillerkaa.
How a girl should take care of her husband when she takes a husband.
Tua-lli waten anguanka tuani tua-i uksuillerni.
Then I caught them [instructing] there in the winter camp.
Ena amiik uaken caniqerrilitarluni canegnek, naqugtarnek tupigluki iterniryailkutnek.
The house’s door had grass placed on the side, woven grass belts to keep out the draft.
Tua-lli-wa-gguq nevilleraat iliit-am cali
Then, one of the girls too
Waten family-nek ena atauciq pingayunek enelgutkurpallutullruut, murilkanka.
I observed that one house like this would have three families living together.
Cetamanek-llu yungqetullrulria family-nek.
It would also be occupied by four families.
Nevilleraat-gguq iliit anqertaquq.
They said that one of the girls would run out.
Tua-llam wangliungeqatartut.
Then they’d start speaking of her.
Iliin-llu-gguq imkut ingkut caniqerrilitat tapeqluki au͡g’arluki kapuyukaralget can’get.
They said that one would even take of the grass block that was stuck with tacks.
Tua-i pingayiriaqan-gguq arnassagallraam im’ taquitaqaa.
They said that when it happened for the third time, the old woman gives her [her future].
"Atak’-gguq au͡gna tua-i pili, caniqaam yukniaraa."
"Let her do that, so that she will be the person of the threshhold."
Caniqaq-qaa nallunritan?
Do you know what a caniqaq is?
Nauwa?
Where is it?
Amiigem ug’um taqu͡ra caniqauguq.
The threshhold of the door out there is a caniqaq.
Caniqamek pituat, caniqaq.
They call it a caniqaq.
Qau͡gna-wa enem egkua kitkacagaani amiigem ciuqra qau͡gna egkuq. Makuk-wa tua-i taquuk.
Inside in the wall of the house, the area in front of the door is the egkuq. These are the taquuk [threshold].
Tuaten igloo-nek [enepianek] enengqellermeggni.
Like that, when they had sod houses.
"Caniqaam yukniaraa."
"Let her be the person of the threshhold."
Aren, kingunertaqaa-gguq. Caniqaq-llu yuungnaqelriit atutukiit.
Oh my, they said she would [?call her back]. Those who subsist also use the threshold.
"Natrem yukniaraa."
"Let her be the person of the floor."
Cuna-gguq tua-i ciunra, ciunerkaa enik’acagarluku.
Apparently, it was because she was [?weighing down] her future.
Aanairulluni, aatairulluni, wantaqluni, wantaqluni qanruyun atunritem ugaani.
She loses her mother, father, stays here, stays here, because she doesn’t practice traditional wisdom.
Tuamtellu qakmani tauna im’ qasgimi anqertelalleq
Then outside in the community house, the one who would run out
Pingayiriaqan-gguq tua-i angullualleraam taquitaqaa.
They said when he does that a third time, an old man gives him [his future].
"Atak’-gguq au͡gna tua-i pili, qengaruum iquani keggutekegciniartuq."
"Let him do that, so he will show his nice teeth at the end of a snowbank."
Taringan-qaa?
Do you understand it?
Waten mean-angqertuq:
This is what it means:
Iqukvat tamaita ellarrlugiurturatullermeggni, ellarrlugiutullermeggni
When all [?] would always prefict bad weather bringing famines, when they predicted bad weather
Tua-i-gguq paluluni mat’umun. Qengaruk-qaa nallunritan?
They say he starves and [ends up] here. Do you know what a qengaruk [snowbank] is?
Qanikcaq.
It’s snow.
Yaani iquani, keggutai-wa qercurpak.
Over at the end, his teeth are very white.
Tua-i-gguq palu’urlurlullinilria.Tua-i keggutekegcialuni-gguq.
They say the poor guy starved. They say he’s showing his nice teeth.
Tua-i tuaten ayuqellrulliniut.
That’s what they were like.
Cali nasaurluut qalarutaqamegteki qanrutetulliniit
Also, when they spoke to the girls, they would tell them
"Qayu-llu tua-i uingekuvet, uiu͡rlurpenek paluiciqelriaten."
"Should you end up taking a husband, your husband will starve on you."
Tang Kass’artaitellrani, una-wa uinga.
You see, when there were no Caucasians, and here’s her husband.
Tua-i-gguq ellarrluum nalliini
They said that during bad weather causing famine
Nutaan nulirqelriit ayuquciak, uiminun, nuliaminun ayuquciak nasva’gquq.
That’s when a married couples true character, their character towards their husbands, wives, are shown.
Yua-gguq iliin uiu͡rluni palivkatua nallmikun neryugluni, nangusnguarluni-llu.
They say that some makes her husband starve, wanting to eat for herself, and pretending there’s no food left.
Tuaten tua-i alingnarqetacia. Alingnaqsaaq[luni].
That’s how scary it is. It’s scary.
Tua-i waten ayuqenritlermeggni iqukvat tamaita tua-i waten neqsuutelliqellermeggni-llu.
This was when they weren’t like now, every [?famine], and when they didn’t have modern fishing implements.
Atam tua-i tamaa-i tamana tua-i alikellrukeka wiinga.
You see, I was scared of that.
Maa-i unuamek nalqegcipiartukut, wiinga-ll’ ilalirluci, makunek-llu freezer-aanek.
We’re living in easy times today, and I’m with you, and [we have] these freezers.
Qangvallauciilngurmek nutak’acagarmek nernariaqan iliini ner’aqluta.
Sometimes we eat something fresh that we don’t know how old it is.
Uum canimelli’irrluku qanengssakartua.
I’m telling a story closer to this time.
Tuaten tua-i ayuqellrulliniut yuut au͡gkut yuullermeggni.
That’s what they were like when people back then lived.
Camek tua-i...
Something...
Waten Kassiyurturatullruut allamiaqan.
They would hold a Kassiyuq dance festival every year.
Kassiyuq una yugnek kelgiyarauguq.
For Kassiyuq, they invite people.
Una yuulaq nunat pikaat tamarmeng kelenrilnge’rmeng.
This yuulaq pair of ceremonial drums belong to all villages, even if they don’t send invitations.
Yuulalituut cauyagnek malrugnek eciriluteng
They make a yuulaq pair by putting skins on two drums
Atakutangssaaryungaqameng-wa tua-i qakemkut neqangssaliaritnek.
When they want to start dinner, the food that the women out there made.
Uumek au͡gna cimiqerluku piqatartua.
I’m going to change that topic to this.
Cauyagnek malrugnek eciriaqut.
They put skins on two drums.
Tua-i-llu tan’geraaraan cauyak im’ kaugtuarlukek.
Then when it starts getting dark, they beat the two drums.
Au͡gna-w’ aataka, au͡gna-llu ug’um arnassaga’urluum aatii akiqliqlutek aturpagatullruuk
My father, and the father of the old woman downriver would sing opposite each other
Tau͡gaam yuarutkek elitellrunritanka.
But I didn’t learn their songs.
Anglanissiyaaglua pillruaqama elicuitanka.
When I have too much fun, I don’t learn them.
Canek elisngangqerrsaaqua ilaitnek yuarutet iqupkuitnek.
I have some incomplete knowledge of songs.
Tua-i iqukiareskan man’a nallunrilkemnek aturciqua Yugcetun.
When this is over, I will song some that I know in Yup’ik.
Aturpaganaurtuk.
They would sing loudly.
Tua-i-ll’ piuraqerluni arnaq iterluni qasgimun imumek neruka’rmek tegumiarluni, qantamek.
Then eventually, a woman would enter the community house holding a nerukar, a [ceremonial] bowl.
Kanavet-llu nacitem qainganun ellirraarluku yurarluni, wagg’uq ingularluni. Taqngami-llu anluni.
Then after she put it down on the floor down there, she would dance what they called an Ingulaq dance. Then she went out when she was done.
Muluvkenani tuavet arnaq itertuq qantunguarmek tegumiarluni.
Before long, a women entered there holding a bowl.
Kiituani tang una
Eventually, here
Nacitat tua-i uutun waten ayalertutatullruut.
The floor planks used to be as [?slanted] as this.
Kenillra qasegpiim, nacitet-llu waten.
The fireplace of the big community house, and the floor planks like this.
Muirnaurtuq imkunek qancunguarnek neruka’rnek.
It owuld be filled with those nerukar bowls.
Itenriata-ll’ tua-i nutaan cauyak qerrlukek.
And when the stopped coming in, they’d put the drums away.
Nerluteng imkut qasgimiut Kass’artauyugnailngurnek
The men of the community house would eat food that absolutely was not Western
Qamiquyagarnek tepnek, mak’anek, puyanek, qerpertanek, neqerrluarnek.
Little fermented salmon heads, aged salmon egg ice cream, moss with aged seal oil, whitefish roe ice cream, dried fish.
Wangkuta tan’gurralle’rni tua-i, "Puyat-assirtut," wagg’uq puyat.
We boys [would say], "Moss with aged seal oil is good," what they call puya
Puyat, puyautet
Puyat, moss with aged seal oil
Yuut puyautaicuitellruut. Urut imkut, urut uqumek mecirluki, au͡gkut urut nunam urui.
People were never without puyat. That moss, soak the moss in seal oil, the moss from the land.
Urucararmiunek qanlalriit maani. Urut.
There’s Urucararmiut [People of Moss]. Moss.
Uqumek mecirluki.
Soak them in seal oil.
Puyaliqataameng-llu tua-i tauna uru meciumakii [?] passiqcaarluku uqumek kuv’aqluku.
And when they were going to make puya, they’d crush that soaked moss and pour seal oil into it.
Qatkacagarluni tua-i, eyucuarluni.
It was very white, and a little congealed.
Tau͡gaam tamakut puyat egmian neryaraugut tua-i cukangnaqluteng.
But those puyat need to be eaten right away, and quickly.
Wagg’uq teng[luni]. Uitaskuni tua-i qivia allakarluku tengluni.
They say it "flies away." If you leave it, the berries separate and "fly away."
Tuaten tua-i.
Like that.
Assipiat neqet
Such good food
Qamiquyagarnek tua-i tuaten.
Including litte [fish] heads.
Tua-ll’ tua-i cali uksumi
Then also, in the winter
Uksumi una cali apqiit Itruka’ar
In the winter, the "Inviting-In Feast" Itruka’ar
Makumiut Itruka’armek acituat yuraryaraq.
The people call that dance festival Itruka’ar.
Apqaitnek Itruka’ar tauna anglukurtarnek yuarutetangqertuq, yuarutengqetuut.
During what they call Itruka’ar, they have shaman songs.
Itrukaraliarameng angulkullret au͡gkut tangtullruanka.
When they brought in the Itruka’ar bowls, I used to see those shamans.
Ellaita yuratuit, malrugnek arnaunregnek, ataucirrarmek angutngunercirluku.
They would dance, with two women, and one single man to join them.
Nutaan-llu makut piyulriit elitaameggnek cali angalkuunrilnge’rmeng tua-i.
And those who wanted to, [would dance] whatever they knew though they weren’t shamans.
Unisteka-w’ yuiarucitullruuq puqignitullruatni.
My late parents would write songs because they said he was skilled.
Itruka’ar una tamatuuguq.
That is what this Itruka’ar festival is.
Itruka’armek agayumek acirluku pituluteng.
They called it the Itruka’ar ceremony.
Una-w’ aipaa Kevgiq.
And the other one, Kevgiq, the Messenger Feast.
Yuraryaraq nutaan.
Now that’s a dance festival.
Nunat waten Kevgirqameng
When villages held this Kevgiq Feast
Ukut nunalget
This village
Waniwa waten mean-iqerluku: kelegyukuvet tua-i elpet camek piyuumatengqerquvet, Tuntutuliarmun ayagceciyartuten angutegnek malrugnek kevgagnek.
This is the meaning I ascribe to it: if you want to send an invitation for something that you want, you would send two men, kevgak [messengers], to Tuntutuliak.
Qalurrirlukek, tua-i alerqurlukek tuaten. Tuaten tua-i.
[?Tell them], and describe to them [what you want]. Like that.
Ukuk wani kevgak aya’agqamek
When these two messengers went
Tuani kingunermegni mikelnguq tauna aatii piyuumatii tuani ciunragni ilurii, ilurii aqvaniluku kevgirniluku.
They would refer a child’s father’s request from their home to their destination, saying that they’re getting, inviting, his cross-cousin.
Ayuqeliluku-ll’ tua-i. Tuaten tua-i.
And he’d also make a request. Like that.
Canek tua-i piyuuterluteng Kevgirqameng
They’d have different requests furing the Kevgiq Feast
Nutegnek, kapkaanarnek, ikamragnek.
Guns, steel traps, a sled.
Canek tua-i piyungssaarlutneg, iluriinun cali ikayuasqelluku.
They would want some various things, and ask their cross-cousins to help.
Tua-i-llu Kass’aqsiginermeggteggun pingameng pelarvagmek-llu piaqut.
Then when they did that further into Western contact, they’d ask for huge tents.
Pelarvagmek pelatekaryugluteng.
They wanted huge tents.
Aglirtuusqelluku-llu nutegmek anarrluurqualriamek ugaan’ nutaraam.
He’d also ask him to [?bring] a gun that was so new that it was as black as feces.
Tua-i-gguq, pit wani, tan’gerpiit ciikallrat tunguuq, tua-i taman’ umyuaqluku.
They said it because of how black crowberry diarrhea is.
Tuaten tua-i yuraq Kevgiryaraq ayuqellruuq anguvilqallrenka.
That’s what the Kevgiq dance festival was like where I was born in time to remember.
Tuaten tua-i wiinga-ll’ ilagaqaullua Kevgilriani.
I would also join the Kevgiq Feast like that.
Tau͡gaam tua-i angutngunerciucugyaaqekiitnga, aren yuraneq, yurayuitua.
But they asked me to be the male dancer, oh my, I didn’t Yup’ik dance.
Tau͡gaam aturpagatullruunga cauyarteńguaqlua-llu
But I would sing and be a drummer.
Tua-llu?
Well?
Calirraq, cali-qaa cangimirtuten?
Do you want to listen to more?
Ii-i, makut-mi?
Yes, what about these?
Angalkugnek-qaa piciatun angullrunrituten?
Were you born in time to see any shamans?
Tangerqallrunrituten angalkull’e’rnek tuunrillralrianek piciatun alingnarquuralrianek?
Have you eveer seen shamans doing any scary shamanistic magic?
Aren tuunrilriit waten angalkut tamakut tamaani yuut atullruit ciuliamta.
Oh my, the shamans who practiced their powers back then, the people, our ancestors, practiced them.
Ciuliaput piciatun yuullrunritut au͡gkut.
Our ancestors back then didn’t not live purposelessly.
Tamakut angalkut atullrulliniit ukvekpiarluki.
They practiced shamanism with complete faith in them.
Yuum temiinek ikayuringnaqelriit naulluulrianek
The ones who try to help the bodies of the sick
Umyuarrliqenrilnguut, umyuarrlugciyuilnguut
Those without malicious intent, who do not have malicious intent for others
Tamakut angalkut atullermeggni yuut piciuluteng atullrulliniit ukvekluki, law-rit-llu aturluki.
When those poeple practiced shamanism, they truly practiced it with faith, and followed their laws.
Waten cuq’lirituut: tallimani ernerni una anirtungnaqkeseng uluarasqevkenaku.
They set this period of time: they told the ones they were trying to save not to use a knife for five days.
Tua-i tuaten.
Like that.
Tang-gguq ilii, piciungami
Look, they said, some people, since it’s true
Iciw’... ukaqsigiqerlua qalangssakarlii.
You know... let me come closer to speak.
Iciw’ Agayutem Satan-aq paat’naqellrukii, an’giliurta tauna.
You know, Satan was God’s partner, that high-ranking angel.
Tua-i-llu piciungami ukvekesteńi niisnga[ciqaa].
Then since it’s true, one who believes in it will obey it.
Yaa, piciatun akusrarutnguluni tau͡gaam atullrunritliniat.
Yes, but they didn’t mess around with it aimlessly.
Tuunritarkateng, qasgimi tuunrilrianek tangtullruunga cauyarluteng.
The one they use spirit powers on, I would see them practicing shaman magic with drums in the community house.
Tua-i-llu-wa-gguq tamaani ciungani
Then they said that in the past back then
Tuunritarkaq-gguq piyuasciigalnguq akigarluku qasgitaqaat, arnaq angun-llu, angalkuk malruk.
They said that the one that two shamans were going to use their powers on who couldn’t walk, they would bring them to the community house, woman and man.
Tua-lli-wa-gguq iliini piluaqaumaaqami taukuk imkuk ikayuqlutek caarrluinek imkunek, caarrluinek nang’iluku.
Then they said that when that person was [healed] well, those two [shamans] would help to get rid of all of his impurities.
Piyuasciiganani itleq, piyualuni-gguq an’aquq.
They said the one who couldn’t walk in, would go out walking.
Tua-i nangluku naulluutii au͡g’arluku.
They would get rid of all of his ailment.
Tuaten tua-i.
Like that.
Tua-llu cali ilii-am waten
Then also, some of them like this
Angalkum ilii yugmek umyuarrliquciluni piaqan, tauna-gguq yuk naulluugura’arqan naken kelgulluku.
When some shamans harbered malicious intent toward a person, when that person was sick for a long time, he’d invite him from somewhere.
Kelgulluku. Taun’-gguq naken tekitaquq. Pistii tang yuaraqaa.
[The shaman] invites him. They say he arrives from somewhere. You see, he looks for who invited him.
Tamaantelliniaqan-gguq qaspessaagulluku pisqaqaku
They said that when he’s there and tells him to go get a thin pullover garment
Nutaan imumek umyuarrluutiinek angicivka’rqaa tauna, umyuarrliquskii au͡g’aritelluku.
He has [that shaman] with malicious intent go free, having him forgive him for his malicious intent.
Tua-i caarkaunrirluni tua-i, tuqutairulluni.
He becomes safe, without the threat of death.
Tuaten ayuqelliniut.
That’s what they’re like.
Tua-i tau͡gaam cali tamaani cali ciuqvatagni
But also, back then in the distant past
Arcaqassiyaalria, arcaqassiyaagluni pilria tua-i kasnguksugnaunaku.
The one who was too bad, they would feel no shame about what they would do to him.
Tua-i tuqutetullrulliniat angalkuq nallunailqurpassautessiyaalria.
They would kill the shaman that was too infamous.
Tau͡gaam-gguq eyurtekangqeng’e’rmi aullu inerquusngaluni eyuqaasqevkenaku.
However, they said that though one would defend him, they would admonish them against ever defending them.
Tau͡gam-gguq imkut saaniicuaraat, tamakut tau͡gaam tatamuravkaqateki-gguq tau͡gaam nutaan piyugtacimegcetun akiureskilitgu.
But they said those little kettles, only when those startle them should they retaliate as much as they want.
Tua-i tuaten mean-angqelliniuq.
That’s what it means.
Ii-i. Camek cali piyugcit?
Okay. What else do you want?
Niitelartukut ircenrrarnek, yucuayaarnek, [?] caugat tayima.
We hear about ircenrraat, [legendary] little people, [?], whatever they are.
Ircenrrarnek-qaa tangerqaqsaituten yuucirpeni?
Have you never seen legendary little people in your life?
Ircenrraat yucuayagaunritut qanraqameng.
Ircenrraat aren’t little people when they speak [of them].
Tau͡gam-gguq tevirayuut.
But they say they can disappear in an instant.
Aataka qalangssalartuq [?Iigirayuk] uaken uksuillminek anssiirluni, kuigem ceńiikun anguarturluni.
My father tells stories of [?Iigirayuk], hunting seal from his winter camp downriver, rowing on the riverbank.
Atam igvalliniuq qayaqegtaar man’a asgulria tunglirnerakun.
You see, a high quality kayak appeared coming upriver toward him.
Ukut-wa iciw’ kuigni iliini napat ketmun uyangqatulriit.
And these, you know how sometimes in rivers, trees are bent towards the water?
Akunlekqerluki tua-i qayaqegtaar.
A high quality kayak went between them.
Tua-i-ll’ taukut tekilluki umyuarteqliniuq, "Aling, mat’umi-lli ukaqsigpaa qayaqegcilriami."
Then he thought when he reached them, "Wow, this one with a great kayak is so close."
Ukut tua-i tekicarturluki, unisteḿa tekicaaqellinii taukut kavirlit uyangqalriit kuimteńi un’gani, "Qaku-gguq una igvarta?" Pellullinii.
He approached them, and when my late father reached the bent red trees in our river downriver, "When is this going to appear?" He had passed them.
Tayim’ catauani.
It was gone.
Tua-i ircenrraq-gguq.
He said it was a little person.
Tuamtellu qalangssagmek au͡gkuk
Then those two [told] a story
Anaanaq-wa Tuntuaq, Qeng’angiar-llu, tama[ani] im’ anglicartellrak taukuk
The maternal aunt Tuntuaq, and Qeng’angiar, the ones who raised them
Pamani Aruvalnguum ceńiini uksuitulik.
The ones who camp in the winter inland in Aruvalnguq.
Ipugluni can’giirnek nulirra.
His wife ladled out blackfish.
Puqlanek atakutaqatarlutek.
They were going to have a hot dinner.
Aruvalnguum piani, piani Qemiller uitauq ekvicugpak.
Inland from Aruvalnguq is Qemiller, a huge bluff.
Maaten piqalliniuk ikamrat.
They realized that there were sleds.
Kangiqutauguq tauna.
That is an inlet.
Ikamrat upiit asmurluteng qeralriit.
Moving sleds, the crossing [the inlet] by [?pushing their sleds].
Tua-i tangvagluki.
They watched them.
Imna tauna ekvik urenkelluku.
They went straight for that bluff.
Aren, umyuartequk-gguq, "Qaillun-kiq ekvik mayurniarta?"
Oh my, they said that they thought, "How will they climb the bluff?"
Tuarpiaq-gguq imna ekvicuk tekitellermeggni ellu’urtellriit, ekvik imna, may’uqertellermeggni.
They said it seemed like they slid [up] when they reached the bluff, that bluff, when they climbed.
Pavani-gguq tau͡gken merunrani uvertellriami kayimpacugluteng tayim’ ipluteng ircenrraat.
However, they said that in the steep [?face] inland, the legendary little people [?pushed through] and disappeared.
Tua-i tuaten yucuaraunritut.
They’re not little people like that.
Tamakut ircenrraat yucuayaarnek apyuitait tangaastek’lallrita.
Those who’ve seen them don’t refer to ircenrraat as little people.
Wiinga tangerqanritua tau͡gaam.
But I’ve never seen any.
Cali nunallritni tamaani cali qalangssagmek nallunritua.
I also know of a story of one of their old settlements back then.
Ugna Agartessaagam-gguq un’ qagatellra nanvallerpakayak nunallemta kiatiini.
They said there was an old lake source of Agartessaagaq downriver, upriver from our old settlement.
Qungurtallrit-llu maa-i cali alaitut qungurtallrit, nunamun pulksaunateng.
And their graves here, their graves are still visible, not having sunk into the ground.
Nukalpiat ayuqenrilameng qavavet-am Kialirmun sevtelliniat.
Since great hunters were different, they cut the land upriver to Kialiq.
Agartessaagarmiurluq-gguq tauna arnassaga’urluq qiau͡rlurtuq, "Iiiiii."
They said that poor old woman from Agartessaagaq cried, "Eeeeee."
Sev’tellrata-wa pau͡gkut capkutarkai qemit ellmeggnun kalivcameng qunuksaaqluki neqtuan akakiignek.
When the hills that would bar their cutting through the land got stock on themselves, she didn’t want them to be destroyed since they had a lot of broad whitefish.
Tua-ll’ ceńii tauna kellirnermi ircenrrartangqellrulliniami
Then since there were legendary little people on the bank toward the water there
Atam iliit alakartelliniuq angyaq. Nanvakun paug͡kut manialkut apqiitnek Sugtulim manialkut tungiikun qerallinilria angyaq.
You see, one of them noticed a boat. A boat was crossed the jagged ice of the lake inland, through the jagged ice of what they call Sugtuli.
Qerrarukarallilria-wa.
It was probably sailing.
Yui-gguq tang tua-i ayuqenrilngurnek aturluteng una-i
They said the people on it had different kinds of clothes down there
Kavirlinek tuaten canek tua-i atkuunrilngurnek.
Even red things, things that weren’t parkas.
Aling tua-i-gguq tang ciunerkani-ll’ tamakut pitulriit.
Oh my, they said those would happen in the future.
Tua-i-ll’ tuani-am nunallra taun elallalliniat yull’eraat.
Then the people back then would dig into the land that had been there.
Au͡g’um-ll’ ug’um aiparma atsiyarqameng elalalliniit.
And my spouse downriver, they’d dig them when they picked berries.
Tumaumayuitut-gguq ircenrraat aklullrit. Ciqumumarrlainarluteng tumaumayuunateng.
They said ircenrraq things don’t leave trails for long. They always break apart, never staying trails for long.
Ik’iki-gguq iciw’ saskat imkut kelassat?
They said there were so many, you know those glass cups?
Tamakunek [?eriniqumkacagaumaluteng] pitangqerrnaurtuq.
There would be those [?scattered all over].
Elliin-llu tua-i taum aiparma ug’um aanairutiin qalangssakai nassaurluuluni tanglallrulliniami.
And my spouse’s late mother would tell stories of those when we was a little girl because she would see them.
Tumaumayuunateng.
Their trails wouldn’t last long.
Canek-gguq taluyallruarnek-llu.
They said they had things, fish traps.
Nasaurluq-gguq tua-i waten taluyallruarmek tumaqcaarmek ilakengkuni, tua-i-gguq tan’gaurlurmek yung’arkaulliniuq ertem iliini pivakarluni.
They said that when a girl gets a handmade fish trap like this, she will get a male child someday in the future.
Tua-i ciunerkamek-gguq pituut tamakut tuaten.
They say those tell the future like that.
Iliit-llu-gguq-am caqerluni tuani tua-i elagpakarluni elagluteng
They also said that one day, when they’d been digging there
Imkut cuyatangqetullruuq qillertarnek.
There used to be those twisted tobacco leaves.
Irulurugarnek-gguq-am tua-i qillrutarluteng. Tua-i, tua-i-gguq cuyarpagninaqluni.
They said that there were lots of twisted tobacco leaves. They said they smelled like tobacco.
Tangerrluku. Ciunerkamek-gguq pituut tamakut.
You see? They say those tell the future.
Ii-i. Tua-llu?
Okay. Well [anything else]?
Tua-llu? Time-airutukut-qaa?
Well? Are we out of time?
Atuqerciqua tau͡gaam.
I’ll sing, however.
Ii-i, yaa.
Okay, yes.
Atuqaa kitak’. Qalamcikqerraarluku atu’urkan caucianek atuqerniaran.
Please sing. Please talk about what your song is about, then sing.
Tua-llu?
Ready?
Quyatmek Qaluvialleraam yuarutiinek Kevgillermeggni.
Qaluvialler’s song of gratitude when they held the Messenger Feast.
Maa-i tua-i atqestii qerrulliniuq, kiugum panian yua
Now, his namesake froze to death, the child of the daughter of the one upriver
Papam, Pugleralriim, taum Qaluvialleraam atqestii.
Papaq, Pugleralria, Qaluvialler’s namesake.
Kiugna Papaq, taum tua-i yuarutem mat’um atuqerarkama panikaa, piipiqaa.
Papaq upriver is the daughter, the baby of the song that I’m going to sing.
Tuaten tua-i Kevgililuteng-am yuarucillrulliniuq angniutmek imangqenrilngurmek, arivutmek-ll’ imangqerpek’nani
When they held the Messenger Feast, he apparently wrote a song not about happiness, and not about insult
Tau͡gaam ukveraitmek quyatmek.
But about unbelievable gratitude.
Quyan-qaa nallunritan?
Do you know about gratitude?
Quyaaqavet qaill’ umyuangqelarcit?
What’s your mindset when you’re thankful?
Angniq.
Happiness.
Angniq-wa tua-i quyan. Tuaten mean-angqertuq.
Gratitude is happiness. That’s what it means.
Tua-i tamatumek atuqaqatartua waniw’ ak’allarnek qalamciama Kuigilngurmi Kevgirluteng yuarutellratnek.
I’m going to sing that song they sang during the Messenger Feast in Kwigillingok since I’m telling stories about a long time ago.
Carraquinrauguq. Nanilengraan tua-i agnermek ataucimek waniw’ tua-i atuqatartua.
It’s short. Though it’s short, I’m now going to sing one stanza.
Kinkut imkut niicugnilriit-wa asguranaitkacagarmek, piciulrianek qalangssagtua.
To anyone listening, I’m telling stories of things that are not unbelievable, but are true.
Iluramni qakemkuni, waniw’ tua-i atengqertua Kunuin Qinarmiu, Tuntutuliaraam nunaliaqestii.
To my cousins out there, my name is Kunuin from Qinaq, who has moved to Tuntutuliar.
Tuntutuliar-llu 1945 nunaliaqellrukeka.
I moved to Tuntutuliar in 1945.
Tua-i unuamek waniwa quyatekaqa KYUK-t kelgatnga.
Today, I am thankful that KYUK invited me.
Elluatussiyaanricaaqua. Pelluusqelluku waniw’ arenqialluguteka quyatekluku atuqatartua.
I’m not doing very well. I’m going to sing of gratitude to have my misfortune pass.
Nutaan akertem tanqiani cali elluarrluta ilakluta tamamta pekcuumirluta.
Let us all desire to walk well together under the light of the sun.
Quyaukut tagi-yara-ya
We’re thankful tagi-yara-ya
Kanangqaukut tagi-yara-ya
We’re bowing tagi-yara-ya
Ii-rri-rri-yarrai
Elingranaqvaa agya-rrai
What a cause for gratitude agya-rrai
Quyaukut tagi-yara-ya
We’re thankful tagi-yara-ya
Kanangqaukut tagi-yara-ya
We’re bowing tagi-yara-ya
Ii-rri-rri-yarrai
Elingranaqvaa agya-rrai uu!
What a cause for gratitude agya-rra-rrai uu!
Tua-i-wa tua-i.
There you have it.
Tua-llu?
How was that?
Quyanaqvaa cakneq.
Thank you very much.
Ii-i, quyakuvet tua-i cali yuarutkangqertua.
Okay, if you’re happy, I have another song.
Qalangssakuma cali iqupkumek aturyugngalua cali.
If I tell another story, I can sing an incomplete song too.
Imna-qaa Apanuugpiim, Apanuugpak-qaa yuarutaituq?
Does [the legendary hero] Apanuugpak have any songs?
Tua-i yuarutiinek Apanuugpiim nallulrianga.
I don’t know any song about Apanuugpak.
When they would have the woman dancing during the Ingulaq festival, they’d be fast.
Anqarautnek-gguq anguyagtarnek.
They called them songs of victory in war.
Tua-i tau͡gaam anglanissyaalaama Apanuugpallarnek tau͡gam nalluunga.
But since I had too much fun, I don’t know any songs about Apanuugpak.
Avani
Back then
Tamaani-gguq anguyatullermeggni, anguyangqellermeggni-w’
They said that back when used to be at war, when they had wars
Waken tua-i yuk ataucirrartaqami yugmek eyarluku kapluku [?] ilua qamyugluku.
When one person killed another, they would tattoo by poking, [?] closing the inside.
Ilii-gguq tua-i iliini akulrarun tekisngaaqaa eyanek
They say some would have tattoos reaching the middle of the forehead
Igarcuutaitellermeggni pitami amlertaciitnek.
When they didn’t have markers, how many he had killed.
Tuaten tua-i.
Like that.
Tua-i-llu yuarutmek cali ataucirrarmek una iqpkuk nallunritaqa.
I also know one song, but [my knowledge is] incomplete.
Amani Iyuussiimi
Over in Igushik
Maaken-am tua-i taukut Apanuugpak-ll’ ilakluku pillilriit, pingayurrauluteng pillret.
From here, the three who were probably with Apanuugpak.
Tauna-gguq qayaq malirqallrat, maaten-gguq teguat eyarrarluni ataucimek tauna anguyak.
They said that when they caught that kayak they were chasing, they found that that warrior had a single tattoo.
Cunaw’ ataucirrartellrallrulliniuq Kusquqvagmiu tauna.
Turns out, that person from the Kuskowkim had killed one.
Tua-i-llu yuarutmek aturnaurtut, "Eyarralek Paiqatanemni-qaa?"
Then they sang a song, "Right When I was Gong to Pass the One with a Tattoo?"
Tua-i iquklituq au͡gna. Tua-i tuaten.
That story ends. That’s all there is to it.
Apanuugpiim yuarutiinek nalluunga tuaten.
I don’t know a song about Apanuugpak like that.
Tua-i Apanuugpak una anguyagni eneqayarauguq.
Apanuugpak is [told] to remember wars.
Eneqakluku qalangssaguaqetullruat tauna
They told stories of him to remember [wars]
Avnerpak-llu.
And Avnerpak.
Tua-i-w’ quyanaqvaa. Time-airutukut.
Thank you. We’re out of time.
Ii-i. Wiinga-llu-w’ tua-i quyalrianga waniw’ piyunaqlua iquklicamku time-aq.
Okay. I’m also thankful that I was able to make it to the end of our time well.
Yaa, tangrruuqalarciquten Yuut Qanruyutaitni pia[rkani].
Okay, you’ll be seen on the Traditional Yup’ik Wisdom program.
Ii-i. (Ii-i.)
Okay. (Okay.)
Tua-i pitsaqevkenii pinirikuma cali tua-i piyugngaunga.
SHould I get stronger, I can [come] again.
Yaa.
Okay.
Segganqeggikuma. (Ii-i.)
When I have vigor. (Okay.)