You could turn off the TV. (Yaa.)
You could turn off the TV. (Okay.)
Heck no, we want that.
The TV up there.
Yaa.
Yes.
Au͡girautnayukluku. (Camek yuarcit?)
It might interfere. (What are you looking for?)
Just seeing where those went.
How many minutes ayallrurta?
How many minutes has it been going?
Aa?
What?
How many minutes ayallrurta?
How many minutes has it been going?
Kina?
Who?
Tauna.
That one.
Counter-aara tangqerru.
Look at its counter.
Thirteen... 1:39.
Two minutes piqarraarcelluku.
Let it go for two minutes.
Okay.
You know, tape-aq ayagnirtassiirniartuq.
You know, so the tape can try starting.
Qangvaq ayallruceci?
When did you go?
Let’s see. When...
Qitevtevkenak. Qitevcuumiitellrulriaten iciw.
Don’t speak English. You know, you didn’t want to speak English.
Tuesday-mi atakumi maaken ayallruukut.
We traveled from here on Tuesday evening.
Last week-qaa?
Last week?
Yaa.
Yes.
Akmanlluci-llu-qaa one week-arrluci kiingan?
Were you only there for one week?
Pingayiritmi tekitellruukut akmavet, Wednesday morning unuakuayaarmi.
We arrived over there on Wednesday, early Wednesday morning.
Mic-aa-qaa alaiciiquq?
Will her mic be audible?
Anchorage-aamun ciungani pilartuten, qaa?
You’ve gone to Anchorage before, right?
Yaa, yaa.
Yes, yes.
Kiturluku-llu-qaa ayaksaunak?
And have you never gone past it?
Ayaksaunii.
I’ve never gone.
Fairbanks-amun tau͡gaam
Except to Fairbanks.
Akmavet tekitellerpeni, Alaska-mek maaken anllerpeni akmavet
When you arrived over there, when you left Alaska here
Camek irr’itengqellrusit?
What were you amazed by?
Tua-i-wa tamakunek nunarpagnek angssiyaagpakalrianek, tamakunek ciumek irr’itengqellruunga.
Well, those big cities that are too big, those were the first things I was amazed by.
Camek, camek elpeni irrayugluten?
What was amazing to you?
Camek-wa irrayuucuunii. I mean, tangellrenka tamakut pagaaken tangrraqamki angssiyaagpakallratnek.
I wasn’t amazed by anything. I mean, when I saw those things I saw from above, how they were too big.
Tamatumek.
That.
Qaillun ayuqluni un’a tangellren?
What was what you saw down there like?
Tua-i-w’ enenek tamakunek mit’eqatarqamta tangllemnek amllessiyaagpakalrianek ucuryuglallruunga.
When we were going to land, I was in awe how there were too many buildings that I saw.
Laavkaarpauluteng-qaa?
Were they big buildings?
Laavkaarpauluteng-llu.
And they were big buildings.
Tua-i cuculuki maantesqumayaaqluki-ll’ tamakut laavkaarpiit ilait.
I was also envious, wanting some of those big buildings to be here.
Akiitellratnek tuaten cuculua.
I also envious of how cheap they were.
Qaill’ aklut-qaa tamakut wani akiitellriit eneqakevkanritait avani maani wani kiputeqarraalallermeggni iciw’ akiitellrulriit?
Didn’t those cheap goods make you remember how back when they first started buying things, you know, how cheap they were?
Tamana wani qanrutkeqerru.
Please talk about that.
Tamakunek umyuarteqellrunritua. Watua tau͡gaam maa-i yugnek umyuarteqellruunga anagulluteng maani cakniussiyaagpakalrianek neqkanek aturanek-llu.
I didn’t think about those. But now, I think about how people here are struggling too much for food and clothes.
Maa-i watua makut yunraat-llu umyuaqellruanka cakneq.
Now, I strongly remember these people and the young people.
Ceńirqurallerpeceńi-mi canek tangaalallrusit?
When you went visiting, what did you see?
Tua-i-w’ tamakunek laavkaani canek naunrarnek, uqvialle’rnek-llu uqviamcetun ayuqevkenateng.
Well, in those buildings, some plants, and some willow trees that aren’t like our willows.
Naucetaanek-ll’ amllessiyaagnek tangenrritua.
And I didn’t see too many flowers.
Ataucinek tau͡gaam imkunek orange-anek, tamakunek tau͡gaam tangellruunga.
But those single orange ones, I only saw those.
Atsanek-ll’ tangerpek’nii.
I didn’t see berries.
Cali tamaani umyuarteqellruunga, quyallruunga maani makurmiungullemnek.
At the time, I was thinking, I am thankful to be from here.
Iciw’ ak’anurpak uitanricaaqua.
You know, I didn’t stay for very long
Four, three, four days, taukut iluatni uitayaaqua.
Four, three, four days, I was there for that time.
Umyuarteqellruunga qanrucatnga, qanrucanga Bridget-am, "Waniwa-gguq uksuqaat"
I thought when they told me, when Bridget told me, "This is their winter"
Wiinga tua-i tamaanelkuma waniwa, tamaaken wii yuurtellemnek ayagnirlua tamaanelkuma naliak cangalkessanritaqa.
If I were there now, if I were there starting from when I was born, I wouldn’t mind either way.
Tau͡gaam umyuarteqellruunga, "Tamaanelkuma waniwa wak’nirnek ayaglua upakuma tamaavet tua-i cakneq, cakneq cupegcartua maavet Alaska-mun."
But I thoughtt, "If I were there, if I moved there from here on out, I would be very, very homesick for Alaska here."
Umyuarteqlua-llu, umyuarteqaqlua-llu, "Kaaka, makut waniwa yuut maani elisngiimegteggu-w’ cangalkenritlikiit. Taqsuqsuitut."
And I thought, I would think, "Listen, because these people are used to it here, they don’t mind it. They don’t get tired."
Wiinga waniwa ukvengama qangvarpak ukanirpak nak’nirnek tayima quyatma ilaklaraat man’a nunavut.
Since I have gotten faith, since a long time, I’m not sure when, one of the things I’m thankful for is our land here.
Puqigluni Agayutem taqsuqevkayuunata-llu.
God, being smart, doesn’t make us tired.
Allrakum iluani cimirluki cat.
He changes things throughout the year.
Up’nerkami nunanirpak qanikcaq ayagaqluni, cikuq-ll’ ayagaqluni.
In the spring, it’s wonderful when the snow goes, and the ice goes.
Kiagmi-llu neqnek neqkamteńek uptaqluta neqpignek, atsanek-llu uksurpak pikamteńek.
And in the summer, we prepare fish for food, salmon, and berries to have all winter.
Tua-ll’ ataam uksurpak uitaluta. Imna qanikcaq, qanikcaq tekican nunaniryugluta.
Then again in the winter, we stay. When the snow comes, we are joyous.
Makut-llu eglertessuuteput cimirluteng.
And our modes of travel change.
Ikamrarluta, qimugcirluteng-llu ukanirpak pitullrulriit.
We have sleds, and in the past, they would mush dogs.
Tua-ll’ watua amlleq qimugtairucan amlleq yuk snuukurluni fourwheel-arluni-ll’ piyaurrluni.
Then now, since many don’t have dogs, many people have started using snow-gos and fourwheelers.
Tua-i nunaniqluteng tamakut.
Those were wonderful.
Manaryaquluta-ll’ cikum aciani anglaniluta piaqluta.
Then we would go jig in the ice and have fun.
Tua-ll’ ataam up’nerkarluni, ataam qanikcaq taman’ nangluni, ataam mer’urrluni, ataam nutaan tamakut cat can’get-llu cimirluteng nutaraurrluteng.
Then it’s winter again, now more snow again, become water again, and those things including grass change to become new again.
And the berries come again, and the fish come again.
Ataam nunaniqluni, taqsuqsuunata.
It’s wonderful again, and we don’t get tired.
Tamaani tuarpiaq wangni nalluamki tayima cat allat iciw’ anglanirrlainarluteng piyarngatut.
At the time, it truly seemed to that because I don’t know them, others would, you know, always have fun.
Wiinga quyaunga maantellemnek Alaska-mi
I’m thankful that I’m here in Alaska
Tamakunek taqsuqevkaqsaunii piliaqestemteńun iciw’ pimallra.
That our creator, you know, doesn’t make me tired of those.
Tua-i ukanirpak tamana nallungramku umyuama-llu tauna ilaklaraat
Though I’ve never known in before, that is part of what’s in my mind
Iciw’ taqsuqevkaqsaunata Agayutem cat cimirturluki, cakaput cimirturluki pimallinikiikut.
You know, that God doesn’t make us tired of things by constantly changing them, changing what we will have.
Cali-qaa unayuqkatgen ayagyuumauten?
If they invited you again, could you go?
Cali unayaqkatnga ayagyallilrianga.
If they invited me again, I’d probably go.
Ukanirpak waniwa-w’ ukut angliameng irniallrama ayaucungraatnga ayayuitlallruunga.
Up until now, since my children are grown, though they wanted to travel with me, I wouldn’t.
Iciw’ umyuarteqlua maani akirrarmek-ll’ qunulua.
You know, I would think of also being reluctant to spend a little money.
Ellaita-llu akiuciryungraatnga akirrait qunukluki.
And though they wanted to give me money, I didn’t want them to spend that little money.
Iciw’ paqnayugyuunii-llu canek.
And, you know, I wouldn’t be curious about things.
TV-ni-ll’ tangerrlangramki tuaten-ll’ pilarningraitki anagulluni umyuaqa paqnayuyuunani.
And even when I see them on TV, and they say they do those things, I’m not terribly curious in my mind.
Tua-ll’ waniwa au͡g’um nengauma aanii nangteqngan
Then now, since my son-in-law’s mother is sick
Tua-i pinritevkenii qanrutellrani mulungaitniluteng irniatek tamalkuita tangerrsartuuteqatarniluki maurluatnun
I made sure, when they told me that they wouldn’t wait to take all of their children to go see their grandmother
Tua-i pinritevkenii wii-ll’ maliggnaluki, maligucullruunga.
I made sure, [because] I wanted to go with them.
Apepailgatnga-ll’, iciw’ wiinga-ll’ piyullemnek apepailgatnga wangnek maligcugluki maligtellruanka
And before they asked me, you know, before they asked me if I wanted to, I went with them since I wanted to go myself
Kenekngamku tauna maurluat meet-allruamku ak’a ciungani malrurqugnek.
Because I loved their grandmother since I’d met her twice in the past.
Ellminek tailuni maavet kassuuteqatallragni. Meet-allruaqa tamaani.
She came of her own accord when they were going to get married. I met her then.
Ataam-llu call’ kinguakun cali irniangumarilukek ataam cali tailuni cali sister-aminek cousin-aminek-ll’ malilirluni.
Then again afterwards, when they’d had children, she came again along with her sister and her cousin.
Wiinga-ll’ ataam ullagluki maani, maani quyungqaluta uitallruukut.
Then I went to them again here, and we’d stay here together.
Iciw’ kenekngamku, au͡g’umek-llu qetunrarminek cikipigainarluta cikirngakut
You know, because I loved her, and she’d completely given us her son
Iciw’ cangalkenrilamku, amllernek-llu wii angutnek irniangqenrilama kenekluku ilakarput.
You know, because I had no qualms with her, and since I don’t have a lot of male children, we love him as our own.
Cali aanii tauna wii kenekluku.
I also loved his mother.
Ilutequatekluku-llu au͡g’um panillera’urluma piyuilaku.
Also because my dear daughter didn’t have grievances against her.
Cakneq tua-i allragnirpak takumcukluku wangnun elliqluku ayaasqumalaranka ukut.
Since last year, out of great pity for her, [?I bring it upon myself] to ask them to go.
Ullaasqumalallruaqa.
I’d tell them to go to her.
Nulirqeqatallragni tamaani pisqellrunricaaqaqa cakneq ayaulluku akmavet peggluku nanikuavkarnayukluku.
Back when they were going to get married, I really didn’t want her to in case he might bring her over there, abandon her, and make her feel helpless.
Tauna piciunritlinian maa-i cakneq kenekluku.
Since that wasn’t true, I love him a lot now.
Cingumaluki-llu ayaasqaqluki ullaasqelluku tauna maurluat takumcukluku cakneq, kiirraan-ll’ irniaqelliniaku
And I encourage them to go to see their grandmother out of great pity for her, also because he’s her only child
Nallunrilamku qaillun irniami keneknarqetacia, tutagara’urlumi-ll’ keneknarqetaciit qaillun nallunrilamku.
Because I know how much one loves their chidlren, and because I know how much one loves their grandchildren.
Tua-i wangcetun ayuqsukluku cakneq cingumalallruanka allragnirpak.
Thinking that she was like me, I’d encourage them a lot all last year.
Camek tayima qanqeryukuvet. Aptellrunrilkengamnek akmavet ayallerpenek qaneryukuvet wall’ qaneryuumiilkuvet.
You can say something else. You can say something about what I haven’t asked you about your travels out there, or if you don’t want to.
Tua-i-w’ irr’iyullemnek-llu canek angelrianek aptellrukevnga, apcaaqekevnga au͡ga-i.
You also just asked me about what big thigns I was amazed by over there.
Irr’iyullruunga au͡gkunek...
I was amazed by those...
TIme-angqenrilami anagulluta ayagatellrunritaakut canun au͡g’um ayagatestemta.
Since [s]he didn’t have time, our escort didn’t take us to a lot of things.
Tau͡gaam Saturday-mi... let’s see.
But on Saturday... let’s see.
Yaa, Maqinermi ayagatellruakut.
Yes, [s]he brought us around on Saturday.
Canun taukunun ayauskilikut qunguturanun mermiutarnun.
[S]he brought us to an aquarium.
Sea otters, whales, tamakut ellicaumalliniluteng. Cakneq irr’inaqluteng.
Sea otters, whales, those were penned. They were very amazing.
Tamakunek tua-i, arcaqerlua-ll’ tamakunek irr’iyullruunga.
Those, I was especially in awe of those.
"Atak’ tamakut ellicartait," umyuarteqlua, "Angli-lli tamakuni ellicartaitni iciw’ they have patience."
"Look, their keepers," I thought, "Wow, their keepers are so, you know, they have patience."
Qenqercuunateng kaaka tayima ellicamaita ak’aki.
They don’t get angry, listen, as they pen so many.
Tua-i cakneq casqaqaiceteng canaurtut tamakut.
When they were commanded, those [animals] would do things.
Nepliisqaqaceteng-ll’ nepliqluteng. Quyurnisqaqaiceteng-ll’ quuyurniaqluteng.
When they were told to make a sound, they made the sound. When they were told to smile, they smiled.
Tamakunek cakneq irr’iyullruunga tua-i cakneq. Taukunek angelrianek irr’iyupiarallruunga.
I was very amazed by those. I was amazed by those large [animals].