Taumek apciiqamken.
I will ask you about that.
Qaillun-kiq waniw' piniarcia? Nalluvagcia. Elisngassiyaanripagcia.
I wonder how I'll do it? I don't know. I don't know too much about it.
Assirtuq tamakut answer-aaten.
Your answers are good.
Oh okay.
Oh, okay.
Taringamken.
I understand you.
Ii-i.
I see.
Qanemcillren ava-i waniw'
The story you just told
Qanrutellren wangkutnun ava-i pillren,
What you just said to us,
Makut kenkesqelluki waniw' ikiungraameng. Cauniarta-kiq akiliuteq ircaqumteggun?
How we should treat others with love though they are bad. What would be the reward for our hearts?
Ircaqumteggun akiliutii kinguqvaarni assirluku.
The reward for our hearts will be good in the future.
Uitanqegciluta uitallerkarput akiliutngungaciiqliniuq. Iciw' yuk...
It seems that our reward will be that we will live in peace. You know, a person...
Avani-gguq yuut ciuqvaarni tamana tamaa-i cali qanruyutelleq yuut tamarmeng
They said that people long ago, there is also traditional wisdom that all people
Elluarlluteng ilait piksaitelallruyaaqlilriit.
Some of them probably do not live right.
Caunrilkinritellerkaq uiminek tamaa-i.
That is how one shouldn't disparage their husband.
Kinguqvaarni uitanqegciluta assirluta uitallerkarput.
So that we will be able to live peacefully in the future.
Yaa.
I see.
Tua-i arcaqalria qanrusken. Camek cali allamek pirkaituten?
You've said the important thing. Do you have anything else?
Wiinga au͡gna wiinga iciw'
Personally, you know
Avani ciuqvaarni ayuqucillerput tangerrluku, waniwa-llu cali ayuqucirput
Looking at how we were back then, and how we are now
Wiinga amllerqunek takumcuyulartua ayagyuanek.
Many times, I pity young people.
Iciw' takaunateng-wa tua-i wall'u-wa yuucurlagluteng pilriit.
You know, they act in socially unacceptable ways, or they are leading bad lives.
Akusrarnarqellriit cumigulluki.
They focus on misbehavior.
Tamakut wiinga takumcuklaranka iciw'.
I pity those, you know?
Akusrarrlua anglillrunrilama. Akusrarrlua anglillrunritua.
Because I didn't grow up mischievous. I didn't grow up mischievous.
Assiinii-llu iliini assiitelangerma assiini,
And being bad, even though I was bad sometimes,
Irniamnun aanaulleq takaqaqa.
I treat being a mother to my children with respect.
Assirlua tau͡gaam yuuyuglua umyuarteq'laama.
Because I only have my mind on wanting to live well.
Maa-i mat'um nalliini takumcuyulartua ayagyuanek
These days, I pity young people
Qanruyutnek-wa tua-i nallulrianek tua-i-wa qanrutkumayuilata.
Those that do now know traditional wisdom because they are not spoken about.
Waten tau͡gaam man'a calillertek KYUK-kun alaitaqluteng Yupiit qalarucilaqata
But with your work with KYUK like this, if they show Yupiit speaking [about traditional teachings]
Tamaa-i assilriamek caliciquci.
You will do good work.
Man'a-llu man'a-wa Yugturrlainaq pivkenaku
And not doing this only in Yup’ik
Kass'atun, Kass'atun mumiggluku makut ayagyuaput qitevquralriit taringevkarluki pikuvci assilriamek caliciquci.
In English, if you translate it into English so that the young people who only speak English will understand, you will do good work.
Tamaa-i arcaqalria wiinga qanruteksukeka.
That’s the important thing I want to say.
Man'a Yugni piciryaraput mixed-aucamta watua maa-i.
Our Yup’ik ways, since we are being mixed today.
Nulirqellriit Yugglainaunritut. Kass'anek aipangqertut.
Married couples are not all Yup’ik. They have Caucasian spouses.
Kass'at-llu aipait tamakut taringyunarqut wangkuta Yup'igni
Their Caucasian spouses also need to understand how we Yupiit
Qaillun assirluta nulirqutlerkaput. Kass'at-llu elicugngaat.
How we would be good married couples. Caucasians can learn it too.
Qanruyutet aliartaqluki pinaciaqsaunaki.
Show the traditional wisdom without delay.
Uuggun KYUK-kun wall' tiiviikun amlleqapiaraata watua nulirqellriit elluarrluteng quyungqanrilnguut ayagyuat.
Through KYUK or TV, since there are a lot of married couples now, young people, who are not gathered right.
Yaa. Au͡g'umek paqnayularyaaqua iciw',
Yes. I am curious about that, you know
Ciin-gguq mikelnguut aananun caumanrulartat aatanun pivkenateng?
Why are children more attached to mothers, not fathers?
Aanat enem iluani uitauratuut, aatat-llu anluteng ayagatuluteng, pissurluteng, caliluteng.
Mothers stay in the house, and the fathers go out to travel, hunt, and work.
Aanani wangkuta irniamta caunganrularaitkut,
Our children are more attached to us mothers
Wangkuta home-ami uitauralaamta.
Because we stay at home.
Neqkiurteńguluta, aturait iqairluki, aulukluki tua-i family-put. Aanani wangkuta important-aartukut home-ami.
We prepare food, wash their clothes, take care of our families. We mothers are important in the home.
Taumek irniani, irniat angayuqateng niisngakunegteki,
That’s why if children are obedient to their parents,
Aanateng-ll’ una arcaqerluku niisngakunegtegu assirciquq.
And if they’re especially obedient to their mothers, it will be good.
Aanameggnek niisngainrilnguut aanaitni akngirqelartut.
Those who are disobedeint to their mothers, their mothers get hurt.
Aanat amllermek calirpagtut home-ami.
Mother work hard on a lot of things in the home.
Irniat tua-i tamalkuita aulukluki, kenekluki-ll' tamalkuita.
They take care of all of their children, and love them all.
Man'a tau͡gken irniam aanagni
However, a child who [disobeys] their parents
Narurtaaqunikek aanau͡rluat
If he keeps disobeying them, their poor mother
Akngirtaqluni ircaqumikun. Tamana assirpek’nani.
Her heart will be hurt. That’s not good.
Aaniit yuut takuatgun irniami takuatgun qiangaicaaquq, nalluatgun tau͡gaam qiagaqluni, akngirrluni ircaqumikun.
Their mother would not cry in front of her children, but cry without their knowledge, hurting in her heart.
Tua-i-wa irniani aanateng narurtaaqunegteki tamaaggun aanateng nangciiqliniat.
If their children keeps disobeying their parents, they will make their mother suffer through that.
Man'a aanauyaraq cakneq angtuaruuq.
Being a mother is extremely important.
Man'a-llu maa-i aanauyaraq
And being a mother
Yugni amllerni Kass'ani-llu makuni ayagyuani nallunricunaqluni.
Many people, even among these Caucasians, these young people need to know it.
Aanateng qigcikluki umyugait navgurpek’naki pikuneng tamaa-i assirluteng yuuciqut.
If they respect their mothers without destorying their mental health, they will live well.
Amta-llu qigcikevkenaki pikuneng assiinateng yuuluteng
Yet if they do not respect them, they will lead bad lives
Akusrarrluteng cat makut aturyugluki inerquutai.
Misbehaving, doing the things she admonishes against.
Makut aanailnguut aatailnguut waniw' kitumek iciw’ elicimarqailnguut kitumun ullagyugngaat?
These children without mothers or fathers who, you know, want do not have teachers, who can they go to?
Kinkut ullagyugngaaki nallunriryukaki?
Who can they go to if they want to learn them?
Ii-i, makut elliraat aanailnguut aatailnguut-llu,
Well, these orphans without mothers and fathers
Wiinga elliraullruama elder ciuqlirraam arnassagaam wall',
Since I was an orphan, an elder, an elder lady, or
Arnam wall' angutem old-alriim qalarutaqanga wiinga cakneq quyalallruunga.
When an old woman or man taught me, I would be very thankful.
Tua-i-llu waniwa makut elliraat,
And so, these orphans
Assirluteng angliyukuneng makut ciurlirneteng Yupiit ullagluki,
If they want to grow up well, they should go to their Yup’ik elders
Camek apcugngait. Qanrucugngaaput qaillun assirluku pillerkaitnek.
They can ask them something. We can tell them how they would do well.
Quyana.
Thank you.
Yaa.
You’re welcome.
Cali allamek makunek apyutkangqerkuma
If I have any other questions
Niicugniurlua pikuma iciw’ ilait waniwa maa-i
If I listen, you know, some of them now
Ilait iciw' nepliqallrulriit wall’u-qaa,
You know, some of them had a commotion, or
Assirluten pillruuten. Pekaavkenak pillruuten.
You did well. You didn’t make sudden movements.
Yaa, tuaten piqtaaryuumiilama question-aaten tangerrsullruanka.
Yes, since I didn’t want to do that, I wanted to see your questions.
Yaa, nutaan.
Yes, that’s good.
Waste-aryuumiinaku time.
I didn’t want to waste time.
Man'a qalartellerpuk Kass'at-llu niiskunegneki assiryarluni.
It would be good if Caucasians also listened to our conversation.
Amllerrata Kass'at, half and half-nulirqellriit.
Because there are a lot of Caucasians, married couples who are half [Yup’ik] and half [Caucasian].
Rusty, don’t move around.
You might disturb her.
Nakleng, I didn’t mean to be so imkuciq.
Sorry, I didn’t mean to be so, you know.
Tau͡gaam nepainaku qaneryagan pillruamku waniw’ nepaiqurasqellruaqa.
But since I told him to be quiet when he was talking, I told him to be quiet.
Canrituq. Foster kid-aqaqa.
It’s okay. He’s my foster kid.
Qaa? Assiqtarluni.
Really? He’s so adorably well-behaved.
Two-aagnek pingqertua. Aipaa elitnaurtuq.
I have two. The other is in school.
Qaillun tam’ foster kid-aqluku?
How is he your foster kid?
Through the state?
Yaa. Last year pivkallruatnga.
Yes.They had me do it last year.
Wanigga-ll’ assirluni?
And he’s good now?
Nuu, cali piqataraanga.
No, she’s going to [interview] me again.
This is just cutaways.
I need her to talk at length.
For a long time?
Qaillun?
How?
Piciatun qanaagumaluten.
Speak about random things.
Mikelnguvnek 	qanemcisnga.
Tell me stories about your children.
Qaillun?
How?
Qavcinek mikelngungqercit, grandchildren-aangqercit?
How many children and grandchildren do you have?
Calallrat mikelnguten.
What your children used to do.
Wiinga ten-aanek irniangqertua.
I have ten children.
Tutgaraanka-wa seven-aat. Ikgetut seven-aat.
I have seven grandchildren. They are few, seven.
Tamarmeng-llu taqnerurrluteng, atauciq tau͡gaam kinguqliat high school-arluni kiimi.
And they’ve all become adults, but only one, the youngest, is in high school alone.
Tamarmeng-llu, ilait ellmeggnek pingluteng.
And all of them, some of them are on their own now.
Assirluteng ellmeggnek aulukengnaqluteng.
They’re doing well, trying to take care of themselves.
Waqaa?
What’s going on?
Nuu, cikiryaaqluku.
No, I gave him something.
Oh, cingkaniryukuvgu keluqvaqaniryugngauq cali.
Oh, if you want to push it more, it can go further back still.