Cunaw’ atellgutkekemken.
Turns out, we have the same name.
Qalarrluteng test-arluku.
Please speak to test it.
Yaa, tua-llu?
Okay, can you hear me?
Qalarrluten cali.
Speak more.
Qaillun?
How?
Piciatun.
Any way.
Yaa.
Okay.
Quseryukataryugnarqua wii.
I think I’m going to be coughing.
Kitak’ ayagnia.
Now, start.
Qaill’ ellangellerpeni umyuaqsiu?
What do you remember in your earliest memories?
Yaa, ellangellemni wani ellangellruunga un’gani Tagyaram iluani.
Okay, growing up, my earliest memories are of downriver in Tagyaraq.
Tauna naanguaqsaagaa.
(S)he’s trying ot play with that.
Tauna naanguaqevkenaku. Atam [?]... hey!
Don’y play with that. Look [?]... hey!
Yaa, ellangellemni ellangellruunga Tagyaram iluani.
Yes, growing up, my earliest memories are in Tagyaraq.
Aterluni tauna nunallerput Quunermek.
Our old village there was called Quuneq.
Quunermek.
[It was called] Quuneq.
Ellangarteqarraallemni wani im’ullruunga
In my earliest memores, I, you know
Kiimecukelallruukut.
We used to think we were alone.
Ellamun-llu mom-ama anevkarqanga
And when my mom had me go outside
Tua-i kiarrnaurtua, tuar tang maani avatemteńun ella pimalalria.
I would look around, and it would seem that the world extended to our vicinity.
Iciw’ kiimeta tuar tang yuuluta. Umyuarteqaqlua-llu kiimeta yuuyukluta.
You know, it seemed like we were the only people. And I would think we were the only people.
Ukut-llu angiinka tekitnaurtut yuilqumek tuar. Wangni yuilqumek tekicukaqluki.
And my older brothers would arrive seemingly from the wilderness. I thought they came from the wilderness.
Nunapiamteńek cunaw’ Qinarmek tekitelallinilriit.
Apparently, they’d come from our home village, Qinaq.
Tuamtell’ aataka wani ayagnaurtuq.
Then my mother would travel.
Tekiutnaurtuq canek Kass’artarnek-wa tua-i kipukengaminek.
He would bring back Western things he had purchased.
Cunaw’ Ciutmi call’ uani cali Tagyaram iluani taumek ilura’urluminek kipusvigtelallrullinill’.
Apparently, he would go to the store owned by his male cross-cousin there in Ciun, also in Tagyaraq.
Caaqami cali ayalallruuq.
Some days, he would go.
Maligcugyaaqaqamni yaaqvanun piqatarniaqluni.
When I wanted to go with him, he’d say that was going to go far away.
Tua-i-ll’ apcamni Ekvicuarmiunun ayakatarniluni.
Then when I asked him, he’d say he was going to go to Eek.
It turned out, what did they call their resident Caucasian in Eek again?
Tuavet cali Kass’artelalliniluni.
He’d also buy Western things from there.
Tua-ll’ murilkenglua, maligtelangluku-llu aataka.
Then I became observant, and started going with my father.
Tua-i tuavet wani Ciutmun ilura’urluanun Kass’artaqlunuk. Tua-i kiingan taumun maliketulua caqa’arqami.
We would go buy western things there in Ciun from his cousin. I would only go with him there, sometimes.
Yugnun maliksuitellruanga. Tua-i nacikangramnia maliksuunii, yuilqurrlainarmun tau͡gaam
He didn’t bring me with him to other people. He wouldn’t take me though I was sad over his departure, only [took me] to the wilderness.
Tua-i-ll’ murilkengama nalluyagucuirullua.
Then when I became observant, I had permanent long term memory.
Cali ukut neqlilput Cuuvalegmiut, cali taum tua-i nunakelallemta uakariini
And our fishcamp in Cuukvalegmiut, also right downriver from our old settlement
Taukut cali tua-i tuaten ayuquryukaqluki, kiaguuryuki-llu.
I also thought that place was always like that, and was in eternal summer.
Umyuartequtaqluki tuaten, kiaguuratuyukluki.
I thought of them like that, that it was always summer there.
Tuantaqluteng amllerrluteng taukut.
There would be many staying there.
Aya’agqata-ll’ tang tau͡gken umyuaqngateksaunaki-llu upa’agqamta.
And I don’t think I remembered them when they left, when we moved.
Tua-i-ll’ murilkenglua tua-i.
Then I became observant.
Itrarluta-llu.
And we went upriver.
Tamaani-wa kinguqlinglallruyaaqellriakuk wangkuk.
Back then, the two of us would get younger siblings.
Ugna-llu tungkeqerlunuk yuumallruukuk kiirramegnuk.
[My sibling] downriver and I lived as lone [siblings] for a long time.
Tua-i-ll’ au͡g’umek Qinarmun itranemteggun kinguqlinglunuk.
Then right when we went upriver to Qinaq, we got a younger siblings.
Qurrelvagmun uksuiyaturiluta im’ungluta
When we’d started going to winter camp in Qurrelvak, we, you know
Taumek ug’umek wani kinguqlinglunuk.
We got a younger sibling, the one downriver.
Tua-i-ll’ tua-i tayima.
Then that’s how it went.
Tua-i-ll’ imkulua
Then I, you know
Qukaqlircarametaqluta, cali tuani itrallemteńi Qurrelvagmun uksuillemteńun tag’aqluta.
We’d be in Qukaqlircaraq, and when we went upriver then, we would go inland to our winter camp, Qurrelvak.
Tau͡gaam elitnaurvingan 19...
But when a school was built in 19...
Elitnaungarcata 1951-aami uani Tuntutuliarmi
When thye started going to school in 1951 downriver at Tuntutuliak
Ayayuirutellruukut tamaaken ayagluta.
We stopped being nomadic ever since then.
Tau͡gaam-llu tamaa-i wani qanrucimalallruukuk-llu tua-i
But we would also be told
Waten-llu alerqulallruakuk aatamegnuk:
And our father used to instruct us like this:
"Carangllut-gguq enem iluani carrirturluki. Carrirturluki-gguq cat tamalkuita, natret.
"Always clean off debris in the house. Clean everything, the floors.
"Cat-llu pellernarqengraata ciqirqelluki."
"And though things feel gross, dump them out."
Umyuartequlluki-llu-gguq ciqitaqluki
He also said to think as we dumped them
Picuyuglunuk, wall’ unguvamayuglunuk, wall’u assirlunuk yuuyuglunuk naulluuyuunanuk.
That we want to be good hunter-gatherers, or live long, or live well without getting sick.
Wall’u kenirmigluki-llu-gguq anutaqluki caarrlut.
Or, he also said to put the debris in our front flounces and take them out.
Waten piluki wavet kenimun piluki anutaqluki-llu.
He said to pu tthem here in the front flounce, and take them out.
Atam-gguq tamaani yuut wani tanqingqerrsulriit
Look, he said, back then, the people who wanted to have light
Tanqingqerrsulriit clean up-aarturluteng tamakut pitullrulliniut
Those ones who wanted to have light would always clean up
Tuaten essuiculriit-gguq.
The ones he said wanted to be spiritually pure.
Ilait-gguq tua-i tuaten piuratulrit, naulluuyuunateng-llu-gguq tamakut yuut.
He said that osme of those who always did that, those people wouldn’t get sick.
And on their hems, he said that though they weren’t baptized, they’d emit light from their hems, and the tips of their sleeves, and here from their neck openings.
Waten tanqigmek anllungaqluteng. Tarrarteng’e’rmeng-llu ellami tan’gerciyuunateng.
They’d emit light like this. And though they walked around outside, it wouldn’t be too dark for them.
Tamaa-i tuaten qanrutetullruakuk.
That’s what he used to tell us.
Tamakut-ll’ angllumanrilnguuyaaqluteng, nalluvkenateng tamaa-i.
And those people weren’t baptized, but they knew.
Tuamtellu-gguq naulluulriit pelqevkenaki uqlautekengramteki kenugtelarlaput.
Then he said that we shouldn’t be averse to the sick, but help clean them up though we get dirty.
Tamaa-i-gguq carrluk-gguq yugnun agtuucuituq.
He said that impurities do not affect people.
Menuurcuituq-gguq yuk kevgiulria.
He said that a person who serves does not become impure.
Tau͡gaam naulluulangraata-llu ilani naulluungaitetulliniluni.
But even though those around him are sick, (s)he will not get sick.
Tamaa-i tang.
There you have it.
Tuamtell’ wani kevgiurturalriit
Then, those who serve
Iciw’ tamakut-llu qeciit carrirluki uqlautek’nge’rmegteki
You know, cleaning skins though they get dirty
Erurilriani-gguq au͡ga’atuut, tau͡gaam-gguq yugmun nepcuitut.
He said they come off with washing, but they don’t stick to a person.
Tua-i wani...
Well...
Tuamtell’ cali makut qantat wani
Then these bowls
Makut wani qantat iciw’ erurturluki cat.
These bowls, you know, always wash things.
Neqallret-llu tutmallermun pinrilcaarturluki pitullrulliniluteng.
They would also always discard food scraps where they wouldn’t be tread upon.
Tua-i-ll’ cali wani amlleq qanruyun nalluyagutarput maa-i tamalkumta.
Also, all of us are forgetting much traditional wisdom.
Wangkuta-llu, Yuulriani wangkuta qanruyutet Yup’igtaat nalluyagulluki.
And we, we Yupiit, have forgotten the traditional Yup’ik wisdom.
We’ve forgotten them.
Tuamtell’ cali waten wani
Then like this
Ava-i, icivaq cali Naparyarrarmiumek qalartellriamek niitellrulrianga.
Recently, I also heard someone from Napakiak speaking.
Wiinga-llu eneqerluki, qanruyutek’lalqa-llu eneqerluku waten:
And I remembered the traditional wisdom passed down to me like this:
Eneqaqercetaarluku, eneqaqercetaarluki-gguq.
Try to have that person remember, try to have them remember.
Waten-llu aatama qanrut’lallruakuk:
My father also used to tell us this:
"Eneqaqercetaarluki-gguq nallunringraitki qanruquratuit."
"Though they know them, they always tell them to have them remember."
Taumek-gguq qanruyutnek qanrutestemteńek-llu taqsuqeksaunata, tau͡gaam niicugniaqluki qanrit murilkelluki tangvagluki piarkaulliniluta.
That’s why he said we should never tire of traditional wisdom or our instructors, but we must listen to them, watching their mouths.
Waten-llu qanrut’lallrukiitnga wiinga tua-i assiiturluama
They also used to tell me this, because I was woefully bad
Assiiturluama pilaqiitnga cunaw’ qanruyutmek
Since I was woefully bad, they would tell me what was apparently traditional wisdom
"Yuk-gguq qaskukegcipiatuuq."
"A person has a very good appearance."
Murak-ll’ ava-i imna Naparyarrarmium taum qanrutkellra.
And wood, what that person from Napakiak was talking about.
Murak kiinga ciknayaramun atuuvkenani cali.
Wood is not only used for jealousy.
Yuk-gguq qaskukegcipiatuuq, assirluni tangellra tangniqluni, apqevceńek cute-arluni.
He said that a person has a very good appearance, very nice to look, cute as you call it.
Tau͡gken-gguq tuamtellu-gguq murak angutem tekiciiqaa, murakegtaar.
However, he said that a man may come upong a great [looking] piece of wood.
"Cakneq-lli-gguq equgcigpaa."
"What a great piece of wood."
Equgcilria-gguq tamana qupciqaa, ilua qipepiarluni.
He said he will split that good piece of wood, and the inside will be all twisted.
Tua-i-gguq yuk tuaten, wangkuta-gguq yugni tamalkumta tuaten umyuarput assiiculria tuaten ayuquq.
He said that a person, all of us people with bad minds are like that.
Tuamtell’ cali angutnguli wall’ arnauluni tuaten ayuqluni.
Also, a man or a woman is like that.
Tuamtell’ cali muragmek-gguq tekiciiquq qipepiamek, murak qipluni.
Then he said one may come across a very twisted piece of wood, the wood all twisted.
Tua-i-llu-gguq eqgciatepiarluni tangellra.
He said it looks like a bad piece of wood.
Tua-llu-gguq qupsaagluku qupciqaa, elatii kiimi man’a qaskua qipluni, ilua nalqipiarluni aspiarluni.
Then he said one will try to split it open to find that only the outside is twisted, and the inside is good and straight.
Ikiunge’rmi-gguq yuk, kegginarrliq’nge’rmi, tuaten qipellriacetun ayuqeng’e’rmi
He said that though a person is ugly, has an ugly face, and is like that twisted piece of wood
Umyuaqegcikuni, umyuaqegcikuni-gguq tuaten ayuquq muragtun qipellriatun, ilua nalqigluni, ilukegcipiarluni.
He said that if (s)he has a good mind, they are like that twisted piece of wood with the straight grained inside, very good on the inside.
Tuamtell’ aspiarluni tangellra, straight-arluni murak equgcigciqnganani
Then a straight piece of wood looks good, like it’ll be a good piece of wood
Qupsaagluku-gguq qupciqaat ilua qipepiarluni.
He said they’d try to split it open, and the inside would be all twisted.
Tua-i-gguq cali tuaten yuk ayuquq.
He said that’s what a person is also like.
Kenegnang’e’rmi, kegginaqegcing’e’rmi, assinge’rmi, wall’u waten assirngalnge’rmi
Though they look lovely, have a good face, [acts] good, or seems good like this
Ilua-gguq tuaten ayuquq yuk umyuarrliqellria.
He said that the inside of a person with a bad mind is like that.
Taumek wani
Because of that
Maa-i makut umyuaqelararkaput.
These are things we must remember.
Waten-llu yuut assiilkurluki-llu piksaunki.
Also, do not treat people badly.
Ayuqenritut, umyugait-llu ayuqenritut tuaten tautun muragtun.
They’re different, and their minds are different like that piece of wood.
Muragcetun wangkuta ayuqelliniukut yugni.
Apparently, we people are like wood.
Wiinga-llu tuaten qanrucimalallruunga.
I was also told that.
Qiperrlugluama tua-i ikiungama qanruyutnek niitelallruunga.
Since I was pitifully twisted and bad, I would hear traditional wisdom.
Tua-i-ll’ tuaten, tuaten-llam qanrutaqatnga-llu
Then when they would tell me that
Ap’artelalrianga-llu iliini, "Ciin? Ciin tuaten ayuqluni?"
I would sometimes ask, "Why? Why is one like that?"
Tua-i-gguq yuk tuaten ayuquq.
They said a person is like that.
Qaskukegcilria-gguq tuaten straight-arnganani, ilua qipluni.
They said one with a good appearance looking straight, has twisted insides.
Tamalkurmeng tuaten
All of them like that
Assiitellriit, assilriit-llu tuaten tua-i elatait qipngalnge’rmeng, ilukegciluteng umyuaqegciluteng pitulliniluteng.
The ones [who look] good, and the ones who look bad though their appearances look twisted, have good insides when they have good minds.
Tamaa-i tamakut umyuaqnarqelaryaaqaput makut.
Those are the things we must remember.
Tua-i cali wani
Also
Yuum piqangraakut kiularavkenaki.
Though a person does anything to us, we shouldn’t retort.
Anagyaaqeksaunata-llu, assiryukeksaunata-llu.
And we shouldn’t defend ourselves, and not think that we’re good people.
Maani-llu tarrartellemteńi ilamteńi-llu assinruyukluta piqaqsaunata
And as we walk here, we should never think we’re better than those around us
Tau͡gaam assiilucirput wangkuta umyuaqaqluku.
But remember our own faults.
Tau͡gaam-llu assiilucirput umyuaqaqluku
But also, we should remember our own faults
Ilaliurturalput-llu taqsuunaki wangkuta assiitellerput pivkenaku.
And do not stop interacting with people because of our faults.
Ilaliuqcaarluki tau͡gaam yuut yuunaqliniluta.
Evidently, we must live socializing with other people.
Tuamtell’ cali waten call’ qanrucimalallruukuk:
Then we would also be told this:
Atam-gguq an’aqamegnuk
They said that when we go out
Egmianun-gguq ankumegnuk ellam qukaa tangerqilauk.
They said that right when we go out, we should look in the middle of the [Spirit of the] Universe.
Ellam-gguq Yua elingratartuq.
They said that the Spirit of the Universe is grateful by nature.
Ella-gguq paqnakerrlainarluku, kiarterrlainarluku, tamakut-llu agyat cuqyutet, cuqyutait.
They said to always check the weather, always look around, including at the navigation stars.
Tuamtell’ call’ akerta sass’aqellruluku yuut.
Then people also used the sun to measure time.
Tamaa-i-llu wani sass’anek makunek wani atulangllemni
And back when I started using these clocks
Aataka atam sass’anek piyuitellruuq, akertekun tau͡gaam.
My father, you see, never used clocks, only the sun.
Tua-i wani ellamek-ll’ itraarluni, anrraarluni itraqami qanlallruuq
Then after coming in from outside, after he went out and came in, he would say
"Erneq-gguq qukartuq. Nernariuq-gguq."
"It’s noon. It’s time to eat."
Maaten tang sass’aqa pinaurqa qukarluni, amta-ll’ sass’amek tangerqengaunani.
I would look at my clock and find that it was noon, yet he never saw a clock.
Tuamtell’ caaqami akerta pugqe’rcan egalernun qanernaurtuq, "One kela’agtuq-gguq."
Then sometimes, when the sun appeared in the windows, he would say, "It’s one o’clock."
Maaten cali sass’aqa tangerrnaurqa one kela’agluni.
I would look at my clock and find it would be one o’clock.
Tua-i cali sassauyugngalliniluni pekqurallrakun maaggun tangvagluku.
It can also be used to measure time by watching how it moves.
Ellaitni nallunaunani, wangkutni nallunaqluni tamana.
That is clear to them, and confusing for us.
Nallunaqngalengraata murilkellriit tamakut tuaten pitulliniut.
Though thye seem confusing, those who are observant do that.
Ava-i-am au͡gna-llu uumi tauna icivaq niitellemni, niigartellemni au͡gna
When I recently heard that, when I heard that
Eneqaqaqeka au͡gna cali waten qanrucimalalqa
I remember how I was told this
Yuk pillerkaa.
About what a person should do.
Tuamtell’ cali qanrut’lallrulua
Then they also used to tell me
Makut-wa kasngunarqengraata, takarnarqengraata qanrutkumaarkaulriit.
Though these are shameful and embarrassing, they must be told.
Atam qanrutkumaarkaullinilriit.
You see, they must be told.
Tuamtell’ cali kasngunaqpiangraata qalarutetulliniluku.
Then they would also speak to them though they were very shameful [topics].
Tuamtell’ qanrut’lallruatnga
Then they used to tell me
Nalluyaguartaqa-am qanerkaqa wani.
I forgot what I was going to say.
Iciw’ cakviussiyaallemni
You know, when I had too hard of a time
Cakviussiyaallma kinguani wani waten iliini qanerkanka, pitsaqenritua, nalluyagutelaranka.
After I struggled too much, I apologize, I sometimes forget what I’m going to say.
Tau͡gaam-llu waten umyuaminek-llu ping’e’rmi
But also, though one struggles with mental health
Yuut waten yuut umyuaminek ping’e’rmi
Though people struggle with mental health
Pinarqut, umyuaqnarqut wani.
We must remember them.
Ava-i qanelrianga, ava-i qalarcaaqellrianga au͡g’umek qanqatarlua nalluyagutaqa
I just said, I was just speaking about to say that, and I forgot
Tuani cakviurpapiallemni, ilarrlainaqellruamki-llu taukut uksuq imumi arulaillret week-am iluani.
When I struggled a lot, since they were all my relatives who passed away last winter over the course of one week.
Tau͡gaam kitak’ umyuarteq’lalta
But let us have this mindset
Cakviungramta yuut tamarmeng aturaat.
Though we struggle, all people experience it.
Aturaat yuut tamarmeng.
All people experience it.
Yuk-llu kiimi piyukevkenani, yuut tamarmeng cakviutulliniut umyuameggnek
And a person shouldn’t think they’re the only one, since all people struggle with mental health
Iliini wani cakneq cakviuraqluteng.
Sometimes having great troubles.
Tua-i cali qanrutkumalallret, qanlallret waten:
Also, this was said, people said this:
Yuk-gguq ellminek piyukellria umyuiqetuuq, kiituani-gguq usvillugtuq.
They said that one who thinks they’re alone become severely depressed, until eventually they go insane.
Tua-i-gguq-wa waten umyuarteqngami: "Wiinga kiima nangtequa umyuamnek."
They said it’s because he thinks like this: "I am the only one struggles with mental health."
Tau͡gken ellam iluani yuut tamarmeng nangteqtuluteng maani.
However, all people in the world suffer here.
Taumek wani waten pivkenata, umyuamteńek kiimeta nangteqsukevkenata.
That’s why we should think that we’re the only ones struggling with mental health.
Tau͡gaam umyuaqaqluki allat-llu nangteqellriit, tau͡gaam-llu pray-autaqluki wangkucicetun nangtequrlurmilriit umyuameggnek.
Instead, we should remember others with mental health problems, but pray for the ones who are also struggling with mental health like us.
Maa-i wani cakneq erenret ilaitni cakviurnaqluni erneq tekitelartuq.
Now, some days, a day comes where it is very hard.
Elpeci ap’lararci umyuarpeceńek hard time-arniluci.
You call it, having a hard time with your mental health.
Tua-i tamaa-i-nguuq tamana.
That’s what that is.
Kitak’ kiimeta umyuarteqsukeksaunata.
Now, let’s not think we’re the only ones who think that.
Instead, let all of us people consider each other
Pray-akun-llu umyuaqutaqluta piniartukut.
And let us consider each other in prayer.
Tua-i waten pitalii.
This is all from me.
Tuaten [?].
Like that [?].
Qaillun-wa qanerkailama
Since I have nothing to say
Kiingan qanerkaqngamku qalartellrianga au͡g’umek.
Since it was all I had to say, I talked about that.
Qanra. Qanra.
Its mouth. Its mouth.
Aling kingu’urrluku camera-liurteńgurtellriaten qimugteḿek.
Oh my, you’re late and ended up fixing the camera for the dog.