Waqaa, wiinga Hazel Lincoln-aaruunga, Yugtun-llu atqa Qang’allugauluni.
Hello, I’m Hazel Lincoln, and my Yup’ik name is Qang’allugaq.
Quyana ilagarluta Delta Review-aaqatallemteńi.
Thank you for joining us on our Delta Review.
Atakurpak Kuigglugmiut tegganrat Jimmy Chimigalrea-m ilagarciqaakut.
This eveneing, an elder for Kwethluk, Jimmy Chimigalrea, will join us.
Cali maniqatartukut aipaat ukut yurallrat Mountain VIllage-ami yurarpallratni uumi Agayunermi kitullermi.
We will also be showing the others who Yup’ik danced in Mountain Village for the dance festival this past Sunday.
Ciumek niicugninauraput Chimigalrea qalartellra.
First, let’s listen to what Chimigalrea has to say.
Yugtun taringtukuvci niicugninqegcaarniartuci.
If you understand Yup’ik, listen closely.
Tua-i yugni tamaitni niitellriani wangkutni, elpeceńi tua-i yugni tamaitni
To all people, we who are listening, all of you people
Waten tuaten ayuqesqessaaqut, iliit waniwa tua-i niitnaqsaaqelria.
They are asked to be like this, we need to hear one of them.
Waten qanerluni Philippianes tayima 2:12
It says in Philippians 2:12
Waten qanerluni: "Taum kenkekma maligtaqutelaucirpecetun ilakellerpeceńi watua
It says this: "As you obey the one whom I love as you are together now
"Ilaknrilngerpecia anirtuumallerkarci caliaqiciu qigcigyugluci alinguryugluci-llu.
"Even though I am not your relative, work on your salvation out of respect and fear.
"Tua-i Agayutnguan elpeceńi calilria. Piyuumircetaqluci aturcetaqluki-llu elliin pisqutni.
"For it is God who works in you. He gives you fervor and has you follow his will.
"Caliluci tamaitgun.
"Work through all of them.
"Qanemyuugaqsaunaci, qanekluarpek’naci. Qanernarqutaunaci.
"Do not grumblr, and do not say unfavorable things. Do not make yourself need admonishment.
"Paqnanarqevkenaci Agayutem yuknauraaci.
"So that you will be God’s people without drawing attention.
"Apquciinaci piciunrilnguut assiilnguut-llu akuliitni.
"You shall have no ailments among the false and the sinful.
"Akuliitni-llu tanqignaurtuci agyatun ellam iluani."
"And so that you shall shine like stars among them in the world."
Tua-i-w’ unguvam qaneryaraa maniluku. Tua-i wavet ciuqliliqe’rqa au͡g’umek.
It showed the wisdom concerning life. I started off with that.
Yugni tamamta au͡gna ava-i niitnariyaaqerput, pinrilngurmek ilaunata.
It’s time we people hear that, without leaving anyone out.
Iciw’ tua-i caaciteqsuunata, iqluyuirulluta.
You know, we shouldn’t [?], and stop lying.
Cali-llu ilamteńun maavet ilaput makut umyuarrliqutnanrirluki, umyuangcayuunata-llu yuut nallukiitgun assiitellriamek.
Also, we must stop thinking malicious things about those around us, and do not think bad things about people in secret.
Tua-i waten pitaluku.
That’s all for that.
Wangkutnun man’a tua-i niitnariyaaquq.
It’s time that we hear this.
Tua-ll’ man’a maa-i ak’anek ayaglua allrakuni au͡gkuni pellullerni
Then this, started from a long time ago in those years that have passed
Yuut ilaita pilaryaaqaatnga man’a qanrutkeqaasqelluku uuggun KYUK-kun
Some people tell me that I should talk about this here on KYUK
Waten erinama sagtenrullerkaa tua-i tamana piyaaqluku.
So that my voice would spread out more like this.
Qagkut-ll’ ilaita yaaqvaarmiut Kuigpagmiut-llu pilaryaaqaatnga ak’anek ayaglua allrakuni.
Some people up there, far away from the Yukon, have also been telling me for many years.
Tau͡gaam ukut KYUK-rmiut wiinga tua-i capeqluki ullayuitanka uum ciungani.
But since I found it daunting to go to KYUK, I wouldn’t go to them before this.
Cali-llu yualaryaaqellruunga mat’um-wa tua-i qanrutkarkama wangni pinruluku qanrutkestekaanek.
Also, I used to look for someone to who could speak about this better than I could.
Tau͡gaam ilaita-llam pilaraatnga
However, some of them would say to me
Aren allamek-gguq wangni qanrutkeluaqanrustekaituq. Wiinga-gguq qanruteklaku tau͡gaam.
Oh my, they said that there is no one who can say it better than me. They said that I should speak about it instead.
Tua-i waniwa cayaqlirluku qanqautekqata’arqa.
Now, I am finally going to speak about it.
Atam wiinga tua-i avani ella iqukluku qantullratni, anguanka au͡gkut ella iqukluku qantulriit.
You see, when they used to speak about the end of the world, I was born in time to see the ones who spoke about the end of the world.
Tamana-wa tua-i ak’a yaaqvani piitnaq qanrutketullrat qanrutkelartai angullruanka tua-i.
Well, I was born in time to see the ones who spoke about the time of famine far in the future.
Tua-ll’ tang ataucim tang au͡g’um qanellra tua-i tang waniwa umyuaqelgurikeka tang tua-i.
Then, you see, what that one person said always comes to mind now.
Tua-i-ll’ umyuaqelguriamku ella tang tua-i una aaryaruskeka iqukvanerrlugqurainarnayukluku.
Then since it always come to my mind, I’ve become wary of this world, thinking that it would end badly.
Kiima-llu pinritliniluku. Tua-i ilaita aaryagutaat una ella.
And I’m not the only one. Some others have become wary of this world.
Tua-i tamaani atam maaten murilkessagutua angukara’urluut arnassagaat ilait waten ciisqugni ayaperlukek piyuayaurrluteng
Back then, you see, I realized when I became observant that some old men and women would walk, supporting themselves on their knees like this
Ilait tau͡gken piyuananrirluteng
Yet some couldn’t walk anymore
Arnassagangqetullratni angukara’urlungqerrluteng-llu.
When they had old women and men.
Ilait tegularluki qasgimek anulluki maqilallruut
They would carry some out of the community house to take sweat baths
Taqngameng-llu cali itrulluki piyuananrilriit tamakut.
And when they were done, they brought in the ones who couldn’t walk anymore.
Tua-ll’ ella iqukluku qanllermeggni waten ilait qanellruut:
Then when they spoke about the end of the world, some of them said this:
Tamaa-i-gguq tamakut ak’allaunqurrit tamatum tua-i ellam aciani
They said that those who are the oldest there under the earth
Tamatum niitetullemta aciani yuullret tamakut ak’allaunqurrit
Those who lived, the oldest ones, under the one we used to hear about
Qanertut, "Yuk-gguq yuunertuqeryaaqaquq. Tamana-gguq aipiringaitaa."
They said, "A person lives for quite a long time. (S)he will not live another [life]."
Tua-i cali waten qanertut:
They also said this:
Atam-gguq tamaani... ella iqukluku qantullratni tamaani ciuqvani
You see, they said, a long time ago... when they used to speak about the end of the world a long time ago
Atam-gguq ilait makut nukalpiat
You see, they said, some of these great hunters
Waten qasgimi taklangyullerminek-llu qanelria tauna angukara’urluq un’gani caniqami qanelria niilluku
After this old man was laying in the community house, he said listening to the one by the wall near the door say
Ilii-gguq tang maktaqellria, "A, amci-gguq-qaa piyuan tungenqegturanemteńi."
They said that one of them got up, "Ah, it should happen already while we are [doing well]."
Cunawa-gguq tamaa-i tamatum pistekameng mallgillrani.
They said that it was apparently when the one who would [?take] them was getting close.
Yuut-gguq iciw’ ilacingllermeggni-gguq cunawa ilaciqanricuitut-gguq yuut
They said that when people, you know, apparently waited for others to act, you know people sometimes wait for others to act
Anucimirqecetaarumallerkameng-wa tua-i tamatum piciqiangaqateng mallgikateng.
When they ask to be set free when what they’re about to do is approaching.
Tua-ll’ tamaani, tamaa-i tamatum nalliini
Then at that time, at that time
Wiinga-ll’ tua-i tamakut erenret tanglallruanka. Tuar tang uksumi ataucimi pillrulriit.
I also used to see those days. I think those happened over one winter.
Ernertangyaurtellruuq waten erenrillermi kinguani qavaggun ernertangyarani kiatruarrluku negrem tua-i tungiikun.
Day started breaking after dawn like this further upriver, past where the day breaks toward the north.
Ernekegtaar unuurrluni.
The wonderful day became night.
Tua-i qanlartut ilait tamakut angutet erneruaryaurrniluku, camek iquliqsaunaku.
Some of those men say that the day has become false, without any further explanation.
Tua-llam cat iliitni akusrarrluta tua-i laanguarluta tua-i tan’geriluni tua-i.
Then one day, we were playing excitedly, and it got dark.
Enemun, enemun tua-i anglicartekellregma enekenrilkiignun iterlua.
I went into a house that was not of those who raised me.
Tua-i-ll’ itqanemkun arnaq au͡gna iterluni kingumkun.
Then right when I went in, that woman came in after me.
Tua-ll’ itrami kanani aqumvailegmi qanertuq, "Tua-i-am keggna ernertanglliniuq."
Then when she came in, she said before she sat down there, "There is now day out there."
Tua-ll’ tauna tamatum enem yuin angukara’urluat angukara’urluq qanertuq
The the old man of that house said
"When this world is on the brink [of ending], it doesn’t leave its people in the dark.
"Tau͡gaam-gguq atam elpegcilirraatui.
"But, you see, it gives them notice first.
"Atam-gguq tamaa-i elpegcilirai tua-i tamana aturarkani ellangcautekani.
"Look, it is giving notice to them about the lesson it’s going to teach them.
"Pinariata tua-i elliin yun’i tangerrluki, makut nunami yuulriit tangerrluki tua-i pinariata.
"It sees its people, sees the people on this earth because it’s time for them.
"Atam-gguq tamaa-i nasvagaa ellaitnun tua-i tamaa-i tamaaggun piarkaurrluki."
"Look, it is showing it to them, and will [correct] them through that."
Tua-ll’ qanertuq, "Atam-gguq yuut neryuniuryaaqniartut.
Then he said, "People will wait expectantly.
"Atam-gguq neryuniuryaaqvimeggnek neryuniunrirniartut, neryuniulriartairulluni-llu.
"Watch, as they are eagerly waiting, they will stop waiting eagerly, then there will be no one left who is wating eagerly.
"Atam-llu-gguq ella iqukluku qanelriamek niitnanrirniartut."
"And watch, they will stop hearing anyone say the world is ending."
Tua-i maa-i taum qanellra tua-i nall’aringaarput.
We now coincide with what he said.
Cali-llu-gguq atam qanikcangqerrnanrirniartuq wagg’uq ata ataucimun ellimangkuniu.
He also said that there would be no more snow, that is, when [the world] starts putting it into one place.
Tua-i taum qanellra waniwa tua-i umyuaqelguriaqa.
Now, what he said always comes to mind.
Tua-i ella una aaryagutaqa. Wiinga ellam uum catacia nalluyaaqaqa.
I am not wary of this world. I don’t know what this world is doing.
Tua-ll’ cali waten qanellruut:
Then, they also said this:
"Meluk," kiingan tua-i qanrutketullruat.
"Fish roe," it was the only one they mentioned.
Meluk-gguq man’a tua-i allrakurtaaryaaqeciquq nunam iluani.Tua-i-gguq cangaringaituq.
They said that fish roe would be in the land year after year. They said it wouldn’t spoil.
Yuum iluanun alingnaringaituq nunam iluani tua-i allrakurtaange’rmi.
It will not become dangerous inside a person though it spends year after year in the land.
Tua-i kiingan qanrutketullruat.
That was the only one they mentioned.
Tua-ll’ mat’um nalliini makut freezer-aat piyaaqut.
Then these days, there are now freezers.
Tau͡gaam malruugut makut, freezer-aaq man’a malruuguq.
But there are two things, there are two things [that don’t spoil] in freezers.
Tau͡gaam una sulunaq umyuarteqaqama cali allrakurtaaryaaqmiciquq elluarrluni taryiumakuni
But when I think about this salted fish, it may also spend year after year if it is salted well
Allrakut tegulang’ermiki tua-i cangaringailmiuq tauna.
It may take on years, but that will not spoil either.
Man’a-ggem tua-i freezer-aaq malruuguq. Catacia nallunartuq.
There are two things [that don’t spoil] in freezers. What it does is irregular.
Tua-ll’ cali mat’um nalliini ukut aipaiput tua-i qagruyaaqut watua maa-i ernermi qak’mumi.
And these days, our [Caucasian] counterparts are [?] in this current day.
Tau͡gaam ayainanermeggni-wa nallunartuq umyuarteqaqama.
But as they go, it’s hard to know when I think about it.
Atam niicaurtellrianga ak’anek, ak’arrarnek tayim’ ayaglua
Look, I’ve started hearing since a long time ago, since quite a while ago
Ak’mum nunam wiinga tangssuilkeḿa yugyalriim
In those lands way over there that I do not see where there are a lot of people
It started getting cold where they do not know cold; it started snowing where they do not know snow.
Tua-i tamakut naucetaat assircanrirai.
That is negatively affecting crops.
Cali-llu tayima piyagaat, tua-i cat cali piyugngalriit assircanrirai.
It is also negatively affecting animal young, whatever wildlife there is.
Tayima akemkut wiinga tua-i tangssuilkeḿa yui
Maybe the people of the lands that I do not see
Nasperturluteng ellait, naugillerteng-wa tua-i nasperturluku.
They are trying, trying [things] with their crops.
Umyuarteqaqama tamaańnguaqerlua
When I think about it and pretend I’m there
Unguvaseng tunulluku Alaska-m yuinek arcaqakingaitut.
They will not turn their back on their lives and consider Alaskan people more important.
Cali-am waten qanrutqerciullruunga, mumignganrilngurnek-am qanrutqerciullruunga elisngalriamek:
I was also told this, I was told this that was untranslated from a knowledgeable person:
"Naucetaalget-gguq naucetaamegteggun pimaarkaugut. Neqelget neqmegteggun pimaarkauluteng."
"Those with crops must [survive] with their crops. Those with food [from animals] must survive with their foor [from animals]."
Tua-ll’ tauna waten cali qanertuq:
Then he also said this:
"Atam-gguq tamana mallguskan tamana erneruaq naliuciiqiaqan
"Watch, when the false day that wilts plants is nigh
"Atam-gguq yuut nepengniartut, tua-i ellalkangluteng. Camek atanqaanrirluteng."
"Watch, people will start fighting, acting crazy. They will no longer await anything."
Tua-i tang maa-i man’a cali waten ayuqellria tua-i maa-i nall’aringaarput qakemkuni ernerni watua maa-i.
You see, we are corresponding to what is like this in these current days.
Ilateng tua-i cakenrirluki.
They care nothing for their families anymore.
Aling cali mat’um nalliini nallunaipagta maurluat una qanqerteńgunripagta.
Oh my, it is clear these days that their grandmother is not a teacher.
Cali-llu wangkurlumta tang apa’urlurluitni maani cailkami qanqerteńguvkenata.
Also, you see, we poor grandfathers of their are also not teachers in random places here.
Tuarpiaq tang tua-i makut kingum yui, tuarpiaq tua-i tangvagluki anglanitekellriacetun ayuqluki.
It truly seems that the chidlren of the next generation, it truly seems that we watch them with levity.
Inqautaunata mat’um nalliini.
We have no [?affection] these days.
Tua-ll’ umyuarteqaqama
Then when I ponder
Ella una piciqiaquni waten, uksuq man’a aturciqiange’rmiu
When the world is on the verge of doing this, though it is on the verge of going through this winter
Yun’i qanrusngaitai maa-i watua piqatarniluki.
It will not tell it’s people that it’s going to do it now.
Cunaw’ tang tamaa-i ava-i.
It turns out it was all of that.
Ak’a tamalkuita pinrilnguunaki tamaa-i nasvallruamiu qanrulluki yun’i tamaaggun, tamaaggun piarkaurrluki.
It had already shown its people through that, without leaving anything out, that it would do that.
Tua-ll’ cali waten qanertuq tauna angukara’urluq:
Then, that old man also said this:
"Atam-gguq tamana tamaa-i mallguskan piitnaq
"Watch, when that time of famine is nigh
"Waniwa-gguq ukuk ciiq, imarpinraq, atam-gguq kuignun neq’lirtuutengniartuq, neq’lirtuutengniartuk."
These two, sheefish, Bering cisco, watch, they rivers will be filled with those two fish."
Tua-i-gguq waten yuk nangulluni-w’ tua-i taukuk aipaagnek nerqerarkangqerrluni.
He said that when a person runs out [of food] like this, one of those two will be his source of food.
Taukuk-gguq aipaagnek nerqaquciqsaaquq. Ilangcivkenani-gguq atam kemgiutniartuq, kemga iggniartuq.
He said that he will eat a lot of one of those two. He said that despite that, he will grow skinny, his flesh falling off.
Neqek taukuk elluatuk assilriik uqulgulutek-llu
Those to healthy and good fish that are also fatty
"Tua-i-gguq," qanertuq tauna, "tua-i-gguq taulkuk neqek piitnam tamatum neqek."
"So," he said, "so those two are the fish of famine."
Tua-i man’a avaullrunritaqa. Maa-i-w’ tua-i umyuaqelguriamku tua-i ella una aaryagutaqa.
I haven’t forgotten this. Since it always comes to mind now, I’ve become wary of this world.
Tua-ll’ cali waten qanellruut au͡gkut:
Then, people back then also said this:
"Ukut-gguq waniwa taryaqviinkut, iqalluunkut, qakiiyaankut, taukut-gguq piirtuyuitut."
"These three, king salmon, chum salmon, silver salmon, those don’t run out."
Taumek-gguq maa-i watuam nalliini kingumta yuinun waten au͡gkut ellaita qanruyutekellruat:
That’s why they gave this piece of traditional wisdom to the children of our descendants today like this:
Taukut tua-i kuimallratni yuk piyugngakan qaategtevkenaku piyugngataciatun tamaaken tegutesqelluku.
While those are swimming, if a person is able, he should not be lazy, but take as much as he can from them.
Inerquutekluku man’a uksuaq qagqesqevkenaku.
They admonished against [?being unprepared for] fall.
Tamana-gguq atam aturarkaukuniu uksuq tamakut tamaa-i kinguqliktukai tamarmeng atam-gguq cataitniartut.
They said that if it is going to have that kind of winter, all of the things that come after them will be gone.
Man’a maa-i umyuaqelguriaqa.
This always comes to mind now.
Tua-ll’ tamatum tamaa-i piitnam tuskateng
Then when that famine comes upon them
Cali au͡gna waten qanqautesciullruunga. Ak’arraurtuq.
I was also told about that. It’s been quite a while.
Cali umyuamnun agtuutellruuq waten qanqautesteḿa qanqautaanga
It also moved my mind when the one who told me told this to me
Elliin umyugaanun cali agtuutelliniuq waten qanerluni:
It also moved his mind as he said this:
Tauna-gguq tang qavangurtulria kuvyaluni.
He said that he dreamt he was drift netting.
Tua-i waten aterrluni, qaill’ tua-i kuvyilarceta, kuvyilarceci.
He let the current carry him, however we drift net, you drift net.
Tua-i-ll’ pinariami imegluni.
Then when it was time, he rolled up his net.
Imginanrani neqa kan’a alairtuq, enret tamimek caquluteng amta-ll’ pektanqeggluni.
As he was rolling up his net, a fish appeared down there, entirely covered in bones yet was moving.
Tua-ll’ alairami qanrutlinia tauna cangtaqesteńi
Then when it appeared, it said to the one who caught it
"Uitaqaa. Malrugnek qanerkangqertua."
"Wait a second. I have two things to say."
Tua-ll’ pillinia tauna cangtaqesteńi
Then it said to the one who had caught it
"Tayima-gguq allrakut amllenrilnguut kinguatni piitnaq tut’eqatartuq
"After a few years, the time of famine is going to come
"Cali-llu tegelgem yua pekteqatarluni."
"And the spirit of theft is going to be active."
Atam au͡gkut wiinga tua-i angullrenka, anguyaaqekenka tua-i qanqaquuryaaqellriameng
Look, though the people I was born to see had talked for a long time
Nutaan atam wiinga tegelgem yuanek niitellrianga.
You see, that was the first time I heard about the spirit of theft.
Tua-ll’ taum tua-i qanqautestellma mat’um kinguani
Then after that person spoke to me
Tuar tang maa-i yuut allamiaqan tuar tang arcarikanilalriit. Tuar tang arcarikanilalriit.
It seems that every year, people get worse. They seem to get worse.
Waten ilateng qinuuqluki. Teglegiluki, neqairluki tuaten.
They do not share with their families. They steal from them, even take their food away.
Yuut maa-i watua umyuarteqaqama
When I ponder upon these people now
Mayiteqkuneng uuggun aqsaqumegteggun qaillun pitaqatartat?
If these they desire what was taken away from their stomachs, how far will they go?
Ilateng-llu allurtelarciqait.
They will also take from their families.
Wall’u tua-i yuut makut avanicetun ayuqenrirtut.
Or, these people are not like long ago anymore.
Ilait uluryairulluteng, ilait-ll’ alingnariluteng.
Some have no more inhibitions, and some have gotten dangerous.
Ilii-llu neqrangqerrniluni tuqutauciquq-llu.
And one of them will be killed because he has a little food.
Tua-i taklirivakartuq. Waten pitaaqa.
It’s getting to long. This is all I will say about it.
Quyana Chimigalrea.
Thank you Chimigalrea.
Waniwa Asaacararmiut curukallratni suurkiullrulliniut Imangarmiut yurartai.
Now, the dancers of Emmonak recorded a video when Mountain Village held a challenge feast.
Quyana. WIinga Qang’allugaugua.
Thank you. I am Qang’allugaq.
Uumiku cali ilagarniararpekut Delta Review-aallemteńi.
Join us next time for our Delta Review.