Imkut uivenqellriit [?] tua-i tumaganek pilallruit. Assirluteng.
Those round [?], they called them tannin. They were good.
Yeah, we’re rolling, so thank you for your patience.
We can go ahead and start.
Waniwa canek ak’a imumi niitelallerpenek qanquvet waniwa.
Now, you should talk about what you used to hear way back then.
Ii-i.
Okay.
Ellangellemni yuut waten ayuqellrunritut caarkaiturluteng.
In my earliest memories, people weren’t like this with nothing to do.
Yuilqumek tau͡gaam neqerluteng. Kass’artarnek nerrsiyaayuunateng.
They only ate from the wilderness. They didn’t eat too much Western food.
Maa-i tan’gaurluut uitqapigtelartut, atamek-llu tau͡gaam kaigaluteng.
Now, boys are completely sedentary, and ask only of fathers.
Wii caliaricuitellruama iliirallrunritua atamnek, wangnek-llu pingnaqurallruama.
Since I always had work, I never asked anything of my father, also because I tried to do things on my own.
Muragtaqlua pingayunek-ll’ qimugterlua, ikamrarlua-llu.
I’d go get wood and had three dogs, and a sled.
Imkunek-ll’ arutulinek tua-i kuvyanek muragnek pugtaqutarluteng
And with those drift nets that would deteriorate easily that had wooden floats
Imkunek-llu imarkanek ak’allarnek.
And those old bullets.
Tua-i qemingnaqu’urlua, kaillerkaqa tau͡gaam mukaaritlerkarput-llu umyuaqaqluku, kuingiitellerkaqa-llu.
I’d always try to set the lead line, thinking of how we might go hungry, go without flour, and I’d have no cigarettes
Inerqungraanga ayagaqlua, tau͡gaam qanrutaqanga niitelalllruunga.
Though [s]he’s admonish me, I’d go, but when [s]he spoke to me, I’d listen.
Ava-i cali qanellruuten caliangqerrumalarniluten, calillren-llu assikaqluku. Calivigpenek tamatumek cali qanqaa.
You also just said that you always had job, and that you liked to work. Please talk about your workplace.
Cannery-mi calitullemni [?]turalallruunga.
When I worked at a cannery, I’d always [?].
Ilamni-ll’ tua-i akikanrurrlua inarrlua.
Then I’d owe my peers as I’d sleep at their places.
Calilqa assikluku.
I liked to work.
Ciumek-llu taivkarrlainarlua.
And they’d always let me come first.
Iliini tua-i kiaresngiatengyaaqnaurtua.
Sometimes, I’d feel ashamed.
Makut-llu maa-i agayuviit yuirutut. Yuirutut. Makut TV-t yuirucetait.
And now, there are no more people in these churches. There are no more people. These TV’s are making them empty.
Maa-i makut, imkut-llu canek pilallrita, tamakut cali peggautek’larait
These things, and whatever they call them, they stay up late at night for them
Imumi ak’a TV-rtaitellruuq. Imkut tau͡gaam kenircuutellrat tem’irrnertulriit kiimeng piullruut, makunek cataunani.
Long ago when there were no TVs. There were only those portable stoves that would make rumbling sounds, none of these.
Qaillun-mi wangkuta ayagyuani assirluta calisteńgullerkamteńun alerquryugngaceta?
So what can you advise of us young people so that we will be good workers?
Atam elluarrluni calilria Kass’at assikelaqiit, qailllukuarpek’nani caliani caliaqekii.
You see, the Caucasians like those who work well, one who doesn’t mess around but focuses on work..
Tamaa-i tamakut assikelarait.
Those are the ones they like.
Una-ggem tua-i caqtaarluni calilria ak’anun uitasciigatuq.
One who is distracted when working cannot stay long.
Kanani-ll’ co-op-ami calilria cali qaillukualria ak’anun uitasciiganani.
And a worker who works at the co-op down there and messes around cannot stay long.
Au͡g’aqalaraat.
They fires them.
Cali-q’ tua-i cannery-lartuten?
Do you still work at the cannery?
Taqellruunga.
I stopped.
Calissuutnek tau͡gaam waniw’ akingyaurtellruunga.
Instead, I started getting money from [?].
Akinguqiit cali makunun-wa tua-i pistaini piqa’aqluki piuralaqiit, neqnek tuaten.
The ones who receive money give them to who’s responsible, including food.
Tayima qanruyutnek niitelallruuten ciuliarpenek. Tamakunek cali qanqaa.
You’ve probaby heard of traditional wisdom from your elders. Please talk about those.
Wiinga unisteḿa qanruquralallruanga, "Tua-i qessavkenii pilaasqellua. Atam-gguq qessanqu͡rukuma, unkut unani nallunritaten neqet kuimalriit,
My late father always said to me, :"Never be lazy. If I’m lazy, you know of the fish down there
"Tangaangramki qemineq-llu nallukumku kailarniartua."
"Even if I see them and don’t know how to set a lead line, I will be hungry."
Maa-i tamaaken ayaglua kaiksaitua.
I’ve never been hungry since then.
Kaiksaitua tua-i.
I’ve never been hungry.
Elpet-llu tua-i assirluten tua-i calikuvet au͡g’arngaitaatgetn. Assirluten.
And if you work well, they won’t fire you. You’ll be good.
Wii waniw’ assirlua calingnaqurallruama calinermek taqua.
Since I tried to work well, I stopped working.
Angyakun-ll’ agyuunii, tengssuuterrlainarkunt tau͡gaam.
And I wouldn’t go by boat, but always with a plane.
Ciuqliurrlua ikani misvillermi, ciumek-llu qayagaurtu’rlua.
I became the first in the airport across there, and they’d always call me first.
Taiqataamta-ll’ tua-i ciumek qayagaurlua. Yuuqataamta-ll’ cali qayagaurlua.
When we were going to come, they’d call me first. And when we were going to disembark, they’d also call me.
Taumek tang kiaresngiatenglalrianga.
You see, that’s why I’d be ashamed.
Ciuqliurrlainarlua.
I was always first.
Atam elpet-llu qaillukuarpek’nak. Qanrutqataramken.
Look, you shouldn’t mess around either. I’m going to tell you.
Tua-i calisteńguyaaquten. Qaillukuarpek’nak caliurquvet au͡g’arngaitaatgen.
You are a worker. If you work without messing around, they won’t fire you.
Waniw’ cali qanqautnaluten, wii tang waten ellilrianga au͡g’arpailgatnga.
I also wanted to tell you that I’ve reached this age before I’ve been fired.
Una-ll’ iruka waniw’ waken ayagluni [?]umayaaquq. Iruicaaqua. Una-ll’ plastic-aaruluni malrugnek-ll’ ussukcarluni.
And my leg here is [?] starting from here. I have injured legs. And this one is plastic with two screws.
Qaill’ una mukaaq imumi akingqelallrua cat akiitelallratni?
How much did flour cost back when things were inexpensive?
Akiitellruut pingayutun.
They were inexpensive, $3.
Qaill’ uqamait?
How much did they weigh?
Imna 50 lb-aq akiitqapiggluni tua-i pingayutun.
A 50 lb. bag was very inexpensive, $3.
Saayut-llu malrugtun.
And tea was $2.
Akiinani.
It was inexpensive.
Maa-i-w’ caperrnarilriit. Caperrnariut.
Now, they’ve become difficult [to get]. They’ve become difficult.
Imna allragni ayakautellrat nataqumangaituq.
What they took last year won’t be found.
Massiinallret qanrutekngaitaqa.
I won’t speak of the old boat motors.
Kaassaq-mi qaill’ akingqelallrua?
How expensive was gas?
Talliman...
Five dollars...
Imna drum-aq $25. Akiitqapiggluni maa-i.
A drum was $25. It’s very inexpensive [compared to] now.
Maa-i-w’ caperrnarilriit.
Now, they’re difficult [to get].
Uqulkuut-llu malrugtun akiluteng. Motor oil, $2.
And [motor] oil was $2. Motor oil, $2.
Akiillit-tuq maa-i aklut. Akiillit-tuq.
I wish things were inexpensive now. I wish they were inexpensive.
Ii-i, maa-i-w’ caperrnarilriit, aklut-ll’ akituluteng. Akituriluteng.
Yes, they’re not difficult [to get], and things are expensive. They’ve gotten expensive.
Camek-wa tua-i nangnermek qanqeryukuvet waniwa nangnermek qanqerluten.
If there’s a final thing you’d like to say, say the last thing now.
Pray-aqaqerlii. Pisqumaarpenga-qaa?
Let me pray. Do you want me to?
Yaa, piyukuvet.
Yes, if you want to.
Ii-i.
Okay.
Oh, Lord Jesus, God. Agayun atavut Qilagmetellriami atren kenciknarili.
Oh, Lord Jesus, God. God, our father, who art in Heaven, hallowed be thy name.
Angayuqaviin tekilli. Pisqucin nunam qaingani piuli Qilagmitun.
May your kingdom come. May your will be done on earth as it is in Heaven.
Neqkamteńek ernerpak cikirkut. Assiilngumteńek-ll’ au͡g’ariskut wangkutnun assiilngilriit au͡g’aritelaucimcetun.
Give us this day our daily bread. And forgive us our trespasses as we forgive those who trespass against us.
Picetaarutmun pivkaqsaunata tau͡gaam assiitellriamek aviuskut.
Lead us not into temptation but deliver us from evil.
Angayuqaavik, piniq-llu, ucurnarquciq-llu elpet pikngavki nangyuilngurmek, amen. Quyana Jesus, amen.
For yours is the kingdom, and the power, and the glory forever and ever, amen. Thank you Jesus, amen.
Quyana.
Thank you.
Tua-i elluarrluten calingnaqu’urqina. (Yaa.)
Now, try to always work well. (Okay.)
Maa-i tang elluarrluteng calinrilnguut au͡g’alaqait.
Now, you see, they fire those who don’t work well.
Elluarrluni tau͡gaam caliuralria Kass’am assikelaraa.́
Caucasians like one who works well.
Wii waniw’ au͡g’arpailgatnga [?].
Now, before they fired me, [?].