Arenqiatua wii, iika assiilami-ll’. Qitngiryugtua.
I’m struggling, also because my eye is bad. The light is bright for me.
Tang at’ black-aagnek ackiinrilama.
(Akleng.)
I wish I had black sunglasses.
(I’m sorry.)
Alright.
Talking with Paul G. and Lucy Nicholai for the record
just in case we don’t know who they are sometimes.
(Yugtun-llu.)
Yugtun-llu Cialuq and… Yugcetun ima?
(In Yup’ik too.)
And in Yup’ik, Cialuq and… what’s your Yup’ik name again?
Atpiaqa-w’ Qakvaralriaruyaaqell’ tau͡gaam amaqliirutka yuunrillrani
My real name is Qakvaralria, but when my late older brother passed away
Ciin-tam-kiq tam’ cimirtatgu?
I wonder why they changed it?
Neviarmek pilaraatnga maa-i.
(Ii-i, yaa, okay.)
Now, they call me Neviar.
(I see, yes, okay.)
Atra-w’ Kass’atun nallunritliken.
(Ii-i, yaa.)
You probably know her English name.
(Yes, yes.)
Yaa, nallungailken.
Yes, there’s no way you wouldn’t know.
Yaa. Tua-ll’ Cialuq ciumek mat’um maa-i-rpak
up’nerkartuq qakemna ellavut.
Yes. And then Cialuq first, the season around us
is spring now.
Tua-ll’ inerquutertangqelallruut-qaa tamakut yullret nalliitni
up’nerkami atullerkaitnek?
Were there admonishments in the time of people back then
that they should follow in the spring?
Canek-wa tua. Tua-i tau͡gaam waten…
Various things. This was the only…
So they’re talking with this camera.
Ii-i.
Okay.
Ii-i, kitaki.
Okay, proceed.
Yaa, right around here then they’re talking with [us].
(Ii-i.)
Yes, right around here then they’re talking with [us].
(Okay.)
Waten tua-i au͡gkut, elpet-llu-w’ tua-i nallunrilketen
They [said] this, and you know them too
Au͡gkut aulukestellemta up’nerka’rqan, up’nerka’rqan waten
Our caretakers back then when spring set, when spring set like this
Tua-i cikuliurutraq nantesqevkenaku iinguan.
They would tell us to always have an ice spud because it’s our eyes.
Tua-i ilumun tua elpet-llu nallunrilken tua-i.
Indeed, you know it too.
Allayugmek pitaituq.
There’s nothing else.
Tua-i tau͡gaam waten tua-i ak’allarraat
tua-i ak’allaraat tua-i aaryuitesqevkenata alerqunqegcaaratullruitkut.
The old people, the old people only made completely sure
to admonish us against being reckless.
Yugcetun ima caulriaten cali?
Who were you in Yup’ik again?
Nev’aq.
(Nev’aq, yaa.)
(Nev’aq, okay.)
Neviaq.
(Neviaq.)
Neviar.
(Ii-i, Neviar.)
(Okay, Neviar.)
Ak’a-wa tamaani elpet ilaten nasaurlullraullerpeni
maligtelallrulliketen up’nerkiyaraqata.
Back when you were a girl, you probably went with
your family when they went to spring camp.
Tamatumek-qaa qanqeryuumiiten piciatun tamatum tungiinun?
Do you want to say anything concerning that?
Up’nerkiyaqamta-wa waten Arnangiaraller nalluksi Iqalluunkut aanallrat
When we went to spring camp like this, youpl don’t know
Arnangiaraller, the mother of the late Iqalluk and famiuly
Waten pitullrukiikut ayaganguaqtaqatarqamta natmun yuilqurrarmun:
She would say this to us when we would travel about in the wilderness:
“Ayarulgirluci. Atam pitsaqevkenaci igpallakuvci-llu
ayaruq cani’irrluku nugutekniarci.”
“Take a walking staff. You see, if you should even trip,
you can get out [of water] by putting the staff on its side.”
Tuaten pilallruakut.
She used to tell us that.
Ilaitni-llu atakumi niitelallruunga nepailcaaralaasqelluki.
Sometimes, I’ve also heard them say to be quiet in the evning.
Yaa.
(Ciin tanem?)
Yes.
(Why?)
Tua-i-w’ pitullrukiikut cali nepaunata pilaasqelluta.
They told us to be quiet.
Atam-gguq, nepengyarniaraakut-gguq atam.
They said, you see, that the nepengyaq would be attracted by our noise.
Cam tanem?
(Carayiim.)
What?
(A ghost.)
Cali ukut-qaa Kuigglugmiut ayalallermeggni up’nerkiyarvimeggnun
wall’u-qaa pissuryaraqameng
Also, when the people from Kwethluk would go
to their spring camps or when they went hunting
Yuirut’lallruut-qaa ak’a tamaani?
Would there be no one left a long time ago?
Mayurluteng. Amlleq-gguq unegcuitellruuq.
They went up. They said not many stayed behind.
Wii tamakut nallullruanka ciuqvaat au͡gkut.
I didn’t know about those old things back then.
Amllermek-gguq una yungqessuitellruuq Kuiggluk
They said that there weren’t a lot of people in Kwethluk
Tua-i, tua-i angussaagarluteng pitullruameng ciulirneret qanganaarnek.
Because [our] ancestors would hunt for ground squirrels.
Tua-i tamaa-i yuungnaqutait.
That’s what their subsistence.
Maa-i wangkuta aturciigataput au͡gkut catairutellret.
We can’t live those old ways that were lost.
Tua-i elpet-llu nallunrilketen tua-i.
You probably know them.
Tua-i paigurallemteńi tua-i wii ayayuirutua [Qulmun].
As we always babysit, I don’t go to [Qula] anymore.
Maani-qaa Kuiggluum avatiini pitarkat amllerralallruut tamaani?
Were there a lot of animals they hunted around Kwethluk back then?
Aren, enurnaitellruut ciuqvani imkut au͡gkut aulukestelput
taluyarteggun kapkaanarteggun-llu.
My goodness, they were not scarce when our late caretakers
[set] fish traps and animal traps.
Kapkaanaliyuitellruama qavcirrarnek kapkaanangqetullruama,
unisteka-w’ imna.
I didn’t set animal traps because I only had a few
[from] my late father.
Tua-i Kass’atun maa-i makut Kass’at Yugtun ayuqenriqait
Like Westerners, these Westerners are making these [people]
unlike Yupiit [back then]
Tua-i kapkaanarnek taluyaarnek-llu, taluyarkanek.
[Using] animal traps and fish traps, material for fish traps [back then].
Tua-i tamaa-i wiinga-am tua-i maa-i cali taluyartuqtaumaunga
I am still doing that now with a fish trap
Imanganek-wa tau͡gaam.
Only for black fish.
Ak’a tamaani-qaa yuut piciryarangqelallruut pitat merriartaqluki mermek?
A long time ago, did people have a tradition of
giving water to animals they had caught?
Unkumiutaat. Unkumiutaat.
(Aku’urrluki, aku’urrluki, ii-i.)
Animals from the coast. Animals from the cause.
(They dipped them, they dipped them, yes.)
Tanglallruunga, nalluketen-llu teptukuyiit, iciw’ evv’laavat aciit
assirluteng narellrit qengaitnun piqerluki
I used to see, and you probably don’t know valerians,
you know, the roots of flowes that smell nice placed on their noses
Neqrarrmek-llu wall’ merr’armek piluki.
And they give them a little food or water.
Tua-i-w’ tamalkuita pitullrullikait.
They probably did that to all [animals].
Wii ak’allaqapiaraat nalluanka. Tau͡gaam…
I don’t know the very old ways. But…
Ciin tanem tuaten pilallruitki?
Why did that do that to them?
Allanilluki-gguq.
They said they treated them as guests.
Allanisnguarluki-w’.
They pretended to receive them as guests.
Atam imumi-ll’ maani pitullruut imkut neqet piurluki,
qanritnun-llu iqmiliqaulluki.
You see, they also did that a long time ago to fish,
and putting [food or tobacco] in their mouths.
Unkumiutaat.
Animals from the coast.
Tangvaksaitellruuten? Wangkuta imumi pitullruukut.
Have you ever seen that? We used to do that a long time ago.
Mikluta, sugtuv[kenii], wii miklua mikluta elliraurtellruamta.
We were small, I wasn’t tall, I was small because
we were orphaned when we were small.
Yaa, wiinga-ll’… apteksaitaanga.
Yes, me too… he didn’t ask me.
Tua-ll’ Neviar, ak’a tamaani makut nasaurluut aglenrraraat
And then Neviar, these girls in the year of their first menstruations
a long time ago
Maani-llu-qaa Kuigglugmi wall’u-qaa?
Did they do it here in Kwethluk too or what?
Piyuirutut.
(Aqumgavkalallruit?)
They don’t anymore.
(Did they separate them from society?)
Wiinga-w’ tang imumi qanraqluteng
eyagcetenritaatnga-gguq mayiteqciryuumiilameg[teńga].
Personally, you see, a long time ago, they would say
that they didn’t have me abstain
because they didn’t want me to be destitute.
Amta-ll’ eyagcellua ayagavkaqsaunii-llu.
And yet they had me abstain and kept me from traveling a lot.
Tua-i-ll’ cali upakataamta up’nerkillernek
meq tang aramek milqerceskilitgu.
And then when we were going to move from spring camps,
they had me throw ash on into the water.
Tuaten.
Like that.
Cauga tamana?
(Taringenritliuq.)
What is that?
(He might not understand.)
Meq… araq-qaa nalluan? Iciw’ kaminiat…
The water… do you know what araq is? You know, from stoves…
Qamlleq. Qamlleq-wa.
(Qamlleq.)
Where the fire had gone out. Where the fire had gone out.
(Where the fire had gone out.)
Canaluku-gguq?
What was the reason?
Tua-i-w’ piciryaraqlikiit au͡gkut ciulirneret tamakut.
(Naamell’, piciryaraqluku-w’ tua-i.)
That’s probably the custom of [our] ancestors back them.
(I don’t know, it’s their custom.)
Uum nallullikii.
She probably doesn’t know.
Ciuliamta piciryaraqluku eyatullermeggni.
(Ii-i, qayumi ciuliam piciryaraqaa.)
It was our ancestors’ custom when they abstained.
(Yes, as expected, our ancestors’ custom.)
Eyayuirutut-gguq maa-i. Eyayuirutut.
They say they don’t abstain anymore now.
They don’t abstain anymore.
Eyalriamek wii tangeqsaitua.
I haven’t seen anyone abstaining.
Pagna-ll’ tangaasqeksaunaku aglenraraugaqamta.
They also told us not to look up [at the sky]
during the year of our first menstruations.
Ciin tanem?
Why?
Iingiucara’arnayukluta-gguq.
They said we might lose our eyesight early.
Tua-i-w’ tauten.
That’s how it was.
Makut…
These…
Cali qanrutkelallruit-am tamakut,
ilaitni-llu maa-i-rpak niitelartua waten.
They also talked about those, and I hear about this sometimes now.
Kat’um Paseqam qanrusngualaraanga-am
Paseqaq down there tells me
Manalriit-gguq uumi tua-i cang’aqluteng
That people jigging now catch fish
Tua-i-llu-gguq-am iliit nasaurluut-gguq-am iliit qaill’ pillruami
And then he said that when one of the girls did something
Manaryallrani-gguq-am imkut neqet ayemqertut.
When she fished, they said that the fish “broke.”
Cauga tamana?
What’s that?
Aglenraraat irnicuallret-llu pisqessuitait.
(Tua-i taukuk qanrutkelallrit au͡gkut.)
They tell girls within the year of their first menstruations
and those who miscarried not to.
(The people back then talked about those.)
Nalluyuitelliniit neqngung’e’rmeng.
Even the fish know [that] they [had gone].
Tua-i-qaa tauna kiingan inerquutekaat neqnun?
Is that the only admonishment for fish?
Tua-i waten qanrutkelaqiit.
They talk about it like this.
Arimat-llu, arimat-llu qassasqevkenaki.
And spoiled food, they told them not to eat spoiled food raw.
Aripat-wa pillikai.
(Yaa.)
She’s talking about spoiled food.
(Yes.)
Cali-ll’ iqvaasqevkenaki aglenraraat.
They also told girls within the year of the first menstruations
not to pick berries.
Anllercuasqevkenaki, iqvaasqevkenaki.
They told them not to dig for mouse caches or pick berries.
Eyagluteng-llu qaleqcuugnek qangqiirnek-llu kiingita nerluteng.
They also abstained by eating only grebes and ptarmigans.
Wiinga-w’ tuaten pillrulrianga.
I personally did that.
Qaleqcuuk, qangqiiq neqenka, kiagcetallret-llu neqerrluaraat.
I only ate grebes, ptarmigans, and dried fish from the previous year.
Nutaranek…
(Piyuunata nutaranek.)
Fresh [dried fish]…
(We wouldn’t eat fresh [dried fish].)
Unkumiut atam eyakevkenaki yuvgerilata-gguq imarpigmiutaat.
But they don’t abstain from [fish] from the coast
because they said that ones from the ocean don’t have slime.
Puget-wa.
Surfaced seals at least.
Issurit, maklaaret eyakevkenaki.
They don’t abstain from spotted or year-old bearded seals.
Makut, makut iralut, iralut maani Kuigglugmi Kusquqvagmi
qaillun aptuitki ayagnirluku Iralull’e’rmek?
What do they call these months, these months here in Kwethluk
on the Kuskokwim starting from Iralull’er [January]?
Wiinga Yugcetun nalluanka, tua-i au͡gkut tau͡gaam ciuqliit.
I don’t know them in Yup’ik except for the first ones.
Tua-i-w’ Yugcetun-am ilait pilarait Yugtarnek aterpagtarluki,
puqilriit-wa.
Some call them by Yup’ik names, at least the fluent ones.
Aren, elpet-llu-w’ ilait nallunritlikten Yugtarmek au͡gkut.
I mean, you probably know some of them in Yup’ik too.
Igausngayaaqut tau͡gaam ilait ayuqsuitelarniit.
They’re written, but they say some aren’t the same.
Yaa, qanelput-wa ayuqenrilameng.
Yes, because our dialects are different.
Atam mallgut’nge’rmeng qanellgutkenritut.
You see, they have different dialects even when they’re close.
Tua-i nallunrilken elpet.
You know that.
Tua-ll’ ak’a tamaani agayuviit maani pissiyaangvailgata
And then, a long time ago before churches became prevalent here
Tungmagciaqameng yugnek akluit qungum qainganun ellilallruit.
When they buried people, they would put
their possessions on their graves.
Ciin, ciin tuaten pilallruat?
Why did they do that?
Imumi ciuqvani pitullruut, ciuqvani au͡gkut.
They did that a long time ago, our ancestors back then.
Maa-i-ggem tua yuk tua-i ilaunri’rqan
Now, when a person passes away
Iciw’ nallunrilketen-llu elpet tua-i aklullruarait ekualuki.
You know, you also know that they burn their possessions.
Tua-i ekualuki nangluki. Tuaten maa-i piyaurtut.
(Eggluki-llu.)
They burned and destroyed them. They’ve started doing that now.
(And throwing them away.)
Au͡gkucetun, au͡gkut piciryarait atunrirait.
They don’t follow the old customs anymore.
Tamakut-gguq, iciw’ piciatun egatet, saaniiget, yaaruitet, uyamiit
They say that those, you know, various things,
pots, kettles, storytelling knives, necklaces
Alailutekluki-gguq qungumun.
Those were grave markers.
Tuaten qanlallruut.
That’s what they used to say.
Avani-w’ ciuqvani Kass’artailan tua-i ellaita yugurluut tua-i
tua-i callruarait-llu ellimallratnun ellitullrulliniit.
Because there were no Caucasians a long time ago, those people
would put their few possessions where they were to be set.
Wiiinga-ll’ yaani yuvrialallruanka nutellret tuaten.
I also used to examine them over there, even old guns.
Tua-i yuunrirqata ellitulliniluki.
They say they would put them when they passed away.
Maa-i-ggem tua-i yugnun piqa’aqluki.
These days, they give them to people.
Assinruuq nutaan au͡gkucetun pivkenateng.
It’s better, unlike before.
Elpet-llu tua-i nallunritaten.
You know them too.
Nasaurluut alerquutaitnek, alerquutekaatnek
maa-i-rpak atu’urkaatnek camek qanqeryulliuten.
Would you like to say anything about traditional instructions
that girls should adhere to these days.
Nasaurluut-wa inerqutullrukait watqapiar-llu
tan’gaurlull’er quuyuquluarautesqevkenaku.
They used to admonish girls against ever smiling at a boy.
Arnaq-gguq tuquuguq.
They say a woman leads to death.
Waten qanraqluteng: “Arnaq-gguq tuquuguq.”
They said this: “A woman leads to death.”
Wiinga tua-i atakumi-llu watqapiar mulusqeksaunii.
They also told me never to stay out late in the evening.
Tuaten tua-i iciw’ cat-llu carayagmun-llu teguciqnilua.
They said, you know, that some creature would take me.
Elpet-mi? Tan’gaurluut-qaa maa-i-rpak niitarkaatnek
piciatun qanruyutmek qanqeryuumiituten?
What about you? Do you want to say any traditional wisdom
that boys these days should hear?
Tua-i-w’ tau͡gaam alerquukaramnek ava-i iciw’ qanruaresqemken?
You know, I only told you about what instructions I had?
Tua-i waten watli’rqan ayarurraq cingilek cukuliurutmek pitukevvut
When [the season] became like this, the staff with a point
that we call an ice spud
Tua-i tamakunek piitesqevkenata.
They told us to always have those.
Tumkaq-gguq apertutuat. Ilumun piciuqapiartuq.
They say they show the way. Indeed, it’s completely true.
Tua-i mamkilnguq nalluvkenaku.
You will know thin spots.
Tua-i tuaten pitullruut au͡gkut ciulirneret.
That’s what those elders back then used to say.
Tua-i ava-i qanruartellrukemken ciungani ciunguluku ciumek
tua-i alerquute[llret] au͡gkut.
Before, the first thing I told you about was those people’s instructions.
Ak’anun-llu wii qaillun-wa angtaluta elliraurtellruamta
tua-i wangkutnek caqtarturluta.
And for a long time, because we were orphaned when we were young,
we did things ourselves.
Tua-i tau͡gaam yuk qanruyuterramikun yuuciqliniuq.
Tua-i yuuciqliniuq.
Evidently, a person will only live by his traditional wisdom.
He will live [that way].
Uitayukuni-ll’ tua-i camek piinani.
And if he’s sedentary, he won’t have anything.
Tua-i elpet-llu murilkelaqeten ilait maa-i caitelartut.
You also observe these people who have nothing.
Apqiitnek qessaluteng tua-i callerkameggnek.
They call that being too lazy to do their work.
Tua-i tau͡gken imna qessaniuqtarturalria tauna caileng’e’rmi
tukuulriatun-gguq ayuquq.
However, if one works hard despite not wanting do, even if he doesn’t
have anything, they say it’s like he’s rich.
Tua-i caitevkenani tua-i muralleraungraata-llu makunek.
He has things, even these pieces of wood.
Tua-i ilumun piciuqapiartuq.
Indeed, that’s completely true.
Tua-i au͡g’urluum ava-i kinguqliata maa-i tangvallruamia
Because that dear youngest one watched me
Waten muraggarnek quyurtelartuq tua-i ellimenrilengramni
tua-i tangvallruamia.
He gathers wood like this even though he is not ordered to
because he watched me.
Tua-i amllermek qanerpagkailngua.
I don’t have much else to say.
Mat’um-qaa nalliini elpeni makut ayagyuat akusrarneruut?
These days, to you, are young people mischievous?
Yaa.
(Qaill’-wa pila[rtat].)
Yes.
(I don’t know what they’re doing.)
Wiinga-w’ tua au͡gna-w’ tang…
(Allayuurtut wii tangllemni.)
Personally, that one, you see…
(They’re different from what I’ve seen.)
Tau͡gaam allayuurtut maa-i mat’um-wa taangam, taangam pikai.
They’ve become different now because of alcohol.
Imumitun ayuqenriqapiartut. Elpet tua-i nallunritaten.
They’re nothing like a long time ago. You know them.
Tua-i yuk-llu una cavkenani tarrilluni, ak’a-ll’ tuquqerluni
taangam pitaqluku.
And a person wanders around for no reason,
and he’s immediately dead at the hands of alcohol.
Qanqataunateng tuaten.
(Imumitun pinrirtut).
They also speak without thinking.
(They’re not like before).
Yuut tamarmeng nallunritait makut ciulirneret waten pilauciit.
These elders know that every person does this.
Tua-i taangam mat’um cukatqapiararai.
Alcohol is killing them off very quickly.
Ilait-llu malikluteng tua-i ataucikun tuqurnaurtut.
And some go together and die at once.
Wall’ kill’uteng, tua-i kit’erpallurluteng-wa pilalriit.
Or they drown, they mostly drown.
Ilait-llu maa-i-am allayuurtellret ukaqvanernek tuqucaurrluteng.
And some who have become different recently kill [themselves].
Inerquutnguyaaquq man’a tua-i ellminek tuqutellerkaq.
Suicide is admonished against.
Arnaq ayagneqluku tuqutaqluteng.
(Yaani man’a ella piunriqan tamakut anirtuumangaitut
ellmeggnek tuqutellret.)
They kill [themselves] over a woman.
(Someday when the world ends,
those who’ve committed suicide will not be saved.)
Tua-i yuk nangtequrang’e’rmi tua-i uitali.
Even if a person is suffering, may [s]he stay.
Ayuqniange’rmi-llu tua-i ilamitun pinrilnge’rmi
tua-i ilani tupagaqata tupalartut.
And even if [s]he wants what others have despite not being like them,
his peers wake up when they wake up.
Tua-i wiinga tua-i waten tua-i waniw’ tangrrarpenga.
Now, you see me here.
Yuugua tua-i tua-i waten tua-i.
I am alive like this.
Tau͡gaam uku’urluuk waniw’ aulukeqtarturalaranka.
But I take care of these two here.
Maa-i tau͡gaam ciunganitun piscii[galilua].
Akleng, kuvyassiyaanrirlua-llu.
But now, I can’t do what I used to before.
Pity, I don’t go drift netting much anymore too.
Maa-i neqem nalliini tua-i ataucirqumek
iliini-ll’ aipiriqerlua.
Now, during fishing season, I go once and sometimes a second time.
Tau͡gaam imuggun petugarrarkun tua-i tamaa-i
neqnek quyurutkelallqa, neqrarnek-wa.
But I use a tethered net that I used to use for fishing,
at least small fish.
Man’a-qaa piciatun elpenek…
Does this, from you…
Huh?
(Okay, keep going.)
Man’a-qaa elpetek kiuyukuniu kiuniaraa.
For this, whichever of you2 can answer this.
Wangkuta Yugni nerangnaqsaraq atulalput
atuqengaput-llu watua mat’um nalliini cagmarnarqenrituq-qaa?
Should we Yupiit not lose our past subsistence
that we also use today?
Cagmagnarqenrituq ilumun.
It truly should not be lost.
Aren tua-i yuum angussagcuukarani,
atam imkut ava-i qanrutenritliaten.
My goodness, what hunting implements a person has,
I didn’t tell you about them, you see.
Unisteḿa imkut taluyarraat yuugaqamiki tang qulvaqernaurai.
When my late father removed his little fish nets, he would put them up.
Tua-i piciryaraqluku.
That was his custom.
Maa-i-ll’ wii, maa-i wii tamakut aturciigalkeka.
Tangvallruyaaqaqa.
And now, I can’t do those.
I watched him.
Makut-qaa man’a nerangnaqsararput aipaimta alerquutait
cagmarcetellriatun pingevkaraa?
Is our [Caucasian] counterparts’ instructions [or laws]
making it like our subsistence is being lost?
Qaill’-wa piat.
I’m not sure what going on with them.
Ilait-wa maa-i, aren taluyateng-llu yuuyuirulluki.
Some people now, my goodness, they don’t remove their fish traps too.
Atam qanpagalluku qanpagaluten.
Speak loudly to him.
Atam wii qaskilnguut taringekluten taringetuanka.
You see, I don’t completely understand when people speak quietly.
Ak’a-qaa tamaani kencik’lallruit tegganret?
Back then, did they respect elders?
Pissuuteteng?
Their tools?
Nuu.
(Aa-a.)
No.
(Okay.)
Tua-i-wa tegganret, tegganret-qaa takaqelallruit?
Elders, did they respect elders?
Takarnarqellruut imkut ciuqliit
au͡gkut wangkutun ayuqenrilnguut, ciuqvallret au͡gkut.
Those people back then who are not like us,
those a long time ago, were intimidating.
Tua-i elpet-llu nallunrilketen tua-i piyarait.
You also know their customs.
Tua-i qaill’ pisciiganaki.
We couldn’t treat them in any [bad] way.
Takarnaqluteng. Itellriami-ll’, itellriani-ll’ enemun kiavaqerciiganani.
They were intimidating. And when going into a house,
they couldn’t go further inside.
Kiavaqertesciigat’lallruunga inerciigalnge’rma.
I couldn’t go inside even though I was mischievous.
Tua-i caperrsuglua kiavallerkamnek uani amiigem taqu͡rani.
I was hestitant to go inside out by the door.
Kiavaasqaqatnga tau͡gaam kiavaraqlua.
I would only go inside when they told me to.
Maa-i kiaggun enem iquakun anengnaqtuut.
Now, they try to go out at the end of the house inside.
Mat’um-qaa nalliini man’a Yugcetun qaneryararput
cagmarnarqenrituq ciin-llu makunun ayagyuanun?
(Yaa.)
These days, should our young people keep from losing
our Yup’ik language and why?
(Yes.)
Ciin cagmarnarqenrita?
Why shouldn’t we lose it?
Tua-i-wa makut tang qitevquralriit Kass’atun qanruqu’urqait
tuar tang usvituvlaalalriit-llu.
You see, these people who speak English, the ones they speak
[only] in English to, seem like they’re not completely wise.
Wiinga-w’ ukut tutgara’urluunka Vera-m yui
qanruteqtalaryaaqluku aaniit
My grandchildren here, Vera’s children, I tell their mother
“Atam Yugcetun qalarut’larki taringeluaqerluten taringelarnauraatgen.”
“Look, speak to them in Yup’ik so that they’ll completely understand you.”
Man’a-qaa Yugtun qalarcaraq elicungcarturlitgu elitnaurvigni?
Shoud, they teach this Yup’ik language in schools?
Yaa, please.
Yes, please.
Tua-i-qaa?
Is that all?
Two minutes left on this tape.
(Okay.)
Tua-i-q’ taq’ukuk?
Are we2 done?
Tua-i-wa taqsaaqellilriakut.
(Aa-a, quyana.)
We’re done.
(Okay, thank you.)
Yaa, let’s see.
(Tua-i kitak’…)
Okay, let’s see.
(Well now…)
Una-qaa, una-qaa Kuiggluk nutem maantellruuq?
Has Kwethluk always been here?
Aren, maaten ellangua Kuiggluk wanlluni.
My goodness, Kwethluk was here in my earliest memories.
Wangkuta uantellruukut uaqvani, enet-wa qavcirraan.
We were far downriver, and there were only several houses.
Yugyallrunrituq waten.
It wasn’t populous like this.
Tua-i avani kipusviim ing’um nalliini kanani.
It was at the time of the store down over there.
Aterpagtaqluta Kiaqlirmiunek.
The called us the Upriver People.
Waniw’ una Kuigglugmiunguqapiartuq.
This here is the original Kwethluk.
Wiinga-llu Iigmi ellangellrulrianga.
My earliest memories are in Eek.
Ellangnemkun-llu wagg’uq au͡gkunun Apruka’armiunun atrarluta
wagg’uq…
And in my earliest memories, we were going down to
what they called Aparuka’armiut, as in…