Kitak’ qanraqaa.
Please speak.
Tua-llu-q’ tua-i qaill’ ayuqeqatarta qanaallerpuk?
What’s our conversation going to be like?
Assirciqnganani-q’ tua-i piuq tuani massiinaam iluani?
Does it seem like it’ll be good in that machine?
Tua-i-w’ taklirinrilengraan-llu antarkaten aneskuvki egmianun
camek nagutaunak.
Even if it’s not too long, you can say what you have to say
without lingering on anything.
Assirtuq, canrituq.
It’s good, it’s fine.
Wiinga-wa ellangellemkun elpe’ngllemkun qanaalalrianga.
I only speak of my earliest memories and what I’ve realized.
Cali-llu maa-i-am elpengukut wangkuta tegganerni
Also, we elders have realized now
Maaten elpengukut nunavut man’a nakmiin nunavut
pikenrilriatun ayuqlirillrullinikvut.
We realized that it’s like we don’t own our land here,
our very own land, anymore.
Maani tua-i nunamteńi umyugiurngairulluta.
We don’t do what we want on our land anymore.
Tuamta-ll’ cali maani unani mer’utemteńi umyugiurngaunata.
And then, we can't do what we want in our waters either.
Tau͡gaam wani wii qaillun umyuartequralartua
ukegkut yuugarkat umyuaqaqamki.
But I do have some ideas when I think about
the people who will live in the future.
Wangkuta waten ellilriani camun amlleret allrakut tekilluki
maktangaitukut naucetaaruamta yugni.
We who have become like this will not be standing for
many years because we people are [like] flowers.
Kingunerput tuaten nauluni.
Tamakut tuaten naulriit ciunret piunrirluni.
Our offspring grow too.
Those first ones who grow pass away.
Tamana piciuguq.
That’s true.
Mat’umek wani umyuartequralartua:
I always think about this:
Uani Naparyarrarni tayima 1971-aam tungiini
Kass’aq tekiteqarraalleq waten qanellruuq:
Downriver in Napakiak, probably around 1971,
a Caucasian who came for the first time said this:
Pissuryaramteńek-gguq cuqcirinrilkumta nunakaitukut.
If we don’t determine our hunting grounds, we won’t have any land.
Tuani-llu inerquryaaqekenka maligutesqevkenaki
tamakunun allotment-aatnun. Cunawa.
And at the time, I admonished them against following
those allotments. Turns out [I was right].
Uumiani taum kevgaq tekitenqigtellria qanertuq waten:
Shortly after, that representative arrived again and said this:
Nuna-gguq man’a patuluku Kass’at taiqatartut.
Caucasians are going to come and cover this land.
Tamatumek-gguq pilinrilkumta nunakaitukut pissurvigkaunata-llu.
[S]he said that if we don’t do that, we will have no lands
or hunting grounds.
Akleng, ukveu͡rlurluta-am wangkuta allotment-aanek qaqiutellinilriakut.
Pity, we believed and established allotments.
Tuamta-llu maaten ellangukut taum kinguani
And then we realized after that
Makut wani irniaput tutgaraput-llu maaken wangkutnek
cataunateng, imkut tua-i kenkataput nutem.
That our children and grandchildren have nothing from here
from us, the ones we’ve always loved.
Ukunun aipamteńun tun’aput-qaa? Pikiutekaput-qaa?
Did we give them to our [Caucasian] counterparts?
Did we give it to them?
Tua-llu-w’ umyuartequralalrianga waten:
And then I think like this:
Wangkuta-mi tegganernun, tegganerni wall’u vote-aryugngalriani
nangkumta caqatarta man’a?
When we elders, we elders or those who can vote, are gone,
what’s going to happen to this?
Kia maktatqatartau yuuyaramta tungiinun?
Who’s going to uphold it to our way of life?
Cuqtellemni wii kia maktasngaitellinii.
By my estimate, no one will uphold them.
Tamakut-llu irniamta Yuunge’rmeng maktasngaitelliniluku
tamana ciumuruskunegteggu.
And even though our children are Yupiit,
they won’t uphold it when they go forward with it.
Tuamta-ll’ cali waniw’ qaneryararkaqa yuut amlleret assikenritaat.
And then, a lot of people don’t like my advice.
Yuut-llu amlleret nall’artevkenaki tayima qanaaciqngatua.
I may not speak correctly about many people.
Waten niitukut, niitellruunga wii qangvaurtellria ukaqvaggun:
We heard, I personally heard recently some time ago:
Yup’ik Nation-aarurrluta-gguq wangkuta yuullemteńun ayagciqukut.
If we become the Yup’ik Nation, we will proceed
to our way of life.
Maaten tang, maaten tang tamana wii yuvri’rqa
I examined it and realized
Yup’ik Nation-aaruluta natmun yuuyaramta tungiinun
ayagngaitellinilriakut tau͡gaam uungukumta traditional-aaruluta.
That if we’re the Yup’ik Nation, we will not go anywhere with our
way of life, but only if we are traditional.
Traditional-aarukumta Kass’amek atanrunata,
wangkutnek tau͡gaam ataniurluta ciungani pillemcetun.
If we are traditional with no Caucasian governers,
but govern ourselves as we did in the past.
Man’a-llu allotment-aaq maa-i unuamek nepngurtuq
Yugnun tauna elliin nunautekniluku.
And this allotment has become a cause for unrest
for Yupiit today who claim they own that land.
Man’a maa-i tamamta taringumayaaqerput:
nepngurutnguuq nunautengqelleq.
Wr all understand this:
land ownership leads to unrest.
Tau͡gaam nunamek waten angtuarpagmek cet’riluci
akmavet qanerluci pisqumalaryaaqamci.
However, I want youpl to outline a huge area of land like this
and speak of it to [non-Yup’ik people] out there.
Umyuaqa qanlaryaaquq tuaten pisqumaluci.
I say in my mind that I want youpl to do that.
Waniwa akmavet igallruunga allragni.
Last year, I wrote to them out of state.
Waniwa-llu tutgarama elliin ayagcetelqeńgamiu
tamana wani iqukarrluku qanresqumiinga qanertua.
And I am speaking of it because my grandchild sent it
and wanted me to end it with that.
Waten qanellruunga, amllerrsaaquq qanelqa, ellangellruniluta
yup’ut tutgaraput-llu tayima tamariniluki.
I’ve said this, I’ve said a lot, that since our earliest memories,
our children and grandchildren are lost.
Tuamta-ll’ cali tamariniluta nunamteńi maani
allanrulriatun ellirluta.
And I say that we are lost in out own lans as if we've become outsiders.
Nuna-llu man’a umyugiurutkescigaliniluku ak’a.
Tuar allanruluta.
We’ve already become unable to do what we want on this land.
It’s like we’re outsiders.
Kitaki tamana arenqiakekumteggu, ilumun arenqiakekumteggu
traditional-aaq tau͡gaam tangerrnaurput.
Now, if we disapprove of that, if we truly disapprove of that,
let us look at the traditional [way of life].
Waniwa amlleret usviilkeciqaatnga.
Many will call me crazy now.
Yup’ik Nation-aaruluta ayakumta akmaken Kass’anek
ataniurterluta ayagciqukut.
If we go forth as the Yup’ik Nation, we will be governed
by Caucasians from out there.
Atam cuq’erteqernaurput. Ak’a AVCP-m ataniraakut.
Let’s gauge the situation. AVCP already governs us.
Ayagcuutekamteńek-llu Yup’igkun kalikat taqumarillriit
tayima tamakut aturluki ayaasqelluta.
Official documents have been established to go as Yupiit
and we are told to go forth with those.
Tamaa-i tang Kass’akun ayagaarkat, ayagarkat.
That is the way to go as Westernized [people].
Una tau͡gaam traditional-aaq ellminek piugarkaq,
ellminek piyullermikun ayagarkaq.
But the traditional [way of life] is for us to be ourselves,
so we can go forth as we want.
Umyuama wii cucuksaaqaa nutem tamana
ellangutkellruamku avaken ayagluku.
In my opinion, I prefer that because it has been
part of my earliest memories from long ago.
Nunarraat kitumek atanrunateng. Ilameggnek tau͡gaam
tegganermek atanerluteng pillruut tamarmeng.
Villages didn’t have governers. All of them were
only governed by one of their own elders.
Mat’umek wani amllenrilengraan tutgarama umyugaa
narurcuumiilamku qanqertua.
Even though it’s not a lot, I’m speaking about it
because I don’t want to disregard my grandchild’s opinion.
Tua-llu qaill’ ayuqa man’a elpeni?
How does this seem to you?
[?]
Assirtuq. I like it.
It’s good. I like it.
Yuungnaqellminun-wa tua-i tungiinun.
About how one should traditionally live.
Man’a cali tutgarama-am tukriarucaku tayima amlleq
nallungramku tau͡gaam ellmacuar tangrrucimtun, nallunrilucimtun.
Because my grandchild also brought this up, even if I don’t know
a lot, [I’m speaking] only about what little I understand and know.
Tua-i ellmacuar tangerqallruaqa wiinga.
I only saw a little of it.
Wangkuta-wa tangerqallruarput man’a apyutii
maaggun carugarnek tangenrritlemteggun
We saw what [s]he asked about through
how we didn’t see a lot of these [Western] things
Canek piinata anglillerni tamamta.
All of us who have grown up without anything [Western].
Tua-llu uumek waten aptaanga: wangkutnek-gguq piurqumta
qaillun-gguq yuullerput ayagciqa?
And then [s]he asked me this: if we [govern] ourselves,
how will our lives go?
Kiuyugngaaqa uumek: ciulirneret tau͡gaam ellangviullruut
ciulirnerem alerquutiikun ayagluni.
I can answer with this: the ancestors were the only ones to
grow up with, going though what the ancestors instructed.
Ciulirnerem-llu alerquutiikun anguss[aagluteng]…
[They] also hunted with the ancestors’ instruction…
Kitak’ cali apyutkellrat ataam cali tailluku ayagnirniartuten.
Now, start by bringing up what they asked.
Yaavet-qaa ekumanrilnguq ilakevkenaku iqulirluku?
Leave out what’s not recorded in there and finish it?
Yaa, kitak’ au͡gna ataam [qane]llren apyutkellra
tailluku cali ataam ayagnirluten.
Yes, please start by bringing up what you [said] about his question.
Ii-i, yaa, au͡g’umek-wa natmun arulailqa uunguciircamku.
(Canrituq. Ayagnirluten.)
Okay, yes, I have no idea where I stopped.
(It’s okay. Just start.)
Uumek wani tutgarama apcanga qaillun Yuut ellmeggnek
ellmeggnek piurquneng ayakuneng pillerkaanek aplua.
When my grandchild asked me, [s]he asked about
what will happen if Yupiit governed themselves.
Apcanga tamalkuan nallunrilengramku tau͡gaam tua-i
ellma nallunrilamku
When [s]he asked, even though I [don’t] know everything
since I only know a little
Kiima-w’ nallunritenritaqa. Ilama-llu nallunritaat
waten carugarnun ellangellrunrilngurni.
I’m not the only one who knows. My peers who did not
grow up with a lot of [Western] things like this know it.
Qanruyuteput tua-i niitengnaqluki atungnaqluki-llu pilallruamta
imumi camek allamek akirugarmek piitellemteńi.
We tried to obey and adhere to our traditional wisdom
back when we didn’t have a lot of things including money.
Tua-llu? Ukutgun tau͡gaam yuk ayagarkauguq ciulirnerteggun.
You see? A person must only go forth
[with the wisdom of] the ancestors.
Ciulirneret, ciulerneq taillruuq nutarauvkenani,
nutem piuluni, nutem qanruyutnguluni.
The elder did not come as a new thing,
[but] as an ancient thing, ancient traditional wisdom.
Ukut-llu munallruluteng neq’liurteput, neqmun alerquuteput.
And those who worked on fish for us were dexterous,
those who instructed us on fish.
Waten alerquumaluta: neqmek neqallermek-llu
sagciluta pisqevkenata kumiviitellemteńi.
We were instructed like this: do not make a mess
of food and food scras when we didn’t have freezers.
Cuqluku-llu una ulligcista. Cuqluku taqtuluta.
And it depends on the fish cutter. We stopped depending on her.
Tua-i apqiitnek spoil-ararkanek piyuunata.
We wouldn’t [gather] what would spoil, as they say [in English].
Tuamta-llu ciulirneret alerquutiitgun nunami pekluta.
Ciulirneret tau͡gaam alerquutiitgun.
And then we also walked on land as the ancestors instructed.
Only though the ancestors’ instruction.
Arcaqerluku alerquun niisngangnaqluku uskuarmi up’nerkami-llu.
We especially tried to obey instruction in the fall and spring.
Tua-i taukuk aarnarqellriaruan nunam qainga
mer’et-llu makut qaingat.
It was because the land and the water were dangerous
in those2 times.
Taukugni aarnaqngan tamakunek arcaqerluta
ciulirnerem alerqualallruakut tamatumek.
Because it was dangerous in those2 times, our ancestors
especially instructed us on those.
Tuamta-llu yuullerkamteńek mat’umek
ilamteńun makunun yugnun yuullerkamteńek
And then about how we should live,
how we should live treated our fellow people
Yuunitekluta pisqevkenata inerquumaluta.
They told admonished us against [treating them badly]
just because we’re people.
Tamatum nalliini taringumallrunricaaqerput wangkuta man’a
tau͡gaam kinguqvaarni elpekellruarput.
We didn’t understand this at the time, but we realized
what it was later.
Una wani yuunitekluni yuuyaraq waten ayuqelliniuq:
Living life [treating others badly]
just because we’re people is like this:
Yuunitekluni-gguq yuulria qaneni negtaayuitaa ilaminun,
cangayullerkaa-llu yuum umyuaqevkenaku.
A person [who treats others badly] just because he’s a person
does not watch what he says to other people,
and gives no consideration about offending them.
Cali-llu kenekmek piitelliniluni, umyuaqegtaarmek-llu piitelliniluni.
He also does not have love or good thoughts.
Tuaten-llu ayuqellria apqiitnek erneq aipirluku unguvayuunani-gguq.
They say that one who is like that
does not live another day, as they say.
Taumek tamakut wangkuta teggutekaput tamaa-i
Those are our sources of support
Makunek kalikarteggun ayangvailemta,
kalikam mat’um ayangvailgakut.
Before we started going with these books,
before these books started dictating us.
Naklegnarqellria takumcunaqluku.
We had mercy on someone pitiful.
Cali-llu man’a wani naklekutvut aturyugnaunaku
state-aq pingqelliniuq waten:
Also, the state apprently has this without our compassion:
Eighteen-aaqan-gguq yuum yun’i peggliu qanrutenrirluku,
allakaan-llu yuuvkarluku.
A person should abondon his child when he’s 18,
stop teaching him, and have him live separately.
Tamana wangkuta alerquutekenritarput Yugni.
That is not how we Yupiit are instructed.
Yuum-gguq angukara’urluurteng’e’rmi, panini-ll’ ak’allaurtengraan,
qetunrani-ll’ ak’allaurtengraan iqlutun cingyuitaa.
They say that even when a person becomes an old man, though his
daughter gets old, though his son gets old, he does not steer them wrong.
Waten qanrucimauq taqsuunaku.
It’s said that we should not stop [caring for them].
Tau͡gken makut aipamta ayallra man’a
wangkutni arenqianaqluni cakneq.
However, the way our counterparts go
is very unsuitable to us.
Maa-i makut wani elitnaurat tamarmeng cakenriraitkut ciulirnerni.
Now, all of these students disregard us elders.
Makut tau͡gaam kalikat nallunrilketeng kiingita usvikluki ilumun.
They only trust in the wisdom of the books
that they know, truly.
Kingum yua ayuqucirtuqalriani tua-i nakqapiarmek kiuluni.
A child of the next generation talks back straight away when instructed.
Wall’u cangayugluni qanrutniluni, kituggniluni, kitugtengnaqniluni.
Or he is offended by instrucion when they are corrected.
Quyanaqvaa tutgara’ar uum mat’umek qanqautamken.
I am so thankful, my grandchild, that I’m telling you this.
Wii pikenritaqa. Nutem piuguq avaken ayagluni.
It’s not mine. It’s ancient from long ago.
Makut wani wangkuta nallunrilkengaput
quli’irnek ayagluteng avaken piugut.
What we know here is from ancient legends.
Kiituani yuugukut, yuurtut.
Kiituani unuamek tekitut tayima maa-i umyuaqesteḿeggnun.
Eventually we’re alive, they are born.
Eventually, they’ve come to those who remember them.
Quyanaqvaa.
Thank you very much.
Quyanarquten elpet, alapen’errlua-ll’ maavet itrama.
I should dearly thank you,
also because I’m surprised to have come in here.