Qivrunrilkumegnuk piyanritarpuk tauna ungungssiq tauna nerrleq.
Were we not sad over our loss, we wouldn’t have killed that animal that ate.
Kingumek nerluku nangluku yuut.
Afterwards, the people ate the rest of it.
Way in the...
Nerluku-w’ tua-i wangkuta-llu nerluku tauna nerrleq tauna. Neqkailamta allamek tua-i nerluku.
We also ate what had been eaten. We ate it because we had nothing else to eat.
Pissuryarat pagkut pagaani ingrini amllertut.
There’s a lot of places to hunt up there in the mountains.
Waniwa ciuqliq: Evsairniit pissuryaraugut.
Here’s the first: Evsairniit is a place to hunt.
Tua-i-llu tungii: Nacarkarniarmek pissuryaraq mayuumayaraat.
And the next: a hunting place is going up from Nacarkarniar.
Tua-llu pingayuak: Ilutuqacuk, wiinga-w’ nunautekeka.
And the third: Ilutuqacuk, my lands.
(Kangerpakmailianek-llu imkunek.) Yaa.
(And from Kangerpakmailiat.) Yes.
Naqerpak-wa. Nurtuutaraq-wa.
Then Naqerpak. Then Nurtuutaraq.
Lots of camps [?] upriver.
Qanirtuum-wa Qagatii.
Then Qanirtuum Qagatii.
Way up there, [?].
Way of up there, [?].
Naqerpagmek tauna pilaraat wavet Kuinerram Qagatiinun ayagyaraq.
They call it Naqerpak where it goes it goes here to Kuinerram Qagatii.
Kuinerram-llu Qagatiini waniw’ walirnermi nanvam keluani Equgniilngurni cali pissuryaraq tauna.
And on this side of Kuinerram Qagatii, inland from the lake, Equgniilnguut is also hunting grounds.
Una-wa cali uani igyaraani pissuryaraq cali nutaan pissuumayarat.
And then downriver near its mouth, there’s a hunting ground that they hunt in for a long time.
Ukut-llu Kuigglugmiut tuavet uksuarmi ayalartut nangluteng angutet.
And then every single man from Kuiggluk goes there in the fall.
Tua-i Alussistuaqata’arqata tau͡gaam tekitaqluteng.
They would only return when Christmas was nigh.
Pika-i-ll’ pikna Naqailngurmek pilaqiit cali pissuryaraq tauna pissuumayaraat.
And up there where they call it Naqailnguq is also a hunting ground where they hunt for a long time.
Pissuryarat tua-i pagaani tamalkuita nallunritanka.
I know all of the hunting grounds up there.
Ingriúrlurmek aterluni. Ingriúrlurmek aterluni ingriq.
It’s called Ingriúrluq. The mountain is called Ingriúrluq.
Una-wa uatiini Elngurtuliarmek cali aterluni.
And downriver, it’s called Elngurtuliar.
Ukut-wa akiatni Qikertat.
And across from them is Qikertat [Islands].
Ukuk-wa taum Elngurtuliaraam keluani Napanguliignek aterlutek qiurek qulmun napalutek.
And these two inland from Elngurtuliar, the upright boulders are called Napanguliik.
Una-wa aciagni Ingrilukaak-gguq. Tua-lli tua-i cali taukuk pissuryaraulutek.
And beneath them, they call them Ingrilukaak. That is also a hunting ground.
Tauna-llu pikani akiani Iluvagtuq. Iluvagtuq-gguq. Cali pissuryarauluni tauna.
And then up there across from it is Iluvagtuq. They call it Iluvagtuq. That’s also a hunting ground.
Tua-i-llu kiatiini yaani Ulurrugnaq-gguq ingriq uverrluni tua-i, uverqurluni.
And then upriver and to the side, the moutnain Ulurrugnaq is steep.
Uverqurluni ketmun.
It’s slope goes toward the water.
Qukaani-wa can’gurneq una. Can’get naumaluteng qagkut.
And in the center is a grassy area. The grass grows upriver.
Taum-llu qukaani naumalriim tamakut-am, ciuqliit qanlartut
In the center of those plants, the elders say
Tauna-gguq yuk mayullruuq.
They say that a person went up.
Tua-i-llu qukaqerluni aaqilluni tua-i. Aciminun-ll’ uyungluni aaqilluni.
And then when he reached the middle, he became wary. He was wary and squat down below.
Qaill’ pisciiganani, ayagciiganani.
He couldn’t do anything, couldn’t go on.
Tua-i-gguq pika-i qukaa can’gurnerulartuq ingrim pik’um man’a tekilluku.
They say that the center of that mountain up there is a grassy area to this day.
Tua-ll’ kiatiini, kiatiini Atsartuliar-gguq ingricuar angevkenani. Cali pissuumayaraq.
Then upriver, they call the small mountain Atsartuliar. It’s also a hunting ground.
Tua-i-llu taum ingricuaraam cali keluani kuignayuk, kuignayuk kelutmun Kuignayugpagmek aterluni.
And the the small river inland from that small mountain, the small river going inland is called Kuignayugpak.
Nutaan tauna cali pissuryaraq, pissuumayaraq.
Now that is a hunting ground where they hunt for a long time.
Tua-llu Qanirtuum Kuiganun waniw’ tekiteqatartua.
And then, I’m going to go to the Qanirtuk River.
Qanirtuum Kuigan ceńiini... ingriq ima tanem im’ camek pilaqiit?
On the banks of the Qanirtuk River... what do they call the mountain again?
Ulurrugnaq. Tauna cali tua-i pissuumayaraq.
Ulurrugnaq. That’s also a hunting ground.
Tauna-llu kiatiini... cagnek im’? Cayagtuli? Nuu.
And upriver from there... what is it again? Cayagtuli? No.
Nallukenka wiinga. Nanglliuq?
I don’t know them. Is that all?
Nuu, nangekstaitut. Nangyugnaitut.
No, there’s more. There’s a lot more.
Tua-ll’ pikani Ircaqurrnaq.
And then up there is Ircaqurrnaq.
Cali pissuryarauguq tauna. Ircaqurrnamek aterluni.
That’s also a hunting ground. It’s called Ircaqurrnaq.
Tua-llu wani ketiini ingricuar ayuqii. Ircaqurrnayagarmek aterluni.
And then toward the water, there’s a similar mountain. It’s called Ircaqurrnayagaq.
Tua-ll’ yaani kiatnii Evsaiksugaak. Cali tamaani pissutuluteng taum yaaqsinrilkiini.
And then over and upriver are Evsiaksugaak. They also hunt not far from there.
Wani-llu Qerrirtaq.
And here is Qerrirtaq.
Qerrirtami cali tuani pissuryarauguq, tang nutaan pissuumayarauluni.
Qerrirtaq is also a hunting ground where they can hunt for a long time.
Tua-i-llu kiani Cingikeggliq.
And then upriver is Cingikeggliq.
Cingikegglimek aterluni ingriq cingickeggluni qulmun.
The mountin with a sharp upward summit is called Cingikeggliq.
Tua-ll’ ukatiini Kuigglugmun atrarluni ingriq Canirngalria-gguq.
And on this side, they mountain going down to Kuiggluk is named Canirngalria.
Tua-llu taum akiani Qupun. Quputmek aterluni.
And then on the other side is Qupun. It’s called Qupun.
Yaani-w’ iquani Canyon-aamek aterluni Kuignayuggaq cali.
And then over at the end, it’s name is Canyon, Kuignayuggaq.
Wani-llu akiani tauna Nacarkarniarun.
And on the other side here is Nacarkarniarun.
Nutaan pissuumayaraat mayuumalriit.
Now that place where they go up is a hunting ground.
Tua-llu cali taum Nacarkarniarutem akiani...
And then on the other side of Nacarkarniarun...
Unaten pivkenaku.
[?Don’t use your hand.]
Aa?
What?
Evsairniik. Evsiarniik-gguq.
Evsairniik. They call it Evsairniik.
Tua-i cali tauku pissuumayarak tua-i taukuk ak’anun.
They also hunt there for a long time.
Yeah, take a break, rest, stop for a minute. Yeah, stop. (Ii-i, taqsukuvet.)
Yeah, take a break, rest, stop for a mintue. Yeah, stop. (Okay, you can stop.)
Au͡gkut tua-i pissumayarat tamalkuita ava-i qalarutkuraranka.
I’ve just talked about all of those hunting grounds.
I don’t know how to talk Kass’aq.
I don’t know how to talk in English.
Has he mentioned any stories of big creatures?
Neqerpangqertuq.
It has big fish.
Yaa, qanrutkaa ava-i. He already.
Yes, he just talked about it. He already did.
Did he talk about, anything about the skeleton, ribs, skeletons on the beach?
It’s long time.
Yaa, did he talk about that though? (Yaa.) The skeletons on the beach? (Yaa.) Okay.
Okay, did he talk about that though? (Yes.) The skeletons on the beach? (Yes.) Okay.
[?] the father, her father, long time, the bones.
White bones? (Yaa, yaa.)
White bones? (Yes, yes.)
He get big hole. (Right.) In and out, the kids are playing there.
That’s the story we heard.
She said long grass, that he’s on ground place, that old place.
She said long grass, that’s he’s on ground place, that old place.
Do you know which side of the lake those were on? North side?
Nuu. (South side?) Kuiggluk side.
No. (South side?) Kwethluk side.
Kwethluk side of the lake?
That’s east side?
Yaa.
Ukatmun caumaluni waten. Yaa.
It faces this side. Yes.
Kiillaraliin, Heart Lake, Kuiggluk, this side.
Kiillaraliin, Heart Lake, Kwethluk, this side.
This side, that’s where the bones were? (Ii-i.)
This side, that’s where the bones were? (Yes.)
Yaa, tua-i nauw’ imna map-an? I’ll show you. Nauw’ im’ map-an?
Yes, where your map? I’lls how you. Where’s your map?
Okay, George can you get that? It’s back in there, top one.
Tunglirnera map-am, Kuiggluum tungiinun imna waten iciw’ ayuqelria?
Toward it on the map, you know it goes like this toward Kwethluk?
Right or left? Right?
Nauw’ im’ Kuiggluk. Maa-i tang Kuiggluk.
Where’ Kwethluk again? Here’s Kwethluk.
Yaa, it’s this side.
Yes, it’s this side.
We always stay this side.
Kuikayak ava-i.
There’s Kuikayak over there.
Can you this aloud?
Can you say this aloud?
Kuikayak maa-i.
Here’s Kuikayak.
Ii-i. Crooked Creek Mountain. Yaa, waniwa.
Yes. Crooked Creek Mountain. Yes, here it is.
Killalin nauwa? Maa-i tang.
Where’s Killalin? Here it is.
Kuik ava-i... (Kuigceńaq waniwa.)
The river over there... (Here’s Kuigceńaq.)
Upper Fall-aq Igceńaq, Qurrlurta.
Upper Fall is Igceńaq, Qurrlurta.
(Yaa.) Eskimo name, Qurrlurta.
(Yes.) Eskimo name, Qurrlurta.
Taryaqvagtuli waniwa.
Here’s Taryaqvagtuli.
Yaa, waniwa-w’ tua-i kanani walirnerani.
Yes, here it is down there on this side.
Walirneranetuq wani. (Yaa, ukalirneranetuq tuani.)
It’s on this side. (Yes, it’s there on this side.)
Evon Qugg’aq, [?].
You know stories, or?
Nuu, it’s older than.
No, it’s older than.
She’s teaching for hunting, walking.
No stove, just tent in the winter.
When you went to Heart, like, did you walk?
Nuu, by plane.
No, by plane.
Oh, this time? Long time, a long time ago, though, did you walk?
Dogs. (Dogs.) Dog team.
She went Heart Lake in the winter?
Spring. (In the spring for the thaw?) Beaver hunting, that kind.
Now it’s, fall-ami tau͡gaam this year.
Now it’s, only in the the fall this year.
How many years, that was long time. Her daughter went up there.
I think [?] sickness.
They flew up this year?
Is the lake, the lake’s good now? There’s no big fish in the lake? It’s good? No...
She got lots of talaarit. Caulriit ima talaarit?
She god lots of talaarit [rainbow trout]. What are talaarit again?
Canek ima tam’ pilaqait fish-at?
What do they call those fish again?
Kina? Kina?
Who? Who?
Trout-at-wa nanvani.
The trout in lakes.
No big... (Citegnat.)
Small ones we’re fishing. (Citegnat.) We’re fishing, we’re eating small ones.
But no creatures in there like the stories anymore.
Sometime, her youngest brother, but way up from mountainside, he saw something bubbling the water.
Sometime, her youngest brother, but way up from the moutnainside, he saw something bubbling the water.
And then he saw lots of spots.
Down, way down, it’s clear, you know, the clearest water?
Clear water?
Yaa, way down there, he saw the spots, black.
Yes, way down there, he saw the spots, black.
When was that?
Almost jump up.
This time? This trip?
Nuu, long time, her brother, when she was...
No, long time, her brother, when she was...
She’s in hospital now.
So did people get scared and stop going there, or people always went there?
But me, I’m scared I might eat airplane.
Really, I’m scared. We might eat.
You ever, you or Wassilie ever hear of a stone face on top of a mountain by Kiseralik?
Stone head, face?
Nuu, I never go there, Kiillaraliin.
No, I never go there, Kiillaraliin.
Can you ask him? A stone head by Kiseralik? Does he know? Can you ask?
What head?
Stone, rock, on top of a mountain.
I think, nuu, nalluaqa.
I think, no, I don’t know it.
Did you know Old Man Reed had a mine up on the Kiseralik?
[?] I always went up, always [?].
Only went up to...
One time, he went up to Kiillaraliin, but always rain.
One time, he wen tup to Kiillaraliin, but always rain.
Some stories we’ve had, the people go up to Kiseralik all the time, but they were afraid to go to Heart Lake, ’cause there’s supposed to be a creature over there. So they never did go to Kiseralik, I mean, to Heart Lake.
We talked to Fanny, Fanny. (Yaa.) Yaa.
We talked to Fanny, Fanny. (Yes.) Yes.
When she was young, her brother, David Jackson?
Long time, she was up that way.
Atam, I’ll show you Kiillaraliin. Take it.
Look, I’ll show you Kiillaraliin. Take it.