Akluit-llu eru’urqamteki angutet akluit allakartetetullruit aanamta.
And when we washed their clothes, our mothers had us
separate the mens’ clothes.
Wangkuta-llu arnani akluput allakartelluki
They also had us separate we women's’ clothes
Tua-i kencikngamegteki.
Because they were respectfully careful with them.
Waten man’a ava-i qanrutkurallerci pissuryaraq pitekluku pitullruut.
As you’ve said, they did this because of their hunting.
Arnam aklui allakarmeng iqairumaarkauluteng arnartarrlainaat.
Women's’ clothes would have to be washed separately
only with women’s clothes.
Atutullruaqa-llu wiinga.
Tua-i atutuaqa tan’gaurlurugarnek-llu irniangqerrama.
I also used to do that.
I do that because I have a lot of male children.
Tua-i-ll’ ukut wani angutem aklui mermun tuavet
arnat iqairitellratnun pivkenaki.
And then, they wouldn't wash the men's clothes in the water where the women's were washed.
Uum wani nutaan nutaramek emirluki angutem pii piarkautullruut.
They were supposed to wash men’s clothes in new water.
Ayuqucirtutullruitkut waten ilarqutevkenaki aulukesqelluki qigcikluki.
The instructed us to take care of them without mixing them
like this out of respect.
Cam iliini aptua, “Ciin waten pivkalarciki?”
One day, I asked, “Why do you have them do this?”
Aanamnun aptetullruunga nallukemnek.
I used to ask my mother about things I didn’t know.
Tua-ll’ waten aanama pianga:
And then my mother said this to me:
Waten-gguq ava-i qanrutkurallerpecicetun wanirpak
She said, as youpl just did now
Pissullerkaat, pitengnaqlerkaat yuilqumek pitekluku
tuaten pimaut makut.
They are [washed] like this because of their hunting,
because of their subsistence in the wilderness.
Taringellemnek maa-i qaneryuglua qanertua sassairutqatalliniamegnuk.
I wanted to talk about what I understood
because we’re2 running out of time.
Tua-i-llu wangkuta cali arnani neqnek aulukilriani
And then we women who take care of food
Tua-i qigcikluki angutet unangkengait melqulgungraata caungraata
tua-i angutet unakellrit qigcikluki aulukellruaput.
We respected what the men caught, animals with fur, no matter what
they were, took care of what the men caught out of respect.
Tamana tua-i alerquun atungnaqu’urluku.
We tried to adhere to that instruction.
Uqlaulluki pillrunritaput.
We didn’t pollute nature with them.
Pitaita enrit, carrluit, iluita-llu carrillrit uqlaulluki aulukellrunritaput.
We didn’t take care of them to pollute nature with the bones, scraps,
or guts of what they caught.
Ca tamalkuan apyutektullruaqa aanamnun.
Ilarugailama apyutektullruanka.
I asked my mother about everything.
I asked about them because I didn’t have a lot of relatives.
Tua-ll’ waten pitullruanga:
And then she would say this to me:
“Ava-i uqlaupakaqumki-gguq tamakut pitai uum aiparma,
tauna-gguq nakriaruciiquq, yuilqumek-llu pitqerciigalilunii.”
“If I pollute nature with what my spouse catches, he will become
a bad hunter, and he will not catch anything from the wilderness.”
Tua-i-gguq-wa uqlaulluki wiinga tuaten tua-i piciqellrii uqlauskumki,
pitarkam pinrirluku.
She said that if I pollute nature with them, that will happen,
animals will no longer come to him.
Tua-i-ll’ ukvekluki wiinga.
Ukvektullruluki tamakut tuaten pitullinillrat.
And I believed them.
I believed that that would happen to them.
Cali-llu ava-i qanellruunga pingnaquralput arnani uitaurayuilamta,
yuilqumek pingnaquratuamta piyararrarluta-llu pitullruluta.
I also just talked about we women’s subsistence because we weren’t
sedentary, we also had gathering spots in the wilderness
because we subsisted.
Qigcikluku yuum pivianun, yuum piyaraanun pisqumamayuitellruukut
They told us not to go to people’s gathering spots out of respect
Taum-wa yuum tauna piyaraqngaku qigcignaqluni
umyugaa nall’artenritlerkaa.
We should show respect for that person’s gathering spot
in case they would be offended.
Tua-i pivimteńun tau͡gaam wangkuta pingnaquratullruukut
piciatun pivkenata.
We tried to go to our own gathering spots, not random places.
Tua-i-llu cali niitetullrulria qalartellrianek
I also used to hear people talk
Angutet-gguq makut pissurtet pissulriim canek aruarkanek
tuani-llu taluyam nuniini kuvyam-llu nuniini aruarkanek piyuitut.
They said that they wouldn’t put what hunters caught where they would
spoil around that fish trap or drift net area.
Tauna-gguq kuvyiryaraq neqem aruvikellrukani
allrakuani nurciarkauguq neqmek.
They said that if food spoils aroudn that drift net area,
fish will be short the next year.
Pitangqerrngaunani tuaten amllertalriamek.
It would have as much [as it usually does].
Tauna-llu cali taluyaq pissuun kuicuarmi tuani civingalria
And that fish trap that is set in that creek
Kuicuar-gguq tamana cali pissurvikestiin kencikaa.
Aruiviksuumiitaa elliin pissuryaraqngamiu.
They said the fisher respectfully watches over that creek.
He doesn’t want anything to spoil there because he fishes there.
Aruivikumallrukuni-gguq ungungssimek
camek tua-i pitamek taluyat nuniit
They said that if any animal spoils there around that fish trap
Allamiani nakerrluni cali pitangqerrngaituq pissulallratun.
It would have as much fish as it used to catch the next year.
Tamakut tang wangkuta asgurakellrunrilkeput avani ciuqvaarni.
You see, we didn't doubt those back then.
Ca tamalkuan au͡gkut yuut qigcikellruat
yuilqurrungraan nunaungraan-llu.
The people back then respected everything, even the wilderness and land.
Ava-i qanllemtun watua nunam qainga tangniirupailgan
As I just said, before the land became an eyesore
Makunek kalikallernek can-allernek-llu patuvailgan
nunam qainga menuitellruuq
The land used to be pristine before it was covered
with these paper products and cans
Nunat-llu nuniit elaqvanun assirluni tangerrnarqetullruuq.
And areas far out from villages looked good.
Mat’um nalliini yuum tekiartellra tamarmi elitaqnarqelartuq.
These days, you can tell every place a person has come to.
Una yuum tekitellrullinikii canek-llu egqaqilliniluni
maa-i cat cautellminek atullminek.
A person would come upon this place and throw things away,
his old things and things he’s used.
Mat’um nalliini tuaten nuna ellirtuq.
These days, that’s what the land has become.
Menuitenrirtuq yuilqurtuumarmi.
Even the wilderness is no longer pristine.
Qigcikenriryugnarqaat.
I don’t think they respect it anymore.
Tua-i tuaten taktaaqa.
[Okay.]
That’s all from me.
She says that…
Naunraat, kuiget, nanvat-llu, tamakut qigcik’lallrukci tamaani.
Youpl respected plants, rivers, lakes, those things back then.
Kencikluki qigcikluki.
[Yaa, yaa.]
Respectfully watched over them and respected them.
[Yes, yes.]
Au͡gkut mat’umi-llu kuigpagmi maani Kusquqvagmi
tayima Yukon-ami-llu piciquq
Those things even here in this great Kuskokwim River,
probably on the Yukon too
Yuut alerquutengqertut kuigmek mat’umek
kencikluku piklerkaanek.
People are instructed to respectfully watch over this river.
Tua-i-gguq cali wangkutni up’nerkami wall’u kiagmi-llu
Also, for us, in the spring or summer
Imkunek au͡gkunek ciuliamteńek alerquutengqertukut
We have instructions from our ancestors
Mat’umun kuigmun kiagaqan kiagtetarnek allragnillarnek
neqlernek egcivikesqevkenaku watqapik.
In the summer, we should never throw old food
from the last summer or year.
Tua-i-gguq tamakut kiagtetaat tamaani pilallrata tamana
neqem nayussiyaagngaitaa
They said that if those year-old [foods] go there,
the fish won’t go around it too often
Tua-i imkucetun kuiggaarcetun uum qanrutkellracetun
tamana taum nunii neqengqerrngaunani elluarrluni.
Like that creek that she talked about, it won’t have
a healthy amount of fish around there.
Tau͡gaam-gguq kiagtetaat tamakut egtevkenaki mermun tamaavet.
Instead, they said not to throw those year-old [foods] into that water.
Elagluku-gguq nuna teq’aqilaput tamaavet alaicetevkenaki-llu.
They said we should bury them in pits so that they’re not noticeable.
Tau͡gaam-gguq makut tua-i nutarat neqet iluit qiluit-llu egtengramteki
But they said we could throw fresh fish along with their guts
Unavet tau͡gaam tutmararkaunrilngurmun kuvesqelluki
yuum tutmarngailkiitnun, etuuralriamun, entaanrilngurmun-llu.
We should only dump them down where no one will tread,
where no person will tread, somewhere deep where the tide
does not go out too much.
Tua-i-am maa-i egciyaurtut mer’em ceńaq tua-i man’a
neqngurrluku tamakunek alerquuteseng maligtaqunrilamegteggu maa-i.
They’ve started throwing them away these days until the shore
has been covered in food because they don’t adhere to their instruction.
Tua-i cali tuaten kuigem mat’um un’um kuigpallraam
kencikluku atullerkaa tuaten ayuquq wangkutnun.
That is what respectfully watching over this great river
when we subsist from it is supposed to be for us.
Okay, as far as the river’s, in spring or summer,
the rules of their forefathers were that they were told not to throw
If there should be leftovers that can’t be eaten from the winter,
that you do not throw these into the river.
If you do, there’s a chance that the new fish will not
come to that river.
Au͡gna, au͡gna wani taringecurlagnayukluku nallulriarulaata makut,
una-llu wani yaquleyagiurteńek pilria.
In case what was just said may be understood because these
people do not know, including this Fish and Game officer.
Neqnek wangkuta egcisciigatukut,
yugmek-llu egcilriamek niiteksaitua man’a engelkarrluku.
We cannot throw food away, and I have not heard of anyone
throwing food away to this day.
Tau͡gaam ellaita ukut qatellriaput neqnek egqaqilartut.
Our Caucasian counterparts, however, throw food away.
Tua-i.
That’s all.
He didn’t want any misunderstanding of throwing away.
He’s saying that the native people as a whole are told
that you don’t throw away food.
He just wanted to make that clear because
he doesn’t say that they do that.
But he has seen, you know, people, you know,
who don’t have that kind of rule
Throwing fish away just the way the are.
Icigg’ qigcik’kuvgu-gguq ca imna neqngungraan
You know, she asked if you respect something, even fish
Qaill’-gguq-qaa icigg’ cut-atullruaci qigciklerpeci pitaciatun?
You know, would youpl cut them a certain way out of respect?
Wall’u-gguq-qaa tauna piciatun kepuryuumauq neqa?
Or, can that fish be cut in any way?
Makut tamaa neqet wangkutnun cali inerquutekumallruut imumi,
tayima-wa tua-i unani-ll’ imarpigmiutaat pillilriit.
We had admonishments surrounding these fish back then,
and they probably had them with marine animals down on the coast.
Neqet wangkuta piqertuutamek aturluta kepuusqevkenaki,
tau͡gaam uluamek aturluta kepluki uruumakata.
They told us not to cut fish with axes, but with knifes if they’re thawed.
Tamaa-i tamat tamakutgun tau͡gaam pisqelluki.
They told us to only use those [knives] on everything.
Inerquutauluteng piqertuutaq aturluku neqnun taukunun pisqevkenata.
They admonished us against using axes on those fish.
Kumlaskata tau͡gaam ner’arkaukatki qimugtet maani tagumarilriit
Only when they’re frozen and the dogs inland will eat them
Kuigmi cali piqertuarluki inerquutekluki neqa tauna
unani wall’ akulmi.
They admonished us against using axes on that fish
down by the water or inland.
Nugumalria piqertuutarmek kepuusqevkenaku
inerquutnguluni tua-i tamana.
That was an admonishment, not to cut fish out of the water with axes.
Tua-i tuaten au͡gna ayuquq. Piqertuutaq atuusqumavkenani
akulmi wall’ maani-llu.
That’s what it’s like. They told us not to use axes
inland or down by the water.
Tua-i piqertuarluku tamana cali assikevkenaku.
They didn’t like when axes were used on those.
Kelgalarniluki cali neqairut’larniluki tuaten
They also said that they [inform others] and that no more fish go there
Aulukestemta tangvagaqamikut picuvvlagluta tuaten
pillrit tamakut neqet.
When our caretaker watched us taking bad care of those fish.
Yaa, he has that answer.
Yes, he has that answer.
Elisa, piqertuarluki?
Elisa, what is “piqertuarluki?”
Axe.
Okay, okay. There’s a way that you cut rather than hitting,
hitting motion like an axe or what
Unless they’re frozen and can’t be cut any other way,
then you show respect if it’s thawed.
Neqerrluaraat, neqerrluarnek pilaqeput tua-i dry fish.
Dried fish, we call dried fish neqerrluaraat.
Leftover-aarqamta qimugtellegnun tua-i tuntuaput.
When we have leftovers, we give them to those who have dogs.
Taumun qimugtelilriamun yugmun tua-i tunluki cikiutekluki.
We give them as gifts to those who have a lot of dogs.
And he also wanted to say that if they have leftover, like…
…cat-wa ayuqenrilnguut naunraat.
…different kinds of plants.
Au͡gkut-llu berries-aat tua-i-w’ unitetuaput iqvasqenrilkeput
tau͡gaam atsalingraan, you know, tegumanrilnguut.
We also leave those berries that we don’t want picked,
but even if there are a lot of berries, you know, that aren’t taken.
Tau͡gaam uniciaqameng aqvaarkauluki atsat
piyualuni pillrukuni pavani atmagluki.
But when they leave berries, they would get them
with knapsacks if they walked inland.
Unangliqkuni tua-i uniciqerluni natmun tuavet
piarkaunrilngurmun nutaan aqvaluki taukut atsat.
If [s]he picks a lot, [s]he will leave them where they won’t
be picked and then go get those berries.
Wall’u yuk ikayungqerquni tua-i unicivkenani piarkauluku.
Or if a person has help, [s]he will not leave [berries].
Cali atsaungraata tamaani-am yuilqumi amllengraata
pitsaqutmek tutmarluki pisqevkenaki
And even if there are a lot of berries in the wilderness,
they said not to purposefully tread on them
Makut salmonberries-aat, tan’gerpiit.
These cloudberries, crowberries.
Tau͡gaam amlliurluki avitaalriacetun.
Instead, they should keep from stepping on them.
Tua-i ilii pinritsaange’rmi amllessiyaagqameng tutmalaraput.
Sometimes, though we try not to, we tread on them
when there is too much.
Cali imkut naunraat nertukput wangkuta, quagcit, quagcit,
angukaat-llu, napat-llu akuliitni atsat
And those plants that we eat, sourdock, sourdock,
and wild rhubarb, and berries among trees
Tamaa-i cali nallullikci ilait mercuullugpiit,
agautaat, atsaanglluut
Youpl probably don’t know about some of them [like]
high-bush cranberries, red currants, black currants
Tua-i cali tamaa-i tamakut iqvatukeput napat iluatnek.
And those berries we pick among trees.
Tau͡gaam inerquutnguluteng-am ilait.
But some are admonished against.
Nallullikten tayima tulukaruut atsaitnek neqaitnek
You probably don’t know about baneberries that ravens eat
Waten tua-i plant-aq atsarugarnek nevumaluni waten kavirpak.
A plant with a lot of berries sticking on it that’s all red.
Tua-i-gguq tulukaruut neqait.
They call those baneberries.
Nerkumteki tamakut naulluqertarkauluta.
If we eat them, we’ll get sick.
Cali yuilqumi imkut inerquutnguluteng neresqevkenaki
kanaqliit neqait. Uquutvaguanek-wa pilaqeput.
They also admonish us against eating those things muskrats eat
in the wilderness. We call them poison water hemlocks.
Tuqunaqluteng tua-i poison-aaruluteng tua-i tamakut.
Those are deadly and poisonous.
Cali tua-i tamaa-i tamakut mulngakluki
irniamteńun apertualuki assiiluciat.
We should also be wary and tell our children that they’re bad.
Cat-llu tua-i tamakut naunraat neryunarqellriit cali apertualuki.
We should also tell our children about those edible plants.
Ikiituut tuaten tamakut tamaa-i nertukput.
We also eat those wild celery.
Cuassaaryaraput-llu makut Kass’at apqaitnek spinich,
tua-i allakarmeng-am nunamek teguyarauluteng
Our greens that they call spinich in English
are gathered separately from the land
Ciilqaat tuaten tamaa-i tamakut.
Including those fireweed.
Makut-llu napat cuyait naugaararqata cali
imkut tegg’ivailgata nerluki.
And when these tree leaves are newly grown,
eat them before they harden.
Tua-i unatminek cayugluni nerluki,
tua-i egmian tamualuki nerluki imkut.
Pull them with your hand and eat them,
chew and eat them right away.
Tamakut assirluteng naugaararqameng.
Those are good when they’re newly grown.
Tua-i tamakut nertukput naunraat tamakut.
Those are the plants that we eat.
Ilait-wa tua-i nallunrilketen cat tua-i naunraat.
Nallunritlikten cat.
You probably know some of the plants.
You probably know some.
Imkut wiinga nalluanka ilait.
I don’t know some of them.
Makut tang tua-i imkut, imkut waterlily-nek pitukait
Yugtun im’ caulriit?
Those things they call waterlilies, what are they in Yup’ik again?
Wiinga-w’ au͡gna qitevtellren taringenrilkeka.
I didn’t understand what you said in English.
Imkut nauw’ cuyarpalget nanvani kuiguani-llu pugtalriit?
Those ones with big leaves floating in lakes and oxbow lakes?
Imkut-qaa? Canek ima tanem pitukait?
Those? What do they call them again?
Nallunaicaaquq-am atra.
(Nallunricaaqaqa.)
Its name is obvious.
(I do know it.)
Paparnat pilliut?
Do you mean paparnat?
Paparnat.
Yellow pond lilies.
Tua-i tang tamakut atutaciit nallukenka.
I don’t know how useful those are.
Wii-ll’ nalluanka.
I don’t know either.
Tua-i au͡gkut ava-i waten ilait umyuaqekenka qanrutkanka plant-at.
I talked about some of those plants I thought of.
Ilaqerciqan au͡gna qanellra?
Will you add to what he said?
Carrarmek ilaqaqerlaku.
(Ii-i.)
Let me add a little.
(Okay.)
Tua-i-wa ava-i makut-llu naunraat ilakekai uum
kalikam uum iluanelnguum naunraat-llu tua-i makut pillerkait.
These plants are included in those paper and what to do with plants.
Makut-llu cat tua-i anagulluki uitaarkauluki
cumerrnarqellrunritut wangkuta nallemteńi.
These things that were not excessively abundant
were not easily gathered in our time.
Caanguaruarkaq tua-i caanguaruarkaukan amllessiyaakuni
caanguaruciqngami ilii unakellemta.
Some of what we gathered would be wasted
if [we gathered] too much that would eventually be wasted.
Tau͡gaam tua-i engelqerrluta cumercetetullruitkut
tua-i egtarkaunrilngurmek nang’arkamteńek
Instead, they would have us gather according to what we needed so that we would not throw them away but finish them.
Yuilquq-wa tua-i qigcikngamegteggu yuut imkut
Because the people back then respected the wilderness
Cat-llu piyarameng nunait tua-i ava-i qanllemtun qigcikngamegteggu.
And they respected their gathering grounds as they said.
Amlleriluku ca ciptarkauluku pivakaasqessuitellruat wangkutnun.
They didn’t have us gather too much exceeding what we needed.
Tegussiyaagesqessuitellruat ciptarkauluku.
They told us not to gather more than we needed.
Tua-i-w’ alinguqelriatun piluku yuilquq yuilqurrungraan.
It was like they feared the wilderness even if it was just the wilderness.
Cat-llu nauyaraata nunaita alinguqellriatun-wa tua-i.
And it was like they feared the places where things grew.
Amllermek, amllerpagmek ciptarkamek avurcecuitellruitkut
aanamta wangkuta.
Our mothers wouldn’t let us gather a whole lot
more than we needed.
Ellait-llu-wa tua-i pitullrullilriit.
They probably also did that.
Tau͡gken-am makut ilait naunraat cali amlleriluki piaqamteki
kenirarkat, kenirluki piarkaput au͡gkut-llu quagcit wall’ angukaat
However, when we gathered a lot of some of these plants that we would
cook, the ones we would cook, sourdock or wild rhubarb
Tua-i tamakut tau͡gaam tua-i wiinga kiingita kenirluki amlleriluki
pit’laraput qemagtelaamteki kenirraarluki.
We only gathered a lot of those because we would
store them after cooking them.
Tua-i tamakut tau͡gaam tua-i wiinga kiingita kenirluki amlleriluki
pit’laraput qemagtelaamteki kenirraarluki.
However, they told us not to gather more than we needed if we weren't going to use them.
Okay, as for berries, he says much like what they had said…
Maa-i-wa elitnaurvigmi Kass’artarrlainarmek elitnaurameng,
iciw’ nalluit-gguq amlleret.
Because they’re only learning Western things in school,
you know, they don’t know a lot.
So, Eliza is saying that, you know, there was just so very much
that we can learn of our culture, the ways.
Even just the plants by themselves, if you look at that leaving
everything else, they’re really just numerous
That we can learn and our children can learn, but they’re not
learning because they’re not taught in schools.
Ilumun amlleqapiartuq nallukengarci,
elpet-llu-w’ nallukengaten aperyaraungraata.
There is truly a lot that youpl don’t know,
and things you don’t know including words.
Nallukengaci amlleqapiartut.
There is so much that youpl don’t know.
Cali-llu waniwa qanrumayaaqelriaci tamatumek.
Cali ilii cali qanrutkumanrituq cali.
And now, youpl have been talking about that.
Some of it is still not talked about.
Tamaa-i tau͡gaam taringevkarluku piaput, piukut waniwa.
But now, we are helping her understand.
Au͡gkut-llu-w’ tua-i ava-i…
And what was said just now…
Quyana.
Thank you.
Ilaput.
Our companions.
Au͡gkut nangneqliqluki piqataranka neqkaput makut plant-at.
I am going to end with those plants that we eat.
Cali avelngaat ikayularaitkut neqkamteńek ayuqenrilngurnek.
Voles also help us with different foods that we eat.
Aterpaggluki-llu pingailketen tayima ayuqenrilata atrit.
And you probably won’t say them by name
because they have different names.
Tua-i avelngaat cali nertukemteńek uksuarmi neqkarcilartut
caqussayuteng tua-i tamakut imirluki muirluki.
Voles also gather food that we eat in the fall
filling up their caches full.
Wangkuta-ll’ yuarluki tua-i nunam iluanek camaken.
And we look for them under the ground.
Tua-i tamakut cali nertukput avelngaat quyurtelarait
ayuqenrilnguut atellgutkevkenateng.
Voles also gather those various things that we eat with different names.
Un’gani-llu cali tua-i tauna coast tua-i cali tamakut avelngaat piit
ayuqenrilnguut cali nertukput quyurtetuluki ellaita.
And down on the coast, those voles also gather
different things that we eat.
Tua-i tau͡gaam wangkuta neqairluki teguigaqluki
tua-i-w’ assiata.
But we take their food from them because they’re good.
Akutaqluki atutuluki.
We use them for Yup’ik ice cream.
Tua-i nangneqliqluku au͡gna piaqa.
That’s the last thing I’m [saying].