Ii-i.
Okay.
Au͡gkut ava-i waten qalarutkellrenka amllertaluki.
This is will be all for what I’ve just spoken about.
Tau͡gaam cali nutaan uum tememta-w’ tua-i anirtuumangnaqlerkaanek maani nunam qaingani
But also, in order to try to keep our bodies safe here on this earth
Yaa, picurlanritlerkaanek cali qanqatartua.
Yes, I’m also going to speak on how it wouldn’t get into misfortune.
Waniwa mat’um nalliini
Now, these days.
Uksumi ukut waniwa ellalliurcuutet: qerrulliik, ellalliurcuun
These rainproof clothese in the winter: rainpants, raincoat
Taukut tua-i uksumi waten cataicunailnguut ayagaluni.
Those should not be absent in the winter like this when traveling.
Tua-i uum temem waniw’ assirluni
For this body to be good
Tuaggun cali maani nunam qaingani pekeskumta yuilqumi ukut tua-i waniw’ ellalliurcuutet cataicunailnguut.
Also through that, if we walk on this land, in the wilderness, these rainproof clothes shouldn’t be absent.
Uum temem assirluni pillerkaa.
It’s so that this body will be good.
Tua-i-llu pitsaqevkenani cali ellalliurcuutaunani yuilqumi arenqiallugeskuni
Then, should a person get into misfortune in the wilderness without rain gear
Ellaqerruskani tua-i wangkuta alerqutullruitkut
If the weather turns bad on them, they used to instruct us
Ayuquciiruskumta-gguq, ayuquciireskumta ayagiinarpek’nata arulaiqilta.
They said that if we get lost, we shouldn’t keep going but stop.
Wall’u pirtunguskakut nutaan-gguq waten tua-i nangrramta pikumta
Or if a blizzard hits us, they said that especially if we [have nothing but] what we’re standing in like this
Camek-wa tua-i piinata ayagakumta, aklumek kangcirarrarmek-llu piinata
If we travel without anything, and if we don’t have the supply tarpaulin
Waten alerqutullruitkut:
They used to instruct us like this:
Tua-i-gguq arenqiallugeskumta pirtunguskakut waten qanikcaq elagluku.
They said if we come to misfortune, if a blizzard his us, to dig into the snow like this.
Tua-i itqilta camek tau͡gaam cali tegumiarrarluteng.
We should go in, but they’d also hold something small.
Una-gguq waniw’ ayaruq uum temem cali anirtuumatkaqaa.
They said this walking staff would be salvation for this body.
Wall’u uksumi ayaruilkuni ca-w’ tua-i naparraq tegumiaqluku ayagakuni
Or, if [s]he has no staff in the winter, it [s]he holds on to a branch while going
Tua-i-llu pirtunguskani, ayuquciiruskuni elaulluni qanikcautelluni.
Then when a blizzard hits and [s]he is lost, [s]he should dig and have the snow cover them.
Tau͡gaam cali imkunun, kanarviknernek iciw’ aptukput ilutulriit.
But also, to those things, you know how we refer to those deep [hollows/depressions] as kanarvikneret.
Pirciqan pagna qertuluni, tua-i-llu una ilutuluni
If there’s a blizzard, and [the summit] up there is high, and this [depression] is deep
Tamaavet-gguq qanikcaucetenrilkilta.
They said we shouldn’t have the snow cover us there.
Imumun-gguq tau͡gaam waten qerkilngurmun elagluku tauna.
Instead, they said that we should dig into a low hill
Itqumta tuavet tua-i engelqayaguskumta una imna itlerput patuqerluku qanikcarmek.
When we go in when we fit in there, we should close our entrance with snow.
Tau͡gaam-gguq engelqiutevkenata.
But, they said not to get it too small.
Waten elliuraqluku qanikcaq, una-llu naparrluku pagaavet ukilluku pikna.
Do this to the snow, and set this [staff] upright to pierce [the ceiling] up there.
Tua-i qanikcauskakut pikna tau͡gaam waten elliuqaqluku.
If we get covered in snow, do this [to open it] up there.
Umcikuni-gguq qanikaam aciani epciquq yuk.
They said if a person is airtight under snow, [s]he will suffocate.
Ataucirqumek epsarpiallruukut pavani.
Once, we almost suffocated inland.
Pingayuuluta: kinguqliqa, au͡gna-llu Kuigglugmiungurtelleq, wiinga-llu.
There were three of us: my younger sibling, and that one who moved to Kwethluk, and me.
Waten ilutuuralriami pelatekarluta pillemteńi
When we set up a tent in a deep [depression]
Unugmi pirtunglliniluni waten anuqlirluku pillemteńi. Ellaqertelliniluni.
A blizzard started at night when we [set up] when it was windy like this. The weather turned bad.
Uiga’rtua epsalngupiarlua. Mak’arcaaqellrianga puukarluku man’a.
I opened my eyes and felt very suffocated. I quickly got up and hit this [ceiling].
Cunaw’ tua-i waten engillinikii qanikcaam.
Apparently, the snow was weighing down on it like this.
Pegnem tuani anellruukut, akluput-llu mecungluteng.
We got out after much struggle then, and our things were wet.
Amta-ll’ ella qakemna nengelvagluni.
And yet, the weather out there was very cold.
Qanikcaam acia waten umcigluni kiirtulliniuq epsalngunaqluni.
When it’s airtight under the snow like this, it’s evidently very hot and hard to breathe.
Qanikcaq tua-i waten urugturluku akpulut qaingit mecunglluteng inarrviput.
The snow kept melting like this and made our things, our beds, wet.
Taumek tamana waten inerqutullruitkut:
That’s why they would admonish us like this:
Ellaqerruskakut tuaten tua-i ilutulrianun uqitesqevkenata, qanikcautesqevkenata.
If the weather turns bad in us, we shouldn’t shelter in deep [depressions], shouldn’t let the snow cover us.
Tau͡gaam qerkilngurmun wall’ qanikcangraan mamkitarkamun.
Instead, [shelter] on a low hill or where it will be thin despite snowing.
Waten cali ukiarrluku pikna, tuaten tua-i arula’artaqluku.
Also, pierce [the ceiling] up there like this, and even move it back and forth.
Tuamtellu cali waten nallunrilkumteggu kingunerput tekitarkaunrilkumta
Then, if we also know that we’re not going to make it back home
Camek-gguq kapuarciluta nunam taum ciunemta tungiinun itqilta.
They said we should stick soemthing in the land toward our destination and go in.
Tua-i-gguq assirluni eruskakut
They said that if dawn comes with good weather
Imna tua-i tauna nalluvkenaku ayuquciitevkenaku ciunerput amna ullagarkauluku.
We will know and not be confused, and will go to our destination over there.
Tang tua-i man’a
This, you see
Au͡gna-w’ tua-i elpekqallerput apertuarassiyaagumanriami-w’ tua-i, wangkuta-llu apertuanriamteggu
Since noticing things is not demonstrated too much anymore, and since we don’t demonstrate it anymore
Waten nallungekput.
We’re starting not to know it like this.
Cauciirulluta mat’um nalliini.
We are ignorant these days.
Ava-i au͡gna waten amlleriuq.
That’s all for that [subject].
Tua-llu cali umyuaqelalqa
Then, what’s also been on my mind
Au͡gkut makut anglicartellemta ilaput nalluvkanritellruit
Those who raised us back then didn’t keep us from knowing our relatives
Nani nunani allani uitangraata.
Even if they’re in other villages somewhere.
Iciw’ maa-i ilu’uqniluki, angakniluki, anaanakniluki, nuliacungaqniluki
You know, these days, they’re told those people are their [male to male] cross-cousins, maternal uncles, maternal aunts, [male to female] cross-cousins
Tamakut apertuamalaryaaqut.
Those do get pointed out.
Maa-i mat’um nalliini waten cakuciirulluta pilriakut.
These days, we don’t know anything like this.
Waten avani wangkuta waten tan’gaurlullraullemteńi apertuatetullruitkut au͡gkut anglicartemta.
Back when we were little boys like this, those who raised us back then would teach us.
Waten-llu nunanek tekitaqameng, ukut ilakellriit tekitaqameng
And when they arrived from [other] villages like this, when these relatives arrived
Apertuatnauraitkut.
They would point out to us.
Wangkuta-gguq tauna-llu cakukut.
They said we and that person are related somehow.
Ilu’urqukut, wall’ usrukukut, tuaten tua-i.
We’re [male to male] cross cousins, or we’re [male to female] niece/nephew, like that.
Tamaaggun waten nalluyuqenriqertaqluki apertuamataqameng.
Through that, we’d suddenly figure out [how we’re related] when they’re pointed out.
Tau͡gken mat’um nalliini tuaten cakuciirulluta.
These days, however, we don’t know how we’re related like that.
Maaggun-llu cakuciirutlemteggun, apertuacimanritlemteggun
And through this, not knowing how we’re related, how we’re not shown [how we’re related]
Mat’um nalliini nakukutengluteng yuut.
These days, people are starting to fight each other.
Amta-ll’ waten ilakutaqluteng-llu ping’e’rmeng nallukulluteng. Inglukutengluteng mat’um nalliini.
And yet, though they’re related like this, they’ fight. They’ve started fighting these days.
Au͡gkut avani nepaitellruut yuut.
People back then were peaceful.
Tua-i nakukutellriartaunani.
There was no one fighting each other.
Au͡gna ava-i waten qanengssaka pitauq.
That’s the extent of my story of that.
Mat’um nalliini maa-i waten, yaa, ayuqsugnairutukut au͡gkucicetun ciuliamcecicetun.
These days, like this, yes, we’re no longer like our ancestors of old.
Man’a waten assiriyaaquq. Assiriyaaqukut. Assirinilaryaaqekaitkut mat’um nalliini.
Now, it’s gotten better like this. We’ve gotten better. They said we’ve gotten better these days.
Tau͡gaam assirinritukut. Wangkuta assirinritukut.
But we haven’t gotten better. We haven’t gotten better.
Au͡gkut ilakulluteng pillruut.
People back then were tight-knit.
Assiriyaaqukut nangteqenrirluta
We have gotten better without struggling for:
Kass’at makut aklirtungluta aturamteggun, ayagassuutemteggun, catgun tua-i, neqkamteggun, makutgun-llu enetgun
These Caucasians have provided us with our clothes, our vehicles, various things, our food, and our buildings
Nangteqenrirluta, nengelvagnanrirluteng unugmi, kiirpiurturangluta.
We stopped suffering, stopped being afflicted with great cold at night, started being hot all the time.
Assiriyaaqluni.
It had gotten better.
Tau͡gaam assiirulluteng, assiirulluta mat’um nalliini.
But they’ve gotten worse, we’ve gotten worse these days.
Nakukutengluteng. Tuqurqutengluteng.
They’ve started fighting each other. They’ve started killing each other.
Qaneryaram mat’um apertullra natruartevkenaku.
It went exactly as this Bible said it would.
Kitak’ waten tua-i niicugnilriani tan’gaurlurni, nasaurlurni umyuaqelarniarci au͡gna niitellerci.
Now, you boys and girls who are listening like this, remember what you just heard.
Au͡gkut anglicarteput waten ayuqellrunritut.
Those who raised us back then weren’t like this.
Aturanek amllernek enem iluani pitangqellrunrituq enait waten ayuqellrunrilameng.
There weren’t a lot of accouterments in a home because their homes weren’t like this.
Unugmi-lli qava’arqameng nengelvagmi qaltat tua-i makut mernek imalget cikumaluteng, cikuaqluki.
And when they slept at night in the extreme cold, these buckets filled with water would freeze.
Kaminiam-llu qainganlengraata, imkut saaniiget puqlanillrung’e’rmeng ilait tua-i cikumaaqluteng
And even if they were on the stove, even though those kettles had been warm, some would [end up] frozen.
Ii-i, tua-i waten... (Qaillun-mi...)
Yes, this [is it]... (So, how...)
Kitak’ apyuten, apesnga.
Now, your question, ask me.
Qaillun iciw’ auluklerkait angutet, arnat.
You know, how to take care of men, women.
Iciw’ angutet qanruyutait arnanun, iciw’ qaillun angutet iciw’ qanruyutait qaillun kassuusngalriit iciw’ auluklerkait aipateng.
You know, men’s traditional wisdom about owmen, you know, how men, you know, their traditional wisdom, how married couples, you know, take care of their spouses.
Ii-i.
Okay.
Waten maa-i kassuusngalriit, ukuk kassuutellriik
Now, married couples like this, this married couple
Agayulirtem tuaten aptelarak.
The priest asks them a question like that.
Agayutem ciuqerrani aptelarak waten:
In front of God, [s]he asks them this:
"Tua-i-qaa aipaqutarkaugutek qigcikullutek, maligtaqullutek, uivnun maligtaqulluten?
"In your marriage, will you respect each other, obey each other, obey your husband?
"Wall’u uingulriami nulirpenun maligtaqulluten."
"Or, you who is a husband, obey your wife."
Tuaten waten pimalaryaaquq tamana
That’s how this is done
Tau͡gaam waten alerquumaluta:
But we’re instructed like this:
Tua-i-gguq ukuk waten nulirqellriik waten kassuusngalutek pikunek tua-i assirlutek piyukunek
They said this married couple, if they’re married like this and want to do well
Waten maligtaquuraullutek narurtaagutevkenatek.
They must obey each other like this, not disobey each other.
Uini tua-i una murilkelluku anrutaa aklui-llu, makut-ll’ aklui.
[S]he must watch their husband, his stomach and his possessions, and his clothes.
Makut-llu cali unangkengai murilkelluki.
And [s]he must watch over [the animals] he catches.
Tuamtellu cali uingulriim cali una nuliani aulukaani
Then a husband also with his wife whom he takes care of
Enem ilua man’a arnam aulukaa, enem iluanelnguut angutem unangkengaa.
A woman takes care of the inside of a home, the things in the home that the man caught.
Tau͡gken cali uingulriim cali qagna ella enem elatii
However, a husband also [works] out there, outside the house
Wall’u yuil[qumi], tamaa-i tamana caliarkaa.
Or [in] the wilderness, that’s his responsibility.
Nuliaminun aulukutekai cali murilkelluki.
He must also watch over what he needs to take care of for his wife.
Mer’et maa-i makut enem iluani aulukutnguut arnamun.
Water inside the house is a way to take care of a woman.
Tua-i-llu cali tamana pingraan waten, waten-wa tua-i maligtaquuraullutek inglukutaagutevkenatek.
Then even if it’s like that, they must obey each other without being at odds with each other.
Waten inerquumauk assirlutek piyukunek:
They’re admonished like this if they want to do well:
Kenkuterrlainayuitut aipaqutellriit.
Couples don’t always treat each other with love.
Waten tau͡gaam...
But like this...
Qaillun ima tanem pilaqait?
What do they tell them again?
Inglukutaagutevkenatek-wa tua-i pillerkaak.
They shouldn’t be at odds with each other.
Aipaan camek-wa tua-i qanruskani umyugaan pekyutkaanek
If one’s spouse tells them something to make them upset
Uingulria-gguq tauna tuaten nulirran qanrutengraani
They said that for a husband, even if his wife says something to him like that
Imna umyuami-w’ tua-i navgutkengraaku ayuqelivkenaku pikuni
Even if it destroys his mindset, if he doesn’t do the same
Tua-i nulirra tauna ingluilkuni camek taqciquq.
If his wife has no opposition, she will stop things.
Tuamtellu cali angutiin arnaq cali
Then [if] the man [does the same] to the woman
Umyuani-w’ tua-i kenkevkenaku wall’ ayuqucianek pikuni
If he’s not in a loving mindset or talks about her behavior
Tauna-gguq taringecurlagpek’nani cali arnaq tuaten pikili, inglulitevkenani.
They said the woman shouldn’t misunderstand like that, and not make herself an opponent.
Ingluliurulluteng cat quyungqasciigatut.
People in any relationship who are at odds cannoy stay together.
Wall’u anelgutkellriit inglukeg[sigg]luteng ayuqevkenateng pikuneng quyungqasciigatut.
Or if siblings do not interact with each other well, they cannot stay together.
Tua-i-llu ukuk nulirqellriik tuaten tua-i ayuqekunek inglukuugullutek pikunek assirlutek pingaituk.
Then if this married couple is like that, if they are at odds with other, they won’t do well.
Nutaan-llu mikelngurmek alairikunek
And especially when they bring forth a child
Tua-i-gguq taum nutaan inerquutqapiarqellruyaaqaput tamana.
They said with that, that was something we were especially strongly admonished with.
Umyuarput assiitaarluku wangkutnun pisqevkenata mikelngungkumta.
They told us not to have them come to us when we upset if we have children.
Mikelnguut-gguq makut waten nallutaitut.
They said that these children are not ignorant like this.
Au͡gkut waten ayuqellrunritut-llu tangvallrenka.
And the ones I watched back then weren’t like this.
Iciw’ tua-i imkuvkenateng, takumteńi camek umyuarteng kiutaagucuunateng.
You know, they didn’t, you know, they wouldn’t argue about their thoughts in our presence.
Tau͡gken mat’um na[lliini] qaill’ maa-i ellirtat?
These days, however, what did they become?
Tua-i yugyangraan-llu ukuk nulirqellriik piyukunek assiilngurmek eqtaagullutek qan’ataagutarkaulutek.
And even if there’s a lot of people, if this married couple wants to speak badly, they will angrily argue.
Maa-i mat’um nalliini navguutngussiyaalria nallunritarput.
These days, we know what causes too much destruction.
Una waniw’ mat’um nalliini atuqengaat man’a, man’a, man’a-w’ tua-i taangaq nulirqellriik navguuteksiyaagaak.
This, what they’re abusing these days, alcohol is what destroys a married couple.
Yugyang’e’rmeng-llu amlleng’e’rmeng tamatumek atungaqameng tua-i avvutaqluteng.
And even if there’s a lot of people, when they start abusing that, they divorce.
Navguutqapiarauluni.
It’s a source of great destruction.
Amta-ll’ makut qanrutestemta makut-llu aipaimta caliaqsaaqluku.
And yet, our instructors here and our [Caucasian] counterparts are working on it.
Ellaita pikngamegteggu tau͡gaam tua-i caliaqsaaqluku.
Since it’s what they [brought], they’re working on it.
Nangyutkaat mat’um nalliini man’a, man’a-w’ tua-i taangaq.
These days, this alcohol torments them.
Au͡gkut avani waten, waten pillrunritut ava-i qanengssakekenka.
People back then didn’t do this, the ones I just talked about.
Nuliameggnek tuquciyuunateng. Irniameggnek yagirayuunateng.
They never killed their wives. They never raised their hands against their children.
Mat’um nalliini tua-i navguutqapiarauluni nulirqellrianun.
These days, it’s the cause of destruction for married couples.
Ava-i apeskevnga qaillun nulirqellriik ayuqerkauciagnek.
You just asked me what a married couple must be like.
Assirlutek yuugarkauguk camek tua-i piksailkunek.
They will live well if they don’t [abuse] anything.
Utumalutek yuugarkauguk man’a inerquun taangaq atunrilkunegnegu.
They will live better if they don’t abuse this alcohol that’s admonished against.
Yaa, tua-i au͡g’umek...
Yes, what I just said...