Naamikik’. Cameng kangilirluku tauna pikumteggu.
I don’t know. We should explain the meaning behind that.
Kangia tauna wii kangingumanritaqa tau͡gatnatullrunrilama.
I don’t know the meaning behind that because I’ve never done that.
Tauna wangkutni Kiatiirmiuni maani tuatnatuukut-llu.
We from the upper Nushagak River also do that.
Makunek alingnarqellrianek pitaqamta qavani
When we catch these dangerous animals upriver
Taqukanek-llu tan’gerlinek-llu, tamakunek pit’eqerraaraqamta
When we first catch bears, black bears, those things
Imna auganek pitamta taum alingnarqellriim qanra aitarrluku
The blood of that dangerous animal we caught, we open its mouth
Nuaganek kautetuukut tegulluta.
We reach in and take its saliva.
Nutaan-ll’ unatemteńun pirraarluku kegginamteńun minguulluku.
And then after putting it on our hands, we apply it to our faces.
Tua-i-gguq tamatum pitarkam tangerqunikut
They say that when that bear sees us
Tamaaggun ellait[nguluta] yuuluta ellmegcecicetun tangerqunegtekut
When they see us living as themselves through that [saliva]
Ullagluta tua-i piarkauvkenata waten pitangyuutekluta.
They will will not come to us and attack us like this.
Tamatumek takaryuuterluteng ellaita nuameggnek
minguutellemteńun kegginamteńun.
They respect [and acknowledge] their saliva that we applied on our faces.
Au͡g’utun ayuquq.
That’s what it’s like.
Tua-i tuacetun pilarait alikluku piarkauvkenateng.
They do that and should not be afraid of it.
Okay, we asked the original question about
the ritual of getting the first seal.
Akaurtuq pinanrii[cata] makuneng agayulirteńeng makuneng pingata.
It’s been a long time since they’ve stopped doing that
since they’ve turned to these priests.
Maa-i akaurtuq pinanrillrat.
It’s been a long time since they’ve stopped.
Wanigga kangia kangirqelluku,
Explaining the meaning behind it,
Kangia tauna ayagningellran tau͡gatnayaurtellrata kenglii
wanigg’ nalqigutekqataraqa, qanrutkeqataraqa.
I am going to explain, talk about the reason
that they have started doing that.
Ak’a-gguq au͡gani piyuitellruyaaqut, tau͡gatnayuitellruyaaqut.
They say that a long time ago, people didn’t do that.
Tau͡gaam taum mikelnguum atiin taum nakacugnun ayautesqellran
But that child whose father sent him away in those bladders
Ayautellrata taum, ayaucitellrata al’rrakurrluni uitaluni tamaani.
When they sent him, he stayed there for a year.
Unguvalriit tamakut seal-at makliit ilagarluki uitallermini tau͡gani
When he was there with the living creatures, the seals
Tekicami utercami al’rrakuan tau͡gaam keyian tauna ayallni nallairngan
When he returned only after [the year] of his stay had passed
Tamatumeng tau͡gatnayaurcitellrullinii taum mikelnguum.
That child had them start doing that.
Tau͡gaten mermeng piyaurcitellrullinii tamakut seal-at.
He had them start giving water to those seals [they had caught].
Taum tau͡ga tauna kengelkelluku piyaurtelliniit.
During his time, they had started doing that [to seals].
Taum mikelnguullermini ayallrem tamakunun
unguvalriit nuniitnun ayagviatnun amavet kengllilluni
When he was a child, he had gone where those living creatures go
over there, staying with them
Uterrluni-llu keyian al’rrakuni, al’rrakuq naangan.
And he only returned after a year, when a year had passed.
Ayallni tauna nallairngan tau͡gaam tekitellrulliniuq. Tauna.
He only came [back] when his trip had passed. That [child].
Taum tau͡ga piyaurcitellrullinii.
He had them start [giving water] to [seals].
Tamakut seal-at pitaqaqamegteki nakacuit egcuunaki qerrutullruit.
When people catch those seals, they don’t discard their bladders
but inflate them.
Taukut imkut seal-at tamalkuita nakacuit qerrurluki
kiagpak-llu qemangqaluki.
They inflated every bladder from those seals and kept them all summer.
Uksuaran, uksuaran-llu nutaan qagerqelluki
And when fall came, they deflated them
Cikum acianun [?] tayima atertelluki.
Sending them with the current under the ice.
Tua-i-ll’ tuatnatullruit tamakut seal-at pitaqaqamegteki nakacuit.
And so, they would do that to the bladder of the seals they had caught.
Tua-i anernara tauna tuantelalliuq.
I think its spirit is there.
Nakacuan iluancukluku pilarngatait.
It seems they think it’s inside its bladder.
Taum-gguq tua-i tai[?] allamiaku.
They say that [the seal] returns the next year.
Tuaten qantuluteng pitullruut tamakut.
That’s what those people used to say.
Taukut tua-i pitaqetukai-gguq tua-i tauna nakacugaq tau͡gaam
pitaqestektuminun utertetunia pitaqe[tuminun].
They say that the ones who had caught those bladders,
they return to the ones who caught them.
Tamatumek-am tuaten pinguarcelluku pitullrulliniit.
They apparently thought that that's what they did.
Ataam taisqumaluki nakacuit-llu ayagtelluki Nakaciuraqameng.
They would ask them to come again when they sent off the bladders
during the Bladder Festival.
Qanrutekluku tauna-gguq tua-i…
They say that that…
Wanikuarqu. Una mumigterraarnauqa.
Later. Let me translate this first.
Kurt Bell…
…angalkum taukuk nulirqelriik yuak.
…the shaman [send] the child of that couple.
Tua-i unguvayuunatek taukuk nulirqelriik yuk’ek ciungani.
Tuquurluteng.
In the past, that couple’s children wouldn’t stay alive.
They kept dying.
Tua-i-llam tauna tua-i iliit irniara nutaan
And then, one of their children.
Taum angalkum tuaten piyugluku taukuk yuak
nakacugnun ilaulluku ayagcecugluku.
That shaman wanted to do that to their2 child,
include him with the bladders being sent.
Tua-i taum angalkum tuaten pivkarluku
That shaman had hit to do that.
Tamakunun unguvalriit nuniitnun.
Send him to the land of those living creatures.
Enenguluku tau͡gaam tauna unguvalriit nuniit tangerrluku elliin
He, however, saw the land of those living creatures as a house.
Tua-i tekicami makut seal-at nuniitnun uksurpak.
When he arrived at the land of these seals in the winter.
Ilaita-gguq-am tua-i nakukaqluku tauna,
tauna ayagcetaulria nakacugteggun.
They said that some of them picked on him,
the one who was sent with the bladders.
Tamakut seal-at issurit-llu tua-i ayuqevkenateng tuani.
Those seals and spotted seals were different there.
Ilaita-gguq-am tau͡gken kenkurluku piaqluku tua-i tauna.
Yet, they said that some of them treated him with love.
Tua-i-gguq tamaani nutaan utertellmi kinguani pissuryaurcami
They said that when he started hunting after he returned
Elitaq’larai tamakut issurit wall’u nayiit.
He would recognize those spotted or ringed seals.
Tua-i elitaqluki yugcetun wangkucicetun.
He recognized them like us people.
Tua-i-gguq tamakut pissungellermini tamaani elitaq’laamiki
They said that when he started hunting then, because he recognized them
Pitpalarai cakneq tukniaqluni tua-i.
He would strongly shoot them with arrows.
Pitgarluki-w’ tua-i, narulkarluki-ll’ call’ cakneq tua-i elitaq’laamiki.
He shot them with arrows and harpooned them hard
because he recognized them.
Tua-i-am tuaten taman’ ayuquq.
That's what that's like.
He expanded on that thing about boy going out to the seals.
There was a man and a wife whose children would not live.
They kept dying and dying [?]
And so, this one child [?]
[?] that child with a bladder out to the sea.
And so, that’s what he did.
And, and then that boy…
…tau͡gatnaluni ayallrulliniuq tamaavet tungiitnun tau͡gatnayarturluki.
…he traveled there like that to them to do that to them.
Okay, he…
…caknerpak pivkenateng.
…they didn’t do it very excessively.
Tau͡gaam tayim’ makut nallukeci tua-i-am tuaten pitulit.
But you probably don’t know those that do that.
Tarringaqa.
(Ii-i).
I understand it.
(I see).
What he’s saying is that those people that were,
Whats he's saying is that those people that were,
Or, those seals that he recognized that were good to him,
He made sure that he made a good clean kill.
You know, really made sure that he did that.
It seems like this was a really important ceremony to go through.
Ciin-gguq Kass’at tekiqercilluki tau͡gaten pinanrillruat?
Why did they stop doing that after Caucasians arrived?
Imkut agayulirtetangan pinanrirluki tuaten.
(Ii-i).
When the priests appeared, they stopped doing that.
(Yes).
Agayulirteńeng makuneng tau͡gaam pingan
Only when these priests appeared
Tamana tamaa-i makuneng agayulirteńeng pitangengan
Because these priests appeared
Tamana tau͡gatnayaraq pegtelqaat aturnanrirluku.
They forsook that and stopped doing it.
Ii-i. Waten-qaa? Ukuk naliagneng?
I see. Like this? Which of these2?
Kayngukluku wall’u-qaa taqesqelqaaci?
Were they ashamed of it or did they tell youpl to stop?
Taqesqenrilengraiciteng tau͡ga tamana tamaa-i aturnanrillruat.
Though they weren’t told to stop, they stopped doing that.
Camun tamana aturyararteng tamatum seal-amun
Their practice with a seal
Atutukseng tamana aturnanrillruat.
They stopped adhering to their practice.
I’ll do one, and I hear something different over there.
But Kurt Bell says that after the missionaries came,
they stopped on their own.
Qanqeryugngaunga-qaa?
May I say something?
Ii-i.
(Ii-i).
Yes.
(Okay).
Au͡g’umi wani, yaa, kegginaanun taqukat,
black bear-at wall’u brown bear-at
In what they said, yes, to the bear’s faces,
black bears or brown bears
Qanra wani, maa-i qanranek piluteng kegginaa pitullinikiit.
It’s mouth, they take [saliva] from its mouth and apply it to its face.
Wiinga tan’gaurluulua…
When I was a boy…
Kituuyit?
(Edward Weiss).
Who are you?
Waten pillruatnga au͡g’um ap’ama:
My grandfather used to tell me this:
Tan’gerliq tuqulluku nutgaarluku
After shooting and killing a black bear
Tua-i-ll’ tuaten, waten qamaken nuaganek kegginaqa mingugtelluku
unatenka-llu.
And then like that, I should get saliva from inside [its mouth]
and appy it to my face and my hands.
Tua-i-ll’ waten qanrullua: anglikuma-gguq pissuryaureskuma
And then said this to me: when I grow up and start hunting
Pitsaqevkenii-gguq tan’gerlim wall’u tamakut brown bear-am
akngirrluni tegukunia
Should an injured black bear or those brown bears take me
Kegginaqa-gguq tangerciqaa nuaminek pimaluni.
It will see my face with its saliva on it.
Taumek-gguq aneryaarvikngaitaanga.
He said that that’s why it won’t breathe on me.
Aneryaallrit, nuagit black bear-at tukniqapiartut nuagit yugnun.
Their breath, black bear saliva is extremely potent on people.
Taumek waten aneryaarvikluku tuqutelallinikait kegginait puvvluki.
That’s why they evidently kill people by breathing on them like this
and making their faces swell.
Tuaten-gguq pingaitaanga.
He said that it won’t do that to me.
Tua-i-llu kinguani qaillun tayim’ allrakunglua, 25-aarlua
And then after that when I had reached a certain age, 25
Nutecurlagluku tan’gerlim tegullruyaaqaanga, nutka teguluku waten.
I missed a killing shot on a brown bear and it took me,
took my gun like this.
Tau͡gaam kegginamnun aneryaallrunrituq,
tau͡gaam waten ulurlua aneryaaraqluni.
However, it didn’t breathe on my face, but turned like this and breathed.
Tamaa-i tamana alerquutektulliniat, maa-i-llu cali.
That’s what they instructed, even now.
Ava[?]
Just now [?]
Okay, that’s [?] why from up the Kuskokwim.
He said when his grandfather…
Elliin tangrruallrani elpeci older men
As [s]he imagines you older men
Umyuarteqtullrulliniuci respect-arluki qigcikluki pitarkat.
You apparently respect, qigcikluki, animals that we hunt.
Maa-i-rpak-gguq-qaa umyuarteqlerpecini
[S]he said that now, in your opinions
Makut kinguliaci tau͡gaten,
tau͡gaten-gguq-qaa ayuqluteng piut elpecicetun?
Do yourpl descendants do that as youpl are?
Wall’u-gguq-qaa pinritut?
Or are they not doing that?
Pinrilkata-gguq waten umyuartequci pitarkat nangnayukluki?
If they’re not, [s]he’s asking if youpl think that the animals we hunt
will decline.
Wanigga wii…
Now, I…
…cuaqaqataraqa apyutii.
…I am going to briefly [leave] her question.
Makut seal-at makut un’um imarpiim pitarkai
nangllerkaitneng umyugartuyuitua
I am not worried about the depletion of these seals,
the animals down from the ocean that we hunt
Makuneng tau͡gaam tengmiat makut piyagait, kayanguit.
But these chicks, eggs, of these birds.
Makut yug’enka wii irnianka inerqutuanka waten
irniarita tukellrata nalliini:
I admonish my children, my offspring when their chicks hatch:
Angu nutegyasqevkenaku, tamakut-llu piyagauluki pisqevkenaki
mikelnguuluki.
Do not hunt when they are chicks, when they are young.
Tau͡gaam piyaaqengraan, kayimyaaqengraan
tamakut aanait waten carraugaqata irniarit
But even when they hatch, their mothers,
when their chicks are small and young like this
Inerqutuanka tau͡ga wii pisqevkenaki.
I admonish them against hunting them.
Tamakut mikelnguut wii-ll’ irnianka tamakut tau͡gaten ayuqsugnarqut
tengmiatun piyagartun.
Those young and my children are probably like those chicks.
Tamakut pitekluki inerqutuanka
That’s why I admonish them
Irniaqenrilengramki tamakut kayanguit tengmiat piyagait tukraqata.
Even though the [chicks] when the birds’ eggs hatch are not my children.
Angturriqvaaraqata-llu kia yuum malingcarluku ayauskaku,
ayauteqatallinikaku
And when they’re getting larger, if someone takes them away to tame them,
is apparently going to take them away
Inerqurciqaqa angu aanii aanak ukuk qaqillukek angu pisqevkenaku.
I will admonish him against killing them all,
including the mother [and father].
Tuqutesqevkenakek aanak taukuk aulukestairuciqniluki taukut irniari.
I tell them not to kill the mother [and father]
saying that their chicks will have no one to take care of them anymore.
Tapirviitniluki makut naruyat.
I tell them that these seagulls cannot be taken care of by anything else.
Naklegnaqniluki tamakut mikelnguuniluki
aanaituraluki tamana aulukestaraunaki pillerkait.
I tell them that they are young and pitiful
should they lose their mothers, their caretakers.
Taumeng tang inerqutuanka.
I admonish them about that.
But he tells his children about the birds that,
when birds have this, you know, when the eggs start hatching
And the mothers [?]
Tua-llu cakananinrituq.
And then it’s no different.
Wangkuta pissulallruukut, tua-i-llu aanamta pitarput kencikluku.
We used to hunt, and then our mothers would rever our catch.
Quyakluku cakneq.
They were very thankful for it.
Tua-llu maa-i wangkuta aataurtellriani,
taum-llu tua-i aanaulriim nallunritai qetunrangqerrami
And now, we who have become fathers,
and she who is a mother knows them because she has sons
Qetunrani qangqiirtaqan cakneq quyakluku ciuniularai.
When her son catches ptarmigans,
she is very thankful for them and welcomes them.
Tua-i ikgelkevkenaku.
She doesn’t think it’s too little.
Pitai tamalkuita quyakluki kencikluki-llu.
She is thankful for and reveres all of his catches.
Sagcetevkenaki [?]mun-llu pisqevkenaki avaken inerquutekngamteńek.
Tua-i.
She doesn’t leave them scattered or doesn’t let them go to the [?]
as we were always admonished. That’s all.
Ernerpak maa-i-rpak…
Now, these days…
…wiinga tamana nalluaqa.
…I don’t know that.
Wangkuta tang aanaulriani ayagyua[?] qanrutestailngukut.
We mothers, you see, [who are] young[er than you]
have no one to instruct us.
Atawauyartuq-qaa makut maani qanerceskuvciki KYUK news
Would it be well if you had them instruct here on the KYUK news?
Or, time-amek cikiqerluki ayuqucirturluta wangkuta.
Or, give them time to instruct us.
Yuungnaqellriit amllertut irniaput. Nalluukut.
We have many children who are trying to make a living. We don’t know.
Wiinga-llu irnianka nalluvkaranka.
I am also leaving my children in the dark.
Tua-i-wa niicuilama akaurcan aanairuyuciqa.
It’s because I’ve never heard them since I lost my mother so long ago.
Ak’allaraat makut wiinga qalartellrit assikanka. Piciugut.
I like when these old people speak. They are true.
Maa-i cali piuyaaqut, tau͡gaam tamartut.
It’s still [practiced] now, but it’s disappearing.
Kass’at elitnaurutet pugelriit iptait.
The Western teachings that have appeared are eclipsing them.
Atawauyartuq time-amek Kass’amta cikiqaqakut.
It would be well if our Caucasian partners gave us time.
KYUK radio wall’u news-atgun ciulirneq qanqaquni
elitnaurluki irniaput ikayurciqaakut.
If an elder speaks on KYUK radio or on the news,
teaching our children, [s]he will help us.
Time-amek cikircetkatki quyanaqsartut amllerkun elicartuq.
We would be thankful if they gave them time, and they would learn a lot.
Quyana Larissa.
Thank you, Larissa.
Alerqutuitkut-am pissuqataqumta tan’gerlit…
When we’re going to hunt, they instruct us concerning black bears…
Muragmek ayarurkamteńek pisqelluta.
They tell us to make a walking staff out of wood.
…tua-i-w’ ayaruq uksuarmi-w’ atuulria tua-i
mamkilngurmun cikum wall’u aarnarqellrianun.
…a walking stick is useful in the fall for thin ice or dangerous things.
Tauna-am avani qau͡gkumiuni alerquutnguuq.
That was an instruction back then for the people up north.
Ingrinun canegnun pissuqataqumta wall’u ayagakumta
When we’re going to hunt in the mountains, in the grass,
or when we travel
Ayaruq tauna tegumiaquraasqelluku.
They told us to keep holding that walking staff.
Tua-i-llam ayagpakarluta tan’gerlim curukarciqliniakut.
And as we travel, a black bear will eventually attack us.
Tua-i-gguq makut tan’gerlit yugtun ayuqut.
They say that these black bears are like people.
Unatemegteggun waten tegutuut.
They take things with their forepaws like this.
Egmian-gguq wani nutegput teguvailgaku ayarumek cikiqilarput.
They say that before it takes our gun, we should immediate give it a staff.
Tua-i-gguq taum anirturciqaakut.
They said that that will save us.
Nutaan cikirluku teguqerarkauluku tayim’ wangkuta nutgarkauluku.
We give it, it will take it, and we will shoot it.
Imumi tamaani.
That was a long time ago.
…angalkungqellruukut, angalkungqelallrulliniukut.
…we had shamans, we apparently had shamans
Tamakut tamaani piciruitnek wangkuta ap’laraput.
We call those superstitions.
Yaa, piciruitniluki, tua-i angalkurtauluni.
Yes, we say they are superstitious, originating from shamans.
Wait, wii tarringenritaqa tauna. Piciruiq?
Wait, I don’t understand that. Piciruiq?
Iciw’ tua-i piciuvkenani angalkurtauluni tamana.
You know, that’s not real and originates from shamans.
Angalkuq tuunrangayagtauluni wangkuta apqemteńek.
We say that shamans are of the devil.
Tamakut tamaa-i ukvengamta mat’umun Agayutmun
When we acquired faith in God
Tamakut tamaa-i amlleret iinrut-llu pegingaut tayima.
Many of those and traditional medicines are forsaken.
Pegingaurtut.
They’re forsaken.
Tua-llu maa-i nunamteńi unani ceńarmiuni
And now in our village down among the coastal people
Man’a maklagcaraq pegcuitarput.
We haven’t forsaken the practice [surrounding] catching seals.
Maa-i ayagyuarunrilengraan-llu allrakuaqan up’nerkami
pitqerraarqan maklagmek, cali allragni pitellruluni
When this person, even if he’s not young, catches the first seal
in the spring, having also caught one the previous year
Ciuqlirmek angun pitqerraarturarqan qamigatuli
When the first one who goes seal hunting catches the first [seal]
Maa-i apqemteńek uqiqurrlainalartuq maklagmek taumek.
They always distrubute that seal, uqiqurluni as we call it.
Maklak tua-i ciuqliq pitaa yugnun tamalkuan aruqutketuuq
kemggartuumaan.
Every part of the first seal that he catches is distributed to everyone
including what meat it has.
Tua-i ciuqliq tua-i ayagyuarunrilengraan.
The first [catch], even if he's not young.
Allamineq tamak’acagaan maa-i cali pegteksaunaku man’a tekilluku.
Every single year, we still haven’t forsaken that to this day.
Tauna tua-i maklak taguskatgu itumlluku tamalkuan aruqutkaqluku
kemggartuumaan.
When they bring that seal on land and [butcher] it into pieces,
they distribute all of it, including what meat it has.
Tuaten tua-i wagg’uq uqiqurluteng.
That’s what they call uqiqurluteng.
Au͡gna tua-i pitangyu[?], wangkuta-ll’ [?]
That [?first] catch, we also [?]
Tuaten tua-i pituuq. Maa-i pegteksaituq.
That's what happens. We haven't forsaken it.
Maa-i-am atam nunamteńi tuatna[?].
You see, [we do] that in our village.
Una tua-i ciuqlirmek maklageskan
tua-i ellait neryuniurluteng nunat arnat.
When this person catches the first seal,
the women of the village wait eagerly.
Tauna-llu kemga kiingan pivkenaku.
And not only its meat.
Uqua canek tau͡gaam tapirluku.
They include other things to its blubber.
[?]
Lumarrarnek-llu tua-i.
And pieces of cloth.
Tauna kiirrainaan pivkenaku, tua-i Kass’allararnek tapirluku [?].
They don’t give it by itself, but add Western things to it [?].
Okay, he’s also responding to your earlier question
if those rituals are still…
For him, this, Phillip Moses from Toksook Bay said
They still do the first seal, not only the first young man seal,
but the first maklak of the season.
but the first beaded seal of the season.
What they still do is, they still, the women look forward to this.
They cut the maklak up into blubber and meat
They cut the bearded seal up into blubber and meat
And then they call the whole village to come
for the share of the whole thing.
So, they don’t keep it for themselves.
What they do is they give it away to everybody else in the village.
And not just the pieces of the seal,
But they also today include, like, things they buy from the store:
Pieces of cloth, or crackers, or whatever, you know, whatever…
Ca-gguq imna pitekluku tamana maklak cikiutektuatgu ilameggnun?
She asked the reason behind giving that bearded seal to the others.
Tua-i waten piciryaraqluku waten:
This is their tradition:
Kina imna ciuqlirmi waten up’nerkami piaqami neryutuuq
tamakunek maklagnek.
When the first one catches a seal in the spring like this,
he wants to eat those bearded seals.
Tamana pitekluku neryutullrat
Because they want to eat
Avani-w’ pitekluki pituameng waten uksumi
tamakunek maklagnek piyuitut.
Back then, since they did it for them, they don’t [eat] bearded seals
in the winter like this.
Tamana meaning-aangqertuq apyutii kenkuyutnguluni.
The meaning behind what she asked is showing love for each other.
Kenkuyun tua-i meaning-aara tauna. Yaa.
Its meaning is love for each other. Yes.
Yaa, tauna. Tamakuuguq. Kenkauguq.
Yes, that. That’s what it is. It’s love.
Okay, you asked for the reason for this sharing, you know?
He said, Phillip Moses said…
…kencikiyaramek waniwa 10-12 caliarkaullruukut.
…we were going to work on showing reverence from 10-12.
Waniwa tua-i wii qanqaqatartua carrarmek 12 kelakatallinian.
I’m going to talk a little since it’s nearing 12 o’clock.