Iciw’ maa-i irniat ilait cayunqeggiatetuut, ilait-llu cayunqeggluteng.
You know, some of these children don’t like doing things, and some do.
Ila-i.
Oh my goodness.
Wiinga tau͡gaam [?] pikuma-wa.
I should be on [?].
Yaa. (Good.) Ii-i.
Yes. (Good.) Yes.
Atam-qaa aptelarniarpenga?
Will you ask me questions?
Yaa.
Yes.
Qanqall’eryugngaunga-llu Kass’atun elitnaulqa carraungraan Kass’ani uitalallruama.
I can also speak some English even though I didn’t go to school for long since I used to stay with Caucasians.
Nani Kass’ani?
Where with Caucasians?
Cakayiinkuni, John Samuelson.
With Cakayak and family, John Samuelson.
Qanrutkeciqaqa.
I’ll talk about it.
Kass’at Nunapicuarni. (Taukuni-qaa anglillruuten?)
The Caucasians in Nunapitchuk. (Did you grow up with them?)
Nuu, part, iliini tau͡gaam.
No, part[ly], only sometimes.
Nani? Nunapicuarmi-qaa Samuelson-aankut?
Where? Was the Samuelson family at Nunapitchuk?
Yaa, uitatullruut.
Yes, they lived there.
Nunacuarmek move-arluteng Nunapicuarmun. Tuani Cakayak kiputellruuq.
They moved from Nunacuar to Nunapitchuk. There, Cakayak traded.
Tauna-qaa kiputeqarraarluku?
After he bought that?
Kiputesteńgullruuq cakenpak.
He was a prolific trader.
Apqiitnek-llu kupcaari amllepiarluteng.
And he had very many of what they called his merchants.
Tuani tua-i kipusvingqellruuq Nunapicuarmi.
He had a trading post there in Nunapitchuk.
Nunacuarmiut ancatni. Ancitullruut nunat.
[That was] when Nunacuarmiut exiled him. Villages used to exile people.
Nunapicuarnun-llu piluni.
And he went to Nunapitchuk.
Iciw’ ancituut. Ancitullilriit-wa cali maa-i, Kass’at apqiitnek kick out-arluki.
You know, they exiled people. They probably still exile now, kicking them out as they say in English.
Tuaten pimallruuq Cakayak Nunacuarmek Nunapicuarmun.
That’s what happened to Cakayak from Nunacuar to Nunapitchuk.
Maa-i-w’ allaullilria. Imumi-w’ tua-i tuaten.
It’s probably different now. It was like that back then.
Ciin-gguq antellruatgu?
Why did they exile him?
Picingssaungan-wa amllernek irniiriang anteskiit.
They exiled him because he would fool around and had many children.
Tamana qanrutek’laaggu.
Speak briefly on that.
Qanrutekngaitaqa.
I won’t talk about it.
Assirtuq Cakayak.
Cakayak was good.
Ilumun irnillruuq amllernek, irniirillruuq amllernek.
Indeed, he bore many children, he sired many children.
Taumek aneskiit.
That’s why they exiled him.
Assilriit yuut nunat ancuitait.
Villages don’t exile good people.
Tau͡gaam when they do something wrong.
Only when they do something wrong.
Kitak’ ak’a nasaurluullraullerpenek tamaaken umyuaqellerpetun qanrutkeqerru.
Now, please speak about things you remember back when you were a little girl as you remember it.
Tua-i-w’ ava-i qanelrianga avani Nelson Island-aami yuurtellruyaaqua, tau͡gaam nani yuurtelqa waniw’ nalluamku.
I just said that I was born over on Nelson Island, but I don’t know [exactly] where I was born.
Tua-i-llu waten ayalalliniameng iciw’ move-arluteng, nunalinqiggluteng
Then because they travel like this, you know, move, nunalinqiggluteng
Angayuqaagka-am taukuk taillinilutek maavet Kusquqvagmun.
My parents apparently came here to the Kuskokwim.
Qaill’ piamek piak.
I’m not sure why they did.
Tua-i-ll’ Oscarville-ami Kuiggayagarmi anngarput Cakayiim atallran Oscar Samuelson-aam pistekluku.
Then in Oscarville, Kuiggayagaq, our older brother was Cakayak’s late father’s, Oscar Samuelson, helper.
Aanaput-llu neqlisteńguluni taumi Oscar Samuelson, Cakayiim atallrani.
And our mother would work on fish there with Oscar Samuelson, Cakayak’s late father.
Tua-i-ll’ tuanlluta kiagpak. Uksuaran-llu Akulmun tagluta Kassiglumun.
Then we were there all summer. And when fall set, we went up to Kasigluk in the Akula region.
Tuanlluta tua-i. Tua-i tang tua-i tuani Kassigluni how many years-kiq uitallruceta?
We were there. You see, I wonder how many years we stayed there in Kasigluk?
Imkut yuut caceskitellrulliniameng, tua-i-am elitnaullerkarput pitekluku angayuqaagka imkuk... caceskit’urlulliniut imkut yuut.
Because people were apparently fickle, for our eduction, my parents... those poor people were apparently fickle.
Nunapicuarmun-am move-aqilta, cunaw’ elitnauristengqataata. Egmian elitnaurvingellrunritut.
We moved to Nunapitchuk, it turned out because they were going to get a teacher. They didn’t get a school right away.
Qaillun tamaani wani elpeci angayuqaci elitnauq umyuaqekutelallruatgu?
Back then, what did your parents think of going to school?
Cingumallruiceci-qaa elpeci irniamteńi Kass’atun elitnauresqelluci?
Did they support their children having a Western education?
Qaillun niitelallerpenek tamana cali qanrutkeqerru.
Please talk about what you heard about that.
Qaillun niitelalqa nalluaqa.
I don’t know what I heard.
Tua-i taukuk angayuqaagka cingumalliamegtekut elitnaullerkamteńun Nunapicuarmun move-autellruitkut Kassiglumek.
Because my parents probably supported our education, they moved us from Nunapitchuk to Kasigluk.
Nanvarnarrlagmi-ll’ cali nunartangqellruut Nunapicuarmiut avalirneratni.
There was also a village in Nanvarnarrlak over from Nunapitchuk.
Tua-i-llu elitnau... nuu, elitnaurvingellratni taukut move-allruut Nunapicuarmun.
Then the school... no, when a school was built, they moved to Nunapitchuk.
Tuani ima tang wangkuta move-aqainallemteńi elitnauristet enemetellrulriit. Elitnaurvigtaunani.
Just when we moved there, the teachers were in houses. There was no school.
Agayuvillermi-ll’ pia-i agayuvigmi elitnauraqluta. Kianlluni kiaqlimteńi.
And we’d have school in the old church inland. It was upriver, upriver from us.
Tau͡gaam how many years-kiq? Tuar tang two years agayuvigmi elitnaulriakut wall’u-qaa one year.
But I wonder how many years? It seems that we went to school in the church for two years or one year.
Tua-i-llu pia-i old school-aq tauna tang piurtellrani Number Two-rmiut pia-i Nanvarnarrlagmiut move-allrungatellinilriit Nunapicuarmun.
Then when that old school inland was built, the ones in Number Two from Nanvarnarrlak inland moved to Nunapitchuk.
Nunarpallrauluteng, Number One, Number Two, tuaten-llu aterluteng.
It was a big village, Number One, Number Two, and they had those names.
Cingumalliamegteki-w’ move-alriit-llu taukut nunat Nunapicuarmun.
Probably because they were supportive, those villages also moved to Nunapitchuk.
Tuaten.
Like that.
Maa-i cali makut-wa ciulirneret tayima-ll’ un’gani pitalguteten waten qanlartut:
Now, these elders, and probably your peers, say this:
Elitnaullermeggni, elitnaullermeggni tamaani elitnauristaita-llu Kass’atun, aren nuu, Yugtun qanresqeksaunaki.
When they went to school back then, their teachers would tell them not to speak English, I mean no, in Yup’ik.
Cakneq murilkaqluki. Qaill’ elpeci pilallruceci?
They were very strict. What did you do?
Tuaten.
Like that.
Qanelria-ll’ una punish-araqluku corner-aamun nangertelluku, corner-aaq cauluku how many minutes.
And they’d punish one who spoke [Yup’ik] by sending them to the corner, and they’d face the corner for several minutes.
Tuaten pitullruitkut.
That’s what they did to us.
Tua-llu cali nerevkarpek’nata, no lunch.
Then they also wouldn’t let us eat, no lunch.
Nertullruut-qaa?
Would they eat?
Tua-i-w’ tamaa-i anucimirqecetaaralallrukaitkut.
That’s how they would chastise us.
Cali-llu tuar niitelallrulrianga, tau͡gaam wii tangeqsaitua.
And it seems I also heard, but I never saw.
Piqertualallruit-gguq canek imkunek. Iciw’ spank.
They said they would be spank them with those things. You know, spank.
Wii nalluanka.
I don’t know about them.
Maa-i-mi wangkuta elitnaulput, elitnaulput-wa cumikenrungataput elpeni elitnaullerpet nalliini.
Now, it seems that we are more focused on school than when you went to school.
Maa-i-qaa? Ii-i.
Now? Yes.
Cumikelliamegteggu-wa elitnaurturalalriit.
They go to school for a long time probably because they focus on it.
Wangkuta-llu-wam tuani elitnauristengqarraallruamta Yugmek.
Our first teacher then was also Yup'ik.
Iciw' [?Anrok], Sam [?Anrok]. Tauna.
You know, [?Anrok], Sam [?Anrok]. That one.
Paniminek aiparluni Ruth Hall. Ruth Hall-aurtellruuq yaa-i.
[S]he was accompanied with their daughter, Ruth Hall. She became Ruth Hall over there.
Taukuk tua-i ciumek elitnauristeńgurtellruuk Nunapicuarmi. Ciuqlikacagaulutek panikellriik.
They were the first to become teachers in Nunapitchuk. The very first ones, parent and daughter.
Ungalaqlirnek cunaw’ tailutek.
Apparently, they came from Unalakleet.
Tua-i tuaten.
Like that.
Tuaten-wa tua-i anucimirqecetaarucillruut.
That’s how they would chastise them.
Iqmigngaunateng-llu elitnaurvigmi.
And they wouldn’t chew tobacco in  school.
Ava-i ayagnirpailemnuk qanellruuten niicuilkengarpenek qanqatarniluten.
Before we started just now, you said you were going to say something you never heard of.
Ii-i, waniwa-w’ tekiteksailkevvuk.
Yes, we haven’t gotten to that yet.
Kitak’ waniwa (Ii-i.) qanrutkeqerru. (Ii-i.)
So now, (Okay.) please talk about it. (Okay.)
Wiinga wani... waniwa-q’ teguqcaarararpecia? Yaa.
I... are you recording me now? Okay.
Yaa.
Okay.
Mat’um nalliini wii tukuurtessiyaagata yuut, iciw’ tukuurcamta qaneryugtua.
Because people are too wealthy tehse days, you know, since we’re now wealthy, I want to say something.
Wangkuta arrsaullruukut.
We were poor.
Wiinga-ll’ arrsaullruunga angayuqaagka...
I was also poor with my parents...
Amta-ll’ wangkuta angniraqluta, ner’aqluta, tua-i happy.
And yet we were happy, we’d eat, just happy.
Tau͡gken tuaten ayuqluta.
Yet we were [poor] like that.
Enemta iluit cataunateng.
There was nothing in our houses.
Kankuk tau͡gaam yaassiiggaak... qulqitnek-llu tang waniw’ tangeqsaitellrulrianga.
Only two small boxes down there... and, you see, I didn’t see any shelves.
Yaassiiggaak kanani pinaurtuk.
There’d be two small boxes down there.
Ikirrlukek tang aanaput yuurqaqatalliniaqameng saskanek ancinaurtuq, tua-i-ll’ qaingagni yuurqerluta.
You see, my mother would open them when they were going to have hot drinks and take out cups, then we’d have hot drinks on top of them.
Tuar-llu tang eruriyuilngukut. Naamell’.
And it seemed we wouldn’t was dishes. I don’t know.
Tua-i wii ceńirtaalgullruama tang qaunqessiyaallrunrilkenka.
Since I’d always visit others, you see, I didn’t take care of them too much.
Tua-i-llu maa-i mat’um nalliini anagutut people.
Then these days, people are excessive.
Yugtun... Kass’atun-qaa mumigciiqaten qanellrenka?
In Yup’ik... will you translate what I say into English?
Arcaqerluk’ tang ayagyuanun niitesqumayaaqekeka tau͡gaam qitevquraqtalaameng Yugtun-llu qanyuunateng amlleq taringengaitaat.
You see, I especially want the youth to hear this, but because they always speak English and don’t speak Yup’ik, they won’t understand a lot.
Ilii-w’ Kass’atum piqaqulaqumku canritlilria.
It’s probably fine if I periodically do some of it in English.
Mat’um nalliini anagutpiarluteng eneput.
These days, our houses are very excessive.
We’re rich right now.
We have everything in the house.
Ca tamalkuan avaliqluku. Tuar wangkuta Kass’at, Yuuluta tau͡gaam.
We have everything. It seems we’re Westers, yet we’re Yup’ik.
Tua-i-llu wiinga taukuni Cakayiinkuni Johnny Samuelson-aaq trading post-arluni Nunapicuarmi uitavallutullruunga nasaurluulua.
Then I mostly stayed there with Cakayak and family as a girl, where Johnny Samuelson had a trading post in Nunapitchuk.
Nulirra tang una cassiyaayuunani, iciw’ tua-i mulngaku’urngataqluni.
You see, his wife wouldn’t do much, you know, seeming to always be careful.
Wiinga tang eruringuarturnaurtua. Agleqsaunii-llu maybe 10 years old, or nine, tamaani.
You see, I would always was dishes. And I didn’t have my first menstruations [at] maybe 10 years old, or nine, at that time.
Cat-llu makut perrirturaraqluki pisqelaaki taum nulirran.
And I’d always wipe [dust] off of things because his wife would tell me to.
Cunaw’ Kassaungamek.
Apparently, because they were Caucasian.
Tua-i half breed, avguami uinga. Nulirra-w’ caullrua.
Well, half breed, since her husband was half. I’m not sure what his wife was.
Tuaten wii anglilua.
I grew up like that.
Utertaqama-llu uitarrlainanrilama ilamnun-am family-mnun utertaqama
And when I went home, since I didn’t always stay with my family, when I went home
Imkuni Kass’ani pilalqa ayuqeliluku enemteńi.
I would do the same in our house as I did at the Caucasians’.
Cat makut kitukcaarnaunka. Cunaw’ dust out-alallrullinikenka-ll’ cat.
I would fix these things. Apparently, I’d also dust things out.
Assircaarturluki pinaunka tang.
You see, I’d do them well.
Tua-i taukugnek elillua.
I learned from them.
Mat’um nalliini high school, college pitanguq.
These days, there is high school, [and] college.
Umyuarteq’lartua, "Makuskiq maa-i nallunritpiarpagtut, qaillun-llu enem iluan clean up-aallerkaanek."
I think, "These people absolutely know things, including how to clean up inside the house."
Tuaten umyuarteq’lartua. Tuaten wii ayuqelqa Kass’ani uitaqtaqalqa pitekluku elitellruunga tamatumek.
That’s what I think. Being like that, I learned it from being among Caucasians.
Tua-i-llu mat’um nalliini wii taumi cali Nunapicuarmi arnassagaq au͡gna arnassagaurpallrunritliniuq taum nalliini.
Then these days, that old lady there in Nunapitchuk apparently wasn’t a very old lady at the time.
Ceńirrviktullruaqa.
I would visit her.
Tauna tang iternaurtua arnaq eruriqcaaralria caminek.
You see, I’d go in and that woman would be steadily washing her dishes.
Saaniini-ll’ makut perriqcaarturnaura waten kaminiami qaingani.
And she’d steadily wipe her kettles like this on top of her stove.
Tua-i-ll’ itraqama taum arnam uutautengqelaan saarralanek, iciw’ saarralanek uucitulriit yuut.
Then when I went in, since that woman had burnt sugar cantly, you know how people make burnt sugar candy.
Wii tuar candy-rtaitellrulria tamaani.
It seemed to me that there was no candy back then.
Taum arnam uutamek cikiqernauraanga, wiinga-ll’ iqemkarluku.
That woman would give me burnt sugar candy, and I’d put it in my mouth.
Saarralarninaqluni neqniqluni.
It tasted sweet and delicious.
Tamana pitekluku tauna arnaq ullagyutullruaqa.
That was the reason I’d want to go to that woman.
Taum caaqami pilaraanga arnam, "Ilung’," ilungaqliniamia, "Ilung’, wangtun piyaureskuvet aipangkuvet wangtun pilaqina.
Sometimes, that would would say to me, "Cuzz," because I was her cousin, "Cuzz, if you became able like me and get married, do what I do.
"Cangqelarniartuten atam.
"Watch, you will have things.
"Caten eruyuunaki enevet iluani," tua-i nasaurlullraulua, "uitaskuvki dust-am atam patularniarai.
"If you don’t wash things in your house," I was a little girl, "if you leave them, watch, dust will cover them.
"Kiituani assiirucan qel’kenriran eggluku-llu."
"When it eventually gets bad, you don’t keep it anymore and throw it away."
Tauna-llu nutarauyaaqluni tau͡gaam dust-am iqam patuluku.
And that may be new, but dust and dirt covers it.
Tua-i-ll’ aglumanairulluni piksuumirutnariluni-llu.
Then it becomes undesirable and you wouldn’t want it anymore.
Taum tang pitullrukiinga tuaten.
You see, that’s what she’d tell me.
Waten-llu piaqlua: ellii-gguq children’s home, Moravian home, nani anglillruuq.
She also told me this: she grew up somewhere, children’s  home, Moravian home.
Tua-i-w’ Kass’ani-am pillilria.
It was probably among Caucasians.
Tamaaken-gguq nallunrillruuq how to clean up the house.
She said she learned how to clean up the house from there.
Ala-i mat’um nalliini makut teenagers, they’re smart.
Oh my, these days these teenagers, they’re smart.
They know how to clean up the house. They know how to do everything.
But they just sit and watch TV all day, maybe.
Lazy, never do anything.
Tua-i, tua-i tamaa-i.
There you have it.
Arnam taum arnaurrluni arnassagaam alerqualallra...
That woman who became and old woman’s instruction...
Arenqiapaa. Ila-i.
Oh no. Oh my goodness.
Canrituq.
It’s okay.
Tua-i?
Ready?
Waten pilaraanga: "Ilung’, iliini atam uingniartuten."
She’d say this to me: "Cuzz, watch, someday you’ll get a husband."
Uingelleq, have husband.
Uingelleq, have [a] husband.
"Tuaten atam piniartuten.
"Watch, you will do that.
"Tua-i-llu tuateun pikuvet eruyuilkuvki caten cangqerrngaituten.
"Then when you do that, if you don’t wash your things, you won’t have anything.
"Uin-llu atam picupiaryaaqniartuq, arrsauniartuten atam."
"And watch, your husband may be a very good hunter, watch, you will be destitute."
Tuaten pilallruanga.
That’s what she’d tell me.
Cunaw’ tang enem iluani cat take care-arnarqellinilriit, iciw’ tua-i auluknaqluteng.
It turned out, you see, that things need to be taken care of in the house, you know, need to be taken care of.
Tua-i mat’um naliini wii tua-i tamaani elisngariyukelqa Cakayiinkuni uitaqtaaralqa.
These days, I thought I’d become knowledge about that back when I would stay with Cakayak and family.
Elitnaulallruyaaqellrianga-w’ tua-i tuar tang aren wii ikgelan elitnaulqa elitelqa pitailnguq.
I had gone to school, but it seems, I mean, since I didn’t go to school for long, I didn’t learn much.
Tua-i-ll’ mat’um nalliini waten cali qanlartut:
Then these days, they also say this:
"Arnanek-gguq irnialek arnaq, atam-gguq taum arnam aanani tangvagniaraa enem iluani.
"A woman with female children, watch, that woman will watch her mother in the house.
"Tua-i-llu-gguq calillra callra arnam cali taum irniaran ayuqeliyugngaluku."
"Then her work and what she does, that woman’s child can copy her."
Piciugut makut.
These [words] are true.
Wiinga-ll’ waniw’ nine-aanek irniangqertua, five girls, four boys.
And now, I have nine children, five girls, four boys.
Ukut-llu five girls ayuqenritut tamarmeng. Iciw’ ayuqenritut.
And these five girls are all different. You know, they’re different.
Tamalkuita-ll’ taukut wii kenkepiarluki.
And I love them all very much.
Tua-i-ll’ caliyaurcama cali mingeqsaurcama tua-i
Then when I started making things and started sewing
Ukut-ll’ angliriluteng ukut yuungnaqengluteng paniinka.
And my daughters grew up and started making their own living.
Caliurnaunka mingqurluki-ll’.
I’d keep making them  things and sewing them things.
Iliini enaitnun it’lartua cailkama tauna im’ mingqelqa. Umyuaqa tang pinaurtuq.
I’d sometimes go in their houses, and what I sewed would be on the floor. You see, I’d be upset.
Cunawa-m’ tua-i assircaarluku call’ tauna uitaarkaq cailkamtelluku.
It turned out that what was supposed to be kept well was on the floor.
Iliinun panima iternaurtua neat.
I’d go in one of daughters [and the house is] neat.
Aren, caliallrenka-ll’ makut kenkumaluteng.
Oh my, what I made would be treated with love.
Tua-i-ll’ tuaten piama waniwa irniamni five girls, malruk, atrit aperngaitanka, wii tangerturallemni neat.
Then when I did that, among the five girls of my children, two of them, I won’t say their names, are neat from what I’ve seen.
Kass’at apqiitnek neat.
Neat, as they say in English.
Assirtuk. Tamarmeng assiryaaqut.
They’re good. All of them are good.
Tua-i-ll’ waten piunga: mingqaallrenka aturiallrenka taukuk care-aqapiarluki.
Then I realized this: those two would take great care of the clothes I sewed.
Arcaqerluni-am aipaan care-aamiki eniinun itraqama tua-i tanglaamteki
Since the other especially cares for them, when I go into her house because we see them
Kiagmi caliallrenka mingqaat atkuut, piluguut, furs, fur clothes kiagmi tangerqayuitanka eniin iluani, nothing.
In the summer, the things I made by sewing, parkas, fur boots, furs, fur clothes, I never see then in her house during the summer, nothing.
She put them away.
She put[s] them away.
Iciw’ put away-larai.
You know, she puts them away.
Kass’ani nallunritua fur-at uitavingqertut pitalqellriamek enemek.
I know that in the West, fur [clothes] have places, suitable spaces.
Kiircetevkenani, nengllirpek’nani, maybe meduim.
It’s not hot, it’s not cold, maybe meduim.
Tua-i-ll’ fur-ani assirluteng.
Then their fur is good.
Atam cat wani makut skin-at agaurarqameng years and years aturviirutetuut uuluteng.
Look, when these skin clothes hang for years and years, they’re no longer suitable to wear [?from wearing out].
Tegukumni-ll’ una atkuk allegluni. Uuluni.
And if I take this parka, it rips. [?It wears out].
Tua-i-llu waniwa niicuilkemnek makuni TV-ni qalartua.
Then now, I’m speaking about what I don’t hear in these TV’s.
Amlleq qalartelartuq avani imumi tamakunek.
Many would speak of those long ago.
Mat’um nalliini arcaqalriaruuq tukuussiyaagata yuut Agayutem cikiutekngateng cat.
It’s important these days because people are too wealthy, since things are God’s gifts.
Enem iluani cat Agayutem cikiutekai.
Things in the house are God’s gifts.
Arnam take care-ararkaugai assirluki.
A woman must take good care of them.
Ilii angutem pituuq atam.
You see, some men do [that].
Wii waniw’ nengaungqertua ayuqenrilngurnek.
Now, I have different sons-in-law.
Iliin uinga nuliani ikayuayunqeggluku.
Some of their husbands likes to help their wives.
Irnianka-w’ tua-i tuaten ayuquten ilait.
Some of my children are like that.
Iliin-llu uinga uitauratuluni.
Some of their husbands is sedentary.
Arnii nallmikun kiiryugluni caliluni.
His wife is hot and works around him.
Angutiin-llu ikayuyuunaku, angutnguami-wa.
And her husband doesn’t help her because he’s a man.
Angutet qagaani caliarkaungameng outside work, arnaq-llu enem iluani inside work.
It’s because men are supposed to work out there, outside work, and woman in the house, inside work.
Tau͡gaam ayuqenrilata yuut ayuqenrilngurnek-am ukut paniinka aipangqelartut.
But because people are different, my daughters have different kinds of spouses.
Ilait tang nuliat, tamakut-am wii assikpiaranka aipait makut aipateng care-aqait.
Some of their wives, you see, I really like those spouses who take care of their spouses.
Angli-ll’ taumi assirpaa.
My goodness, that person’s so good.
Pituaput.
We tell them [that].
Keneknaqluteng.
They are lovable.
Uitauryulriit waten, qaill’ atak’ apqerlaku?
Those who are sedentary like this, how should I say it?
Mat’um nalliini-llam qanlartut, "Weird."
These days, they say, "Weird."
Weird-aq una wii taringyuitaqa.
I don’t understand this word "weird."
Tuar-llu tang tauna tuaten uitauralria weird-alria.
It seems that one who’s sedentary like that is weird.
Wiinga atam qalartaqama temcinarqellrianek avuaqluku pituunga.
You see, when I speak, I add in some silly things.
Tua-i man’a maa-i arcaqerluku qanruteksullruaqa.
I especially wanted to talk about this.
Makut teenager-aat mat’um nalliini catussiyaanritellrat I sorry for them.
How teenagers these days don’t really do anything, I [am] sorry for them.
Aanait-llu caqtarturnaurtut, pania-wa un’ inarrluni naaqillria.
And their mothers would keep working, while her daughter here lays down and reads.
Tua-i-w’ puqiameng pillilriit kalikanek.
It’s probably because they’re fluent [enough to read] books.
Ilii-ll’ apqiitnek video, teng teng teng teng teng.
And some what they call video [games], ding ding ding ding ding.
Aqumluni couple hours calinami nangerrluni aanani ikayurluku wall’u atani.
[S]he sits down for a couople hours when they should work, standing up and helping their mother or father.
Tua-i makunek qalartua.
I’m speaking of these things.
Ilakelaatgu-llu Agayun, Agayutem cikiuta enem iluani take care-arnarqelliniut assircaarluki.
And because they’re with God, we must take good care of God’s gifts in the house.
Tamaa-i tamana arcaqerluku imku’rqa, qanruteksullruaqa caliarkaq amllepiassiyaagan mat’um nalliini enem iluani.
That’s what I especially wanted to, you know, talk about because there’s way too much work to be done in a house these days.
Arenqiatuq nerlaamta-llu taqnaurtukut tang estuuluq pengilun’ erurarkat.
It’s unfortunate because we’d eat, and when we’re done, you see, the table would have a mountain of dishes.
Wall’u qulqitet ingkut erurarkarugaat.
Or in the shelves over there, so many dishes to wash.
Tua-i-ll’ aanaq una caqtarturluni.
Then this mother keeps working.