Au͡g’umek tua-i Alussistuamek qaillun, qaillun nallunriqarraallerpeceńek [?]yugallerpeni una wani cikiqengyaraq qaillun alerquutekellruatgu?
About Christmas from before, when you first learned about it when you were [?growing], what instructions did they give about generosity?
Avani au͡gkut ciuqliput nepaitellruut. Nepaitellruut.
Back then, our ancestors were peaceful. They were peaceful.
Tua-i waten ciulirnemeggnek qanrutesterluteng, inerqurterluteng, ayuqucirturterluteng.
They had their elders like this to instruct them, admonish them, and advise them.
Cali-llu waten tukuullrunritut avani ciuqvani. Canek-llu makunek Kass’artarnek teguqerrartevkenateng.
Also, they weren’t wealthy a long time ago. And these Western things weren’t on hand.
Tua-i waten ilateng piilnguut ikayurluki, tua-i alerquutekluku. Tuaten ayuqellruut.
They would help those around them who didn’t have anything, as was traditionally instructed. That’s what they were like.
Cali piilnguut waten tangerrluki piilutaitnek ikayurluki, navrilluki cali piilnguut. Tuaten ayuqellruut yuut au͡gkut angullrenka.
Also, they helped those who didn’t have anything by looking at what they didn’t have, and also lent them things. That’s what the people I was born in time to see were like.
Tua-i-llu man’a waten castailnguq iciw’ tua-i elliraat makut, aipainret pinarquciicetun tua-i ikayurluki.
Then one who didn’t have a provider liket his, you know, these orphans, widows, they helped them with whatever they needed.
Ikayualuki akinaullerkameggnek pivkenateng.
They helped them without expecting payment.
Tamana-am akinaullerkaq inerquutekluku-am cali.
They also admonished against expecting payment.
Waten pisqevkenaki: "Uum, uum akinaurniaraanga. Waten pilaku." Tuaten pisqevkenaku.
They told them not to do this: "This person may reward me. Let me do this." They said not to do that.
Tau͡gaam tua-i waten akinaunra umyuaqevkenaku ikayurluki ilateng arenqiallugtellriit.
Instead, without thinking of payment like this, help those who are in misfortune around them.
Kevgailnguut kevgarturluki. Tuaten ayuqellruut yuut.
Seeve those who have no helpers. That’s what people were like.
Camek tamana wani kangingqerrniaqluku akilircetaarpek’naki canrituq, kiik’ ikayurluku. Camek kangililallruatgu?
What did they say was the meaning of being okay without payment, but to go ahead and help? What meaning did they prescribe to it?
Waten kangililallruat: tua-i-gguq tamaa-i tamana kingukegtuq.
They prescribed this meaning to it: that has good aftereffects [later in life].
Iciw’ akqutmek, akqutmek niicuitukut avani. Akeqnerrlugutmek-llu niicuunata.
You know, we didn’t hear promises back then. And we didn’t hear threats.
Tuaten ayuqellruut yuut.
That’s what people were like.
Qaillun-mi pitariluten elpet, qaillun tayim’ pitariluten Alussistuamek niiteqarraallrusit? Qaillun-llu pillrusit Alussistua[?].
So, how old were you, how old were you when you first heard about Christmas? And what did you do [?] Christmas?
Alussistuamek tua-i niitelangukut wangkuta. Qaneryaramek tua-i niitelangukut.
We started hearing about Christmas. We started hearing the Bible.
Qaneryariurteḿek tua-i cali nalluluteng tua-i, tau͡gaam tua-i niitaqluteng, niitelangluteng.
And they also didn’t know of preachers, but they would hear of them, started hearing of them.
Caqaameng tua-i piinanermeggni tua-i qaneryariurta tekicaurrluni.
And one day, eventually, a preacher started arriving.
Qaillun-mi elpet Alussistuaq piqarraallrani elpet qaillun...
So, when Christmas first start, how did you...
Alussistuaq tua-i piqarraallranek ayagnillranek tau͡gaam tua-i niitelangluta.
We only started hearing of the first Christmas and when it began.
Tua-i-ll’ Alussistuaryaurrluteng iciw’ tua-i tuyumek cikiumiimeng ugkut nunallret tayima Qinarmiullret wiinga ellangvikellrenka.
Then they started having Christmas, you know, when they were given a pastor downriver in the old village of Qinarmiut where I grew up.
Tuyumek cikiumiimeng taum tua-i Alussistuaq takumni piyaurcetellrua.
When they were given a pastor, he started the Christmas tradition in my life.
Qaillun pivkaraqluci?
What would [s]he have you do?
Tua-i Alussistuaq maa-i tua-i atulauciacetun makutgun Qaneryaratgun aturaqluku.
They’d celebrate Christmas as they do now, celebrating as told in this Bible.
Tua-i cikiqaquuraulluteng-llu tua-i piaqluteng iciw’ tua-i cali carrluarnek tua-i.
And they would give each other things, you know, including little things.
Waten ayuqellrunritut yuut avani ciuqvaarni.
People weren’t like this a long time ago.
Qaneryaraq-llu man’a alaillrani waten ayuqsugnaitellruut.
And when this Bible appeared, they were absolutely nothing like this.
Canek tau͡gaam tua-i cikiqaquuraulluteng. Neqerrluarnek tuaten cikiqaquuraulluteng tua-i pinaurtut.
Instead, they’d give each other things. They’d even give each other smoked dried fish.
Kass’artarmek piitellermeggni neqet avatiitni canek-llu cikiqengaqluteng?
When they didn’t have Western things, what else would they give aside from food?
Tua-i-wa neqnek, neqnek tua-i.
Well, food, [they’d give] food.
Cali-ll’ piilnguut pikalget tua-i carrluarnek tua-i cikiqaqluki pitullruit.
Also, for those without anything, those who had [something to spare] would give them some little things.
(Aturpagayuunateng-qaa camek nalluluteng?) Aturpagayuunateng-wa.
(Would they not sing because they didn’t know?) They wouldn’t sing.
Tau͡gaam iciw’ ingularcuutnek-am cali quliraat yuarutaitnek, aren tamaa-i tamana nallunritelqa ayagmek.
But, you know, they’d [sing] Yup’ik dancing songs from legends, oh my, that’s what I knew from the beginning.
Quliraat yuarutaitnek aturluteng yurarnaurtut cauyarluteng uksuarkami uksurpailgan.
They’d sing songs from legends, Yup’ik dancing, and drumming at the cusp of fall before winter.
Tua-i-am piciryaraqluku yuut.
It was the people’s tradition.
Tua-i-ll’ uksum iluani nutaan kelegluteng yurarluteng tua-i.
Then in the winter, they’d finally invite [other villages] and have a dance festival.
Pikangqerrucirmegcetun neqnek, neqnek tua-i.
They’d [bring] as much food as they could.
Kass’at-llu piyaurcata cali Kass’artarnek-am cali pilangluteng-am tua-i.
Then when the Caucasians came, they also started [giving and eating] Western things.
Tua-i tuaten pitullruut au͡gkut wii angullrenka, pilangeqarraallret-wa tua-i.
That’s what the ones I was born in time to see used to do, the ones who first started celebrating.
Uum-qaa yuum piciryaraa tayima wani piilnguq cikiqalaasqelluku pingqerrutacimitun
This person’s tradition of giving to one who doesn’t have anything as much as they can
Elpeci murilkengllerpeceńi-qaa ayuqngatlinia makut wani aipaimta piciryaraqluku cikiqengluteng wall’u-qaa qaill’ tamana ayuqellinia?
When you started becoming observant, does it seem the same as our counterparts’ tradition of giving, or what is that like?
Atra-llu, atra pitekluku-llu ukut iciw’-llu kingunrulriit
And on account of one’s namesake, you know, these next generations
Taum ilairutmeng atranek atellget-am cali tauna tamana pitekluku cikiqatulliniluku tauna.
Those who are named after their late relative, they’d also give them a gift for that reason.
Tuaten-am pitulliniluteng.
They would do that.
Alussistuam nalkenrilengraaku?
Even if it wasn’t Christmas time?
Yes, even if it wasn’t [Christmas] time.
Tua-i-llu-qaa qaillun pitariqerluten makut wani tuyut wall’u agayulirtet
And so, how old were you when these lay pastors or priests
Ayagcetat-wa qaillun pitariluten tekitelangellruat maavet?
How old were you when these traveling priests starting arriving here?
Ugkut ellangvikellrenka muragcaurrlua, napacaurrlua tuyumek cikiumallruut.
Where I grew up downriver, when I started getting wood, getting trees, they were given a lay pastor.
Tua-i waten qallataqluni tauna qasgimi.
[S]he would preach like this in the community house.
Qasgimi tua-i mat’umek Qaneryaramek qalartaqan tua-i niicugniaqluku tua-i.
When [s]he spoke of this Bible in the community house, we’d listen.
Tua-i-ll’ tamatum kinguakun tayima tua-i cayaurtengluta tua-i.
Then after that, we started doing [various non-Yup’ik] things.
Au͡gna ak’allaq qaneryariurta cali tekicaurrluni, ak’allaq tua-i.
That old preacher started arriving, an old person.
Pektesteńgullrungatelliniuq tauna Kass’aq.
It seemed that Caucasian was sent all over.
Yaaqvarmiu amta-ll’ tua-i Yugcetun qalartetuluni.
[S]he was from far away yet spoke Yup’ik.
Maa-i wani nunat ilaitni, nunat ilaitni tegulluteng aternek cikirturilartut.
Now in some villages, in some villages, they take names [at random] and give presents.
Tamaani-qaa [Alussistualallruut]?
Back then, [would they have Christmas like that]?
Waten piyuitellruut tuaten watqapik.
They never did that at all.
Qangvaq piyaurtut waten.
They’ve started doing this sometime ago.
Qangvarraq tua-i nutaan. Qangvarraq tua-i.
It was only until recently. It was recent.
Tamakut-qaa tuyut tekitellriit agayuvigni, aren qasgimi-wa quyurtevkarluki-qaa qaillun Alussistuaq atulallruatgu?
When those lay pastors came to the churches, I mean, would they gather people in the community house, and how did they celebrate Christmas?
Alussistuaq tamakut atuqsaitaat.
Those people didn’t celebrate Christmas.
Allanret tekitellriit tau͡gaam uum tuyum tuanelnguum Alussistuaq-llu tua-i man’a aturyaurtelluku takurramni tua-i.
But the guests that came, this lay pastor among them had us start celebrating Christmas in my short life [at the time].
Qaillun aturcetaqluku?
How did [s]he have you celebrate?
Tua-i-wa aturcetaqluku waten Alussistuarcuutnek-llu iciw’ tua-i atualuteng-llu piyaurrluteng Alussistuarcuutnek.
[S]he had us start celebrating like this with Christmas [songs], you know, they started singing Christmas songs.
Tua-i tau͡gken carrluarnek tua-i cikiqaquuraulluteng tua-i. Tua-i carrluarnek tua-i cikiqaquuraulluteng.
However, they would give each other little things. They’d give each other little things.
Nutaan piyaurrluteng takumni.
They only started in my lifetime.
Elpesmi maa-i wani camek mat’umi allrakumi Allrakumi piyuutengqercit?
So, what do you want for Christmas this year?
Niicugnilriit niitevkarluki.
Have those who are listening hear.
Tua-i una Jesus-aam yuurtellra niicimayuitelqa avani tua-i wangkuta, wangkuta pitekluta
The birth of Jesus, that I didn’t hear about a lot back then, for our sake
Matuulliniuq: tua-i man’a tua-i tangrruunrilnguq man’a tua-i unguvavut man’a tua-i Anerneq Tanqilria man’a tua-i unguvavut.
This is what it is: this, our unseen life, this Holy Spirit is our life.
Tamatuulliniuq. Waten-gguq ayuquq man’a: iciw’ Agayun piniungami
That’s what it is. They say this is like this: you know, because God is powerful
Iciw’ tua-i man’a Qaneryaraq kemgurrluku, tangrruurrluku tangrruunrilnguq, niicimatuli tau͡gaam.
You know, he made this Word flesh, made seen what was unseen, only heard of.
Tangrruurrluku kemgurrluku yuurtelluku.
He made him seen, made flesh, and had him be born.
Tuaten-gguq yuurtellruuq Jesus-aaq.
They say Jesus was born like that.
Yuurtelluku atiin. Tua-i maavet nunamun tunluku cikiutekluku. Tua-i cikiutnguluni.
His father had him be born. He gave him as a gift to this world. He was a gift.
Piciuguq tua-i man’a.
This is true.
Waten iciw’-am cali yuarutet iliitni waten qaneryarartangqellria: "Tangvaglua ukveqiciu ciuniurluku-llu cikiuteka."
Like this, you know, in one of the songs, there are lyrics like this: "Look at me, believe and accept my gift."
Tua-i waten ciuniunritesteḿinun iciw’ tua-i Jesus-aaq ciuniunritesteḿinun waten-am Qaneryarani qaneryarartangqertuq:
To those who do not accept him like this, youo know, to those who don’t accept Jesus, there is a verse in the Bible like this:
"He makes only those who believe in him worthy to become God’s people, the ones who believe in his [Jesus’] name." There’s a verse like this.
Tua-i tua-i-llu ciuniurteńi ciuniurteḿinun pulaluni unguviinun
Then for those who accept him, he goes into their life
Ciuniuqani-w’ tau͡gaam, piciuliuni tau͡gaam pikuni ciuniuqani.
Only if [s]he accepts him, only if [s]he accepts him in earnest.
Tua-i-ll’ taumun yugmun anirturilriarurrluni. Anirturteńgurrluni tua-i.
Then he becomes a savior to that person. He becomes a savior.
Tau͡gken ciuniuqsaitesteḿinun anirturilriarurteksaunani taumun yugmun.
However, to one who hasn’t accepted him, he doesn’t become a savior to that person.
Tua-i-llu waten ayuqelliniluni, waten-am qaneryarartangqertuq cali tayima:
Then it’s like this, there’s also a verse like this:
"Kenkekenka inerqularanka anucimircetaarluki-llu. Taumek tengruluci umyualinqigci.
"I admonish those whom I love and chastise them. For that reason, enthusiastically repent.
"Tangerrluku-llu nangerngaunga amigmi tukriarlua-llu.
"And look, I stand at the door and knock.
"Yuum-llu erinaka niiskuniu amik-llu ikirrluku itervikciqaqa nerellgutekluku-llu elliin-llu wiinga." Tuaten-am qaneryarartangqertuq.
"If a person hears my voice and opens the door, I will go in and eat with them, and them with me." There’s a verse like that.
Tua-i-llu yuum ciuniuqsailkuniu cailkamceciiqellinia anirturteksaguteksaunaku.
Then if a person doesn't welcome him, he will leave them on on wayside without having become their savior.
Tuaten ayuqelliniuq.
That's what it's like.
Tua-ll' au͡gna Agayutem-wa tua-i elpengcautii qanrutkeqeryugyaaqluku waten. Erinaka-w’ tua-i saagartesqumayaaqluku.
Then I want to talk about God’s advice like this. I want my voice to spread.
Yuk waten au͡g’acurlakuni, waniwa-llam niitellriakut akwaugaq Kuigglugmi-gguq qama-i ilangartut.
If a person passes away in sin, and now, we heard yesterday that someone passed away upriver in Kwethluk.
Tua-i-llam tua-i au͡gna cali-am waken qanelria waten qanerluni:
Then that person from here also said this:
"Ellminek yuulriamek ellminek-llu tuqulriamek ilaitukut. Tau͡gaam yuullemteńi Atanermun yuugukut."
"There is none among us who lives by themself or dies by themself. But as we live, we live for the Lord."
Maa-i ukvelriim qaneryarartaa waten qanerluni: "Atanermun yuugukut. Tuqukumta-llu Atanermun tuquciqukut."
The believers’ creed says this: "We live for the Lord. And when we die, we will die for the Lord."
Taumek yuungramta wall’u tuqungramta Atanrem pikaakut. Tua-i ukvelriit tamaa-i qanrutkumallrat piciuluni-llu. Piciugarkauluni.
That’s why whether we live or die, we are the Lord’s. That’s what believers have said, and it’s true. It must be true.
Tau͡gken piciunrilnguut aturngaitaat tamana.
However, those who aren’t true won’t experience that.
Piciunrilkuni yuk tuquciquq tua-i-ll’ unguvii pellucurlagluni.
If a person isn’t true, they will die, then their life will pass in misfortune.
Tua-i tau͡gaam kenermetarkauluni.
Instead, [s]he will be in fire.
Au͡gna tua-i yugnun erinaka-w’ tua-i saagarrluku cali-ll’ aipaimteńun makunun erinaka [saagarrluku].
I spread my voice about that to the people, and [I spread] my voice to our counterparts here.
Aipartek umyuaqelaryaaqaqa uumirpak ak’a una qanrutkeqeryugyaaqluku tau͡gaam takaqlutek nalluyuqlutek.
I’ve been thinking of one of you lately wanting to speak of this, but I was uncomfortable and intimidated by you.
Tua-i-ll’ airpartek umyuaqelaryaaqluku mumigteqaasqelluku qanelqa.
Then I thought that one of you would translate what I said.
Yuk au͡g’acurlakuni, man’a unguvani pellucurlakuniu
If a person passes away in sin, lives this life unacceptably
Tua-i tau͡gaam nanvamun ek’arkauluni akwarpak akwanun tua-i kenermetlerkaminun pilliqetataunani.
Instead, [s]he will go into the lake forever, to be in fire forever in the utmost suffering.
Man’a unguvavut tua-i arenqiiryarai-llu arenqiirturyarai amllerrsaaqut.
There are many ways to resolve our lives.
Tua-i tau͡gaam yugmun waten maantenriqan qama-i niitukut.
But when a person is no longer here, we’ve heard [of one] upriver.
Tua-i-llam taumi kep’uq tua-i.
Then at that time, [the life] stops.
Iciw’ tua-i arenqiirtuumarmi-w’ tua-i.
You know, with whatever resolution [that life] had.
Kitak’...
So now...
Kitak’ atam una...
So then this...
Waten tang umyuaqa ayuqsaaqellria: aiparpetegnun imna-ll’ Aqum’aq-llu qanelqa Kass’atun mumigartesqumayaaqluku.
You see, this is my thought: that either you or Aqum’aq would translate what I said into English.
Tua-i elluarrluteng pillerkaat elpekesqumayaaqluku.
I want them to understand how they could [live] well.
Ataki.
Let’s see.
Man’a wani calivigput-am piciurkiutengqertuq waten...
Our workplace here has a policy like this...
Maa-i umyuaqutmek assilriamek tuyuqerkut qanrulluta umyuarpenek iciw’ Alussistuaqegcisqelluta.
Now, wish us good tidings, tell us of your thoughts, you know, wishing us a Merry Christmas.
Ii-i, tua-ll’ waniwa qanqauteknauqa canun imkunun niicugnistengqerrarkaukuma.
Okay, so let me talk about it now if I have some of those people to listen to me.
Jesus-aam yuurtellra atam Agayutem... tua-i-q’ waniwa? Waniwa-q’ tua-i?
Jesus’ birth, you see, God... is it going now? Is it going now?
Yaa.
Yes.
Atam Agayutem kenkiin nunam yuinek, ellarpiin yuinek kenkitacian angtataitetacianek
You see, God’s love fo the people of the land, how there is nothing greater than his love for the people of the world
Waten ayuqelliniuq Jesus-aaq una, waten Qaneryaranek qanrutkumauq waten qanerluni:
This is what Jesus is like, it is told like this in the Bible saying this:
"Nutemtellrani Qaneryaraq uitallruuq, Qaneryaraq-llu Agayutmi uitallruuq, Qaneryaraq-llu Agayutnguluni."
"The Word was always there, and the Word was in God, and the Word was God."
Atam waten ayuqellinilria: ava-i qanelria Qaneryaraq nutemtellranek, ayagneranek qanerpek’nani.
Look, it’s like this: it just said when when the Word has always been, not talking about its beginning.
Atam Agayutem kenkiin angtataitetaciani tua-i waten, waten ayuqelliniluni, kitak’ atam taringluku:
Look, how there is nothing greater than God’s love, it’s like this, now understand it:
Tuani-gguq atam taum tanqia mat’um tanqian, tanqia anaggluku tanqingqertuq.
It says that there, you see, it’s light has a greater light than the light here.
Cali-llu taukuk atam iluani eluciq angnirluni nunaniq tua-i tau͡gaam camek avuunani.
Also, inside those is a shape that is happy and joyful but without anything added.
Tua-lli-wa cali waten yuarutetangqellria, yuarutni qaneryarartangqelalria:
Furthermore, there’s also a song like this, there are lyrics in a song:
Jesus-aaq-gguq agallrunrilkan tamarmi yuum yuucia tamaumayartuq.
It said that had Jesus not been hung, every person’s life would be lost.
Tua-i-ll’ Jesus-aaq atrallruan waten ayuqelliniluni: atam kenkiin angtataitetacia.
Then when Jesus came down, it was like this: look how there is nothing greater than his love.
Atam tanqik, tanqik nuniq, camna-wa tan’geq nangteqnaq tuqu, pellernaq.
Look at the light, the wonderful light, and the darkness below, miserable death, repulsive.
Tua-lli-wa kenkitacirmitun Agayutem tuarpiaq tauna Jesus-aaq tuarpiaq tamaa iivkarluku.
Furthermore, with the extent of God’s love, it truly seemed that he sent Jesus down right away.
Tuarpiaq nunam yuini yaaqliurrluku, nunam yui ukaqliurrluki kenkiin angtataitetacia.
It truly seems that he put [Jesus] over from the people of the land, put the people of the land closer to him with the greatest love.
Ak’akika tua-i mat’umek au͡gna assikaqa-llu. Cangakenritaqa tua-i.
With so much for this, I like that one too. I don’t mind it.
Tua-i-ll’ pitsaqa’artevkenaku au͡gna qanruteksugyaaqelqa pitsaqa’artevkenaku pillerkangqerqan pisqumakuviu-llu nutaan piyarluku.
Then should there be time for me to talk about what I wanted to, and should you want me to, I would.
Kitak’ Merry Christmas-aaqerkut wangkuta tangvalriani maa-i.
Please wish a Merry Christmas to us who are watching now.
Tua-i niitellriani tua-i tamarpeci tua-i waniw’ hello-ramci tua-i Merry Chrismas-aarluci.
All of you who are listening now, I say hello and wish you a Merry Christmas.
Quyana.
Thank you.
Yaa.
You’re welcome.