Yaa, kitak’ Betty, Akiaq wani imumi iinriurteńgullruuten.
Yes, okay Betty, you were a health aide long ago in Akiak.
Ciuqliit iinriurtet ilakellruatgen.
You were part of the first health aides.
Kitak’ tamaani caliarpet ayuqellranek qanemcitqerkut.
Please tell us what your work was like back then.
Tua-i waniw’ ayagnillranek ayagniqarraallemnek ayaglua qanemciciqua qaqitenrilengraan.
Now, I will tell the story of when it started, starting from when I began, even if it’s not complete.
Ayagniqarraallruunga waten:
I first started like this:
Tamaani yuungcarista tekitaqan, iinriurta-llu tekitaqan
Back then, when the doctor would arrive, and the nurse would arrive
Cucuk’laatnga qanerciisqelluteng qanercirluki ayagnilallruunga.
Since they chose me to speak for them, I’d start by speaking for them.
Ayagnillruunga, ima-llu-qaa elisngalua.
I started, and I was knowledgeable.
Taringenritaqamki-llu qanellrit yugmun egmirteqatarqamki
And when I didn’t understand what they said when I was going to pass on their words to a person.
Meaning-aarit apqaurluki yuungcarista taringenritaqamku wall’u nurse-aq.
I asked them about the meaning when I didn’t understand the doctor or the nurse.
Taringaqamku meaning-aara Yugtun taringcuararqamku tua-i egmirtaqluku yugmun.
When I understood its meaning a little in Yup’ik, I would pass it on to a person.
Iinrunek-llu ciki’irqatki, igaulluki tua-i, ellaita igaulluki label-aarinun aperturturluki taumun yugmun cikiraqluki.
And when they gave them medicine, they would right them down, indicating them on their labels, and give it to that person.
Tua-i tuaten ayagnillruunga.
That’s how I started.
Waten-llu tekitarkaugaqameng yuungcaristet wall’u iinriurtet
And when the doctors or nurses planned to arrive
Nallunricecaurrlua.
They started letting me know.
Tua-i wii elisnganrilama
Because I wasn't knowledgeable
Piyuumiitelqa pissiyaagpek’naku.
I wouldn’t follow my disinclination too much.
Tau͡gaam tua-i ikayuangnaqu’urluki qanemkun uuggun.
But I would always try to help them with my speech.
Tua-i-llu tang piqerluteng wiinga elitnauristet, elitnauristet ullagluki.
Then one day, I went to the teachers.
Yuum aqvaaqanga
When a person came to get me
Atra ellirraarluku qanellra pitacirramtun arenqialliqutii igaulluku
After putting their name, I’d write down what they say their problem was as best as I could
Qavcinek-llu ernernek ayagniucia ilait qanernacialaata.
And how many days it started since some don’t say it right away.
Tua-i iinrumek-llu cali wangnek tunllerkait nalluluki.
I also didn’t know how to give them medicine by myself.
Tua-i tamakut qanrutkellrenka elitnauristem apiatallerkaa utaqaaqluku.
About those things I talked about, I’d wait for the teacher’s lunch.
Apiatarqata igaq tauna agutaqluku, tunluku elitnauristeḿun.
When they had lunch, I’d bring that writing over, and give it to the teacher.
Qanercuuterutaqlua. Tua-i naaqerraarluki maliklua.
He would put me on the phone. After I read them, he’d go with me.
Kiingan qanerrsuutet elitnaurvigmi uitaluteng tamatum nalliini.
The only phones would be in the school at that time.
Imkut sugturpat piqarraallret elitnaurviit qamani BIA-mi piullratni.
Those first very tall ones upriver when they were BIA schools.
Tua-i elitnaurista report-araqluni yuungcaristeḿun.
The teacher would report to the doctor.
Tua-i-llu yuungcaristem yuk tauna cali qanercuutekun qalarucani igauqurluki wii tangvauralaamki.
Then when the doctor spoke to that person over the phone, he would write them down since I would watch them.
Elitnauristem igauqurluki qanellri, iinrut-llu tamakut.
The teacher would write what he said, including those medicine.
Assirinrilkan-llu cali
And if he doesn’t get better
Maavet hospital-aamun tamakut iinrut atulqellrin ikayunrilkatgu taitesqaqluku. Igauqurluki.
If the medicine he took didn’t help him, they’d say to bring him to the hospital here. I wrote these down.
Tua-i maligtaqulaatnga wiinga caperqenrirluki elitnauristet
Since they would obey me, I wasn’t intimidated by the teachers anymore
Uamtengramki nallunailngurmek.
Though it was clear I was taking up their time.
Tua-i-ll’ qanenriami iinrivigmun ayaullua taum elitnauristem.
Then when he stopped speaking, that teacher brought me to the clinic.
Alerqualua tua-i taum yuum atu’urkainek.
He would instruct me on what that person should do.
Tua-i tuaten piurluki.
I would do that with them.
Tua-i-llu nutaan 1960-mi
Then in 1960
Au͡gna man’a qallatelqa uum 1960-m ciukaa.
What I talked about was before 1960.
Nineteen-sixty-mi council-aat teguatnga, quyurrluteng December-aami ilaklua wiinga.
In 1960, the [tribal] council took me, meeting in December with me.
Tua-i-ll’ tuani
Then at that time
Qanrullua waniwa tegunilua, ikayualaasqelluki waten tekisngalriit.
They said that they’ve taken me, and to help those that arrive like this.
Tua-i qaill’ piviilama piyunarqekuma piciqnilua.
Since I had no choice, I said I would do it if I were able.
Tua-i tuaken nutaan 1960-mek-am cali au͡gna pellulriatun ayuqluni.
And since 1960, it was like what was before had passed.
Nineteen-sixty-mek taqevkenii, tau͡gaam elitnauristet ullagluki.
I didn’t quit in 1960, but I went to the teachers.
Tua-i-llu cat iliitni elitnaurista au͡gna, cimiraqluteng, cimiraqluteng.
Then one day, that teacher, they would be replaced, replaced.
Iliit au͡gna atra nalluyaguteksaitaqa ulla’agqa.
I went to one of them, whose name I haven’t forgotten.
Tau͡gaam aperturngaitaqa atra. Tua-i elisngaqapigtaqa.
But I won’t say their name. I know it clearly.
Ulla’agqa. Ciungani ullagaqluku.
I went to them. I’d go to them in the past.
Au͡gkutun tang ciuqlirmitun una pivkenani.
This one wasn’t like the others before them.
Qavcirqunek ullagcetqerluni qanrutaanga ullallemni
After going to them several times, they told me
Waten pianga: ellii-gguq iinriurteńguyarturluni wall’u yuungcaristeńguyarturluni tainrituq Kuigglugmun.
[S]he said this to me: [s]he didn’t come to Kwethluk to be a nurse or a doctor.
Elitnauriyarturluni-gguq taiguq.
[S]he said [s]he came to teach.
Tua-i-ll’ piaqa
Then I said to them
"Tua-i-wa wiinga-llu Kass’at qaneryaraat elisnganrilamku wiinga-ll’ elpeceńun ikayuryulalrianga elitnauristeńun ak’anek ciuvnek ayaglua."
"Since I do not know much about the English language, I also need you teachers’ help since way before you."
Tua-ll’ pianga, iganka-gguq naaqelarai.
Then [s]he said that [s]he reads what I write.
Camek-gguq ayuquciiteksaituq.
[S]he said that there was nothing confusing.
Wangnek-gguq report-alarlii imkut amkut aperturluki.
[S]he said that I should report by myself, briefing them over there.
Radio-tgun-gguq wangnek report-alarlii.
[S]he said that I should report on the radio by myself.
Tua-ll’ piaqa, "Usuuq, wiinga tang waniwa yuurterraanemnek tailrianga ukani kingumni una erneq tekilluku.
Then I said to them, "Hey you, since I was born, I have come from all the days before me to this day.
"Ataucirquungraan radio-t button-aarat negteksaitaqa."
"Never once have I pressed the radio’s button."
"Nuu, elitnaurciqamken. Elitnaurciqamken waniwa maliklunuk taglunuk."
"No, I will teach you. I will teach you if you come with me inland."
Piaqa, "Piyukuvet."
I said, "If you want to."
Eniinek anulluku tag’ukuk apiatam nalliinguan.
I took them out of their house, and we went inland since it was lunch time.
Tua-i-ll’ itramegnuk, imkut tua-i waten pitullratni iciw’ sassaunateng, yuungcaristem ikirtellerkaa utaqaluku.
Then when we went in, when they used to do this, you know, with no clocks, we waited for the doctor to be open.
Ciumek qanelriim qanellra niitaqamegteggu kiutunganaku tamatum nalliini.
When they heard the first one speaking, I think they would then answer.
Tua-i-ll’ uum elitnauristem pianga, "Tangvakia. Tangvlagluten qanerceciiqamken."
Then this teacher said to me, "Watch me. I will watch you and have you speak."
Angraqa.
I agreed.
Tua-i-ll’ tua-i imna qayagaurcuun pirraarluku uum qayagaurluki tua-i.
Then after making the call, [s]he called them.
Qamna-llu wangnun report-aqniluku qanrutekluku.
Then [s]he said to them that it was my report.
Tua-i-ll’ aren, tangvagluku eligartenritaqa.
Then, oh my, I didn’t learn right away from watching them.
Tau͡gaam tua-i una qallatellra, negtellri nalluluki imkullrit piluki.
But what they said, I didn’t know what they pressed.
Qaqiucami pianga
When [s]he was finished, [s]he said to me
Taum-llu ima tanem iinrut alerquutekai ellirraarluki tua-i yuungcarista qanrucamiu
And after [s]he put the instructions for the medicine, when [s]he spoke to the doctor
Waniwa-gguq wangnun repeat-arcetqatarai qanellri.
[S]he said [s]he was going to have me repeat what [s]he said.
Yuungcaristem cangelkenritaa. Pisqaa. Angraa.
The doctor was fine with it. [S]he told them to do it. [S]he agreed.
Tua-i-ll’ wangnun taicaku
Then when [s]he brought it to me
Ayaumiin umeksailan taicaku, taicamiu pianga, "Kitak’ au͡gna qanrutkesqelluku," tua-i-ll’ niicugniciqnilua.
Since it was still going and [s]he gave it to me, [s]he said to me, "Now, talk about that," then that [s]he would listen to me.
Ciuqamni uitaluni.
[S]he was in front of me.
Tua-i-llu qanellri tua-i niitniluki.
Then I said I heard what [s]he said.
Uum patient-aam alerquutai-llu iinrukai-llu niitniluki.
And I said I heard what the patient needs to do, and their medicine.
"Tua-i-qaa assirlua niitamken?"
"Did I hear you right?"
Iciw’ over-aarciiganii-llu wii. Over-aaneq nalluqapiggluku tamatum nalliini over-aatullratni.
You know, I couldn’t say "over" either. I didn’t know how to say "over" at that time when they used to say "over."
Aren, assirtuq-gguq. Assirtuq-gguq. Assirlua-gguq taringaqa.
Oh my, [s]he said it’s good. [S]he said it’s good. [S]he said I understood it well.
Tua-i-llu taqngamku tua-i taum elitnauristem pianga
Then when I was done with it, that teacher said to me
Waniwa-gguq waken ayaglua wangnek qayagaularciqua.
[S]he said that from then on, I would call by myself.
Piaqa, "Unuaqu kiima qayagaurngaitua. Maligciiqerpenga." Maligciiqaanga-gguq.
I said, "I won’t call by myself tomorrow. You’ll go with me." [S]he said [s]he’d go with me.
Tua-i-llu-am tua-i apiataurcan ullagluku, taum tua-i patient-aam taukut pii avaliqluki
Then when it was lunch time, I went to the, bringing with me that patient’s things
Aqvaaqatnga waten igauqurluki pilallruamki pitacirramtun tua-i.
Because when they got me, I’d write them down as best as I could.
Tua-i-llam ulliimni pianga, "Tua-i-mtaq qanercuuteqatartuten?"
Then when I went to them, [s]he said to me, "Are you going to make the call?"
Angerluku tua-i.
I said yes.
Kitak’-gguq tua-i...
[S]he said that I should...
Uum-am im' akwaugaq im' pilararkaulua, kitak-gguq taglua qayagauryarturlaku yuungcarista.
After the previous day, [s]he said that I should go inland and call the doctor.
Piaqa, "Maligglua. Elitellrunritaqa negtaallerkaq."
I said to them, "Come with me. I didn’t learn what to press."
Ellimauq-gguq. Iciw’ ellirpaumauq igarpak kanani.
[S]he said it’s on there. You know, it’s there in big letters down there.
Tua-i-ll’ maliklunuk taglunuk.
Then we went inland together.
Tua-i-ll’ pianga itramegnuk taukut tua-i negtaarraarluki naaqesqelluki ukut.
Then [s]he said to me when we went in to press these and read these.
Man’a apertuusqelluku Kuiggluk ellimalaan.
[S]he said to indicate Kwethluk since it’s put there.
Naaqluki taukut, tangvagluki naaqluki wavet.
Reading those, I looked at and read those here.
Ak’aniqanrituq. Tua-i pillangraata nunussiyaagpek’nani kiulua.
It wasn’t long. Though it was sudden, [s]he answered me without scolding too much.
Tua-i qanrulluku taumek.
I told them about that.
Qanruqaarluku, piurallri qanrutkurarraarluki
After telling them, after saying what [s]he said
Iinrunek tamakunek pisqelluku.
[S]he said that they should take that medicine.
Tua-i cali igaulluki tangvangraanga taum elitnauristem.
I also wrote them down though that teacher was watching me.
Taqngama tua-i taqlua.
When I was done, I was done.
Taum-am ik’iki pikilia wangnek-gguq iinrut tangerrluki amani paivcarturlaki.
[S]he told me to look at the medicine by myself over there and set them out.
Tangerciqai-gguq atakurpak. Eniitni uitaluni, yuungcaristem eniini.
[S]he said that [s]he would look at them that evening. [S]he was at their house, at the doctor’s house.
Taukut tau͡gken qanercuutet pamani elitnaurvigmi.
However, the phone was inland at the school.
Atam waten nalluluni arenqiatuq.
You see, it’s distressing when one doesn’t know like this.
Imkuuq, alingurnarquq yugnun. Yugnun alingurnarqessaaquq.
It’s, you know, scary for people. It’s scary for people.
Tau͡gaam imutun tua-i eliquralriatun ayuqnaqliniami tua-i maqariinarnganani.
But since it’s like it takes getting used to, it seemed that it became more [?manageable].
Ircaquq-llu nutngauciqenrillmenek nutngayuirulluni.
And what used to make the heart pound doesn’t make it pound anymore.
Cangalliurnanrirluni.
It isn’t bothered anymore.
Tua-i-llu qavcirqunek maligqaarlua uum kelucanek cikiraanga.
Then after [s]he went with me several times, [s]he gave me keys.
Taum pam’um kelucainek, enem-llu iinrut kelucaatnek cikiraanga.
[S]he gave me keys for [the school] up there, and the clinic’s keys.
Ullanrilnge’rmi wangnek elitnaurvik kelucaumaaqan ikirrluku iterlua qanercuutelaasqellua.
Even if I didn’t go to them when the school is locked, [s]he told me to open it, go in, and use the communication device.
Cali iinrut pisqaqateki atrarlua qanenrilnge’rma ikirrluku iinrut pilaasqelluki.
Also, when they said to prepare medicine, [s]he told me to go down, open it without notifying anyone, and prepare the medicine.
Tua-i tuatnayaurtua training-aarpailegma.
I started doing that before I went to training.
Tua-i-ll’ nutaan tuatnayaurteqerlua training-aamu eklua.
Then just when I started doing that, I got into training.
Nutaan tua-i training-aaryaurcama imkut aturluki piqacaarangnaqu’urlua tua-i tuaten piaqlua.
When I started training, I would try to do what I had done like that.
Malruurtellruukuk tau͡gaam ayainanmegni tamaani training-aaqatarluta.
But we became two as we were going back when we were going to train.
Malruulunuk waten.
There were two of us like this.
Tau͡gaam-am malruulunuk calingengamegnuk neryuunanuk.
But when the two of us started working, we would eat [lunch].
Apiatayuunanuk.
We wouldn’t have lunch.
Ten kela’agmi ikirtetuluni, yaavet ima tanem camun? Five kela’agmun pilaryugnarquq tamaani piqarraallemegni.
It would open at 10:00, until when would it go? I think it would be until 5:00 back when we started.
Apiatayuunanuk elitnaurista elitnauranek taivkarituan
We wouldn’t have lunch because the teacher sent students to us
Tua-i yaavet umellranun.
All the way until it closed.
Umgem-llu kinguani nutaan yuut aqvaaqatkuk tuavirtaqlunuk.
And after closing, when people came to get us, we would go there.
Tuavet ayagaqlunuk.
We would go there.
Unuungraan-llu qavamegni iterluteng tupagtaqatekuk tua-i wii-ll’ kiima pivkenii.
And when they came in at night while we were sleeping and woke us up, and I wasn’t the only one.
Tua-i aqvaaqatkuk taumun yugmun ayagaqlunuk.
When they came to get us, we’d go to that person[’s house].
Wiinga-llu tamaani elitnaullma kinguani tuar tang iinrut-llu tunllerkait ancurtukenrilriatun ellirluki nallunaitaralriit.
And after I trained then, it truly seemed that I was not reserved to even give them medicine [since] it they became clear.
Tau͡gaam imkut taringevlacakaqenka, atrit-llu taringevlacakenka pivkenaki.
But I would give out what I didn’t fully understand, including the names I didn’t fully understand.
Yugmun tunyuunaki nalqiguterraarpek’naki.
I wouldn’t give them to a person without explaining them.
Tua-i waten una wavet pitaluku.
This is it for that [story].
Au͡gna cali ciunra amllertuq.
There is a lot before what I just said.
Ayagniqarraallemnek ayaglua wavet training-aallemnun qanertua waten.
Starting from what I first started to my training, I’ve spoken about this.
Ava-i qanelriaten wani ayagniqarraallerpeni tua-i camek elitnaurutaunak pillruniluten.
You just said that when you first started, that you did it without any training.
Qaillun man’a tamana tua-i pingnatullren alerquutiitnek
How does this pertain to instructions on how to make your own living
Alerquutiitnun ekumauq, pingnatugluni-gguq yuk pairkauguq.
It’s in their traditional instructions, that a person must make their own living.
Qaillun ayagyuat tamatumun calimun pingnatugyaramun alerquryugngasikut wangkuta?
What can you instruct to us young poeple about how to work to make your own living like that?
Atam ava-i qanrutamken waten: "Wiinga umyuaqa aturluku pingnatugpek’naki
You see, I told you this: "I didn’t choose to work hard with them on my own
"Tau͡gaam tua-i yuungcaristem iinriurtem-llu qanellra egmirrluku, egmirteqtarturluku wii umyuaqa aturluku pingnatugpek’naku"
"But I passed the doctor’s and nurse’s message, passed it on in my hard work that wasn’t my choice."
Tuaten pillruunga. Ayagnillruunga avani camek iinrumek auluklerkaanek nallulua.
That’s what I did. I started back then without knowing how to take are of medicine.
Tua-i tau͡gaam elitnaurama tua-i eliteqtara’arlua eliteqtararalqa aturluku piqcaararaqlua.
But when I  went to training, I would do it according to what I had learned.
Qaillun-mi qitevtelangellrusit, wall’u Kass’atun taringelangellrusit tamaani wani elitnauristet tekitaangvailgata?
So, how did you learn to to speak English, or how did you learn to how understand English back before teachers came?
Tamatum-qaa ciungani elitnaullruuten?
Did you go to school before then?
Tamatum ciungani elitnaullruunga.
I went to school before that.
Tau͡gaam waniwa tamaani wiinga igaq elitnaueqerraallemni
But back when I first learned writing
Tau͡gaam taqnerurrlua-w’ tua-i ellakamnek ellanglua tayima pillilrianga elitnaullrullilrianga.
But when I became an adult, I think it was when I learned after becoming aware.
What year-aq nalluku.
I don’t know what year.
I can’t say what it was to this day, yet I went to school when it was in a building.
Elitnaurviuvkenani, enemni tau͡gaa.
It wasn’t a school, but in a house.
Tua-i tamaaken ayagluta elitnaurluta, kiituani elitnaurviliut.
We started going to school from then, and they eventually built a school.
Tua-i-llu elitnaurvilillratni elitnaurvimta wiinga-llu 5th grade-aq tekilluku taqlua.
Then when they made schools, in our school, I stopped at the fifth grade.
Tua-i tuaken grade-at fifth grade-aq tekilluku.
Those was my education until the fifth grade.
Tamaani-qaa elitnauqerraallerpeceńi elitnauristet Yugtun qancaunritellruaci wall’u-qaa qaillun qanercetaallruaceci-qaa?
Back when you first started learning, were you not asked to speak, or to speak in Yup’ik?
Aren, qanqaunritellruyaaqaakut
Oh my, they told us not to speak [Yup’ik]
Wangkuta qitevvneq nalluamteggu niicugnillrunritaput.
Since we didn’t know English, we didn’t listen to them.
Qitevteqtarararangluci-llu-qaa:
So did you start speaking English?
Ii-i, tua-i-ll’ pinginanemteńi wangkutnek, wangkutnun piyaurrngamta, elitnauristem-llu qanrutaqatkut taringyaurrrluku
And as we went, when we started [speaking amongst] ourselves, and we started understand when the teacher spoke to us.
Wangkuta-llu ellii qaneqtararaucaurrluku.
And we also started speaking to them.
Allat tamaa-i Kaatulit-llu pavani Kuigpagmiut waten qanlartut maa-i
Others, even the Catholics up on the Yukon, say this now
Tamaani ellait elitnauryukarraallratni anucimirqecetaaraqluki-llu-gguq Yugtun qanraqata.
Back when they first went to school, they said they’d be punished when speaking Yup’ik.
Qaillun elpeci pilallruicecei?
What did they do to you?
Wangkuta anucimirqcetaayuitaakut, Yugtun wangkutnun qalarutengramta.
They wouldn’t punish us even if we spoke Yup’ik to each other.
Tau͡gaam tua-i qanerluci Kass’atun elitnaurtuci. You, all the school boys and girls, speak English, not Eskimo language.
But you are speaking English as you go to school. You, all the school boys and girls, speak English, not Eskimo language.
Wangkuta qaneryaraqngamteggu
Since it’s our language.
Tamakut qanlallri elitnauristem wii man’a call’ tekilluku umyuaqelaranka.
I still remember what that teacher said to this day.
Ii-i, quyana wani qanemcilluta.
Okay, thank you for telling us the stories.
Aa-ang.
You’re welcome.
[?] uani Napaskiarmi cali ilakaat.
They’re also related to [?] in Napaskiak downriver.
Tua-i ugna Paul Guy-aaq ugkut Guy-at ugkut uani tutga’rqanka Napaskiarmi.
Paul Guy, the Guy family downriver in Napaskiak are my grandchildren.
Atii tau͡gaam wii yuk’aqa.
But his father is my child.
And Andrew Guy-aq-llu au͡gna tutgarqelluku?
And Andrew Guy is your grandchild?
Ii-i, tutgarqelluku.
Yes, he’s my grandchild.
Nallunricaaqaqa.
I do know him.
Ii-i.
I see.
Uumi-llu... eleven-aarulliniluteng tutgaraten.
And recently... so, you have eleven grandchildren.
Ii-i.
Yes.
Phillip Guy-am irniari, amaqlian-llu irniari waten
Phillip Guy’s children, and his older brother’s childre like this
Twelve-aarullruyaaqut. Six-aaqetaarlutek tamarmek yungqerrsaaquk.
There were 12. They both have six children each.
Tau͡gaam amaqlian yua atauciq allragni yuunrillruuq.
But one of the children of the older brother passed away last year.
Iluperangeksaituten-qaa?
Have you not gotten any great-grandchildren yet?
Iluperangeksaitevkenii.
I did get great-grandchildren.
Iluperangqerrlua waniwa. Qavcinek ima tam’ iluperangqellrianga?
I have great-grandchildren. How many great-grandchildren do I have again?
Atam Kiarrngualuk
You see, Kiarrngualuk
Au͡gna-wa kinguqliq...
Then the younger one...