Living a life that is not as hard, nor should... not a very difficult life.
Tua-llu?
Ready?
Maa-i-rpak elitnautuukut, elitnaurvigluteng-llu.
Now, we go to school, and there are schools.
Elitnauriyaraq tang cimilria, ayuqenrilria.
You see, teaching has changed, not the same anymore.
Elitnauqerraallemni tayima Kass’atun qanerciigatellruunga.
When I first went to school, I couldn’t speak English.
Tau͡gken Kass’acetun qanerciigalnge’rma qanrucimalallruunga
However, even though I couldn’t speak English, I would be told
Elitnaurviim-gguq nunautiini wall’u avatiini uitakuma Kass’aturrlainaq qalareskilii.
They said that if I was on school grounds or around it, that I should only speak in English.
Tamana tuaten ayuqenrirtuq.
That’s not like that anymore.
Maa-i village-aanun ayagaaqamta
Now, when we travel to villages
School-ani-llu piaqama waten murilkurnaurtua elitnauristet elitnauriaqluteng tayima something called "bilingual education."
And when I go to schols, I would observe teachers teaching something called "bilingual education."
Taringumatacimtun-llu tayima tuaten elitnaurvigni tamakunek elitnauritulini pitangqerraqan Yugtun-llu qaneryaramek tayima elitnauritulliniut.
And from my understanding, when schools have those kinds of teachers, they apparently also teach how to speak Yup’ik.
Cumikarnaqsaaqvaa-llu tuaten pilliniata.
We must may attention since they’re doing that.
What about the schools today?
So much have changed since I first stepped into a classroom.
At one point, although some of us are not able to speak English
We were actually prohibited in some instances from speaking our language.
Yet, we didn’t know how to speak English.
Like I stated, so much have changed since that time.
Today, throughout my travels throughout the region, I’ve seen something called "bilingual education."
It’s my understanding that in these instances, that Yup’ik is taught
And that Yup’ik, in some instances, is actually encouraged to be spoken on school grounds under those circumstances.
This is very encouraging because one of the basis of our society is our language.
Tua-llu?
Ready?
Umyuangcaqaqernaurtukut.
Let us ponder for a moment.
Ca pininrua piniqapiggluni?
What is the most powerful?
Atam.
Look.
Aperyarat, wall’u qaneryaraq. Waten wangkuta qaneryaraput piniqapigtuq.
Words, or language. Our language is powerful.
Elitnauristeḿa iliit angutngurtellruuq.
One of my teachers has become an old man.
Waten-llu qanruartelallruanga:
And he used to tell me this:
"Kitaki, camek ilavet aperyaranek aturluni qalaruskaten niicugniurqina."
"Now, when our peer speaks to you with words, listen."
One of the strongest sources of force known to mankind is words.
This source of force is known to all the societies, although they may not be able to communicate with each other.
Yet, it’s the very words, that is one of the strongest sources of force in the universe.
Primarily because of the fact, when you say something using words
What you have stated forever escapes through your mouth to the people.
That’s why I think one must be very careful in their use of words
Because at some point, what you stated using words at some point may come back and haunt you.
Tuamta-llu
And so
Wangkuta ayagyualriani arcaqerluta makut ciuliaput iliini takaqeksaitaput.
Especially we young people have sometimes not shown these elders respect.
Takarnaqsaaqut. Takarnaqeqapigcaaqut.
They must be treated with respect. They must be treated with great respect.
Yuuyaram-wa qaillun-llu yuullerkaa, yuukumta pillerkamteńek qanrutetuyaaqaitkut.
They tell us about the Yup’ik way of life, how one should life, and what we should do in our lives.
Atam.
Look.
Camek qanrutetuitkut ikayuryugyaaqngamegtekut cakviussiyaagluta yuusqumanrilamegtekut.
They tell us things because they want to help us, because they don’t want us to struggle too much as we live.
Qanellrit-llu tayima takarnaqeqapiggluteng.
And what they said deserves great respect.
Ciumuassiyaagluta piksailkumta, iliini-llu umyuaqeqa’aqluki alerquuteput yuukumta cakviussiyaagngaicugnarqukut.
If we do not do things we’re told not to do, and if we sometimes remember our instructions in our lives, we will not struggle too much.
What about respect?
We must respect our elders.
They alone are the people who can speak about life based on experiences of life.
They alone are the people who can speak about life based on experieces of life.
When they’re speaking about life based on experience of life, you cannot be any stronger.
If we respect and listen to what they have to say
And perhaps remember a very little portion of what they have to say to us
And perhaps remember a very little portion of what they have to say to us.
We might find that living this life will be a little bit easier to cope with.
Remember, when they are giving us an advice
That advice is based on the very basis of their experience, and they want to share that with us.
That advice is based ont he very basis of their experience, and they want to share that with us.
We should be thankful for what they have to tell us.
Tayima waten alerquagaqamegtekut ukut ciuliamta
When our elders instruct us like this
Alerqualaraakut ikuuyuryuumiamegtekut.
They instruct us because they want to help us.
Alerquagaqamegtekut alerqualaraitkut yuullerteng tangerrluku, allat-llu yuullrat tangerrluku ikayuryugyaaqngamegtekut.
When they instruct us, they instruct us based on their own life, and based on other’s lives because they want to help us.
Tua-llu?
Ready?
Ava-i au͡gkut qanellrenka amllenricaaqut, tau͡gaam wangkutnun ayagyuanrulrianun ataurtut.
What I just had to say wasn’t much, but they are connected to us younger people.
Wangkuta-wa ayagyualriani, ayagyuarturalrianun ataut.
We young people, they are connected to us young people.
Tua-llu?
Ready?
Ciuliarurtellriit-mi wall’u taqnerurtellriit?
What about those who’ve become elders or adults?
Cauga caliarkaat wall’u ikayuutekaat?
What is their job, or the way they help?
Umyuartequrallemni ellaita-llu ikayuryugngaitkut.
When I think about it, they can help us too.
Tayima qanruqu’urqatkut assirciquq.
If they keep speaking to us, it will be good.
Qaillun yuuyaramta ayagturallerkaa pitekluku qalaruskatkut assiryartuq.
If they speak to us about how our lives should go, it would be good.
Tua-llu?
Ready?
Qanqainarcetevkenaki camek qanrutaqatkut quyavikaqluki pikumteki assirciquq.
Without letting them just speak, when they tell us something, it would be good if we thanked them.
Maa-i alerquutait eliqu’rqumteki piyuumiutait-llu assiryaryugnarquq.
Now, it would be good if we learned their instructions and their desires.
Thus far, I have been talking about the responsibilities of those of us who are young, maybe relatively young
Thus far, I have been talking about the responsibilites of those of us who are young, maybe relatively young
And lastly, maybe for those of us who are young in mind, heart, and soul.
What about the elderly, or the elders?
What is their responsibility? Or, better yet, do they have any responsibility?
Yes, in my very humble opinion, they also have some responsibility to us.
They must speak out as a group about our cultural values
Before what is left of our values is gone.
I believe, again very humbly, that it is the responsibility of our elders
To teach us what we must do to continue with our values.
But again, it is the responsibility of those of us who are young, relatively young, and young in mind
But again, it is the responsibility of those of us who are young, relatively, young, and young in mind
To hear and listen what they have to share with us.
I think when they’re talking about values, Yup’ik values
They’re talking about something that sometimes is hard to grab.
Yupiit piciryaraitnek yuut qalartaqata iliini taringesciigatnarqeńgalngurnek qalartelartut, tau͡gken tuancaaqluteng.
When people speak about Yup’ik traditions, they sometimes say things that we can’t seem to understand, yet they’re right there.
Ayagyuanrullemni imumi avani apa’urluma pissuryaramek elitnaullruanga.
When I was younger back then, my grandfather taught me how to hunt.
Qaillun angutem yuullerkaanek elitnautullruanga.
He used to teach me about how a man should live.
Ayuqucirtuutai ilii tayima aturluku piaqama cakviussiyaaksaitua.
When I would sometimes adhere to some of his instructions, I wouldn’t struggle too much.
Maurluma-llu
And my grandmother
Tayima qanrucimalartua, maurluma-gguq arnam qaillun yuullerkaanek neviarcaq qalarut’lallrua.
I am told that my grandmother would speak to a young lady about how a woman should live.
When I was a young man, one of the things that my grandfather taught me was how to go after game.
I was quite fortunate in that I had that privilege, I had the opportunity to be taught those skills.
I was quite fortunate in that I had that privelage, I had the opportunity to be taught those skills.
Whenever I have an opportunity, I try to share that, share what was taught to me.
But sometimes I don’t. That’s my fault
But sometimes I don’t. That’s my fault.
Although I was raised by my parents, I spent a lot of my time with my grandfather.
In looking back, I understand
That my grandmother used to teach values that should be respected and gained by the young ladies on how to be a lady.
Tayima ciuliamta qaillun yuuyaramek qalarutaqa’tkut wall’u elitnauraqatekut
When our elders speak to us or teach us how to live
Quyavikaqluki pikumta assirciquq.
It would be good if we thanked them.
Atauciq, atauciumek ciuliamta qanrutetuitkut, tamalkumta-llu nalluvkenaki.
Our elders tell us one thing, and all of us know them.
Yup’ut Yupiit qaneryaramek waten ayuqellriamek qanlartut:
Our Yup’ik people say a piece of traditional wisdom that’s like this:
Yuk-gguq unguvaqallermini taktaciatun eliqurciquq.
They say that a person will learn for the length of their life.
Piciuguq.
It’s true.
Qaillun-llu wangkuta yuuyararput, Yupiit-llu piciryarait, Yupiit-llu piyuumiutait piyukumteki
And if we want our way of life, and Yup’ik traditions, and the things Yupiit desire
Wangkutnek eliskumta ciuliamteńek wall’u Yuullgutemteńek assirciquq.
It would be good if we learned by ourselves from our elders or our fellow Yupiit.
What was taught to us by our elders is something that we should be sharing with others.
They taught us values of life, hoping that we’re going to be learning something in life.
I think in turn, we must, we should and must teach the children what was taught to us by our elders.
There is a saying within the Yup’ik society that goes something like this:
"A person will not stop learning as long as they can breathe."
This is very true, because as I travel throughout the region, I’ve been adviced, or given advice by our elders
And I’ve learned on a daily basis what our way of life is.
I think if we are to continue with Yup’ik values
We must seek to learn all that we can from our elders, from others
As long as the Creator is generous enough to allow us to continue to breathe.
Ava-i au͡gkut qanrutkurallrenka amllenricaaqut.
There wasn’t a lot that I had to say.
Tau͡gaam piyunartacirramtun qalarqu’rtua
But I’ve been speaking to the best of my ability
Cikiutellemnek-wa ciuliamteggun.
Through the gifts I received from our elders.
Qaillun-wa Yupiit piciryarait piugurluteng piarkaukata
If Yup’ik culture is to somehow continue
Tayima ciuliamteńek eliskumta, tua-i-llu elitelput waten ilamteńun qalarutkaqluki.
If we learn from our elders, then speak about what we learned to those around us.
Tuamta-llu ayagyualrianun qalarutkaqluki pikumteki assirciqsugnarquq.
Then it would be good if we also spoke about them to young people.
In closing, I would like to say that what I had to say was not very much, however, I did the best that I could under the circumstances.
What I shared with you this morning was what was shared with me, or, what I had learned from our elders.
I would like to take this opportunity to thank the Kuskokwim Community College
For giving me an opportunity to share what little knowledge I have gained from our elders, from others
Over the last several, over the last couple decades.
Nangnermek-llu ukut Kuskokwim Community College-aat quyaviksuganka
And lastly, I want to thank Kuskokwum Community College here
Waten ilagarluci au͡gkunek-wa tua-i capeqluki
For being with you here today about what I found difficult
Caliaqesqellra caperqengramku tayima qalarutkuraranka.
Through I found it difficult to work with, I spoke about them.
Tau͡gaam cali waten elitellemteńun kinguliamteńun au͡gkunun ayagarkat pitekluki quyavikanka.
But also, I thank them for this, for the sake of what we learned and our descendants who are going to go.
At this point, I would, I’ll turn the show back to...
[?] pilii.
Allow me to [?].
Ii-i.
Yes.
Taqsukluten-wa.
I assume you’re done.
Ii-i, taqua.
Yes, I’m done.