Tuamta-llu cali can’giircuuciryaurcami alerquagurlua asgurcuutnek.
Then when he started making blackfish traps, he instruced me on the [asgurcuutet].
Kuimteńi tamaani Qissunami asgurcuucirluni alerqualua taluyilartuq.
When he used an [asgurcuun] there in the Qissunaq river, he would instruct me as he fish trapped.
Cali tua-i pau͡gani kuicuarni kelumteńi uksuarmi aniullratni can’giircuutet civvluki.
Also, when the creeks inland from the main river snowed in the winter, he set the blackfish traps.
Tua-i unugpak [?erneqir’uurturnaurtut].
They would [be set] all night [?into the day].
Piyaurcama wangnek tua-i alerquutai aturluki pingnaquraqlua.
When I started going by myself, I would always try to heed his instructions.
Tua-llam caqerlua negirlua uatemteńi Qissunam ceńiini aqesgircuutnek, cukarak-llu kapuarrlukek.
Then one day, I set willow ptarmigan snares downriver from us on the banks of Qissunaq, and stuck the stakes.
Tua-i-ll’ maaten neganka takullemini piaqa ingna aqesgircuutemni ingna tungulria ingna tekicartu’rqa pekluni.
Then when I went to check on my willow ptarmigan snares, I found something black moving as I was about to reach it.
Napingalliniluni imarmiutaq.
Apparently, a mink had gotten caught.
Maaten imna pelacinaggaumilria-wa negaq tauna kepeksaitellia-llu.
I found that while the snare was also just twine, it didn’t cut it.
Qukamikun negalliniluni.
It had gotten snared in its middle.
Qaill’ tua-i picirkailamku kaugtuutarkamenk yuarlua tangvaglaamku ellii tuquciaqan imarmiutarnek.
Since I didn’t know what else to do, I looked for a club since I watched him kill minks.
Uyaqurrit, uyaqurrit teguqerluki qipngamni tua-i tangvaglaucimtun.
I took its neck and twisted it as I used to watch.
Tau͡gaam tuquqainanrituq.
But it didn’t just die.
Qiptulliniut wani qet’nge’rmeng, inglugtun tau͡gaam tegulriani nutaan.
They twist though they’re held, but [die] when held on either side.
Pinauraanga, "Tuaten-gguq pisciigataqata ircaqut qecuk’arluku tuqutellrat assinrulartuq." Alerqualua.
He’d tell me, "When they can’t die like that, it’s better to kill them by pulling their hearts." He instructed me.
Tua-i tuaten pituriluki.
I started doing that.
Kapkaanarturyaurcama-llu yuilqumi anerteqaqan imarmiutaq tekitaqamku tua-i ircaqu͡ra qecuk’arluku egmian tuquq’ernaurtut.
When I started trapping in the wilderness and mink is alive when I reach it, I’d pull out its heart, and they die right away.
Kaviaret tau͡gken cali kapkaanaq’ngamun tekitaqama tua-i ciugarrluku tau͡gaam uyaqurrit tuqucilartuq tangvagaqamni.
However, when I come across a fox in a steel trap, I would watch him lift its head up and kill it by its neck.
Elliitun tua-i piuraqlua.
I do it like him.
Tuamta-ll’ nucirlua ayagyaurcama, alerqurnauraanga assi’irqan cella maligcuarturaqama kaviarnek
Then when I started traveling with a gun, he would instruct me when the weather was good while chasing a fox
"Pitsaqa’artevkenaku pitaqekuvgu assiqan cella caviggalgira’arluten amiirrarniaran tuani.
"Should you catch it when the weather’s good, bring a little knife and skin it there.
"Uqamalkutaqevkenaku kemga ut’ruqu’urniaran."
"Don’t weigh yourself down with its flesh and bring it home."
Tua-i tuatnaqarraallemni tangvaglaucimtun ellii
When I first did that, as I used to watch him
Pamyuit ullirtevkenaki, qaill’ piluki keggmaqaraqarraarluki man’a pamyuq nucuglaraa.
Without cutting the tail, he would somehow bite the tail and pull it out.
Tua-i au͡g’arnartuq im’ pamyuq cavkenani.
The tail would come off without a problem.
Tuatnaqarraallemni keggmaqtaryaaqekeka man’a qainga.
When I first did that, I tried biting the skin here.
When I pulled the tail, I think I only took off the fur, but the skin was left.
Ak’aki neng’uq imna melquq pamyuq.
So much of the tail fur stretched.
Quyanricaaqua. Tua-i katurqaarluku ut’rulluku.
I wasn’t happy. After I gathered it, I brought it home.
Tauna-llu pamyua kepluku, enra kepluku piciqngaku elliin tekiskema.
And I cut that tail, cut the bone, because that’s what he used to do.
Tua-i tekicama mingqucelluki aanamnun tamakut amia au͡g’arraarluku.
When I arrived, I had my mother sew them on after I removed the skin.
She sewed the fur on and made it into a tail.
Alerqualua nutaan pianga carrarmek-wa caquqerluki keggmaqa’arlaasqelluki qamkut
He finally instructed me to cover them with something and bite deep inside
Kiitellratnun amiit tamakut.
Until those skins come off.
Cenkarmek tau͡gken piaqama qaill’ tuqutesciigat’la’rqa anerteqaqan.
However, when I catch a land otter, I can’t kill it when it’s alive.
Tuquqainayuituq, cenkaat.
It doesn’t easily die, land otters.
Tua-i cayaqlirluku tua-i kaugtuarpaka’arqamni ilii tuquurainalartuq.
When I keep bashing them, some of them finally steadily die.
Mermiut pingrilnguut, mermiut piaqameng, eplalliniut egmianun mermetaqameng.
Non-aquatic animals apparently drown right away in water.
Tua-i tamakut pissuryarat alerquutai piyaurcama tua-i aturturluki.
When I started, I followed his instructions on hunting.
Catairut’ng’ermi-llu tua-i alerqualua tuaten piurlaasqellua tua-i alerquucimitun.
And even if he’s gone, he instructed me to do that according to his instruction.
Uum cali maliksaurcamia Peqiciram atiin cavailegmi, ug’um Peqiciram atii
When Peqiciraq’s father starting going with me before he passed away, Peqiciraq’s father downriver
Cali nutaan yuilqumun ayagallua yaaqvanun qimugtetgun.
He brought me deep in to the wilderness far away by dog sled.
Maligqura’aqluku.
I followed him.
[?Ciisqeḿaqlemteńi] uivluku pissuuteturaqlunuk.
We’d go around [?] and hunted.
Unavet cali ayagaqamnuk Qucilgaq uivluku tamaani pitulunuk.
And when we went down there, going around Qucilgaq, we’d [hunt] there.
Ii-i, qanerturluten arulairpek’nak. (Ai?) Qanerturluten.
Okay, keep speaking, don’t stop. (What?) Keep speaking.
Tua-i Qucilgaq uivaqamegnegu qimugtetgun calanrituq.
When we went around Qucilgaq by dog sled, nothing would happen.
Tau͡gaam up’nerkami qayakun malikaqamku, up’nerkilaami uani uatemteńi Quuqamek pilallratni
But when I went with him in the spring by kayak, because he would set up spring camp downriver from us where they called it Quuqaq
Atairutma tekitellrani pia qanrulluku
When my late father arrived, he told him
"Tauna anelraulluku cakmani. Uum-llu anngiin ayagasngaitaa," Eritailnguq piluku.
"Take him downriver. His brother won’t travel with him, " referring to Eritailnguq.
"Ayagaqurarru cakmani nunavni. Anelraa." Malikuraasqellua.
"Take him to your village downriver. Go downriver." He told me to follow along.
Tua-i qayakun uivaqamegnegu Qucilgaq
When we went around Qucilgaq by kayak
Ciuqlirmi piqarraallemegni tevcarat yuaqaqluki.
When we first did it, we’d look for portage routes.
Kepngamegnegu kelutmun, nanvamun qakvaamnuk
When we cut inland through there and came up on a lake
Tevcarat yuaqaqluki tamaaggun, tamaavet-gguq Elurtulim kangranun.
We’d look for portage route through there, to the headwaters of what they called Elurtuli.
Tua-i kanaamegen’gu carvanian uatmun nutaan cetulunuk.
When we went down to it, since the currrent was strong, we went downriver.
Nequturian-ll’ un’gani akiqliqu’urlunuk anguanglunuk kanaqlagcurlunuk.
And when it widened downriver, we started rowing side by side hunting for muskrats.
Tua-i pivakarlunuk iliikun cenkarmek-ll’ pairkengnaurtukuk tamaani pilrianek.
As we went, we’d sometimes pass land otters swimming there.
Tua-llam caqerlunuk cenkarnek pillmegni igvaarrluki ua-i qanikcarkun tagluteng.
Then as we saw land otters, we appeared on them going up to the land through the snow.
Cetamauluteng, aanameggnek cunaw’ ilangqellinilriit.
There were four, apparently with their mother.
Pianga, "Kitaki tevcaraulliata tuaggun tev’ut."
He said to me, "Okay, they’re going through there probably because it’s a portage route."
Maligarrluki tua-i.
We followed them.
Nutka teguluku, qayaqa unilluku, maligarrluki.
I took my gun, left my kayak, and followed them.
Qau͡ga-i tangrramki nanvarrarmun kanalliniluteng. Nanvarraq uivarrluku.
When I saw them upriver, they went to a pond. We went around the pond.
Pika-i qakvaata ullagluki.
When they went out up there, we went to them.
Maaten imna tekitanka tevcaratgun tumlliut. Maa-i-ll’ ataam kuigmun tamaavet Elurtulimun una ava-i kanalliniluteng.
I arrived there and found tracks on the portage route. And they went down to the river again, here to Elurtuli.
Alakarrlua tuani tangrramegteńga.
They noticed me when they saw me.
Taqililuteng puguralartut tamakut cenkaat.
Those land otters [?] when they appear.
Taikanirluteng pugurallratni uirraluteng, tuaten aaniit tauna.
When they appeared coming closer, they growled, even their mother.
Nutegluku, taqinarpek’naku tau͡gaam.
I shot it, but didn’t instantly kill it.
Ayanrilan, ika-i akimnun tagngan can’gurnermun nutaan qayaqa aqvaluku.
When he didn’t go, since he went up to the grassy area across from me, I went to get my kayak.
Utaqaurallinilua.
He was waiting for me.
Pianga, "Kuigmun kanaqata mat’um ilakaa. Wii uivurciqua anguarturlua. Elpet tevluten tuaggun maliggluki."
He said to me, "If they go down to the river, it’s part of this. I will go around rowing. You portage through there with them."
Tauna tayim’ tuqungraan-tuq akma nall’artellruku un’ aniit.
Though their mother died across there, I hoped he’d come across it.
Tua-i qerarlua. Aturkuki tevcarat tevlua.
I crossed. I portaged through the route.
Tekicamku qayaqa atrarrluku piaqa tuquksaitelliuq cali.
When I got to it and lowered my kayak, I saw that it hadn’t died yet.
Tekicamni atraqerrluni tau͡gaam elluaciqevkenani.
When I reached it, it went down, but it wasn’t doing very well.
Twenty-two-ngqerrama canimelan pulngarrluku nutaan pitaqluku.
Since I had a .22 and it was close, I shot it again and caught it.
Irniari tau͡gken maani au͡gatemni piluteng, puguraluteng.
Its young, however, were popping up around me here.
Tua-i nut’gayaaqluki.
I tried shooting at them.
Pitangyugpakarluki anagialuki. Tamariluki tayima.
Since I was in too much of a hunting frenzy, they ran away from me. I lost them.
Tauna tau͡gaam aaniit.
[I only caught] their mother.
Utaqaurluku tauna malika.
I waited for my companion.
Muluuraqerluni yaaqsilliniami cingik tamana.
He tarried since that point was far.
Ama-i cingqullagtuq yaaqsigpek’nani.
He made a [gun] popping sound over there not far away.
Tekicami pianga, ataucimek-gguq cenkarmek tuani pairrluku nutegtuq.
He said when he arrived that he passed one land otter there and shot.
Pianga, "Taukut piyagaat ilakngataat. Piyagaunrituq-gguq. Angelriaruuq-gguq."
He said to me, "I think it’s one of those young ones. It’s not young. It’s big."
Piyagai taukut tayim’ tamariamki pianga, "Taglunuk-wa piani nunapigmi qavartara’arluk unugpak anguallruamnuk.
When I lost those young, he said to me, "We should go inland and set up camp on the tundra since we rowed all night.
"Qavarta’arluk piani nunapiim qainganun qayapuk tagulluki." Uciirlunuk tagulluki.
"Let’s set up camp inland on the tundra and bring up our kayaks." We unloaded and brought them up.
Tamaaken uqviarrlunuk pilunuk. Cainiliurlunuk yuuraqara’arrlunuk. Quunirluni.
We gathered willows there. We made a kettle of hot water and drank something hot. The weather was calm.
Piqerluni pianga, "Atam igvalria cakem’ kanaqlaunritell’. Min’get unegkut ukatmurtellriit."
As we were there, he said to me, "Look, something that’s not a muskrat appeared downriver. The wake of something is coming from downriver."
Maaten piaqa minegpaggauluteng. Kanaqlauvkenani.
I saw that it left a big wake. It wasn’t a muskrat.
Igvaqerluni-ll’ tayima, tagngami tayima alainqigtevkenani.
When it appeared and went inland, it didn’t appear again.
Pianga, "Nunii ugna paqteqarru qayan atrarrluku."
He said to me, "Take down your kayak and check where it went downriver."
Maaten imna tauna min’girtellran nunii tekitaqa tevcaraullinilriit makut.
I reached where its wake ended, and found a portage route here.
Culurrlua tuavet, .22-q teguluku, taglua maliggluku.
I docked there, took the .22, and went inland along it.
Nanvarrarni piani keluqvaarni kanartua, kanani cikumi kan’a tungulria pektaqluni.
I went down to a pond far inland, and something black down on the ice would move.
Taungulliniluni.
It was that thing.
Malruurrlutek avvlutek, ataam katurtaqlutek.
It would split into two, then come together again.
Atauciq tauna tuunrituli Qupanuarmek pilallrat
That one who had shamanistic powers whom they called Qupanuaq
Tua-i ataucirquunrilngurmek takumni tuunriqaqulartuq.
He’s excercised his shamanistic powers in front of me more than once.
Tua-i caqerlua Cuukvagtulimun maligullua, tuantelliniluni.
One time, I followed people to Cuukvagtuli, and he was there.
Tuunrivkallratni-am qasgimi atairutka-ll’ maligucami aturteńgulaami
When they had him call upon his spirit helpers in the community house, and my late father went since he was a singer
Akiqliqluteng cauyarluteng qasgimi aturlaameng.
They drummed side by side since they sang in the community house.
Qavaqallinilua cauyalriik taukuk.
I fell asleep [betwen] those two drummers.
Una wani Nick Beans-aq canimni, anngaqa-llu akunleragni wii qavarlua, qavallinilua.
I fell asleep between Nick Beans beside me, and my older brother.
Tua-i tupak’artua qasgi man’a cingqullagluni, aglut pagkut imluteng ayimqelluteng.
I woke up to the community house here cracking loudly, the center beams up there splitting and caving in.
Tua-i mak’aruciqa tau͡gaam tua-i. Temlilua qavamni.
That was all I awoke to. I had apparently had a lucid dream.
Cauyat kaugtullratni cingqullalriaruluki pagkuuluki aglut, ayimqellriaruluki niigarrluki.
With the pounding drums, I heard them as the center beams up there cracking loudly as they split.
Anqerrnalua umyuarteqellrianga tayima.
I had the thought to run out.
Maklua qaniqnginanrani tauna uani amigmi imarnitegnek uligluni.
I got up as he was saying his shamanistic incantation at the door, with [the patient] covered with a seal gut rain parka.
Ukuk-llu elucira’artek nangengqalutek-am.
And these two dancers were standing.
Tekicamku-gguq tauna qaniqellria teguluku maaggun nuqtaqa, kanavet-llu nacitnun aqumkallagluni.
They said that when I reached the shaman incanting, I took him here, pulled, and he fell on his behind down on the floor plank.
Tua-i-gguq qaill’ picirkailami atairutma pia, "Aullu-wa-i piluaqanritaaten. Taum picurlagaaten.
They said since my later father couldn’t do anything, he told me, "My goodness, he didn’t do something good to you. He scorned you.
"Temliuq-am. Temlituuq. Temliluni piaten."
"He’s sleepwalking again. He sleepwalks. He did that to you sleepwalking."
Tua-i aqumngami-gguq Qupanuaq qanertuq, "Temlikuni-gguq, qavamini pikuni picurlanrilkiinga."
They said when Qupanuaq sat up, he said, "If he’s sleepwalking, if he did it in his sleep, he didn’t scorn me."
Canritniluku. Canritniluni.
He said it was fine. He said he was fine.
Tua-i ciinllugguaralua. Itraama anqertellinilua.
I regretted it. When I went in, I ran out.
Tau͡gaam qanrutenritaanga [?] Nick Beans-am. Maaten tekitaqa una nayangarluni aqumgaurluni.
But Nick Beans didn’t say anything to me. I reached him and found that he was nodding as he was sitting.
Cunaw’ engelarciiganani yugyiimi qasgi.
It turned out he couldn’t laugh because there was a lot of people in the community house.
Tua-i waten tau͡gaam piurluni, uitavkenani tua-i.
He only did this, not staying still.
Temciyugyaaqluni engelarluni pisciiganani.
He found it funny, but couldn’t laugh.
Tua-i ataam inarrlua, qavallinilua nutaan tayima.
I lay down again and was asleep for good.
Tuani-llu unuaquani-ll’ qanrutevkenii tamaani.
And the next day, they didn’t tell me there.
Cuqartalegmun tau͡gaam tekicamta utercamta nutaan aanairutka qanemcilluku Nick Beans-am
Only when we returned to Cuqartalek, Nick Beans told my late mother the story
Tangvalliniamia tuani Qupanuaq tauna aqumkallagcetlemni.
Since he watched me making Qupanuaq fall on his behind then.
Qacigtenricaaqut-gguq nepailameng. Qasgimi tua-i engelarciiganateng yugyaam[eng] tuunriameng.
They said it was hard because they were quiet. They couldn’t laugh in the community house because the shaman was practicing his powers in front of many people.
Taukuk-llu eluciraralriik tekicamkek mengelvartaarraarlukek anqerrlua.
And when I reached the two dancers, I pushed them to the side and ran out.
Kamilangqiima kumlangata tau͡gaam elaturrami amigmi it’ganka kumlangata tupaglua.
Since I was barefoot, when my feet got cold in the door of the entry porch, I woke up.
Pam’um nuqtaqiinga tunumnek. Maaten kingyarlua piaqa anngairutma nuqtallianga itrullua.
Someone behind me pulled me from my back. I looked back and saw that my late older brother was pulling me inside.
Kiaresngaacaaqellrianga cakneq qaill’ picirkailama, temlilliniama-am tuani.
I felt very awkward because I couldn’t do anything since I sleepwalked there.
Tau͡gaam tekicama nutaan Nick Beans-am aanairutka qanemcilluku.
Only when I arrived did Nick Beans tell my late mother the story.
Qanruyutengqellruukut arnani atakumi-llu tarritesqevkenata, ullagatesqevkenata-llu.
We women had traditional wisdom not to wanter in the evening, and not to have guests.
Una tua-i wiii aanamnek arcaqerluku, aanamnek atamnek-llu waten:
This was important [wisdom] from my mother, my mother and father:
Qalartellriik-gguq camek assiilngurmek niicugninrillakek.
They said I shouldn’t listen to people speaking bad things.
Tua-ll’ qalarucilriamek tangerquma, qalarucilriamek tangerquma
Then if I see someone giving instruction, if I see something giving instruction
Ullagluku nutaan niicugnisqelluku inerquutnek qalartellria.
They told me to go and listen to the one speaking about admonishments.
Tamaani nepaitellruut.
They were peaceful back then.
Tau͡gaam qaneryaram mat’um qanrutkellrit makut wani
But these things that traditional wisdom speaks about
Qanrutkumalria tekirqeput. Murilkelluci elpeci yuuci.
We come to the time spoken about. You, live carefully.
Murilkengnaqluci
Try to be careful
Una tekitaqan tangnerrarpek’naku elitaq’larnaurci, cangayung’erpeci-llu cangakevkenaku.
So that you will not be surprised but recognize what you come across, and not be taken aback though you do not find it right.
Una-llu qanlerayulria angun wall’u arnaq, qastuluni qalarculria
And this man or woman that speaks harshly, one who speaks loudly
Tauna tua-i assikevkenaku.
They do not like that.
Waten-llu tan’gaurluq ayagyuaq takuanun qanleralluku yugnek niitesterluni callallerkaa umyuaqevkenaku
And speaking harshly to this young boy with people listening without regard to how he will react
Tamaa-i tamana caniluku.
They said something was wrong with it.
Tua-i mat’um nalliini
These days
Qanruyutvut man’a eneqangluku-ll’ wii caknengama tutgaramnek wall’u makunek yumnek
Because I remember our traditional wisdom and struggle with my grandchildren or my children here
Caknengama eneqangluku
Since I remember it and struggle
Qanpagayulria tauna, qastuluni qalarculria atawakevkenaku.
I think that person who shouts, who speaks loudly, is not good.
Ellangeqarraallemni imkut qanrutetullruatnga
In my earliest memories, the poeple back then used to tell me
Umyuartungnaqlua-gguq usvitungnaqlua yuukilii.
That I should try to live mindfully and wisely.
Tua-i-llu angliriama tarricaurcama maani, ikamranun-llu maligucaurcama qanrutnauraatnga waten:
Then when I grew up and started traveling here, and went with those traveling by dog team, they would tell me this:
Atam-gguq piyaureskuma, unangyaureskuma yuilqurmiutarnek, imarpiim-ll’ unkunek piinek
Watch, they said, when I became able and start catching animals from the wilderness and from the ocean down there
Amirkaq-gguq una atauciq qemangqaurqumku
They said if I keep this one sealskin with me
Atam-gguq ilangelarniartuq, kiituani-gguq qayarkanrurcan qayaqsagutaqua, qayangua tua-i.
Watch, they said, there will be more, and when they eventually become enough for a kayak, I will get a kayak.
Tuamtellu-gguq pavani yuilqumi imarmiutarmek wall’u tevyulimek unangekuma
Then they said that if I catch a mink or a muskrat in the wilderness inland
Akia-gguq atam qemangqaurqumku egmianun tunevkenaku
Watch, they said, if I save the money without handing it over right away
Carrarmun-gguq atam nutaan kinguqvaarni ilakangkan tunkumku piluaqerniartua.
They said I would do well if I use it for something later when I add to it.
"Umyugailkuvet, umyugailkuvet ilavnek ayuqniallren egmiuciiqan
"If you are mindless, you will go forth coveting those around you
"Ilaten atu’urkameggnek teguqerrartengraata."
"Though those around you get their hands on what they need."
Tua-i umyugaitelliniama ilanka teguqerrartengraata ayuqniarumallruanka.
Since I’m apparently mindless, though those around me got their hands on things, I coveted them for a long time.
Makut maa-i akingukarani check-at quyurquranritlinikai.
He apparently didn’t save up what money he got through checks.
Akingukarani check-at imarkilengraata quyurqurquniki
If he saves what money he gets though the checks are small
Amllerikata tua-i snuukuuq akilicugngariyaryalliniluku.
When they amass, he’d be able to pay for a snow machine.
Massiinaq-llu levaaq akilicugngayalliniluku.
And he’d be able to pay for a boat motor.
Anirtima qanrutaitkut, akikaar-gguq kiturtelluku, egmianun kiturtelluku tun’urluku
It’s no wonder they told us that letting what money we have pass by, letting it pass by right away by spending it
Kipusviit iluatni canek aturanek cucullerput, maligtaquurassiyaagluku umyuarput.
Getting things we want inside stores, giving in to our first inclinations too much.
Kiturtelluki-gguq akikaaraput tamakut aklungengaitukut.
They said if we let what little money we have pass by, we won’t have things.
Angyangengaunata-llu akitulriamek, massiinangengaunata-llu akitulriamek.
We won’t get an expensive boat, and we won’t get an expensive motor.
Taangamek-llu-gguq mer’atukumta akitulriamek aklumek aturngaunata
And they said if we drink alcohol, we will not wear expensive clothes
Akurarutekngamteki-gguq tamakut atu’urkamteńun navrucaryaaqelput.
Becuase, they said, we squander what we would have traded for what we need.
Maa-i nutaan waten angukara’urluurcama tangvagaqa tamana qanruyutellerput.
As I’ve become an old man like this, I’m seeing that traditional wisdom that was passed down to us.
Picimegcetun au͡gkut alerquagiyuitelliniut.
People back then didn’t give random instructions.
Atullmeggnek tau͡gaam ellaita alerquagitulliniut ciumteńi atullermeggnek.
Instead, the give instruction on what they’ve experienced before us.
Iliini-ll’ picurlallerteng aassaqevkenaku atuusqevkenaku inerquutaqluku picurlallerteng wangkutnun.
And sometimes, they wouldn’t hide their mistakes, and admonish us against committing their mistakes.
Qanruyuterugaita imkut qanrutestemta akuliitni piyulria qanruyutem tua-i ilakluku, ciknayaraq-gguq mana’.
The many pieces of wisdom of our instructors, one among them would add this wisdom when they wanted to, what they call jealousy.
Yuk-gguq elluarrluni-llu yuungnaqura’urlulria ciknakluku imna angalkum ciknatarlim
They said that a jealous shaman envies a person who is living and subsisting well
Pinrillugcetaarluku picuirucetaqluku, wall’ tukuuyulallrat man’a navgaqluku elluarrluteng yuuqataryaaqellrit.
They curse them to be bad hunters, or break the wealth of those who were going to live well.
Umyuarrliqluteng tamakut cakneq.
They have very malicious intentions.
Tua-i-llu cali qanruyutet makut:
Then these other pieces of traditional wisdom:
Ilameng-gguq akuliitni ik’ikengraitkut tua-i qessamkaukluta-ll’ ayagyuarlurni maani
They said that though those among us depreciate us, saying we young people here are lazy
Unugmi-llu, aanairucarallruama-ll’ wii unugmi-llu tan’geriaqan anenermek taq’laama
And at night, since I stop going out at night when it gets dark because I lost my mother early
Akeqnerrluggnauraatnga makut, qessamkaukuma tua-i waten kaigasteńguciqnilua.
They would give me a harrowing promise, that if I’m lazy like this that I would be a beggar.
Picurlautek’larciqniluku-ll’ tamana qessamkaulua pirraarlua ilanka uingequkata ayuqniam ugaani.
They said that that would bring me misfortune if I’m lazy when those around me take husbands because I desire what they have so much.
Tau͡gaam tua-i tuaten qanrutaqluta makut wani qanenqegcaarautestemta.
But our thorough instructors would tell us that.
Ilamta akuliitni-ll’ ellalkartevkenata, imumek [?aapiir]tevkenata, murilkevlacagpek’nata, usviitevkenata ilamta akuliitni.
Among those around us, we shouldn’t act senselessly, [?], be unobservant, or be foolish among those around us.
Maktaqameng tua-i qanruqu’urnauraitkut
When they got up, they’d always tell us
"Elpeci-ll’ maa-i ayagyuani irniangekuvci-gguq
"When you young people also have children
"Irniarci-gguq mikelnguungalnge’rmi wall’ pilukuvceńi camek inerququvciu, ’Kitak’ at’ ilaten piqaqatgen qimagaqluki [?ingluliuteng].’
"Though your child seems small, or if you admonish them when you put on their skin boots, ’If you peers do anything to you, run away [?and do not fight them].’
"Atam-gguq cumikeyagatuut."
"Watch, they pay attention."
Tua-i-gguq maa-i makut maa-i ciulirnemta makut tamana ellangeqarraallermeggni niitellerteng tua-i pikluku tua-i.
They said that our elders keep what they’ve heard in their earliest memories.
Qanrutetullruitkut, yuungnaquralriit-gguq nulirqelriik Kass’artaitellrani imumi
They would tell us that a married couple living on their own back when there was no Western contact
Atiita ikamracualleraak makuk taqkunikek
If their father finishes a sled
Qanikciurun-llu muragaq taqkuniu, piqertuutacuar-llu qel’kekuniu, cikuliurun-llu
And if he finishes the wooden sled, and keeps a small axe and ice pick
Tua-i-gguq teguyarangqerciquq tauna family-t ata’urluat arrsaunge’rmi.
They said they will have things at hand though the family’s dear father is poor.
Neqkarcuun-llu-gguq qalu quarruugnek unangetuli qemangqakuniu
And they said that if he keeps the fishing tool that catches sticklebacks
Unarcianek-llu-gguq taluyitukuni neqkanek unangyugngalrianek
And they said that if he makes fish traps that can catch fish out of straight grained pieces of wood
Imarmiutarnek-llu unangyugngalrianek taluyaruanek-gguq civcitukuni
And if he sets fish traps that can catch minks
Arrsaunge’rmi-gguq tukurlirpagtun ayuqluni family-t atakekatni
Though he’s poor, if the family’s father is like he’s rich [in food and tools]
Irniani cirivkarluki aturarrliqengraata aulukciqai pinirillrata yaavet engeliinun.
He will take care of his children with abundance though they have tattered clothes all the way until they become strong.
Kass’artaitellrani makut maa-i qanruyutelput.
This was the traditional wisdom passed down to us before Western contact.
Tangtullruunga-llu wangkuta tua-i arrsagni ayuqemteńek.
I also used to see people like us who are poor.
Makut tang tua-i tan’gaurlurnek yulget carraquineq tau͡gaam iqluluteng arrsaunguaqatullinilriit.
You see, only some who have male children falsly say that they are poor.
Qetunrateng makut pissuryaurtaqata, melqulegcuryaurtaqata
When their sons start hunting fur-bearing animals
Ata’urluat tuk’uqerrnaurtut patagmek tua-i melqulek akikeggillrani
Their dear father would quickly get rich when fur was expensive.
Unaken call’ unguvalrianek tua-i taguquringartaqameng
Also, when they bring in animals from the [ocean] down there
Arrsaucillrat imna nalluyagutnarqluni, ayuqnianarqaqluteng tua-i.
We forget they’d been poor, and covet them.
Atameggnek aulukestekegciaqameng unakengait tamakut kiturcetevkenaki
When their father takes good care of them by not letting what they obtained pass by
Amlleriluki tau͡gaan tun’arkauluki piaq[ameng].
Instead, giving them away when they’ve amassed.
Tuamtell’ qanernaurtut, anngaqelriit-gguq ukut family-t waten ukut nukalpiat tallimauyaaqeciqut
Then they’d say that there may be brothers in this family who are five great hunters
Una-llu-gguq cali nulirqelriit atauciuyaaqeciquq qetunraak.
And they said a married couple may have one son.
Uum-gguq qetunraagnek taukut ayuqniarluki anngaqelriit talliman nukalpiat.
They said that their son here wants to be like the great hunter brothers.
Qessalertevenani nalluatgun inglukluki pingnatukuni
If he’s not lazy and competes with them without their knowledge when hunting
Ukut-gguq pitacirciqai talliman nukalpiat.
They said he would get as much as these five great hunters.
Talliman-gguq nukalpiat nalluatni ingluklerkaat qacignarquq.
They said it’s easy to compete with great hunters without their knowledge.
Nuvkutaagutetuut-gguq ukut anngaqellriit.
They said that these brothers argue.
"Pi-gguq kuvyayaqili; wii kuvyayaryuumiitua." "Pi-gguq muragcuqili; wii muragcuryuumiitua."
"Tell him to drift net; I don’t want to drift ent." "Tell him to gather wood; I don’t want to gather wood."
Maa-i-gguq makut qacignarqutiit ayagnerat iqua.
They said this is what it means when it’s easy to begin [competing with them].
Uum-gguq atauciunge’rmi ayuqeliyugngai ingluliluki.
They said that even this one person can be like them.
Makut maa-i qanruqurauteput ellangyugallemteńi Kass’anek makunek piitellermeggni.
These are the things they told us in our early memories before Western contact.
Neviarcaraat-llu makut uingeksailnguut angliyartullrat maliggluku ayuqucirtuutnek nutaan patutullruit inerquutnek.
And following the growth of these unmarried young ladies, they would cover them with instructions and admonishments.
Agurrluk’-llu yuut tangvanrilkiitni nukalpianun unugmi narukitautesqevkenaki inerquraqluki.
And they would admonish them against ever going to meet a young man at night when people aren’t watching.
Wangkuta-llu unugmi neviarcaraat akuliitni narukitautesqevkenata.
They also told us not to meet with young ladies at night.
Alegyagulluku-gguq nasaurluq yugnek tangvagtaitnitekluta kemga agtuqumteggu wangkutnek-gguq tuquciiqukut.
They said that if we’re confident in touching a girl’s flesh because people aren’t watching, we’ll kill ourselves.
Nulirruarluta tua-i.
We pretend to have a wife.
Tamaa-i atam alingnarcarluku qanrutkaat.
You see, they would speak of that to make it scary.
Arnat-llu makut enemi agleraqata qanrutnaurait
And when these women menstruate at home, they’d tell them
"Kitak’ wak’nirnek ayagluten tua-i eglertuten.
"Now, from here on out, you go forth.
"Nulirtuqsailnguq yun’erra’ar tan’gaurluq anuqiin asguakun agurrluk’ kituryaqunaku, avaggun tau͡gaam uqrakun.
"Never pass an unmarried young man, a boy, upwind from him, but over there downwind from him.
"Tepen-gguq atam narluku narumangniariaa. Assiiruyutekaa-gguq kiituan."
"When he smells your emanations, he will keep smelling it. Eventually, it ruins him."
Tuaten-qaa qanrucuitellruatgen?
Wouldn’t they tell you that?
Qanrutaqluta.
They would tell us.
Au͡gna-q’ elitaqenritan?
Don’t you recognize that?
Qang’a, elitaqkacagarluku.
No, I completely recognize it.
Tepii-gguq narluku.
They say he smells her emanations.
Aipaput kenekluki pisqessaaqaqluki, uiput cumikluki
They’d tell us to love our spouses, to attend to our husbands
Allaliuqsaunata-llu.
And never be unfaithful.
Uimta-llu nalluatni arnaurlulriani wangkuta ayagallerkartuyarrluta
And if we women start going out without our husbands’ knowledge
Kiituani-gguq taum uimta pikenrilkiinek qingangaqluta-gguq.
They said we’d eventually be pregnant from someone other than our husband.
Imkut maaten tamaani ellangeqarrallamteńi qanrutaqamegtegkut ikiu͡k’acagarluku ca ikuggluku qanrutnauraitkut.
When they instructed us in our earliest memories, we found that they would pry out extremeply improper things as they spoke to us.
Tangvagluta-ll’ piaqatkut, waten umyuarteqsaaqnaurtukut wangkuta niicugnilriani:
And when they’d watch us, we who are listening would think like this:
"Aling ik’um-am cunaw’ nallunrilkiikut, tangellrukiikut."
"Wow, that one across there apparently knows us, has seen us."
Tuar tang nallunritkacagarluta ilumun tangellruluta pilaqaitkut.
They spoke to us as if they completely knew us, as if they truly had seen us.
Cunaw’ tamakut qanruciyupialriit ircaqurteng cairluku ellaita atullmeggnek.
It turned out that those who wished to speak would cleanse their hearts of their experiences.
Assirluki yuk agesqelluku qanruturlularyaaqellinikaitkut.
The dear ones would speak to us so that a person would go [through life] well.
Irniau͡rluput-llu waten makut irniaqsagutaqamteki
And when we have these dear children
Agurrluk’ tua-i agutevkenaki, tass’uqluki-ll’ enenun allanun ceńirtaaruqu’urtev[kenaki].
They told us to never bring them, and not to hold their hands to have them visit other houses.
Atam-gguq asriurturlurniartut.
They said they’d become mischievous.
Ikiurlullrat man’a arrasaurlullerput ilalqerluku-gguq atam aanaulriami wani enem nayurtiini.
They said their misbehavior would exacerbate our destitution for the mother who stays with them at home.
Una-wa-gguq aatavut ayagalria pikangengnaqluta.
Our father travels to try to subsist for us.
Pitarra’urlui-gguq tekitaqan quyatekluki ciuniurluki arnaulriani.
They said we women should be thankful for whatever he catches and welcome them.
Wall’ akirrarmek unangekan qenngevkenata wangkuta arnani taqmaqegciyugluta, wall’ camek cap’akiqegciyugluta
Or if he gets a little money, we woman should not be angry wanting a beautiful dress, or some beautiful shoes
Aturaqegciamta-gguq tua-i pikarciaritnek maa-i nangerngiimta.
Because they said we’re standing here with wonderful clothes they’ve gotten us.
Tamakut-gguq navguutekai taum aipamteńun.
They said those are detrimental for our spouses.
Tamakut unangkengarait, uiu͡rlumta unangkengarait munarulluki.
Those things they obtain, we should work skillfully with what our spouses obtain.
Munarcallrani tauna aipa’urluput ukisqirluki.
As our dear spouses work dextrously, help them.
Tamakut tamaa-i anglanitekevkenaki-gguq, akingutaurlui tegulerulluta ayagpek’nata.
They said we shouldn’t squander those things, taking his money and going.
Avani-ll’ ayanantemteńi canun akusrarrnarqelrianun tekiskumta, wall’ mer’aluta, wall’ canun
And as we go, when we come across socially inappropriate things, or drink, or something
Inerqurluta tua-i tamalkuita tamakunek aarnarqelrianek.
They’d admonish us against all of those dangerous things.
Irniamta-ll’ takuatni tuaten ayuqesqevkenata. Alerquaciqaput-gguq.
And they told us not to be like that in front of our children. They said we’d teach them.
Tua-i tuaten tau͡gaam ilalqerpek’nani yuk yuurluqili mat’um nalliini.
May a person live without exacerbating [problems] like that these days.
Tamana-llu tamaa-i akerrneqluggutek’lallrat
That was their harrowing promise
Akusrangkumta-gguq tamakut angayuqamta qanrutestemta, ciulirnemta qanrutaqamegtekut
They said if we misbehave when our parents who instruct us, and our elders instruct us
Akusrangkumta-gguq camek elpek[’ngaarulluta].
They said if we we misbehave, we’ll become insensitive.
Qanrutestevut cumikenrirluku, alerquastevut elluarrluta yuusqelluta, aviranaunata ilamta akuliitni.
We stop paying attention to our teachers, our instrcuts, who tell us to live well, not to hinder those around us.
Tau͡gaam-gguq assirluta tangniqluta enemteńi aqumluta
Instead, they said we should be good and look nice sitting at home
Enevut-gguq uitaqegcinaqniartuq.
So, they said, our house will be nice to be in.
Allaneruaraam-llu nanikualuni itervikekakut uitanqegcivkangnaqluku
And if a helpless guest comes in our house, try to make them feel at home
Imuuvkenata, akusrartevkenata yuukumta.
If we live without, you know, being mischievous.
Tua-i tuaten qanraqata piyugyaaqengramta, amta-llu tua-i iliini canun tekitengaqluta tua-i.
When they said that, though we wanted to, yet we would sometimes come upon things.
Assiryugyaaqellerput man’a ukatairuluku.
We do not fulfill our desire to do well.
Ayagyuarluta-ll’ qingircetlerkaq tua-i alingnaqkacagarluni, mikelngurmek alairillermek.
And it would very scary to be impregnated at a young age, to bring forth a child.
Aatailnguut tallurnaqkacagarluteng-gguq.
They said illegitimate children were very embarrassing.
Inerquutngullruyaaqluni.
It was an admonishment.
Maa-i tamatuullinill’ akusrangllerkaatnek qanlallrat imkut au͡gkut ciuliamta.
This is the misbehavior that our elders back then spoke of.
Inerquutet makut wani assiitellriit atuqsaileng’erpeciki ayagyuani.
You young people shouldn’t do these bad things that are admonished against.
Maligqurassiyaagpegnaki Kass’at makut pisqutait.
Do not follow these Western ways too much.
Canek tua-i makut puyurtull’e’rnek-llu canek pilarniitki iqugglugningqeńilaitki tamakut
And since they speak of marijuana, that it has negative effects
Tamakut atuqsailengraata.
Don’t use those.
Waten tau͡gaam yuuqallerput tang tua-i ikgetlinilria.
You see, we only have a short life like this.
Una wani ayagyuallerput ellangellerput canimelngat’laryaaqell’, amta-ll’ [?] waten pinialiluta carpagciigaliluta.
Though our youth and earliest memories seems close, yet we weaken like this and can’t do anything strenuous.
Taumek mulngakluci tuaten tamakut assiiterrlainaat maligtevkenaki.
That’s what you should be careful like that, not only following those bad things.
Cavvliurluci, yuungnaqluci, akingengnaqluci pikuvci tengruluci quyanarqeqacaarciquci.
If you are buy, subsist, and try to earn money with fervor, we will be thankful for you.
Akinguteci tau͡gaam tuaten elpeceńun, enevceńun-llu aturluki ikayuutekluki, aklukluki.
Instead, use the money you earn for yourselves, your houses, use them for help, and for clothes.
Wiinga-ll’ tua-i waniwa qitevvneq-llu nalluamku qaill’ ucuryagutekevkenaku atuyuilamku tua-i.
And since I don’t know how to speak English, I am not in awe of it in any way because I don’t use it.
Pisqeqapigtaqatnga tau͡gaam ik’um-ll’ aiparma maliklua camek, maligglua camek tua-i tegutaqlua
Only when they really want me to, and when my spouse across there goes with me, I take something
Una-kiq qaill’ tunllerkaa nalluk’acagaamku.
Because I have no idea how to give out this [money].
Quyanaqkacagarluni. Tua-i quyaaqlua nallucimnek uitanqegcilua uitalaama.
I’m very thankful. I’m thankful that I don’t know because I stay peacefully.
Man’a taangaq elpecinun assinritqapiareyaaquq atungnaqellra.
It’s not good for you to abuse this alcohol.
Tau͡gaam taangaq man’a trouble-aamun tau͡gaam pinaqluni.
Instead, this alcohol only leads to trouble.
Cali yuk taangarpakarluni iqlutmun piarkaqenrilkeńi tekilluku ellmineng picurlatuuq.
Also, when a person drinks too much, they go the wrong way and bring themselves to misfortune.
Cali man’a meluk aipaa...
The other one also, smoking...
Patuu.
Close it.
Aipaa tamana meluk man’a umyugamun tau͡gaam ayatulria, man’a-llu tema tapulluku.
That other one, smoking, only goes to the mind, along with this body.
Wii atuyuicaaqaqa qaillun ayuqellra, tau͡gaam niitetuama wanigga tamatumeng melugmeng ayuqucianeng
I don’t use it [or know] what it’s like, but because I hear about what that smoking is like
Umyugaq tau͡gaam nagvutuniluku.
That it only destroys the mind.
Cali qavarturangluni tauna melugpakatuli.
Also, that one who smokes too much starts sleeping all the time.
Tau͡gaten niitetuunga tamatumeng melugaqata.
That’s what I hear when they smoke that.
Ilumuuluni tamana pituyugnarquq.
I think that truly does happen.
Melugpakalria man’a qavarturangluni.
One who smokes too much sleeps all the time.
Cali unim[yugluteng], you know?
[They] also [become] forgetful, you know?
They forgot what to do. Ellirraarluki-llu cat wanirpaagaq nalluyagutaqluki.
They forgot what to do. And after they put something down, they immediately forget them.
Wii qetunrama iliit tau͡gaten, iliit, inerqungramteng
One of my sons like that, though I admonish them
Tamatumeng iliini atuqeryutuata
Since they sometimes use that
Nunutuyaaqanka cakneq wii pirramneng.
I harshly scold them to the best of my ability.
Wangkutnek-wa tua-i wangni, naliata akwaugaq qanrutaanga, [?Ayapqu]gcaram piyugnarqaanga
From us, one of them told me yesterday, I think it was [?Ayapqu]gcaraq
Wangkutnek wii nallemnek tuar tang ayagluta wangkutnek man’a yuum ayallra cimilria.
From us, it seems that starting from my time, the way a person goes [through life] has changed.
Qaa?
Right?
Kass’atun makut kinguqliput ellirtut.
Our descendants have become Westernized.
Kass’arngariut, ilait-llu Yugtun taringesciigaliluteng.
They’ve become Westernized, and some can’t understand Yup’ik anymore.
Kass’aturrlainaq tau͡gaam qalarqurangluteng.
Instead, they’ve started speaking only in English.
Tua-ll’ waniw’ Yugtun yuullerkam ayuqucianek piyaaqengramta
And now, though we speak about how a Yup’ik life should go
Makut tamakut Kass’atun elitellriit qaillun elitnauqatarceta?
How will we teach those who’ve learned English?
Ataam-qaa au͡gna yuuqtallerput tengruluteng ataam ayagniryugngaciqaat?
Will they be able to enthusiastically start our old way of life again?
Caknerluta wangkuta yuullerput.
Our lives where we struggled.
Qimugtetgun-llu ayagaluta, kayimngina’arturluta-llu qugtatullruluta Akulmi.
And we’d travel by dog sled, and gather wood in the Akula region by pushing our sleds without dogs.
Qimugtaunata-llu ayagatullruluta.
And we used to travel without dogs.
Qanikciurutput-llu elluatuullruvkenateng, piqertuutaput-llu elluatuullruvkenateng wangkuta ciuqlirpeceńi.
And our shovels were not sophisticated, and our axes were not sophisticated, we who came before you.
Makut tua-llu-w’ nutaan ciuqliput nutaan tangrruarqamteng nutaan caknepiallruyugnarqut.
Now, especially when I imagine our elders, they probably struggled even more.
Ukatmun Kass’at tungiitnun calissuutait call’ tungiitnun ayallerput maliggluku tuarpiaq qacignariinarluteng cat.
As we went to becoming Westernised along with their tools, it truly seems that things have become easier.
Waniwa-ll’ yaaqsingraan wanirpaagaq tekiarcaurrluku
And now, though a place is far, we’ve started reaching it right away
Wangkuta unuakuyaarmek ayagluta caqtarturatullerput.
The place we’d steadily start going to from the early morning.
Tua-llu?
You understand?
Makut qanruyutait ciuliamta wangkuta qemagngangaicaaqaput elisngastaitni
We who are knowledgeable about our ancestors’ wisdom will not keep them to ourselves
Akaarnun nunami maani nangengqatnguata.
Because they help us to stand on this earth for a long time.
Kenkek’ngaput-qaa tuquyararaasqaput wangkuta yup’ut?
Do we wish an early death on our children whom we love?
Kenkekumteki makunek ciuliamta alerquutaitnek arcaqerluki qanrutarkaugaput.
If we love them, we must especially tell them about our ancestors’ traditional instructions.
Tuamta-llu wangkuta Yugni alerquutengqertukut yuullgutput tamalkuita elluarrluki ciuniuresqelluki
Then, we Yupiit are instructed to welcome all of our fellow people well
Allakaukevkenaki, ilakuyulluta.
Without discrimination, but as a whole.
Kitumek kinkut imkut Alaska-m yui tuaten umyuallgutekluteng ilakuyulluki nangengqasqumaut.
No matter who they are, the people of Alaska are asked to stand together with one mind.
Mat’um ilii, mat’um-am agayumacim ilait waten qanertut:
Part of these, some of these religions say this:
"Wangkuta agayumacirput assirtuq tukniluni-llu."
"Our religion is good and powerful."
Tuaten pinrituq. Tuaten ayuqenrituq.
That’s not the case. That’s not what it’s like.
Ciuliamta ilakuyutiit navyunaicaaqerput wangkuta, piunriyunaunaku-llu.
We should not destroy our ancestors’ community mindset, or abolish it.
Una ilakuyun avaken ayagluni ciuliamta qanrutkaat kenkauguq.
This community mindset, our ancestors have said since long ago that it’s a form of love.
Kenka atunrilkumteggu maani unguvallemteńi qaill’ piluta anirtuumaciqceta?
If we don’t practice love as we live here, how will we be saved?
Allamek anirtuutaitukut.
We have no other salvation.
Ciuliamta kenka atullruat.
Our ancestors practiced love.
Anirtuumaluteng-llu ayaumaluteng tamana atullruamegteggu yuullgutmeggnun tamalkuitnun allakaukutevkenateng.
And they were saved as they went because they practiced that to all of their fellow people without discrimination.
Agayumacit ayuqenrilnguut allakaukucetaangraatkut, tamana allakaukucaraq assiituq uitacurlagnaqluni-llu.
Though various religions try to divide us, that division is not good and leads to unrest.
Ciuliamta tau͡gaam alerquutiit ilakuyucaraq atuqumteggu nutaan uitanqegciluta nangengqaciqukut
Only if we practice our ancestors’ community lifestyle will we stand peacefully
Ukverput-llu qaqimalriaruluni.
And our faith will be complete.
Nunam yuini wangkuta mat’umek ak’allarpall’e’rmek ayuqucirtuutmek teggutengqertukut tua-i taumek.
We people of the earth have a solid foundation with this ancient traditional instruction.
Man’a-llu teggutvut takarnaqpiarluni, takarnairucuunani-llu.
And our solid foundation here is worthy of great respect, and will not lose that.
Makuni maa-i watua tegganeruaramteńi makuni
Here, in what elders we have today
Tamatumi takarnarquciq uitauq.
That is where the cause for respect is.
Takarnarqelriim cam imum tamatum nunam yui tamakut tegguciumaluki.
What is worthy of respect gives a solid foundation for the people of the earth.
Tauna-llu tegguciumasteseng ellaita nalluvkenaku.
And they know the one that gives them their solid foundation.
Taumek man’a ak’allaq ukanirpak tailria teggutekngamteggu
Since this ancient thing that’s come from long ago is our solid foundation
Tua-i nangerngatekluku-llu calritara’urlulriani maani nangerngaurlurtukut.
And since it’s our support for life, we who are healthy are standing here.
Man’a-llu waten ayuqucirput:
And this is what we’re like:
Yuum taum atra, Yugtun atra tua-i pirkaparput.
We value a person’s name, their Yup’ik name.
Cali-llu Yugtun qanerturalleq cali una pirpakarput Yuungamta tua-i.
We also value speaking in Yup’ik because we’re Yup’ik.
Tauna arcaqerluku akulemteńi aterpagtaarturaulluta quyanaqpiartuq.
That especially, calling each other by our [Yup’ik] names, is a cause for great thanks.
Tuamta-llu wangkuta Yugni uumek tua-i nalluvkenata:
Then, we Yupiit also know this:
Atunem ciuniurtaagutlerput, atunem-llu tua-i ilaliurutlerput uuggun elluarucitun ilaliurucarakun.
Welcoming each other, and socializing with each other with this right way of socializing.
Tua-i una wani waten ayuqellerput caknerpak akulemteńi angkacagartuq.
Our behavior like this among ourselves is very important.
Takarnarqucia-llu tua-i tuaten ayuqerrlainarluni, takarnairucuunani-llu.
And its need to be respected is always like that, and never loses it.
Qanikcaq tangerrluku yullret imkut pitullruut.
People back then would look at the snow.
Qanikci’rqan cali-llu ciku, tua-i-w’ cikuli’rqan cikurrlugluni
When there’s a lot of snow, and the ice, when there’s a lot of ice
Qanikcaam akulii cikuluku piaqan, nenglaiteqtaarluni-w’ tua-i
When there’s ice between layers of snow, when it’s been repeatedly warming up
Tamana-gguq tua-i qanikci’rqan, qau͡gna-llu kiatvut qanikci’rqan mel’ituuq. Mel’irnilallruat.
When there’s a lot of snow, and a lot of snow upriver from us, there’s a lot of melt off. They’d say there’d be a lot of melt off.
Qanikcinqurraa-qaa elpet tangvallruan, qanikcinkacagallrani?
Did you see a snowier time when there was a lot of snow?
Qanikcitullruuq imumi mikluta. Maani qanikcipiatullruuq.
There used to be a lot of snow back when we were small. There used to be a lot of snow here.
Enet-llu kankut mission house-at kiimeng qertullrulriit roof-ai tekilluki piaqluni atrarluni.
And the buildings down there, the mission house was the only tall one, and it would reach the roof going down.
Mayurluta pagaavet ellu’urtaaraqluta.
We’d climb up there and slide.
Elaturrat-llu amiiget qanikciurluki waten piaqluki igteńguluteng.
And we’d shovel the doors of the porches like this into a den.
Qaillun, waten maa-i February-q nangyartulria, qaillun tamaani uptelallruat up’nerkiyallerkameggnun?
How, with February ending now, how would they prepare to go to spring camp back then?
Up’nerkiyaqata’arqameng-wa April-aami uptenglallrulriit.
When they were going to go to spring camp, they’d start preparing in April.
Qaniilarluteng-llu canek neqkameggnek up’nerkarpak.
And they’d prepare their food supplies for the spring.
Pelatekateng-llu civcarturluki, and...
They’d go set up their tents, and...
Atam-llu qitevcugniartua.
Watch, I’ll slip into English.
Pinek-llu, angyateng-llu call’ ayaulluki, aguuteteng-llu.
And, you know, they’d bring their boats, and their open canoes.
Cat tua-i aturyugarkateng up’nerkillerni ayaulluki.
They’d bring things they’d need to use in the spring camps.
Nutaan-llu April-aaq man’a qukallra kituan nutaan wangkuta upagluta.
Then when the middle of April passed, we’d move.
Tua-i tekilluta nunakamteńun. Cakneq tua-i assirluni nunaniqluni.
We’d arrive to our settlements. It was very good and pleasant.
Tua-i-ll’ mat’um nalliini waten cali qanlartut:
Then these days, they also say this:
Arnanek-gguq irnialek arnaq, atam-gguq taum arnam aanani tangvagniaraa enem iluani.
They said a woman with femal children, watch, that woman will watch her mother in the home.
Tua-i-llu-gguq calillra, callra arnam cali taum irniaran ayuqeliyugngaluku.
Then they said that woman, her child, will be able to replicate her chores, what she does.
Piciugut makut.
These are true.
Wiinga-ll’ waniw’ nine-aanek irniangqertua, five girls, four boys.
And now, I have nine children, five girls, four boys.
Ukut-llu five girls ayuqenritut tamarmeng. Iciw’ ayuqenritut.
And these five girls are all different. You know, they’re different.
Tamalkuita-ll’ taukut wii kenkepiarluki.
And I love all of them very much.
Tua-i-ll’ caliyaurcama, cali mingeqsaurcama tua-i
Then when I started making things, and when I started sewing
Ukut-ll’ angliriluteng, ukut yuungnaqengluteng paniinka
And these grew up, my daughters started living on their own
Caliurnaunka mingqurluki-ll’.
I’d make them things, and sew things for them.
Iliini enaitnun it’lartua cailkami taun im’ mingqelqa. Umyuaqa tang pinaurtuq.
I sometimes go in their homes, and what I sewed is on the floor. I would feel unhappy.
Cunawa-m’ tua-i assircaarluku tang tauna uitaarkaq cailkamtelluku.
Apparently, they’d leave leave on the floor what was supposed to be kept well.
Iliinun panima iternaurtua, neat.
I’d go into one of my daughter’s, [and it’s] neat.
Aren caliallrenka-ll’ makut kenkumaluteng.
Oh my, what I made would be treated with love.
Tua-i-ll’ tuaten piama waniwa irniamni five girls, malruk, atrit aperngaitanka
Then when I do that, these among my children of five girls, two of them, I won’t say their names
Wii tangerturallemni neat, Kass’at apqiitnek neat.
They’re neat from what I’ve seen, what they call neat in English.
Assirtuk.
They’re good.
Tamarmeng assiryaaqut.
They’re all good.
Tua-i-ll’ waten piunga: mingqaallrenka aturiallrenka taukuk care-aqapiarluki.
Then I realized this: they take great care of the clothes I sewed.
Arcaqerluni-am aipaan care-aamiki, eniinun itraqama tua-i tanglaamteki
Because the other takes especially good care of them, since we see them when we go into her house
Kiagmi caliallrenka mingqaat atkuut, piluguut, furs, fur clothes, kiagmi tangerqayuitanka eniin iluani, nothing.
In the summer, the clothes I sewed, parkas, skin boots, furs, fur clothes, I never see them in her house in the summer, nothing.
She put them away.
She put[s] them away.
Iciw’ put away-larai.
You know, she puts them away.
Kass’ani nallunritua fur-at uitavingqertut pitalqellriamek enemek.
I know that in the West, furs have appropriate places to be.
Kiircetevkenani, nengllirpek’nani, maybe meduim, tua-i-ll’ fur-ani assirluni.
It’s not hot, it’s not cold, maybe meduim, and the fur is good.
Atam cat wani makut skin-at agaurarqameng years and years aturviirutetuut uuluteng.
You see, when these skin clothes hang for years and years, they become unusable [?from wearing out].
Tegukumni-ll’ un’ atkuk allegluni. Uuluni.
And when I take this parka, it rips. [?It wears out].
Yuilqumi-gguq tarrisnginanemni ilamnek arenqiallugtellriamek tangerquma
They said that if I see one of my peers in misfortune as I travel in the wilderness
Pirrangqertacimtun ikayuakilaku.
I should help him with whatever I have.
Alerquumaluta tuaten.
That’s how we were instructed.
Wall’u imarkailkan, wall’u neqkailkan neqkaramnek tuaken avgutesqelluku.
Or if he has no bullets, or is without food, I should give him some of what food I have.
Cali-llu pinauraitkut waten wani:
They’d also tell us this:
Waniwa-gguq atam cam iliini, ertem iliini pikailkumta
They said that someday, if we lack something one day
Waten pikailkumta uninraarturngaitukut.
When we lack something, we will not be [?robust].
Anrutam-gguq qam’um imaitellra anglanarqenrituq.
Theys ay having an empty stomach is not enjoyable.
Yuum-gguq tamarmi ayuqucian nangteqsaram angenqaa anrutam qamum imaunani nangtequteqellra.
They say that one trait among every person is that the greatest suffering is suffering an empty stomach.
Pinirnaunani, uninraarnaunani-llu.
We become weak, and [?without vigor].
Cali-llu neqa, elliin imna neqa qel’kenritqallrulliu, wall’u neqa egtellrukuniu nernarqengraan
Also, if that person does not keep food, or throws food away though it’s edible
Tailuni umyugaanun, tailuni, uurcaraluni arenqiapaa.
When it comes into his mind, when he regrets what he forsook, how unfortunate.
"Imna-llu kitak’ nerurallrulaku egtevkenaku."
"I should’ve eaten that instead of throwing it away."
Tuaten-gguq atam ayuquq.
They said that’s what it’s like.
Ca-gguq tamalkuan umyuamikun aglumayagulluku waten kaigluni.
They say he begins to covet everything in his mind in his hunger like this.
Maa-i makut wani arcaqerluki wangkuta qanruyutektuaput.
This is the important wisdom that we pass down.
Cali-llu uksumi waten nenglem nalliini
Also, in the winter like this during the cold season
Angussaagaqamta nutaan cakviutuamta
Since we especially struggle when we hunt
Tua-i caunata ayaasqevkenata.
They told us not to travel without anything.
Qanikciurutaunata cikuliurutaunata-llu ayaasqevkenata.
They told us not to travel without a shovel and an ice pick.
Cali-llu makut kuiget atrit atengqercelluki.
We should also know the names of these rivers.
Yuum-gguq atam iliin yuk pikaitem nalliini taum-llu neq’rugalgem nuniini nangernganiartuq atra nallukuniu.
They said that one person, you see, during a famine may stand around a place with a lot of fish if he doesn’t know its name.
Yuilqumi pingnatugyarat tamalkuita acirturluki piuratulliniit imkut yuut
The people back then would name all of the subsistence areas in the wilderness
Nernarqellriit neqait ayuqenrilnguut.
The place with various edible food.
Yuum-gguq atra nallukuniu taum kuigem apertuumangraan neqengqerrucia nallua.
They said that if a person doesn’t know that river’s name, he doesn’t know that it has fish though it’s indicated.
Taumek qanrucimaukut, nunam-gguq qaingani, kuiget-llu, nanvarraat-llu atrit cali elisnganarqaput
That’s why we’re told that we should know the names of things on land, rivers, and lakes
Angussaagyarat, nerengnaqsarat.
The places to hunt, to subsist.
Makut maa-i qanruyutektuaput.
This is the traditional knowledge we pass down.
Tau͡gken neqaicuilnguut aperturluki cali.
However, we should also indicate the ones that always have fish.
Qau͡gna-gguq qava-i Ecuilnguq neqaicuituq.
Say that Ecuilnguq upriver always has fish.
"I also hear that the area around Qagatmiut inland always has fish."
Ingrit-gguq makut carvanilriit, maaken ingrinek carvnilria neqem-gguq caumanriyuitaa.
Say that the flowing waters in these mountains, fish don’t stop going to the waters flowing from this mountain.
"Nalayuituq-gguq uksumi caumaurarqamni qallalluni waten pilria wii."
"This churning water does not die out in the winter when I go to it."
Tamakut ullagluki nallunrikumteki, wall’u manarluta, wall’u kuvyirluta angungnaquraasqelluta pilaraitkut.
They tell us to go there if we know them, or fish, or set drift nets and subsist.