Kitak’, yaa, au͡g’u qaneryullren.
So, okay, what you wanted to say.
Ii-i, qaneryullemnek waniw’ qanqatartua makunek.
Okay, I’m going to speak about these things I want to say.
Waten tan’gaurluullemni tan’gaurluullemteńi makunek
These things when I was a boy like this, when we were boys
Makunek-wa tua-i nunam qainganelngurnek neqemteńek pitarkanek
These things on the land that we eat and hunt
Imarpigmiutaat, makut-llu cali yaqulget.
Marine animals, and these birds.
Maa-i mat’um nalliini nang’ut.
These days, there are no more.
Makut waten imarpigmiutaat enurnaringut.
These marine animals are getting scarce like this.
Makut-llu yaqulget cali enurnaringluteng.
These birds are also getting scarce.
Imumi waten tan’gaurluullemteńi, tan’gaurluullemni-w’ tua-i
Back when we were boys like this, when I was a boy
Up’nerkami amllepiatullruut yaqulget.
There used to a great many birds in the spring.
Yuilquq nepaitellruuq.
The wilderness was quiet.
Waten ayuqellrunrituq.
It wasn’t like this.
Tem’ingelriamek waten niicuunata ertaqan, ellami tem’irtellrianek.
We wouldn’t hear things rumbling at dawn, things rumbling outside.
Up’nerkami waten up’nerkiaqameng pavani Akulmi nunanirpak.
When they went to spring camp in the spring inland in the Akula region, it was wonderful.
Yaqulget ayuqenrilnguut qalrialuteng.
Different birds would be calling.
Makut-llu pissulriit waten atakumi atakuara’rqan, atakuaratullruut kanaqlagcualriit
And these hunters in the evening like this, early in the evening, they would spend the evening trapping muskrats
Up’nerkillerni pavani.
In the spring camps inland.
Tua-i cingqullagangnaurtut nut’galriarurrluni waten tua-i piciatun.
They would make loud popping noises, the air filled with gunshots like this, for various things.
Makut-wa yaqulget pavani nanvat ceńaitni-ll’ up’nerkitullruameng.
There were these birds since they set up spring camps inland on lake shores.
Anglanaqluteng yaqulget kuimalriit qalrialuteng.
The swimming birds that were calling were fun.
Nunaniqluni tua-i piaqluni up’nerkami.
It would be wonderful in the spring.
Qaillun wii umyuarteqaqama, pissurnanriiceteng-qaa nang’ut?
How, when I think about it, are they gone because they aren’t hunting them anymore?
Wangkuta-llu tan’gaurlucuarni cali waten elitnauruterluta:
And we little boys also had this lesson:
Pissungqerrluta makunek yaquleyagarnek.
We hunted these little birds.
Amllepiarluteng cali.
There were also a lot of them.
Pitgaquurluki tamakunek yaquleyagarnek pissurnaurtukut.
We would hunt those little birds by shooting arrows at them.
Tamakut-llu pitaput iciw’ egcuunaki.
And, you know, we wouldn’t discard those things we caught.
Makut cali nasaurlullraat meqtayagarluki kenirnaurait.
Also, these little girls would pluck their feathers and cook them.
Tau͡gken cali aanamta imum keniraqluki cali pitaput, egcuunaki.
However, our mother would also cook what we caught, not discard them.
Waten qigcikluki makut nunamiutaat, neqput kencikluki au͡gkut pitullruit.
People back then would respect these land animals, and revered our food.
Mat’um tau͡gken tua-i nalliini qaillun piat?
But what’s become of them these days?
Makut-llu yup’ut pissuyuirulluki imkut makut yaquleyagaat pitgaquurluki pitulput.
And our children have stopped hunting these little birds that we used to shoot arrows at.
Tayima tua-i tangrrunanrirluteng maani nunam qaingani up’nerkami pissulalput.
The thigns that we used to hunt in the spring are no longer seen here on the land.
Tuamtellu cali kiagmi tukraqameng napamiutaat
Then in the summer, when the birds in the trees hatched
Amllepiarluteng puyurcivignun it’raluteng.
There would be a great many of them going into smoke houses.
Wangkuta-wa cali maani pitgaquurqeput.
We would also shoot arrows at them here.
Amiiyaarluki, uuggun qat’gaitgun cilla’arrluki kemgit au͡g’arluki.
We skinned the little things, opened them up here on their chests and removed their flesh.
Uuggun-llu yaqu͡rita piitgun ayagciqerluki.
And we would put props here on their wings.
Nuucirluki-ll’ nutaan napamek agarqurluki.
Then we would [?thread] them through a tree and hang them.
Wagg’uq-qaa nakaculiluki. Tuaten pitullruut.
They called that "making them into bladders." That’s what they did.
Amllepiarluteng yaquleyagaat cakaniyuunateng.
There would be a great many little birds with no change [in population].
Makut-wa cali aulukesteput
Then our caretakers here
Up’nerkamek tua-i ayagluteng yaqulget waten cetunatkameggnun ner’aqluki. Tua-i neqekluki, kayanguit-llu.
Starting from the spring, they would eat birds until they went downriver like this. It was their food, along with their eggs.
Camek niicuunata nangqatalrianek, ikeggliinalrianek.
We wouldn’t hear about them going away or depleting.
Tau͡gaam waten pitullruut:
But this is what they did:
Allamiaquaqan cat ukut ikgetaqluteng, caaqameng-ll’ amllerrluteng.
Every year, there would be less of these things, and there would occassionally be a lot of them.
Waten ikgeliqetaarluteng, tau͡gaam nangyuunateng, cakaniyuunateng.
There would occassionally be less, but they wouldn’t be gone, wouldn’t go away.
Amllerllainarluteng yaqulget imarpigmiutaat-llu.
There was always a lot of birds and marine animals.
Tua-i-llu tamakut waten yaqulget up’nerkami nerluki yaavet tua-i neq’ngellerkaanun.
Then they would eat those birds like this in the spring up until there were fish.
Cetuameng tau͡gaam taqluki, ayanqigtevkenateng.
They only stopped when they went downriver, didn’t go out hunting again.
Nuna tua-i yugtairulluku waten Akula, imarpigmi, unani tau͡gaam Kusquqvagmi.
There would be no one left in the Akula region like this, but only down in the ocean, on the Kuskokwim.
Neqnun cali cauluteng. Amllepiarluteng call’ neqet.
They would turn to fish. There were also a great many fish.
Tamaaggun-wa kencikellratgun Agayutem cikiutekngamiki kencikellratgun tua-i amllerrlainartelluki.
Through their reverence, since they are Gods gifts, they were always in plenty through their reverence.
Maa-i mat’um nalliini umyuangcarqama tamakut neqrateng tua-i makut neqteng murilkelluki, mulngakluki.
When I ponder upon it these days, they watched over and were careful about what food they had, their food.
Neq’lipiatullruuq agaani waten tan’gaurlullraullemteńi.
There used to be a lot of fish across there when we were boys like this.
Puukaquaqluteng-llu maavet ceńamun.
They would also collide here on the bank.
Kuimarqamta-llu iliini maaggun naw’un puukaraqluta neqet.
And when we swan, sometimes the fish would ram into us somewhere here.
Tua-i-llu mat’um nalliini tua-i-w’ kencikenriamceteng cat nangengluteng.
Then these days, since we do not rever them anymore, things are depleting.
Kencikellruit au͡gkut.
People back then revered them.
Tuamtellu waten wangkutnun tua-i yugnun atalliniut makut neqput.
Then, our food are evidently connected to us people.
Tuamtellu cetuanek makut piaqata inerqurnauraitkut ivraasqevkenata, tayim’ cetuarcurqata.
Then when they would hunt belugas, they would admonish us against ever wading, when they hunted belugas.
Maavet ukalirnermun agaantaqamta ivraqaasqevkenata inerquanauraitkut.
On this side, when we were across there, they would admonish us against ever wading.
Cetuarcurniluku tamakut qaill’ pilriit tuaten inerqutullruitkut.
They said that those people were hunting belugas and admonished us like that.
Tua-i-llu mat’um nalliini tayim’ nangluteng pissuyuirucamceteng.
And there are no more these days because we don’t hunt them.
Makut-ll’ imkut yaquleyagaat nangluteng tayima pissurnanriimceteng wangkuta pitgaquurluki.
And there are no more of these little birds because we don’t hunt them with arrows anymore.
Tau͡gken makut aipaimta kellutestaita amllericangnaqsaaqluki inerquuteksagulluki pissuyuirutevkarluki yaqulget.
However, these [Caucasian] counterparts of ours who regulate them, make restrictions to try to elevate their populations, and have us stop hunting birds.
Makut yaqulget arulairucuitellruit au͡gkut anglicartemta.
Our caretakers back then would stop [hunting] birds.
Tua-i waten pavani up’nerkami neqkerraarluki
After that was their food source in the spring like this
Tua-i-ll’ cali cetuameng neqnek pirraarluteng imkut tengesciigaliata ingcata
Then when they went downriver, after [eating] fish, when they were unable to fly as they molted
Piyagaat-llu irniarit angtateksaguarcata
When their chicks, their offspring, became the same size
Nutaan cali tamakut pissungluki.
They would start hunting those too.
Qayateng imirluki tekirqengnaurtut.
They would fill their kayaks and arrive en masse.
Cakaniyuunateng-llu, ikegliyuunateng.
And they wouldn’t be affected, wouldn’t decrease.
Mat’um tau͡gken tua-i naliini cat tamangluteng, yaquleyagaat-llu.
Yet these days, things are disappearing, including little birds.
Wall’u-qaa tua-i pissurnanriimceteng piut?
Or is it because we’ve stopped hunting them?
Tua-i au͡gna waten qanengssaka pitauq.
That’s the extent of what I have to say.
Kitak’ im’umek, iciw’ ayagalriani, tayim’ iciw’ ak’a ayagatullret?
Then, you know, those who travel, you know, those who traveled a long time ago?
Iciw’ pellaalliaqa wall’u-q’ qaill’ piaqata kaingaqameng canek nertullruat yuilqumi?
You know, if they happened to get lost or something happened, what would they eat in the wilderness if they got hungry?
Kaingaqameng-qaa neqkaunateng?
You mean when they get hungry without food?
Yaa, iciw’ yuilqumi pellaakata qaill’ neqkailkata camek neryugngaat?
Yes, you know, if they’re lost in the wilderness without food, what can they eat?
Qaill’ iciw’ uksumi wall’u-q’ kiagmi wall’u-q’ up’nerkami wall’u-q’ uksuarmi?
How would they do it, you know, in the winter or summer or spring or fall?
Yaa.
Well.
Au͡gkut-wa waten alerqutullruitkut tua-i neqkailkumta arenqiallugeskumta
The people back then would instruct us like this if we are without food, if we come upon misfortune
Neqkaunata pikumta
If we are without food
Neqengqerrsugngayaaquq waten:
One can actually have food like this:
Maa-i makut uugnaraat neqkaugut cailkuni yuilqumi, tau͡gaam kenengqerquni.
These voles are a source of food if one has nothing in the wilderness, but only if they have a fire.
Tamakut tamaa-i neqkauyaaqut.
Those are actually a source of food.
Tau͡gken cali niitetullrulua, makut-gguq qangqiiret anait imkut neqnguut.
However, I also used to hear that ptarmigan feces are edible.
Tamaa-i tamakut.
There they are.
Ava-i apeskevnga qaillun neqkailkuneng nerengnaqlerkait.
You just asked me how they could try to feed themselves if they are without food.
Makut uugnaraat uksumi tangrruutuut.
We see these voles in the winter.
Tamaa-i tamakut neqkauyaaqut.
Those are actually food sources.
Tau͡gaam-am cali nerailkuni angu qassaasqevkenaku.
But they also said that if he hasn’t eaten in a while, never to eat raw meat.
Wall’u ayainanermini, akaurrluku-w’ tua-i nereksaitellni waten taluyillruarmek tekiskuni
Or as he travels and he hasn’t eaten in a long time, if he comes upon a little fish trap like this
Iciw’ imkut can’giicuayagaat alungya’rnek pitullrat?
You know those small blackfish that they call blackfish fry?
Angu nerqaasqenritait tamakut elliinek, elliinek pitaqeciqniluku anrutaanun.
They said to never eat those, saying that they will [kill] themselves through their stomachs.
Una neraicaraq, arcaqertuq tau͡gaam una meqsulleq kiimi.
Going a long time without eating, though, the only important thing is being thirsty.
Arenqiallugeskuni ayakuni neqkailkuni meqsukuni
If one comes upon misfortune in travels, without food, and is thirsty
Inerquumaukut taqsuqluta qanikcarmek neresqevkenata meqsungramta.
We are admonished against eating snow when we’re tired even if we’re thirsty.
Qanikcartuaraasqevkenata wangkutnek piciqniluta. Ircaqurput pinialiciqniluku tuaten qanikcarmek nerkumta.
They told us not to eat snow, saying that we would [kill] ourselves. They said our heart would weaken if we eat snow like that.
Tau͡gken merkailkuni ca imna plastic-aaq maavet iterrluku
However, if one does not have water, he should put somehing, plastic, in here
Puqlaminun urugcirluku.
Thaw it with his body heat.
Tuaten tua-i alerqulallruit.
That’s how they instructed them.
Unani-llu cali imarpigmi tuaten ayuqluni.
It’s also like that down in the ocean.
Arenqiallugeskuni merkailkuni pitami anrutaa, iciw’ qilua...
If he comes to misfortune and is without water, the stomach of his catch, you know, its intestines...
Piciatun?
Anything?
Ai?
What?
Piciatun pitani?
Anything he’s caught?
Ii-i, piciatun pitani tua-i maklaarem imarpigmiutaam qilua.
Yes, anything he’s caught, the intestines of a bearded seal, a marine animal.
Kepluku qaillun tua-i pitariluk’ piyugtacimitun maqluku.
Cut it to whatever length he wants and squeeze out the liquid.
Un’a imarpik umyuangarrluni mernaituq meq egyungvailgan.
One should not drink down in the ocean at first instinct before the water comes out.
Arenqiallugeskuni, tamatumek avaqlingqerquni, pitangqerquni
If ones gets into misfortune, if there’s one of those around him
Anrutaa wall’ qilua imna takqupak qaill’ tua-i taktariluku kepluku, maqluku-llu, nutaan-llu qanikcarmek imirluku.
He should cut its stomach, or its very long intestines to some length, squeeze out the liquid, then fill it with snow.
Ayagninqigteqaa.
Please start again.
Ii-i, au͡gna ava-i pilqa.
Okay, what I just talked about.
Imarpigmiutaam qilua maqeqaarluku, tua-i-ll’ qanikcarmek imirluku.
After squeezing out the liquid from the intestines of a marine animal, then fill it with snow.
Tua-i-llu-gguq maavet iterrluku puqlaminun.
Then, they said to put it in here to his body heat.
Tau͡gaam kememinun pivkenaku.
But, do not put it against his flesh.
Maavet tau͡gaam tua-i urugarkauluni, waten piluku iquuk qillerrlukek.
Instead, it should melt here, tying its ends like this.
Tua-i-gguq tuaten unani merkiutuut arenqiallugeskuneng.
They said that’s how they prepare water down [in the ocean] if they get into misfortune.
Maani tau͡gken nunam qaingani tua-i arenqiallugeskuni wall’u kiskuni
However, if one gets into misfortune or sinks into water here on the land
Tua-i egmianun nenglliqan aturani nengllingraan piyugngakuniki egmian yuuluki kumelqerpailgaki.
If it’s cold, he should remove his clothes right away even though it’s cold if he can before they get cold.
Makut tua-i aturani ciulaagluki utumacarluki, all’uki-llu.
He should quickly wring his clothes to make them better, and put them on.
Nutaan-llu askuniki canegtangqerqan maakun ekiarakun piluki imirluku.
Then when he puts them on, if there’s grass, he should fill them through his lining here.
Makuk-llu waten unkut.
And [line] these parts down here.
Waten alerquuterluni nengliqan.
That’s his instruction if it’s cold.
Ukuk tau͡gaam waten taptaarturlukek pisqellukek, ukut-llu waten, ukuk.
But, they said that he should keep flexing these here, and these like this.
Tau͡gken-gguq-am waten uitaurquni cikuskani tua-i ukuk pektesciigalkagnek amllirasciigatarkauluni.
However, they said that if he stays still and they freeze, if these can’t move, then he won’t be able to walk.
Ukuk-llu cali waten pikagnek tua-i pektesciigatarkauluni.
And if these [freeze] like this, he won’t be able to move.