Unaqililuni, una-ll’ unaqilingluni.
This hand has become dextrous, and this is getting dextrous.
Oh, quyanaqvaa-lli. (Ii-i.)
Oh, thank goodness. (Yes.)
Tau͡gaam maa-i tegulautellra piniacugtuq, imucetun ciunganicetun pivkenani.
But now, they are too weak to grab things, unlike before.
Taumek uqamailnguarnek canek tegucuitelalrianga.
That’s why I don’t grab anything heavy.
Au͡g’um tau͡gaam tutgaura’urluma aulukuraurlularaanga.
But my dear grandchild takes care of me.
Camiungua?
Where’s he from?
Tutga’rqa makumiungulria-wa.
My grandchild is from here.
Aanangqertuq. Aanii kanani unani enengqertuq.
He has a mother. His mother has a house down there.
Tutgarqaqa.
He’s my grandchild.
Tua-i tang allragni uumek assilingrilngua nal’aqertellrani.
Last year, I was not comfortable with this when it was paralyzed.
Tua-i pinianani.
It was weak.
Maa-i tua-i cali uqamailngurnek tegutellerkaa murilkurluku pila’arqa.
Even now, I am still careful about grabbing anything heavy with it.
Ayautenrilkaten-kiq cayarcit?
I wonder what would’ve happened to you if he didn’t take you to the hospital?
Naamell’. Tua-i...
I don’t know. Well...
....now, get a good shot, and...
...now, get a good shot, and...
Kituusit Yugtun?
What’s your Yup’ik name?
Cuukvaugua.
I’m Cuukvak.
Cuukvagmek piuratuanga im’ aanallma, aanallma.
My late mother would always call me Cuukvak.
Man’a maa-i qanemcikaput maniciqaput, naunraat-wa pilallratnek, imumirpak-llu iqvauralallratnek
We will show these story about cloudberries and how they pick berries in recent times
Yuut iqvalallrat akutarkangengnaqluteng.
How people pick berries for Eskimo ice cream.
Tua-i-wa.
There you have it.
Miktellerpeni-qaa pilallruuten?
Did you also do that when you were small?
Wiinga-llu aanaka unguvaluni, alqaqa-ll’ unguvaluni, kat’um Mary Evon-am maurlua
Me, my mother was alive, and my sister was alive, Mary Evon’s grandmother down there
Kana-i kankurluut ilakanka.
I’m related to those dear ones down there.
Maurluqaat. Maurluat.
She’s their grandmother. Their grandmother.
Aanangqertut alqama, alqama alqaqlaliaratnek aanangertut ukut.
Their mother is my older sister’s adopted older sister.
Iqvalallruuci?
Would you pick berries?
Ii-i, iqvaraqluta.
Yes, we would pick berries.
Aren tua-i wiinga maligucuktalallruyaaqua nasaurlucuaraulua.
Oh my, I would wish to go with them as a little girl.
Aanama tang qessaknauraanga qiangyugnilua uqilaitnilua-llu.
My mother would refuse me saying that I would start crying and that I was too slow.
Tua-i iliini unegtaqlua.
I would sometimes stay behind.
Iliini-am tua-i aguagtaqama malikelaraanga.
When I was insistent sometimes, she would take me with her.
Qaillun iqvaryalallruceci akaar?
How would you travel to pick berries long ago?
Akaar piyuagurluta ayagnaurtukut.
Long ago, we would travel only by walking.
Unaggun un’a Mamterillrem ketii en’arpaullruuq ak’akik’.
Down toward the water from Bethel, there was a large expansive sandbar.
Kuiggaq-wa man’ Kepenkuyagaq. Nutaan-wa kellia una Kusquqvak, Kusquqvauluni.
And the creek here was Kepenkuyagaq. Then toward the water from there was the Kuskokwim.
En’arpaungan unaggun Ekviim aciakun anelrarnaurtukut.
Because it was a big sandbar, we would go downriver under Ekvik.
Tuaggun-llu hospital-aam ketiikun mayuryarartangqerran waten qanikciurumaluni
And through there, since there was a path up toward the water from the hospital that was shoveled
Tamaaggun mayurnaurtukut.
We would go up through there.
Tua-i utercameng-llu tamaaggun cali unaggun Ekviim aciakun itrarnaurtut qaill’ pivkenateng piyuagurluteng.
And then when they went home, they would go upriver under Ekvik again no other way but walking.
Qaillun akuteqarraarqameng pilallruat? Qaillun canek akuyucilallruat?
How did they make their first Eskimo ice cream? What did they use to make Eskimo ice cream?
Akutaqluteng, canek, tunurrarnek.
They would make Eskimo ice cream out of, you know, a little tallow.
Tunurrarmek-llu egciriluteng tangvallrenka imkut yullret.
And people I used to see back then would render tallow.
Cunawa-qaa yuram-llu nalliini aanaka akutesteńgulallinilria.
It turned out that my mother would be the one to make Eskimo ice cream during dance festivals.
Aquinginanemni tuavet enerrarmun camun, neqiviggarmun iternaurtua aanaka una akutellria.
As I was playing, I would go into that little house, a little food cache, to find my mother making Eskimo ice cream.
Cat tua-i-w’ qasgimun pikaitnek yuut ikayualuki.
She would help by bringing something for the people in the community house.
Yaa, akaar-qaa tamaani angutet qasgimi piuralallratni uptelallruaci neqkait?
Okay, when the men would stay in the community house long ago, would you prepare their food?
Wiinga qasgimun nasaurlurluulua kelgisqaqatnga-llu alarqaqlua kelgitullruunga.
When they asked me to invite people from the community house as a little girl, I would constantly invite the wrong people.
Agayuur, Agayuur nulirran kelgesqaqaku qasgimi
When Agayuur’s wife asked me to invite him from the community house
Qavalriit amllelaata qasgimi cauciinaki wii picimtun piaqluki.
Because there were a lot of people sleeping in the community house, I would wake a random one.
Maknaurtut una allauluni.
They would wake up and this would be a different person.
Nutaan piaqluku wii tauna Oscar kelegniluku.
I would then tell him that Oscar was invited.
Nutaan tua-i paqnauraat. Unilluki an’aqlua.
They would then go to him. I would go out and leave them.
Qaillun uptelallruit, aren, iqvarraarluteng atsatateng qaillun qemagtelallruitki?
How did they prepare, I mean, how did they store the berries that they picked?
Qemagtelallruit assigtarluki, puckanun-llu imirtuulluki.
They would store them in containers, then put them into barrels.
Upluki iqvateng puckurluki
They prepared the berries they picked for storage in barrels
Camun pellernarqellriamun pivkenaki.
So that they wouldn’t be affected by anything repulsive.
Tua-i tau͡gken uksurpak yuut imkut akuqurnaurtut, akutaqluteng.
Yet all winter, the people back then would always make Eskimo ice cream.
Akutarturcetnauraitkut.
They would feed us Eskimo ice cream.
Ayuqenrilngurteggun-qaa pililallruit?
Would they make them with different things?
Ii-i. (Allakauluki?)
Yes. (Separately?)
Ilait-qaa allakauluki pililarait?
Would they make some of them differently?
Naam. Pit-wa...
I don’t know. Well...
Kavirlit tau͡gaam allakarrauluki
The cranberries would be a little different
Tangvallemtun wiinga Akulmi uingellemni ayagayaurcama kavirlitaqlua, kavirlinek iqvaraqlua.
As I have seen, when I took a husband and started traveling in the Akula region, I would pick cranberries.
Tangvallemtun meliqerluki pinek-llu, luqruuyiit-llu meluitnek.
As I have seen, I would put it fish roe, you know, even pike roe.
Meliqerluki qantakun passiluki, passinqegcaarluki meluit.
I would put in fish roe and crush them in a bowl, completely crush the roe.
Tua-i-ll’ kavirlinek cali pinarian piluku
And then when it was time, I would add cranberries
Nutaan kavirlit imkut nutaan passiluki.
Then I would crush the cranberries.
Nutaan qerralluku akulluku imna ellacuar uqiqeraqluku.
Then I would whip it to have it increase in volume occasionally adding a little seal oil.
Qerrarnaurtuq imna qantaq, qantapiarraq imangnaurtuq akutarugarmek.
It would increase and fill the old wooden bowl with a lot of Eskimo ice cream.
Apqiit-qaa...
Would they say...
Apqait-gguq qerpertat tamaa-i.
They called those qerpertat.
Maa-i-rpak-qaa cali pililarngatut?
Do they still seem to make it today?
Ii-i, maa-i cali pililartut.
Yes, they still make some today.
Pililartut-wa nallunrilameng.
They make it because they know how to.
Elpet-qaa maa-i-rpak atsalugpiarutenglartuten?
Do you get cloudberries now?
Iqvayuirutengrraanemnek waniwa iqvaqsairutua, atsanun-llu ayagnanrirlua waniwa.
Ever since I’ve stopped picked berries, I haven’t gone, and I’ve stopped going to berry picking grounds now.
Tau͡gaam tutgarama iqvallermeggnek tekicameng au͡g’ukun kavirlinek payugtellranga tamakuliqerluki tangvallemtun.
But when my grandchild and the others arrived and brought me cranberries they picked in that container, I made that as I’ve seen it.
Tangvallemtun qerpercaaqlua. Tua-i nalluvkenaku.
I made qerpertaq as I’ve seen it. I knew how.
Allanek-qaa tamakut atengqertut?
Do those have different names?
Wall’ waniw’ atrit ayuqenrilnguut akutaat:
Or, here are the different names for Eskimo ice cream:
Ii-i.
Yes.
Passiaq
Crushed fish eggs and berries
Ii-i.
Yes.
Tunguggluk-mi cauga?
But what’s tenguggluk?
Tenguggluk-wa neqet aqsaqu͡rit, neqpiat aqsaqu͡rit tenguit.
Tenguggluk is made from fish guts, salmon liver.
Makut-llu natait cali kepuqcaarturluki
And then cutting some of their parts
Tenguggluk imna akuqaarluku
After whipping the livers for tenguggluk
Qaillun?
How does it go?
Tua-i-wa qell’uku, qell’uku, qell’uki imkut neqet tenguyagait akulluki-llu.
They squeeze the small fish livers then whip them.
Tua-i-qaa?
Do you get it?
(Yaa.) Qantaq imirnauraat qivirluku-llu atsanek akulluku-llu.
(Yes.) They would fill the bowl, add berries, and mix it.
Uqirluku tau͡gaam, uqiraqluku.
But they would add seal oil.
Yaa. (Yaa.)
I see. (Okay.)
Allamek-qaa ilakangqertuten?
Do you have anything else to add?
Naamell’.
I’m not sure.
Allakamek-wa ilakaicugnarqellrianga. (Yaa, quyanaqvaa.)
I don’t think I have anything else to add. (Okay, thank you very much.)
Tangvallemtun tua-i wiinga-ll’ ayagyaurcamegnuk aipangllemni
As I have seen, when I got married and we started traveling
Kavirlinek tua-i iqvangnaqa’artelalrianga irnialleraanka unguvallratni.
I would try to pick cranberries when my children were alive.
Peng’garrluki tuaten kavirlinek iqvarlua.
I would also be worried about them and pick cranberries.
Tua-i tau͡gken passiluki, passiluki akulluki.
However, I would crush them to make Eskimo ice cream.
Mikelngullraat tua-i imkut quyurramta tua-i uitatullruukut Lloyd-ankuk-llu, Old Man Lloyd-ankuk.
We and the children loved together along with Lloyd, Old Man Lloyd and his wife.
Lloyd Nick-aq-llu nulirra-llu.
Lloyd Nick and his wife.
Imna-llu Helen-aaq-llu quyurramta pania-llu uitallruukut.
We also lived together with Helen and her daughter.
Tua-i-ll’ akucama nani wani
And then when I was making Eskimo ice cream somewhere here
Mikelngullraat imkut tailuteng wavet aqumluteng tangvagnauraatnga piqa’aqluteng.
Those children would come here to sit and watch, occassionally tasting it.
Qiviamku-llu nerengluteng. Ilangciksaunaki-ll’ wii akullua, qanruteksaunaki.
And when I added berries to it, they started eating. I ignore them and made the Eskimo ice cream without saying anything to them.
Piaqluki, "Akutalngukuvci taqkici tua-i. Akutaq un’ taqniarartuq."
I would say to them, "Stop when you’ve had enough Eskimo ice cream. This is almost done."
Quyana. (Yaa.) Quyana cakneq. (Yaa.)
Thank you. (Yes.) Thank you very much. (Yes.)
Ellirraarluku kanavet taukunun tuiggluku an’aqua.
After I set it down there, I would look back and go out.
Uicungama-am piyaaqelaraitnga, "Yuraqtarlutek ata."
My male cousins would say to me, "Dance, dear ones."
Aullu yag’arcugnaunii-ll’ anqertaqellrianga umiga’rrlua.
Oh my, I wouldn’t raise my hands to dance but go out and disappear.
Ingulak camek meaning-aangqerta? Camek taikaniutengqerta ingulagyaraq? Cauga?
What does ingulak mean? What explanation does the practice of ingulak have? What is it?
Ingularturatuut waten uksuaryartumi.
They hold the Ingulaq Festival towards fall like this.
Camek-wa iqungqerta? Nallukeka tayima wiinga.
I’m not sure what it means. I myself don’t know.
(Naunrat-qaa kinguatni pilartut?) Ii-i, naunraat kinguatni.
(Would they do it after cloudberry season?) Yes, after cloudberry season.
Tua-i akutat tau͡gaam ikgetevkenateng qasgimi.
But there was a lot of Eskimo ice cream in the community house.
Qasgiqu’urluki, qasgilluki.
They would always take them to the community house.
Allanret yugyakange’rmeng piillitaryugnaunateng tua-i.
Even though there were a multitude of guests, they wouldn’t lack anything.
Tamaaggun-qaa amllermek pilillermegteggun nallunairluteng naunrillruciat?
Would they know how much berries they picked by making a lot?
Yaa.
Yes.
I see.
Tua-i-qaa?
Is that all?
Yaa, quyanaqvaa-w’ tua-i.
Yes, thank you very much.
Qanercetenritarpetegnga amllermek.
You didn’t ask me to speak too much.