Ayagniryugtuten?
Do you want to start?
Yaa, ayagnirnariuq-qaa?
(Ii-i, yaa.)
Okay, is it time to start?
(Yes, yes.)
Atam, can we just introduce ourselves?
Look, can we just introduce ourselves?
Kitak’ ukut. Atrit makut.
Okay, these people. Their names.
Ann [?].
From?
(From Bethel.)
Are you a teacher, or what?
No, I work for [?], and I work for YKHC.
[?]
I’m Lucy Sparck and I work here at KCC.
Nalqiggluki. Niicuitukuk [?] atrit.
Introduce them. We can’t hear [?] their names.
Okay, ingna…
Okay, over there…
…for animals.
Makut imumi-am ayagyuallemteńi makunek elluarrluta
These, back when we were young and [did not watch them] well
Elluarrluta tangvangvailemta makut caliaqestaitnek unguvalriit.
Before we watched the ones working on them who were alive.
Imkut tau͡gaam-am aulukestemta tua-i alerquuterluki
makut yuilqurmiutaat pitullruit.
Our caretakers, however, had instructions for
these animals of the wilderness.
Tua-i caanguaqerkaunrirluku alerquagurluta pilaraitkut.
They would instruct us until we would not waste it.
Ca-llu aturarkaunrilnguq pitsaqutmek pissurpek’naku
caanguaruarkauluku.
They also told us not to delibirately hunt something
we would not use, saying that it would get wasted.
Tau͡gaam qigcikluki pitarkat yuilqurmiutaat pilallruitkut.
Instead, they would respect animals they hunted in the wilderness.
Tua-i-am makut qigcikellriit cali wangkutnun tamakut
ciuliamta elluarrluki ellaita aulukellruamegteki
Those who respected them also [passed] those on to us
because our ancestors took good care of them
Caanguaqevkenaki, uqlautevkenaki-llu pillruitki,
alerquutekellruitki wangkutnun.
Not wasting or polluting with them because they gave us those instructions.
Tua-i-llu wangkuta kinguani tamakut tua-i wangkutnun
taicimalriit qanruyuteput tangaaluki
And then afterwards, we started seeing those pieces
of traditional wisdom that were given to us
Una tua-i ner’arkaunrilkumteggu pitsaqutmek tuqulluku pisqevkenaku.
If we’re not going to eat it, not to deliberately kill it.
Tau͡gaam ner’arkaukumteggu tua-i pisqelluku,
uqlautevkenaku-llu pisqelluku.
But if we're going to eat it, they told us to [hunt it] and not to pollute nature with it.
Cali tua-i tauna kiagmi puqlanilaami
Also, because it’s warm in the winter
Cali tauna tuqutellrukumteggu nani yuilqumi pikumta
If we kill that [animal] as we’re somewhere in the wilderness
Tep’ngareskan cailkamun egtesqevkenaku.
If it starts to smell, they told us not to throw it on the ground.
Tau͡gaam nuna elaggaarluku, nuna elaggaarluku patuluku-llu.
Instead, after digging into the land, cover it.
Tua-i tuaten alerquuterluta.
We had that instruction.
Cali…
Also…
One moment. That’s going to be translated.
Waqaa? Taklilliuq wall’u-qaa?
What’s the matter? Is it too long or what?
Nuu, tauna qanellren taqraarru.
(Ii-i.)
No, finish what you were saying first.
(Okay.)
Au͡gna icigg’ qanrulluki elaggaarluki tau͡gaam tamakut ellisqelluki.
You know, how they told them only to dig and put those.
Ii-i, elagluku nuna.
Yes, dig into the ground.
Cailkamun egtevkenaku, tau͡gaam elaggaarluku nuna
nutaan-llu patuluku tuavet.
Don’t throw it on the ground, but after digging into the land,
cover it there.
Cali-llu nani pikumta neqa camek mat’umek cali tuaten
ner’arkaunrilkumteggu assiireskan
Also, if we have some of this food that has gone bad
which we won’t eat
Tutmallrunrilngurmun ellisqelluku yuum tutmayuilkiinun.
They said to put it where people have not and will not tread upon.
Tua-i tamakut tuaten alerquutekellruluki wangkuta
tamakunek anglicartemteńek.
Those were our instructions from those who raised us.
Cali yuilqumi-am alerquutengqellrulriakut makunek cali
nunam qaingani pissulaamteki tua-i makut
We also had instructions for the wilderness
because we hunt these things on the land
Cali kapkaanarturluteng ilaput pilaameng wangkuta-llu.
Because our familes and we used animal traps.
Tua-i-am cali taum yuum pitaa qigcikluku pisqelluku
wangkuta pikenrilamteggu.
They also told us to respect what that person had caught
because it’s not ours.
Cali alerquuterluta tauna ayakataqan-llu wall’u pitarkaq
tangerrluku tuqutesqelluku wangkutnun
We also had instructions that if that one was going to go
or if we see an animal to kill it
Agarrluku-llu nuniinun tuavet yuan tekiskuniu ayagpailgan
And hang it there so that when the owner comes to it
before leaving
Quyaarkauluni yuk tauna tuaten pitaminek
kitumun imumun tuaten pillrucianek.
That person will be thankful that someone had done that
to what he had caught.
Teglegesqevkenaku pikenrilamteggu.
Inerquuterluta-am tamatumek.
They told us not to steal it because it’s not ours.
We had that admonishment.
Elitengqertuq-gguq yuum waten piurallra.
They say a person can learn to do this.
Yuum piinek pikenrilkeminek tegucullra cali eliterluni
pikenrilkeminek tegucugluni.
One can also learn to talk another person’s possession
that is not his own.
Tua-i-am tamakut inerquutnguluteng wangkutnun.
Those had admonishments for us.
Tau͡gaam-gguq wangkuta tau͡gaam pitamteńek
tuaten atuusqelluta yuum allam pikenrilkiinek tegutevkenata.
But, they said that we should only use what we caught
withought taking another person’s.
Waten tua-i alerquutengqellruukut wangkuta
au͡gkunek anglicartemteńek.
These are the instructions we had from those who raised us back then.
Waten pitaqerluku pilaku.
That is all from me.
Okay…
…[ernerit] pitekluki wangkuta alerquutaitellruukut.
…we didn’t have instructions concerning [their days].
Tau͡gaam-am niitelartukut imarpiim tungiinek-llu
wall’u alqunaq taicingareskan
But, we hear that from the direction of the ocean
or if it suddenly gets foggy
Meq, meq taicinga’arrluni pikan wangkuta maani
kiaqvarmiuni qanlartukut iliini
If the water suddenly gets foggy, we upriver people sometimes say
“Iliit-gguq-am imarpigmi, imarpigmi pitliniuq.”
“So, someone has caught something in the ocean.”
Taicingareskan tuaten tua-i qanerluta tuaten
tuaten tua-i pitniluku, picukluku qanerluta.
When it gets foggy like that, we say that they caught something,
that we think they caught something.
He said that…
…maani.
…here.
Maani-q’ kiaqvani?
(Yaa, nunamiutaat-wa.)
Upriver here?
(Yes, land animals.)
Tua-i-wa makut nunamiutaat…
These land animals…
Nallunrilkuvki uss’ iliit tamakut nalqiga’arteqerki
qaill’ nunamiutaat pilauciat.
Hey, if you know, please explain about some of those,
how the land animals [are treated].
Nunamiutaat-wa makut au͡gkut ciuliamta aulukellrukait kencikluki.
Our ancestors back then took care of revered land animals.
Caluki, tua-i-w’ uqlautevkenaki.
You know, they didn’t pollute nature with them.
Assirluki auluktullruit au͡gkut tangvallma-llu wiinga.
They and the ones I saw took good care of them.
Alerquraqluta-llu tamakut enrit natmun paivngalriamun
egtesqevkenaki kencikluki.
They also instructed us not to throw their bones
in places with heavy traffic out of reverence.
Pitait, pitait angutet kencikluki, kenekluki.
They revered and loved the animals that the men caught.
Egtevkenaki-llu enqengraitki pitullruit.
And they didn’t[carelessly] throw even their bones away.
Elauqurluki-llu enrit elakaulluki, tua-i patuqerluki.
They always dug and covered their bones.
Tuaten egcet’lallruit imumi ak’a.
They used to have people dispose of them like that
a long time ago.
Sagtellriartaitellruuq nunam qainga tamarmi.
There was no mess in all of the land.
Makunek can-allernek, callernek tua-i makunek
Kass’at nerkuaritnek pitangvailgan nunam qainga cataitellruuq.
Before there were these cans, these various Western
garbage materials, there was no [waste] on the land.
Sagtellriamek kalikallermek-llu tangerrnaitellruuq.
There was no visible mess or paper materials.
Assillruuq nunam qainga sagtellriartaunani.
The land was good with no mess.
Yuut nunaseng kencikellruat.
The people revered their land.
Ukut nunat nunaseng avatetuumaan kencikellruat.
They revered their land, including the areas around them.
Wangkuta-llu alerqutullruitkut.
They also used to instruct us.
Pingnaqsaraput arnani, iqvaryaraput,
tarricaraput, kayangussuryaraput-llu
The places we women subsist, our berry picking lands,
where we tread, and our egg hunting lands
Tamakut arulairvikaqamteki uqlarluku unitesqevkenaku.
They told us that if we stop at those not leave it messy.
Callret-llu nerkuaput, ilakuaput agurrluk’ paivngaluki
saggluki uniteqaasqevkenaki
They also told us never to leave our food scraps,
whatever leftovers we had, in open places as messes
Tau͡gaam elakauqurluki patuqerturluki pilaasqelluki.
Instead, always dig and cover them.
Yuut imkut watuam nalliicetun ayuqellrunritut nunatuumarmeng.
The people back then, including their land, was not like now.
Nuna man’a qigcikellruat.
Qigcikluku yuullruut.
They respected this land.
They respected it in their lives.
Well, she said that…
Uniciyuunii wiinga iqvatuunga ilumun.
(Qanrutelqaaci-qaa?)
Truly, I do not leave anything when I pick berries.
(Did they tell youpl?)
Atsanek piaqamta…
(Atsanek uniciyuunii iqvatullruunga.)
When we [pick] berries…
(I wouldn’t leave berries when I picked them.)
Imna-llu iiqupayaaq atauciungraan teguqerluku
tua-i qaltamnun ektuaqa.
I even take a single little seed and put it in my bucket.
Tua-i-llu unatvalqa tua-i cataunani waten-wa umyuarteq’laama
And the place I picked berries has nothing because I think like this
Umyuartequ’urlua kesianek wiinga pituunga:
I always think like this:
“Agayutem ellilqaa una wani. Wavet nauvkaraa wani.
“God put this here. He made it grow here.
“Wiinga picuvvlaglua cekavcilua pingaitua.”
“I will not [gather] without being thorough and scatttering them.”
Maa-i mat’um nalliini ukaqvani mat’umek pingrraanemteńek
waten umyuarteqsaurrlua iqvatuunga.
These days, since we’ve recently gotten this [religion],
this is how I think when I pick berries.
Iiqupayaaq-llu ataucirraq angenqurrilivkenii ayuqluki teguluki.
I also take a single berry all the same
without saying there are bigger ones.
Atauciyagaq-llu iliini iiqupayaaq naumalartuq epumi.
And sometimes, there is a single seed growing on a stem.
Tauna-llu kiigarrluku uamutkengramku ek’artetuaqa.
I also peel that off and put it in even though it takes up my time.
Tua-i piciryaramnek wiinga iqluvkenii qanertua.
I am honestly talking about my personal custom.
Okay, she’s answering it, this, from…
Tamatum nalliini yaqulget amllepiatullrulriit.
At that time, there were a great many birds.
Qangqiiret-llu cali amllepiatullruluteng.
There were also a great many ptarmigans.
Tua-i makunek alerquutellegnek anguyagtem pistainek alairpailgata
Before there were these governement workers with laws
Yuut tua-i up’nerkami tau͡gaam pissutullrulriit
yaqulegnek qangqiirnek-llu.
People used to hunt in the spring for birds and ptarmigans.
Tau͡gaam tamakut pitateng, tua-i-wa taryuq man’a
tekitellruami tamaa nallemteńi wangkuta
But what they caught, because salt came early in our time
Tamakut tua-i yaqulget sulunatullruaput assiirpailgata.
We would preserve those birds with salt before they spoiled.
Makut-llu qangqiiret agarrluki kinercirluki kemgit.
They would also hang ptarmigan meat to dry.
Tua-i tuatnatullruaput tamakut.
We [preserved] those like that.
Cali nuqlitetullruameng tamaani iliini makut kuvyat alairpailgata
Also, because they would sometimes have shortages
back then before these [Western] nets appeared
Arutulinek, arutulinek kuvyangqellruamta tamaani
allrakuaqan cimiryarauluteng
Because we had nets and deteriorated back then
that needed to be replaced every year
Ilii pisciigataqluni, unangesciiganani neqmek amllermek.
Sometimes, it couldn’t catch a lot of fish.
Tua-i tamaa-i tamakut piaqamteki, nutegnek-llu anglanillrunrilamta
When we [hunted] those, because we didn’t have
an abundant supply of guns
Qangqiirnek ciumek pilaamta negartura’arluki tau͡gaam
pelacinaggarnek pissutullruluki qangqiiret.
Because we hunted ptarmigans first, we would trap ptarmigans
with snares made from twine.
Tua-i tuaten pitullruluta amllellruameng tamatum nalliini
We used to do that because there were a lot back then
Makunek igvarivailgata makut qatellriit akmani caliamegteggun.
Before these Caucasians these things with their work out of state.
Makunek-llu melqunek imalegnek paltuugugarnek
Alaska-q patuvailgan
And before Alaska was covered with these numerous coats
that are filled with fur
Yaqulget melqurritnek imarluteng amlletullruameng tamaani.
They were filled with bird feathers because there was a lot back then.
Tua-i tamakut up’nerkami sulunatullruaput yaqulget ilait
kiagmi ner’arkauluki.
We used to preserve some of those birds in salt
during the spring to eat them over the summer.
Cali-llu pilaraitkut imkut, waten kayungussutuukut up’nerkami.
They also told us, [you know] we gather eggs in the spring like this.
Tua-i-llu ukut wani murilkelaamegteki kayangut
Because they observed these eggs
Kayangut yung’artaqata tua-i tuani taqevkalaraitkut.
They would have us stop when the fetuses developed in the eggs.
Kayangut tegunqigtesqevkenaki yungniluki,
yaqulgurtarkaurrniluki.
They told us not to take eggs again because their fetuses
had developed and would become birds.
Tua-i, tua-i tuaten cali inerquuterluta tamakunek.
We also had admonishments like that for those.
Cali tua-i qanrutaqluta imkut anglicartemta waten
Those who raised us would also tell us this
Cali tamakut unangkengaput tuaten cali uqlauskumteki
waten qanerluta, qanrulluta:
If we also polluted nature with those things we gathered,
they would tell us this:
Aulukestemta-gguq uqlaupakaqumteki
wangkutnek au͡g’arciqai tamakut.
If we keep polluting nature with them,
our caretaker will remove those.
Tua-i tuaten qanruyuterluta.
We had that traditional wisdom.
Uqlauskumteki-gguq wangkutnun cikiutekenrirciqai.
They said that if we pollute nature with them,
he will not give them to us anymore.
Yuk-gguq tua-i piyurraarluni unangyurraarluni
unangesciigalituluni uqlaupakaquniki pitani.
They say that after that person is a good hunter and catches a lot,
he can no longer catch anything because he pollutes nature
with what he catches.
Okay, he mentioned [Forest] and asked him a question.
Qaill’ qigcik’lallrusiki tamakut?
How did you show respect to those?
Qaillun-llu… cure them?
And how...cure them?
Cure them? How did they cure them?
You make them last through the winter or…
Would you eat them all winter long?
Qaill’ qemaggluki caluki, icigg’ pegtevkenaki?
How did you preserve them, you know, without discarding them?
Qaill’ aulukluki? Ii-i.
(Ii-i. Auluksuarneq-qaa?)
How did you take care of them? Yes.
(I see. How do take care of them?)
Uksuarmi-wa yaqulget waten piyaraat-wa
The habit for birds in the fall
Kuimanga’artaqata murilkelaamegteki imkut yuut
When they start swimming, because the people back then observed them
Mik’aqameng-gguq yaqulget makut piyagaat neqngunritut
miksiyaagluteng angliriqerpailegmeng.
They said that when bird chicks are small, they are not food
because they’re too small before they grow.
Tau͡gaam tua-i nutaan angliriqercameng yaqiuqlagangartellratni
tamaani tua-i nutaan neqngurcilarait.
Only when they are grown and start flapping their wings, they treat them as food only then.
Nutaan tamaani piyugngaluki pikunegteki yuum
amlleq-llu tamakunek piyuilami
A person can then [hunt] them if he wants to,
and because he wouldn’t catch a lot
Caqapigtellriit tau͡gaam yuut ayagayugngalriit tamakunek
Only once in a great while, people who are able to travel [hunt] those.
Yuilqumun ayagalaameng mat’umi September-aami
atsanun pingaqameng, August-aam-llu maani nangellrani
Because they travel to the wilderness in September when the berries
are [ready], and at the end of August
Tamaa-i tamaani anglirilartut piyagaat.
Those chicks grow at that time.
Tua-i urenkutmek tau͡gaam pissu’urqamegteki
assiriaqata piyagaat tengvailgata
But when people hunt during the time of opportunity
when the chicks are good before they can fly
Tuaten nutaan unangkengaqameng au͡gkut tua-i
sulunarluki pituit assiirutarkauvkenaki.
When the people back then caught some, they would
preserve them in salt to prevent spoiling.
Piilkuneng assiirutarkaugaqata nutaan ilameggnun cikiutekluki
tuaten assiirupailgata.
If they don’t have any and they woould spoil, they would
give them to their families before they spoil like that.
He’s saying that when birds are, when little birds are small,
he said they’re not much of food for them.
But only when they get bigger, people then go after them.
And he’s saying that, you know, from being around here,
he said not everybody went after them.
But those who did, went after them and then salted them again.
And if you…
…-gguq-qaa tamakut, wall’u-qaa tamaa nertulqait?
…she asked if [they stored] those, or did they eat them right away?
Tamaani ilaita kayangut kayangussu’urqameng
tuaten cipnelegmek pissu’urqameng
Back then, when some gathered eggs,
when they gathered more than they needed
Qassaita elaucuitait, cayuitait-ll’ qemagcuitat
tau͡gaam kenirraarluki.
They don’t dig them into the ground raw, or store them,
only after cooking them.
Kenirraarluki nutaan tuaten assiirutarkaunrirluteng taq’lartut.
They’re only done and won’t spoil after cooking like that.
Kenirraarluki tau͡gaam nutaan qemaggluki.
They only stored them after cooking them.
Natmun? Camun?
To where? To what?
Tua-i-wa natmun, natmun pilartatki?
I’m not sure where they stored them.
Ilait cikuvkarluki, tua-i cikumaluteng keniumaluteng
quyuita tua-i qemaggluki.
Some froze them, cooked and froze them, then stored them all together.
Ilaita-llu tamaa ciuqvani uquutnek pingqelallruameng
angtuanek caqussayugnek
And because they had seal oil containers a long time ago,
big seal pokes
Tamaa-i tamaavet ilait camun umyuaqutaqamegteki qemaggluki
They would store some of them in those to prepare for uncertainty
Kenirraarluki tau͡gaam uqumun pulalluki.
Only submerging them in seal oil after cooking them.
Tua-i nutaan pinariata tua-i nutaan kautuarluki
anlluki tamakut kayangut.
When it was time, they would reach in and take those eggs out.
Okay, he’s saying that if people take…
Caugat ukut?
What do these people [work as]?
Ukut Fish and Wildlife-ami work-atuuq, calituuq.
(Ii-i.)
[S]he works, caliluni, at Fish and Wildlife.
(I see.)
YKHC-mi-llu una.
(Ii-i.)
And this one at YKHC.
(I see.)
Au͡gkuneng aptarpenga qaillun seal-at pitaqaqamteki
qaillun piluki [pillerniaratneng].
You asked me about who [we store] these seals when we catch them.
Yaa, mat’um kumlivigtangvailgan.
(Yaa.)
Yes, before there were freezers.
(Okay.)
Kumlivigtangvailgan pillrat ukut nallunricugait.
(Ii-i.)
They want to know how they [stored food] before freezers.
(I see.)
Kumlivigtangvailgan pillrat ukut nallunricugait.
(Ii-i.)
They want to know how they [stored food] before freezers.
(I see.)
Nuu.
No.
Au͡gkunek anerneritnek pitaqaqamegteki unegkumiut seal-at
(Au͡g’um anernerit pitekluki.)
Their spirits when they catch seals down from the ocean
(For their spirits.)
Qaill’ anernerit piluki pilartatki?
How do they [show respect] to their spirits?
Qaillun anernera taum pitaqekuniu tuqukuni
qaillun piluku piciqa?
What will happen to the spirit of that [seal]
when it’s caught and dead?
Nuu, elpeci-ggem qaill’ pitullrunillrungataci mercilluki qaill’…
No, didn’t you say that you did something to them,
giving them water to drink…
Oh, tamakut. Oh, yaa.
Oh, those. Oh, yes.
Pitaqaqamegteki tamaani nayirraungraan
qang’a-llu maklaungraan
Back when they caught them, even if it was a small ringed seal
or even a bearded seal
Waten up’nerkami pitaqaqamegteki, tagutaqamegteki,
enmun itrutaqamegteki
When they caught them in the spring, brought them to land, brought them into their homes.
Nayirraungraan qang’a-llu maklak pitaqaqamegteggu
When they catch even a small ringed or even a bearded seal
Maaggun tau͡ga unataikun ca pitekluku tamana [pillerniaraa]
For some reason, [s]he would [do this] here with his hands
Mermeng ugg’un unataikun kuvqaquuqerraarluku
aitarrluku-gga kemgilengraan
After pouring water on his hands, open its mouth even if it’s skinny
Kemgilengraan qanranun tauna ilakuarteng kuvluku.
Even if it’s skinny, pour that leftover [water] in its mouth.
Tuqumangraan?
(Ii-i, tuqumangraan.)
Even though its dead?
(Yes, even though it’s dead.)
Ullingqangraan enem iluani maklak tauna.
Even if that bearded seal is butchered inside that house.
Tau͡ga-llu tamat-llam man’a maklagmeng
pit’eqerraakacagalria civuqliuluku
And then, the first thing when a boy had his very first catch
of everything, even a bearded seal
Nutaan wanigg’ pissuryaurqaaralria nutaan
maklagmeng pitaqeqarraaraqaku
When one who went on his first hunting trip
caught his first bearded seal
Tau͡gatnarraarluku cali unataikun ugg’un kuv’rraarluku…
After doing that, pouring [water] with his hands here…