...taumek aipangellrulliniunga.
...he became my husband.
Tua-i-ll’ tauma pianga
Then that person said to me
"Kitak’ tua-i itra. Aturaten ukut itrauciiqanka waniku."
"Now, go in. I will bring your clothes upriver later."
Kiani, uani Keggukarmiut kiaqliitni uitaluta Kelliqucirmiuni-gguq wani.
Upriver, we lived downriver upriver from Keggukarmiut in a place called Kelliqucirmiut.
Aren tua-i-llu itrarlua unuakuarmi yuut makut tupalliniata
Oh my, then I went in when these people woke up in the early morning
Kaminiarturayuitellratni, ellakun saanilitullratni kenillerteggun.
When they didn’t use stoves, when they made kettles of hot water outside in fireplaces.
Aren tua-i itrarlua tua-i yuut makut tua-i tangva’gqatnga tua-i cukarikanirlua ulurluki piaqlua.
Oh my, when I went in and these people watched me, I would go more quickly and look away from them.
Aren tua-i itrama tua-i kiiryuama-ll’ u͡gayarlua, taukut-llu ciunerma qaill’ pinrilatnga.
Oh my, when I went it, I undressed because I was hot, and because those before me didn’t do anything to me.
U͡gayarlua tua-i aanama-ll’ imum qaill’ pinrilan camek-llu qanrutevkenii.
I undressed because my mother didn’t do anything and didn’t say anything to me.
U͡gayarlua.
I undressed.
Qavarniama tua-i inarrlua tayim’ qavallinilua.
I lay down because I was sleepy and ended up falling asleep.
Cunaw’ tua-i tuaten aipangucilqa nallumanaluku, kiituan uterrluta kingunemteńun tekitukut.
It turned out that I wouldn’t know that I had gotten married for a long time, until eventually we arrived back home.
Cunawa-gguq waniwa pitsaqutmek tauna angun ciullegyugciurluni tua-i takarnirlua.
It turned out, they said, that that man purposely wanted us to go before him to make me respectfully withdrawn.
Tua-i tuaten tua-i nallunrillruaqa.
That’s how I found out.
Tua-i uingqerruciqa nalluku tua-i yuulua.
I lived without knowing that I had a husband.
Atam tua-i uksuarumainanrani uqtaqutullratni ingkut ellangvillrenka Cevv’arnermiut
You see, during the fall, when the people of Chefornak over there where I grew up used to use hookless lures when dipnetting.
Tuani-qaa yuurtellruuten?
Were you born there?
Cevv’arnermiuni yuurtellrunritua.
I wasn’t born in Chefornak.
Up’nerkami-gguq Isrimiuni wani up’nerkillerni May-aami yuurtellruunga.
They said that I was born in the spring in Isrimiut, a spring camp, in May.
Atakuyartuan-llu-gguq kayangutellriartangqerrluni tauna yuurtelqa.
And they said that near evening, there was someone who found eggs when I was born then.
Nateqsigta tauna Isrmiu? Isrimiut Cevv’arnermiut natiitni?
How far is Isrimiu? Isrimiut, which direction from Chefornak?
Ketiitni camani ingrik. Ingrik-qaa tangeqsaitagken? (Tanglaragka.)
Toward the water down in the mountains. Haven’t you seen the mountains? (I see them.)
Ingriik ketiigni. Ingriik ingkuk ketiigni Qipnermiut akiqliigketa.
Toward the water from the mountains. Toward the water from the mountains across from Kipnuk.
Nunaullruut-qaa taukut wall’u-qaa uksuillret?
Was that a village or a winter camp?
Nunarpauluteng nunauluteng. Enet amllerrluteng nevulget up’nerkissuutait.
They were a big village. There were a lot of houses with sod for their spring camps.
Ukaqliit-wa cali Nuuteqerrmiut cali enetarluteng, qasgingqerraqluteng.
And toward here, Nuuteqerrmiut also had houses, and they had a community house.
Yaaqliit-wa call’ ingkut Cevv’arnermiunek nutaan yulget. Qikertaarmiut call’ yugyapiarluteng.
Over from them was the populated place of Chefornak. There were also a lot of people in Qikertaarmiut.
Canimelulluteng tua-i. Qimugtet-llu nepliralriit alaitaqluteng, yuut-llu tarritellriit alaitaqluteng.
They were close together. And the baying dogs were visible, and people wandering were visible.
Aren canimelutqapiggluteng taukut up’nerkillrit.
Oh my, their summer camps were very close together.
Wani tua-i imkut nauvillrenka wii ukaqliitnun Isrimiunun-gguq wavet up’nerkitullruut, Isrimiuni.
They said that the place I grew up would set up spring camps on this where they called in Isrimiut, in Isrimiut.
Arenqiapaa-ll’ up’nerkiluteng.
Oh my goodness, they were at spring camp.
Makut-wa tang avatiitni ircenrrarugaat.
You see, there were a lot of legendary little people around them.
Uurcartangnaurtuq-llu.
And one with a signaling gaff would appear.
Nunanun-llu waniw’ tekitarkaurrluni uurcaq taun’ tamarluni.
And when the one with the signaling gaff was going to reach the village, it would disappear.
Tamaqertelluku-llu maaken caniatnek ikamrat makut qavciunguluteng-llu tayim’ ketmurrluteng.
And after it disappeared, there would be some amount of sleds going to the water beside them.
Ketmurqaarluteng yuut taukut nunat ukut up’nerkilriit ciungatni piurluteng tamakut ircenrraat.
After they went to the water, those legendary little people would keep ahead of the people from that spring camp settlement.
Ciungatni tua-i piurluteng.
They kept ahead of them.
Ikamrat makut ketmurqaarluteng kelutmurrnaurtut. Ikamrait-wa kavirpak imaqaarluteng unguvalrianek.
After those sleds went to the water, they would go inland. Their sleds were read, filled full with animals.
Tua-i-ll’ atakuqerluku tayima tua-i ikamrat imkut maavet tua-i ingriik tungiignun tayim’ ayagaqluteng.
Then right when evening came, those sleds would go here toward the mountains.
Atakuqerluku nutaan uurcartangluni waken nunanek kingunelegmek up’nerkilrianek.
In the evening, there would be one with a signaling gaff who was from this spring camp settlement.
Tua-i-llu qasgitangqellruuq elatemteggun gguun qasgigpagmek, qasgigpaarayagarmek.
Then there was a community house outside of our house here, a huge community house.
Ap’au͡rlurput una Evngum-gguq una atii tailuni qasgim kepneranun pikavet aqumqerluni
Our dear grandfather, the one they said was Evnguq’s father, would come and sit up there on the above-ground entrance of the community house
Un’a uurcaq tagelria ukavet tua-i aturpauqurluku.
He sang to the one withe the signaling gaff who was coming inland toward here.
Wangkuta-w’ tua-i naseknagni tan’gaurluut-llu unglumakevut, ungluluku niicugnikvut.
And we girls and boys would embrace him like a nest, embraced and listened to him.
Aren kiituani tang yuarutii-llu elitarput.
Oh my, we even eventually learned his song.
Waten tang atutullrulria tauna uurcaq tangvaurluku:
You see, he would sing like this, watching that one with the signaling gaff:
"Uurca-raya-yarra-ii-ya
"One with the signaling gaff-raya-yarra-ii-ya
"Aa-ii-ya can’guaravluarrlugaat
"Aa-ii-ya [?the many blades of grass]
"Issur-issur-issur-issur maklassi-yaa-yarra-ii-ya
"Spotted seal-spotted seal-spotted seal-spotted seal, bearded seal-yaa-yarra-ii-ya
"Aa-ii-ya can’guaravluarrlugaat."
"Aa-ii-ya [?the many blades of grass."
Tua-i elicingqapiggluk’ wangkuta niicugnistaini.
We who listened to him completely learned it.
Uurcam-ll’ imum tekicami urenkelluku ciuqerranun nang’arcami
When the one with the signaling gaff arrived, when he stood in front of him with clear intent
Negcikcuaraminek, negcikcuarani kapuarrluku wavet elliqerluku qanemciluni.
He stuck his small gaff in the ground, put it here, and told a story.
Aqvalgirarkanek, aqvalgirarkat qanrulluki.
He told the ones who would get [the animals they caught].
Tua-i aren imkut ircenrraat ciungatni pillret amllertatait unuaquaqan ketmurrnaurtut.
Oh my, the same number of legendary little people would go to the water in front of them every day.
Amllertacirkait cunaw’ tua-i waniw’ ciungatni maniurluki tamakut.
It turned out that they would show beforehand how many there would be.
Aling tua-i amllertatait imkut ketmurtellret unuaquaqan aqvalgirluteng tayim’ ayaganaurtut.
Oh my, the same number that would go toward the water everyday would go get the animals they had caught.
Aren uksuuluku up’nerkilriit imkut egkuiruqaqnaurtut natermun-llu ciptaqluteng.
Oh my, in the winter, the ones who were at spring camp would fill the walls of their houses, and excess would go on the floor.
Unguvalrianek egkurpallraat qau͡gkut, up’nerkissuutet enet egkuit unguvalrianek muirluteng, natermun ciptaqluteng.
The huge walls in there, the walls of their spring camp houses would be filled with animals, and the excess would go on the floor.
Arenqiapakar.
Oh my goodness.
Tuaten tua-i angullrenka au͡gkut ayuqellruut.
That’s what the people I was born in time to see back then were like.
Kitak’ uitaqaqaa. Kenriutelliniuq-am una.
Hold on, please. This ran out of battery.
...ukut tutga’rma irniarit cali, iluperanka.
...my grandchildren’s children, my great-grandchildren.
Pangall’am yuin alqaat, Nura’ar-wa, pi-wa, Qussauyaq-wa, Arnaaquq-wa, Tikaaq-wa
The eldest sister of Pangall’aq’s children, Nura’ar, you know, Qussauyaq, Arnaaquq, Tikaaq
Ugna-w’ kinguqlikacagiit Nanugaq.
Their youngest sibling downriver, Nanugaq.
Ii-i.
I see.
Uyangqulriim-wa call’ irniari talliman, arvinerkaatnek ua-i aqsangluni.
And Uyangqalria with her five children, pregnant with their sixth downriver.
Miisaam-wa call’ irniari pingayun.
And Miisaq’s three children.
Ciulluum-wa call’ irniara atauciq, kinguqlirkai irnicuaruur[luteng], nuringarmeng an’urluteng.
And Ciulluk’s one child, what would be their younger siblings being miscarried, coming out undeveloped.
Tallimaurcaaqluteng taukut nuringarmeng anellret, kinguqlirkai uum Ciulluum yuan.
There are now five who’ve come out undeveloped, the ones who’d Ciulluk’s child’s younger siblings.
And over in Kwigillingok, Akat’aq’s children are my great-grandchildren.
Atam alqaat maantuq.
Their oldest sister is here, you see.
Tungii-wa tayim’ cali Cevv’arnermi cali ukurrisngaluni.
The next younger one has also married as a daughter-in-law in Chefornak.
Tau͡gaam tailartuq angayuqaagminun.
But she comes to her parents.
Ingna-wa...
The one over there...
Imumi alaitelallruut ak’a avani nallevni.
They were visible long ago during your time.
Nallemni amllellruut angalkut.
There were a lot of shamans in my time.
Kitak’ tamakunek wani qanemcitqerkut.
Please tell us stories about them.
Waten niitelartukut maa-i wani: assilriit-gguq angalkuut, assiitellriit-llu angalkuut.
We hear this now: good shamans, and bad shamans.
Wall’u qaillun. Piciatun pilliunga wiinga. Elpet nallunritaten. Kitak’ qanemciqaa tamakunek.
Or however. I might be speaking nonsense. You know them. Please tell stories about them.
Ilait maaten im’ angalkut murilkenganka tamakut ilait makut yuut qinuciakaqluki.
Some of them, I noticed that some people on the verge of death would hallucinate seeing those shamans that I observed.
Tuquqatalriit-ll’ ilait qinuciaraaqluteng angalkumek taumek qinuciaracirluteng.
And some of the people on the verge of death would hallucinate seeing that shaman.
Tuquqatalriit ilait tuatnaarluteng, taumun tuaten piniluteng.
Some on the verge of death would do that, saying that he was going after them.
Qinuciaraaqluteng.
They hallucinated on the verge of death.
Ilait tau͡gken makut angalkuuniyaaqengraiceteng watqapik camek qanernaaraunateng angalkuugaqluteng.
Even though some, however, were said to be shamans, they would be shamans without every having any word said about them.
Makutun yuunginarrartun ayuqaqluteng qaill’ qanernaunateng.
They would be like ordinary people, with no word said about them.
Tua-i tau͡gaam tamakunek avullugutengqelallruut.
However, there were bad ones among them.
Tangerrluku ilunga’urluan wiinga-llu angalkurtellrulrianga tang.
Looking at his female cross-cousin, I also caught a shaman, you see.
Angalkurtellrulrianga qavamkun.
I caught a shaman in my dream.
Tua-i maaten tang im’ ellangua, qanemcitnaamken, yuilqumi ellangua waten kiirrarma aqumgalrianga nunam qaingani.
One time, I found myself, let me tell you the story, I found myself in the wilderness, sitting all by myself on the ground.
Maaten tang caqalriamek niicama ukatmun takuyartua, amik una.
When I heard something, I turned my head this way and saw a door here.
Talliq-wa tang man’ tallirpilirneq nuna man’ tua-i waten agturturluku agiirtellria.
There was a right arm, you see, touching the ground as it approached.
Umyuarteqa’artua, "Aling aren assilriarunripagta tanem man’a."
I thought, "Oh my goodness, this is not a good things."
Ayumian tekipailganga yaaqsiggaan piicaglua qavamni camani.
Then before it reached me since it was a little far, I prayed in my sleep down there.
Atanermun ikayuusqellua, man’a-llu agiirtellria tekiteqatarteka wiinga inglulurutkaanek eneqanaitnilua, nallunritnilua.
I asked the Lord to help me, and that I knew that I couldn’t think of anything to combat this thing approaching that was going to reach me.
Ayuqiikun ingluliurutkaitnilua, piniliisqellua tau͡gaam.
I said I had nothing to combat with the same power, but asked to give me strength.
Pinimek cikiisqellua mat’um tungiinun.
I asked to be given strength for this situation.
Tekitellerkamnek qungvangama
Because I was nervous as it was going to reach me
Taqngama uitua waten cetungqallemni irugma akuliigni uluaqa un’ ulurpall’er.
When I was finihsed, I opened my eyes as I was sitting with my legs stretched out to find my huge woman’s knife between my legs.
Qaill’ taun’ tailarta? Amta-ll’ wii yuilqumllua.
How did that come? Yet I was in the wilderness.
Teguqerluku.
I took it.
Teguqaamku tangrraqa maa-i tua-i tekiteqatallinikiinga.
When I took it, I saw that it was going to reach me here.
Atam tua-i caunqegcaqka.
You see, I turned to face it straight on.
Tua-i caungamku maa-i tua-i tekiteqataanga waten wavet ciisqumigglua.
When I faced it as it was going to reach me, I knelt here like this.
Uluaq waten epuakun tegukeka inglugtun.
I took the knife with its handle like a [?weapon].
Tuani piicaggaarlua uitellruunga ayuqucimtun ayuqevkenii tua-i pinirnganii-llu.
After I prayed then, I opened my eyes and didn’t feel like myself, and I felt strong.
Tua-lli-wa tua-i maavet unatet elliata waten tallirpilirneret
And so, when this right hand reached here
Wavet uluaq tua-i waten piqerluku ellikeka.
I did this with the knife and set it down.
Tua-i-llu-wa tua-i qiaryigtellria. Qelempaglua-ll’ wii tua-i qiaryigtellria.
Then it started crunching. I shut my eyes fast as it crunched.
Atam qiaryigquraqerluni nunamun kapuartell’.
As it was crunching, you see, [the knife] stuck into the ground.
Call’ im’ qalriuciyaarluni tuar caviyaaq-llu qalrialria. Tayima tua-i qungagarrluni.
Then something screeched, and it seemed like metal screeching. It withdrew into silence.
Aren takuya’rqa talliq im’ tayima.
Oh my, I looked back and the arm was gone.
Aren umyuarteqa’artua, una-w’ uluaq nunamun kapusngalria egkuaminun puukaumaluni.
Oh my, I thought to myself, while this knife stuck into the ground all the way to its handle.
Aren waniwa-q’ [?cull’ mercaaqautmun], tau͡gaam kilirngacaaqaqa.
Oh my, it seemed to [?], but I think I wounded it.
Maaten tang im’ tua makcama man’a avateka kiartaqa, aren unatet makut maani avatemni petgalriit.
When I got up and looked around my, oh my, I saw these hands springing up around me.
Uitavkenateng petgalriit qeckaraqluteng.
The ones that sprang up didn’t stay still, but would jump.
Malirqaaluki tua-i cakiteraqluki.
I chased them and would chop them.
Kiituan uitangut. Uitangata qupurrluki.
Eventually, they stayed still. When they stayed, I chopped them up.
Piciatun egqaqluki makut yuarat, piciatun egtaqluki quyungqavkarpek’naki.
I threw these fingers in random directions, threw them in random directions so they wouldn’t be gathered.
Tua-i nutaan caarkaicukaama nangerrlua uluaqa taun’ qelkarrluku.
When I had nothing left to do, I stood up and kept that knife with me.
Uterqurlua tua-i yaani Kuigilngurmun. Uterqurlua.
I made my way home over to Kwigillingok. I made my way home.
Qavangurtulangellruunga tuaten tua-i tamakunek ayuqenrilngurnek uumun imumun Cegg’amun.
I started to dream about those kinds of things in various ways because of Cegg’aq.
Cegg’aq una.
Cegg’aq here.
Cegg’am waten piyaaqellruanga:
Cegg’aq said this to me:
"Alingnaqvaa-ll’ usuuq tang," taangiqluni
"Oh my goodness, you," he was drunk
"Usuuq tang yuungcariqernaamken."
"Hey you, let me heal you."
Ingna-gguq, ingna-gguq tang yaa-i Ayagina’ar yuungcarallra man’a tekiskii.
He said that he had healed Ayagina’ar over there, the one who made it this far.
"Yuungcariqernaamken.
"Let me heal you.
"Eru’urqavet, ervuqa’arqavet ervuqalaryartuten yuungcarikumken unaken taryumek eruutan avuqerluku."
"When you wash yourself, when you bathe, if I heal you, you would bathe adding in your bathwater with saltwater from down there."
Tua-i-gguq elliin-llu ca im’ yuungcararkaq ilaaqluku yuungcaraqeciqaa
He said that he would add on who should be healed, then heal them
Tautun Ayagina’artun.
Like Ayagina’ar there.
Aren wii tua-i tamana umyuama pinrilaku
Oh my, since my mind didn’t want that
Piaqa wavet canritniluku waten erurang’e’rma.
I told him that it would be fine if I continued to wash this way.
Canritniluku waten erurang’e’rma. Tuaten wii piyuumiitnilua.
I told him it would be fine if I continued to wash like this. I said I didn’t want to do that.
Qavanguqevkalangellruuq tua-i tauna ngelekluku ciuniunritelqa.
He started making me dream since then, because I didn’t accept his offer.
Tua-i tuani tua-i tayima tua qavanguqenrirluku.
Since then, I stopped dreaming about him.
Tuaten tau͡gaam qavangurturaqlua canek tamakunek.
But I would dream about those strange things like that.
Uterrlua tua-i tekillua.
I made my way home and arrived.
Aren maaten tang tuani kiartua taukut unatet kepraarluku
Oh my, I looked around after I cut those hands up
Tuani tua-i up’nerkaryarturtuq
At that time, spring was nigh
Alussistuallruluteng-llu. Waniw’ yaaqsigpek’nani Alussistuallrat.
And they had celebrated Christmas. It was long since they’d celebrated Christmas.
Nuna man’ qainga urullinilria tua-i.
The ground surface had melted.
Nanvat-llu makut urugaqluki, tau͡gaam cikuit urumaksaunateng.
And these lakes were melting, but their ice hadn’t melted yet.
Makut-llu kuiget emiqaqtaangelliniluteng akulait.
And the area between rivers had started gtetting water.
Tua-i kiarrlua nunam qainga tuaten ayuqluku.
I looked around with the land like that.
Uterrlua tua-i tekicama tua-i enemteńun itrama, qavauciqa nallunriqerrluku tua-i tupagyarturlua uiga’rrlua.
When I went home and arrived, when I went into our house, I realized that I was sleeping, tried to awake myself and opened my eyes.
Tua uigarcama tua-i at’urlua tayim’ uum qaill’ piciiranga qanrulluku.
When I woke up and their poor father asked what happened to me, I told him.
Qavangurturnilua au͡g’umek tua-i tuaten ayuqelriamek.
I told him that I had that kind of dream.
Waniwa tua-i qavanguqa au͡gna piciukan kelluqu’rciqnilua up’nerkarpak qaill’ ellam ayuqucianek.
If my dream was true, I said that I would watch all spring for what nature out there was like.
Tua-i waten-am qanruskilaku engelii tekitevkenaku.
I told him this without reaching the point.
Tua-i-ll’ kelluqurlua tua-i.
Then I kept watch.
Imumi-llu avani, pelatekiulallrat-qa nallullruan, Kuigilnguum paingan pelatekalilallra?
And a long time ago, did you know that they would set up a lot of tents at the mouth of the Kuigilnguq River?
Tengmiarsuunkut kiingan anguqallruanka. Nangenruluteng pingatellruut ellait.
I was only born in time to see Tengmiarsuk and family. I think they were the last ones.
Una wani ukalirnerna Kuigilnguum pelatekat un’gani amllepiatullruut uaqlirni.
On this side of Kuigilnguq, there used to be a multitude of tents far downriver.
Waniw’ cali kiaqliitni cali tua-i pelatekarugaat.
There were also a lot of tents here upriver from them.
Agna-ll’ call’ akilirneq ikna pelatelartangqerraqluni pelatekarugarnek.
And across from them, there would be a lot of tents.
Anelraqutullratni painganun Kuigilnguum.
When they used to go downriver en masse to the mouth of Kuigilnguq.
Arenqiapakar.
Oh my goodness.
Tua-i tuaten tua-i.
That’s what they did.
Anelrarluta tua-i ikani akilirnermi uitaluta wangkuta. Yugyagluteng.
We went downriver and stayed across on the other side. There were a lot of people.
Iluraruka-ll’ [?]m Arnaan-llu elaqliqlunuk, canritellrani tamaani cayugnaitellrani.
And my cousin, [?]’s mother and I were neighbors, back when she was alive and well.
Atam tua-i uitaqainanemteńi unaken tua-i unguvalriarqaqengluteng.
As we stayed, you see, they started catching a lot of animals from down [in the ocean].
It’gayagikenka-am ukut qaqingnaqluki tua-i it’gayagiarkanka au͡gkut nayiit amiit.
I made "little feet [?]" trying to finish them all, the ringed seal skins I had to make into "little feet."
Atam piinanemteńi yuk cakem’ amik ikireskii.
As we were doing that, you see, a person out there opened the door.
Pelatekangqertukut imumek tungupagmkek, tanqiucirluku qatellriamek qukaakun.
We had a black tent, with a white part in the middle to let in light.
Tua-i tuaten ayuqukut.
That’s what we were like.
Qanertuq iterluni pama-i yuk pam’ tununmni Qayum atii canritlermini.
The person said as he came in behind me, Qayuq’s father when he was alive.
Tua-ll’ atrat una pia, Acill’aq pia
Then he said to their namesake, he said to Acill’aq
"Iluracung’ tang ikegkut ullakarki."
"Cousin, you should go to them across there."
Tua-i-gguq ata tang ellii iluminek pivakaami ullanrilkai.
He said that he wasn’t going to them because he was having stomach problems.
Tua-ll’ piunga wii cat imkut.
Then I noticed those things.
Aren qanertuq, tauna-gguq Cegg’aq yuunrirtuq.
Oh my, he said that Cegg’aq passed away.
Aren qaillun tua-i pivkenani, qaillun pivkenani tamaani.
Oh my, nothing was wrong with him, nothing was wrong with him at that time.
Aren piunga, "Qaillun un’ pia?“
Oh my, I said, "What happened to him?"
Tua-i-gguq-wam antelallni antellerminiu tua-i yuunrilria
They said that when we coughed up what he coughed up, he passed away
Qecingarcami.
Because he’d started coughing up [blood].
Arenqia.
Oh my goodness.
Tua-i-ll’ tayima tua-i qerarlutek maliklutek.
Then they crossed [the river] together.
Qeraagnek caliyuumiircama calianka peggluki anngama nunam qainga kiartaqa
When they crossed and I didn’t want to work anymore, I dropped what I was working, went out, and look around the land
Imna qavangulqa uksuq umyuaqluku.
Remembering what I had dreamt the last winter.
Tua-i tekitqapiarluku tua-i tauna yuk arulaillinilria.
That person passed away right at that exact point.
Un’a-w’ kuik cali emiqaqtaarluni, makuk ceńak emiqaqtaarlutek pilriik.
And the river down there was getting watery, both sides of the riverbank were getting watery.
Aren tua-i qavangulqa im’ tekitkacagarluku.
Oh my, it was exactly what I had dreamt.
Aren. Tuani tua-i alingepiallruunga.
Oh my. I was so scared at that time.
Alingellruunga-wa.
I was scared.