Waqaa, wii MIke Williams-aaruunga. Waken Akiarmek taillruunga.
Hello, I’m Mike Williams. I came from Akiak here.
Tau͡gaam wani umyuanek ikayuristeńi calilartua.
But I work with mental health services.
Wani quyurvallruukut imumi imakunek Yupiit wani iinruitnek picirluta
Some time ago, we held a large gathering here to talk about traditional Yup’ik medicine
September 17 - 21st.
Waten uumek umyuarteqluta piluta: man’a yuuyaralput wani pinirikaniisqelluku man’a yuulput.
We met with this in mind: to strengthen our way of life in our lives here.
Waten makut wani kitugikanirluku-w’ man’a
To improve these things here
Tua-i nallunricelluki makut ayagyuaput wani makunek Yuut wani yuuyarallratnek.
To have our young people learn about the old Yup’ik way of life.
Cali, tua-i-w’ aulukluki caliaqluki-ll’ makut wani Yupiit wani iinrullrit tamaani yuullermeggni.
Also, we want to take care of and work on Yup’ik medicine that they used in their lives long ago.
Waten makut wani Yuut wani yuungcaristellret wani nallunrirluki
They should learn about these old Yup’ik healers
Kap’itulit, cat-llu canek wani atulallret tamaani cali.
Yup’ik acupuncturists, and the things they used back then
Makut wani naunraat cali igaulluki, elliluki nallunritniararput.
And write and put down these plants so that we will know them.
Cali makut wani elicungcarluki.
Also, we should learn these.
Elicungcautekluki-w’ tua-i elicungcarluki-ll’ makut wani Yuut wani atullrit iinrut.
We should teach and learn these things that Yupiit used as medicine.
Cali makut wani iinrut cali Yupiit wani atullrit cali makunun wani yuungcarvignun atuusqelluki
We also want these hospitals to use these kinds of medicine that Yupiit used
Maani wani avatemteńi.
Here around us.
Cali makut wani qatellriit yuut tailriit akmaken pamani yuungcarvigmi calilriit cali nallunricelluki makunek wani Yuut wani iinruitnek.
We also want these white people that came from downstates who work inland in the hospital to know about these kinds of Yup’ik medicine.
Cali makut wani tegganret-wa tua-i angukara’urluurtellriit, arnassagaurtellriit-llu tua-i
And these elders, those who’ve become old men and old women
Tua-i-w’ man’a aulukellrat wani tua-i assirikaniisqumaluku
We want their care to be better here
Maaken-llu ayagcetenritlerkaat pitekluku cali tamana tangaaluku piluta.
We also looked at how we don’t want them to be sent away from here.
Waniw’ waken uumek Kuigpagmek tailria Noel Polty nasviciiqaakut makunek wani Yupiit wani iinrullritnek.
Now, Noel Polty who came from the Yukon here, will explain to us what Yupiit used as medicine.
Tua-i wangnek piciulriamek qanqatartua waniwa tua-i wii atullemnek.
Now, I’m going to say something true that I have experienced.
Makut maa-i wavet ukut wani cagtellrenka waniwa ukut waniw’ Yup’igtaat iinrut.
These things that I’ve scattered here are Yup’ik medicine.
Wiinga atuqek’ngaqanka. Tamalkuita ukut aturanka.
I’ve taken them. I’ve taken all of them.
Cali-llu makut, cali pill-at makut cali maa-i aturluki waniwa.
I’m also taking these pills here.
Ukut waniwa tapeqluki ayuqluki wii atuqek’ngaqanka. Waniwa tangrraci.
I am taking all of these together now. You see them.
Ukut-llu waniw’ [?] pill, una-llu call’ [?]
These are [?] pills, and these are [?].
Waniwa yuum naulluulriim arcaqerluku una cali ikayuutekciqaa. Waniwa iirumavkenaku qanrutkaqa.
These will especially help a sick person. I am telling it without hiding it.
Okay, cali-llu waniwa caiggluut makut waniwa tangrraput.
Okay, then the wormwood here, we see these now.
Makut waniwa imkut caiggluut-wa tua-i tangellruaci. Waniwa.
You’ve seen these wormwood plants before. Here they are.
Kirciuquvci, qaivceńi maani uitalriamek kirciuquvci
If you have pains, if you have pains here on your body
Una waniwa au͡g’arluku waten
Take this part off like this
Au͡g’arraarluku qang’a-llu piyukuvciu caayumek kuv’vikraarluku im’um kircilriim nalliinun elliluku nemerluku.
After removing it, and if you want to pour tea on it, put it where the pain is and wrap it.
Tua-i yuungcautekluki im’ kirciullerpeceńun.
Use them to treat your body pains.
Room-aliciquvci-llu tauna cali wavet elliluku.
And if you have a lot of room, put that here too.
Wiinga makut wani waniw’ waten ayuquciicetun mermek pirraarluki maavet aturturatuanka waten wani.
Personally, after I steep these in water as they are like this, I apply them here like this.
Waten atu’uqluki.
I used them like this.
Tua-i ikayuutekluki.
They help me.
Man’a kirciraqan mat’umek atu’uqluki. Waniw’.
When this is in pain, I use these. Here they are.
Una waniwa, waniwa kinercirraarluku waten uutun kinqan
This, after drying it and it gets dry like this one
Waten tunguriqreskan like this, waten tunguriqreskan
When it gets dark like this [one], when it gets dark like this
Nutaan ulugluku waten. Uluggaarluku Wesson oil-amek auluku.
Then crumple it like this. After crumpling it, add in Wesson oil.
Infect-alriamun kilinermun waten tua-i au͡gaulluku waten elliluku infect-aqan patuluku-llu.
Take this off a part of it and put it on an infected wound like this if it’s infected, and cover it.
Unugpak au͡g’arciqaa, nugciiqaa infect-alria qamani egmianun.
All night, it will remove, pull out the infection inside right away.
Canarqevkenani-llu, kinguani-llu clean-arnarqevkenani nugcimaluni.
And nothing [else] needs to be done, doesn’t need to be cleaned since it was pulled out.
Cali-llu imumek qaisi man’ ungilaggluni waten pikan, cakneq ungilaggluni
Also, if your body here is itching like this, itching terribly
Una wani mermun hot water-aamun ekqerraarluku ilakluku perriutekluku waten, perrirluku man’a qaini.
After putting this in hot water, use it to wipe like this, wipe one’s body like this.
Cali-llu nasqumteńi, qamiqumteńi cali ungilageskan [?]cukan makuciq cali elliluku waten.
Also, if our heads are itching, tending to [?], put this kind here like this.
Wavet ellirraarluku canvas-amek ellivikluku nutaan unugpak qavarluni.
After putting it here, one should put a canvas on it and sleep all night.
Unuaquani tupagciquq imna qavani infect-allra nasquani nugtellinikii.
He will wake up the next morning with that having pulled out the infection from his head in his sleep.
Waniw’ nallunritarci, you know, that leaf tobacco, cuyaq.
You know this, you know, that leaf tobacco, "cuyaq."
Cali kilip’akuni, ilii-llu kiliquni iliin yuum waniw’ qang’a-llu two inch taktakan
If one also has a big wound, if some person has a wound, or else if it’s two inches long
Nani yuungcautaunani, tau͡gaam waten blackbull-anek makunek pingqerquni cuyanek
If there are no doctors, but if he has these blackbull leaves with him
Tua-i camek pikailami una tua-i cuyaq mermek imirraarluku tuavet elliluku cali ataam, nemerluku-llu pikuniu
Without any other alternative, after filling that tobacco leaf with water, if he also puts it there and binds it
Qac’uqreskuni qat’riqreskuni aunrarngaituq.
When it gets slack, when it gets white, it will not bleed.
Cali-llu mamciquq assirluni.
It will also heal well.
Una imna kegguciqaqamta, tan’gaurlullrauluta iciw’-ggem mikluta kegguciqaqamta
And this, when we had toothaches, you know, when we had toothaches as small boys
Aluqatkanek au͡gaulluta kegguteput keggutelluki uitavkarlaqaitkut.
We would take a piece of beaver castor, and they would have us bite it down on our teeth.
Tamakunek kegguciqsuucirluta.
We used those for toothaches.
Cali-llu ak’a tua-i kegguciqsuutmek aipirluku
Also, a long time ago, along with using it for toothaches
Ukugnun wani uum tepii, aluqatkam tepii narevkallruagka.
I had these two smell this scent, the beaver castor scent.
Ukuk malruulukek, waniw’ uum-llu narluki, ing’um-llu narluki.
There were two of them, this one smelled them, and the one over there smelled them.
Tuaten tepellgutkuk imkutun Kass’at-llu kegguciurcuutaicetun ayuqut.
They smell the same like that, and they’re like Western toothpaste.
Tuaten-llu elpegi’iqluki pituluteng.
They also numb them like that.
Ukut waniwa tangrraci, una wani tungulriaruluni. Tang waniwa tunguuq.
You see these, this black thing. You see, this is black.
Imkuugut teptukuyagnek pitukait, nunami atutuk[ait] tepsarqellriit.
They’re what they call beach greens, the odiferous things they use from the land.
Maa-i tepsarqut tamakucirnimek, nerellrat-llu assirluni cupugvagaqluni.
They smell strongly of those, and they’re good to eat, [?] very much.
Yuum igyariqekuni igyarani aviranarqekan pikailkuni yuilqumi pekeskuni
If a person has a sore throat, his throat bothering him, if he has nothing as he travels in the wilderness
Makucimek nerluni, mecua-ll’ igmarluku.
He should eat one of these, and swallow its juice.
Cali-llu qus’quni, cagmiqkuni waten makucimek tua-i maa-i nerluku, nernge’rmi igmange’rmiu
Also, if one has a cold, if he is lost, when he eats this, though he eats and swallows it
Tua-i qamani tau͡gaam cupugvagluni
It will emanate a scent inside
Imkucetun imkut iciw’ Vicks-at cupugvaglalriit? Tuacetun tua-i cupugvagluni man’a piarkauguq.
Like those, you know how Vicks emanates a strong scent? This will emanate a scent like that.
Waniwa ukut wani teptukuyagnek piaqluki.
They call these beach greens.
Tua-i-llu cali waniwa
Then these too
Nutaan ukut wani.
These especially.
Waniwa ayuqenritut. Ukut wani tangrraci.
These are different. You see these here.
Una waniwa fresh-alriaruuq una.
This here is fresh.
Una caiggluk fresh-arluni qallaucimaluni. Uum egneqaa. Waniw’ waten ayuquq nutarauluni.
This is freshly boiled. This is the liquid from this [plant]. This is what it’s like when fresh.
Una wani waniw’ caiggluum angucalua arnacalua-llu.
This is the male and female parts of wormwood.
Quyurrlutek egalukek waten katurrlukek pinirluni.
It is potent when they’re boiled together.
Waten-llu color-angqerrluni waniwa nutaraunrilami, nalaciraullruami.
And it has this color because it’s not fresh, because it was dried.
Ukuk waniwa yuum una wani iluminek qamani, ilumini qamani ca aviranarqekan
These two, if a person has stomach problems inside, if something in his stomach is bothering him
Ilukaaquni-llu, wall’ quserpakuni, wall’u mat’umek qukaminek mat’umek aviraniurlaquni
And if he has stomach pains, or has a bad cough, or if his back here is bothering him
Wall’u imkunek naugiyukuni, imkunek ungilagtellrianek naugiyukuni
Or if he has malignant growths, those itchy malignant growths
Una wani nerevkenaku, ayuquciatun pivkenaku, kenirraarluku tua-i waken wani mer’aqluni
If he doesn’t eat this, not as it is, if he boils it and drinks from here
Unuaq im’ qanrutkellracetun ik’um mer’aqluni, unuakumi mer’aqluni, atakumi-ll’ mer’aqluni.
If he drinks as the one across there said this morning, drinks in the morning, and drinks in the evening.
Tua-i-llu uum wani una pinialkekuniu nutaan makunek auluku waten wani
Then if he finds that too weak, he should add these like this
Waken kina meq’uni, one cup waken meq’uni aayalnguqerciiquq.
If someone drinks from here, if he drinks one cup from here, he will get dizzy.
Pinirtut makut waten tapeqluteng makut, uumek tapirluteng.
These are strong when added together like this, with this added in.
Tau͡gaam pininge’rmi eliskuniu, elitaqamiu yuum imucetun meqsulriacetun merlaraa.
But though it’s strong, when a person gets used to it, he drinks it as if thirsting for it.
Wiinga tua-i cup-amek mertu’rlartua unuaquaqan tua-i waten pinilriarrlainarmek.
Personally, I always drink a cup every morning, only from this potent one.
Atam tangerqercia waniw.
Look at me now.
Kemgicaaqellrulua, kemenglua-llu waniwa, mat’um.
I had been underweight, now I put some on from this.
Ukut yuungcautet, ukut-llu-w’ pill-at ikayuqluteng caliarat maa-i elpekumaaqa.
I feel the full effects of these [traditional] medicine and these pills working together.
Tua-i-ll’ una wani ukugtun ayuqsaaquq waten keniumaluni. Una kenirauguq.
Then this is like these two, boiled like this. This has been boiled.
Imkunek maa-i napanek pilaraput maani ilaita, wangkuta-llu enrilnguarnek piaqluki qagaani imkut enrilnguat imkut moose-at ner’tukait.
Some peopel from here call them trees, and we call them willow shoots, those willow shoots out there that moose eat.
Tua-i-llu cali qallaulluku waten qallarvaulluku.
Then boil it like this also.
Mikelngurnun, cali una waniwa piniq’apiartuq mikelngurnun.
To children, this is also very potent to children.
Callareskan qanrunani-llu pikan egmian qanrarnun kuvluku igengraani canrituq.
If he has sores, and cannot use his mouth, immediately pour it in his mouth, and it’s fine if he swallows it.
Una wani callartellrianun mikelngurnun, qainganun-llu cali maani imkunun waten callarnernun cali tamaavet kuvuurluku, aunrangraan kuvuurluku.
Use this for children with sores, and pour it on the sores that he has on his body, pour it even if they bleed.
Cali mamciiqaa patagmek.
It will also heal him right away.
Wangkuta-llu cali taqnerni, taqnerungramta waniwa cali qanerput calla’artetulria iliini pivakarluta.
And we adults, though we are adults, sometimes our mouths get sores as we go.
Tua-i merluta tau͡gken meqsiirrluni-llu egmian. Pinirtuq, tukniuq makuciq atullra.
We drink, and we’re immediately not thirsty anymore. Using these is strong, potent.
Cali tua-i uum qaini ungilageskan cali makucetun, waten tua-i makucetun
Also, if a person’s body is itchy, like this too, like this
Tua-i qaiminun maqikuni, wall’u nasquminun-llu maqikuni tua-i aturarkauluku.
He will use it on his body when he takes a steam bath, or on his head..
Imkut-llu nauw’ unatmegteggun waten ungilaksuarturluteng tegucunairut’lalriit-llu waten.
And you know how their hands are so itchy like this that they can’t take anything like this.
Cali makucimun erurluki, waten erurraarluki tua-i mingunrilengraata tuaten eru’uqluki.
Wash them in this as well, then after washing them, you don’t need to apply anything, just wash them like that.
Cali mamciiqaa makucim waniwa enrilnguat imkut piit, egenrat.
This kind will also heal it, the, you know, willow shoot broth.
Wiinga tua-i umyuarteqlartua waten wani:
This is what I think:
Makut wani Kass’at imumek [?] kapsaraakut. Piciatun naullutengqerraqamta nauullutvut tauna tangerrluku kaptuakut.
These Caucasians would give us [?] shots. When we have various sicknesses, they look at our ailment and give us shots.
Tua-i-llu wii umyuarteqlartua
Then I think
Ukut wani, una wani [?] ayuquq imucetun kaputetun atullra amllerami.
These, this is like [?], the shot they give, because it has many uses.
Naulluulria-llu ilii, naulluulriim assirivkarlaraa. Patagmek-ll’ iliikun assirivkarlaraa patagmek unakarkaugaqamiu.
It also heals some who are sick. It also sometimes quickly heals those that it is meant to heal.
Tau͡gaam waten elliin ukvekekuniu
But if that person believes in it like this
Waten wangtun wiinga una waniwa qanganaruaq pirpakaqa ikayuumiinga.
Like me, I highly value this wormwood here because it helps me.
Imucetun kapsuutetun pitarrluku wiinga tua-i meryuglaraqa tua-i ikayuutellra pitekluku.
I like to drink it, [beliving] it as much as those shots, because it helps.
Tuaten cali imkut makut Kass’at imkut [?] kapun imna tua-i ellaita pirpakaat ikayurlaateng.
Like that, Caucasians also value the [?] shot because it helps them.
Wiinga-ll’ ikayurlaraatnga tamakut.
Those [plants] also help me.
Ukut waniwa yuungcautet Kass’at iinruit, wall’u wangkuta iinruput ikayuqluteng calikuneng atam assilliniuq.
If these kinds of medicine work together, Western medicine, and our medicing, you see, it’s good.
Piunrilkevkenaki Yup’igtaat, piunrilkevkenaki-llu Kass’at piit.
Do not belittle Yup’ik [medicine], and do not belittle Western ones.
Tua-i waniwa wiinga umyuarteqlartua waten wani:
Me personally, I think like this:
Makut wani Agayutem piliaqai, nunam qaingani nauvkarluki.
These are God’s creations, having them grow on the land.
Agayutem piliarrlainarnek taqellrinek maa-i nunam qainga pitangqertuq.
The land is filled only with what God created.
Makut wani Agayutem taqellrullinii wangkutnun Yugnun ikayuutekesqelluki yuungcautekluki, iinrukluki pisqelluki.
God made these to help us Yupiit, so that we could use them for healing and medicine.
Wangkutnek qaill’ atullerkaat yuarluku arenqillrakun.
We look for the successful ways to use them by ourselves.
Tamaaggun tamana aturluku wangkuta piarkaugukut.
Through that, we must use them like that.
Piliamteńek wangkuta, wiinga caigglulisciigatua.
Through what we made, I cannot make wormwood.
Una Agayutem piliaqaa wangnun atuusqelluku, elpeceńun-llu atuusqelluku tamarpeci.
This is God’s creations for me to use, and for all of you to use.
Yaa, waniw’ cali quyaviksugluku una Dela Keetz-aaq waken Malimiunek tailria Kotzebue-mek makunek cali nasvicarturluta
Okay, I want to thenk Dela Keetz who came from Kotzebue in the [Iñupiaq] Malimiut region to show us these
Yaa, tua-i yuungcautmeggnek ellait.
Yes, their [traditional] medicine.
Quyavikluku makunek nasvicakut.
I thank her for showing us these.
I’m Dela Keetz from... my hometown is Noatak
Around 75 miles from Kotzebue, inland.
Dela Keetz-aarunga, Noatak-armiungulua yuinaat pingayun akimiarmek mile-anek yaaqsigtaluni Kotzebue-mek.
I’m Dela Keetz from Noatak, 75 miles away from Kotzebue..
Nugtartellruukut ilanka-llu Kotzebue-mun 1963-mi.
My family and I moved to Kotzebue in 1963.
But the people don’t know. I never try to show to the people the way I always help people at home.
I work at home, my hometown, try to help people all my life.
Tau͡gaam tuanleng’e’rma yuut ikayulangramki nallullruatnga
But though I was there and helped people, they didn’t know me
Enemni calilaama nunamteńi.
Because I work at home in our village.
Ikayungnaquralaamki yuut assiriaqata quyalaama tememtun wii pitarrluki.
Because I try to help people, I am thankful when they get better, as if it were my own body.
My heart, always happy, just like I have a joy, happy all the time.
They’re just like my own body.
That’s why I love to help people, anyplace wherever I go.
I doesn’t been trained.
I never trained in the hospital, or in no place.
Just by my own experience, and from the books I’ve read when I’m in school.
I was so interested.
Elitnaurumaksaitua, yuungcarvigmi-llu elitnaurumaksaunii, allani-llu.
I wasn’t trained, and I wasn’t trained in the hospital, or in other places.
Tau͡gaam nallunrita’arqemkun calilartua kalikanek naaqellemkun elitnaurvigmi.
But I work with what I know from the books I’ve read in school.
Cali-llu paqnak’allemkun anglanakelallemkun-llu naaqiaqama ellma taringevguarallemkun
And with what little I understood when I read about what I found interesting and fun
Kass’atun qanerturluta anglirillrunrilamta.
Because we didn’t grow up speaking English.
When something happen to us, when it’s injured or accident or anything
When sometime happen to us, when it’s injured or accident or anything
We should help this way or that way.
Especially, be clean.
Tau͡gaam naaqiyaurcama, elitnauristemta naaqivkaryaurcanga
But when we started reading, when our teacher had us start reading
Paqnak’lallruanka qaillun tememta calilauciit, wall’u picurlagaqamta akngirtaqamta-llu qaillun calilauciit
I used to be interested in how our bodies work, or how they work when we get into accidents or get hurt
Qaillun-llu ikayuumallerkarput.
And how we can be helped.
Cali-llu qaillun auluklerkaat wall’u kilirpagluteng pikata.
And how to take care of them, or if they have large wounds.
Arcaqalriaruluku unatet-llu menuunaki cali caliaqesqumaluteng.
More importantly, they were instructed to work with clean hands.
Tuaten elitellruunga wiinga.
That’s the way I learned.
Igaulluki piksaileng’e’rma umyuaqelaranka.
Even though I didn’t write them down, I remember them.
Elitnauristem-llu naaqevkalallri umyuaquralaranka.
I also always remember what the teacher had us read.
Tuaten yuut ikayuangnaqlemni tamakutgun umyuamnelngurteggun ikayungnaqaqluki.
When I try to help people through that, I try to help them through those things that are in my mind.
I never forget it. It’s in my mind all the time.
That is why I always help people when they need help.
I’ve got lot of things
Just a lot of things to say.
But what I do, I learned from myself.
Ataucirqumek wangnek aknirtellruunga iqulua.
I hurt myself one time and fell over.
Tamaggun-llu ayanqigteksaitelartua iquvillemkun.
And I’ve never went through that way where I fell.
...in my life.
I should be careful when I use ulu or knife when I cut
I shoudl be careful when I use ulu or knife when I cut.
Tuamtell’ cali uluarlua wall’u nuussitgun-llu kiliraqama, tuaten cali mulngaklua uumikuani aturaqamki pilartua.
Then when I get cut usuing an ulu or a [Western] knife, I am also careful the next time I use them like that.
Just like that.
And when I hurt on myself
Like one time...
Ataucirqumek naanguarluta pillemteńi akngirtellruunga wangnek.
Once, when we were playing, I hurt myself.
Aitartenrutassiirluta pillemteńi aitarpallaglua wiinga pinruqangnaqvallaglua.
When we had a wide mouth contest, I opened my mouth too far trying to win.
...make more wider mouth like this.
And I so want to win.
I open my mouth wide, and I can’t close it.
It’s [?], it’s [?].
I try, I try to talk, I can’t talk.
Qanqa-llu mamtesciiganaku, qanerciiganii-llu.
And I couldn’t fix my mouth, and I couldn’t speak.
Tua-i-llu yuut nalluatgun wangnuk agluqugka taamekellruagka akngirtengraagnek.
Then without the knowledge of people, I [?worked on] my jaw though it hurt.
So then I push it out while I was open...
Nuq’errlukek tua-llu ataam cingllemni ek’arrlutek.
I pulled them, then when I pushed again, they went right in.
I put it back in.
So, I know how to work on it.
Qaillun-llu tuaten agluqugnek ek’illerkaqa nallunritaqa.
I also know how to set jaws back like that.
Ataucirqumek cali Shaktoolik-aamun qayagaullruatnga ikayurcetaarluteng Kotzebue-mek.
Once, they called me to go help in Shaktoolik from Kotzebue.
Tua-llu Shaktoolik-aamun ayagyaaqellrianga, tuani nasaurluq tuaten pillinian
Then when I went to Shaktoolik, because that happened to a girl there
Health aide-aata, iinriutiita-wa ekesciigatliniamikek elliin taum wani ayagcetliniluku Nome-amun.
Because their health aide, their nurse, could set [her jaw] back, (s)he had her go to Nome.
Tuani pingayuni ernerni pilliuq, aitangqauralliniluni neresciiganani qanerciiganani-llu.
It may have been three days that her mouth was open, unable to eat or speak.
Maliggluku ayallruunga. Tekicama Nome-amun piunga qanra aitangqaurluni qanerciiganani-llu.
I traveled with her. When I arrived at Nome, I foudn that her mouth was open and she couldn’t speak.
Qaneni mamtesciiganaku.
She couldn’t fix her mouth.
Tamaani-llu arnat uitallruut mikelnguyagaat-llu amllerrluteng, qialuteng tuaten.
There were women there, and a lot of children, and they were even crying.
Water running..
Water running.
She can’t talk. She can’t close his mouth.
She can’t talk. She can’t close his [her] mouth.
And then there was ladies with lot of babies.
"Who’s this baby is this?" "That was mine," a young girl say. "You better take this crybabies out."
Iliit wani qialria piaqa kitumun irniaqucianek.
I asked whose child was the one that was crying.
Iliit ayagyuat nasaurluut qanertuq elliin irniaqniluku.
One of the young girls said it was her child.
Cunawa tua-i tauna enaiqertii Shaktoolik-aami iinriurtiita.
It turned out that it was the one who took the place of the nurse in Shaktoolik.
Qanrucamni anutesqelluku irniara anqerrutaa neplilriami caliyuumiitnilua.
When I told her to take her child out because I didn’t want to work in a noisy environment, she took [the child] out.
Cunawa paqnayugyaaqliniliria qaillun agluquk ataam eklerkaak.
Apparently, she was curious about how to set [the girl’s] jaw back.
Take her out running next door.
Before he come back, I fix it already.
Before [s]he come back, I fix it already.
"Ah, you fix it already? I was going to catch you [?]."
I show him how to. She so want to see me; she so want to watch.
I show him [her] how to. She so want to see me; she so want to watch.
Tau͡gaam uterpailgan ataam wiinga kitugtellruagka.
But before she came back, I fixed them again.
Tua-llu utercan ayuqucirturaqa qaillun tuaten pilriamek pikan eklerkaak agluquk.
Then when she came back, I instructed her how to set a jaw back if that happens.
Luuskaacuarmek tegumialaucirpetun saskan saarraliqatarluku, tuaten tegumiaqnaragken agluquk canitmun
Just as you hold a small spoon to put sugar in your cup, hold the jaws to the side like that.
Qamiqurra-llu cakneq tegumiaqluku.
And hold their head tight.
Nuq’errluku elatmun. Tuaten pilriani ek’artetuut.
Pull it outward. They set right back when doing that.
Just lift it up little bit. It’s easy.
Don’t have to send it to, way off to hospital.
Don’t have to sent it to, way off to hospital.
Ayagcetevkenaku yuungcarvigmun.
Don’t have them go to the hospital.
Tuamtellu ataucirqumek Anchorage-aami quyurvallratni qanerteksuklua cucukelliniatnga.
Then one time, when they held a large gathering in Anchorage, they chose me to speak.
Tua-llu qaillun tusgen yuugareskan qalarutkellruaqa.
Then I spoke about what to do when your shoulder gets dislocated.
And I talked about when you hurt your shoulder.
If you hurt this side, left side, can’t lift your arm, be hurt, it’s hurt, don’t want to lift alright.
Akngireskuvet tuaten iqsulirnerkun pikuvet tallin qulmun yaggluku
If you hurt your left side like that, [unable] to lift your arm up
Akngirnarqeciqsaaquq tau͡gaam ingluanek yuungcaristeḿun ayagyunrilkuvet elpenek qulmun nuqluku eksugngaan
It may be painful, but if you don’t want to go to the doctor, you can pull it up with your other arm and set it
Wiinga tuaten pillruamku.
Because I’ve done that.
Akngirtellruaqa tuska
I hurt my shoulder
Tua-llu qulmun yagtengnaqluku nangengqalua. Aipaanek tallima nuqluku qulmun, ek’arrluni-llu.
Then I tried to pull it up as I was standing. I pulled it up with my other arm, and it set.
Tua-i-llu unaqserrluku uitaluku.
Then I kept it limp.
Tua-i-llu pektaartelluku.
Then I moved it around.
Tuaten naspaallemni assirillruuq, ek’artellruuq.
When I tried that, it got better, got set back in.
Elpeceńek-llu tuaten piyugngaarci.
You can do it by yourself like that too.
Tuani quyurtaallratni atakumi angun iliit igtelliniuq tuss’aratgun, akngirrluku-llu tusni.
When they held their meetings, one of the men fell on the stairs, hurting his shoulder.
Umyuaqertellinia, "Dela-m-ggem qanrutellruakut tuaten pisqelluku."
He remembered it, "Didn’t Dela tell us to do that?"
Tua-llu naspaaluni ellminek ekengnaqlerminiu ek’artelliniluku tuani quyurtaalriit allaniviatni.
Then when he tried to set it, he set it back there where the people who went to the meeting were lodged.
Waniw’ cali quyaviksugluku cali una Mercelas Williams tailria akmaken Ingqilit wani nuniitnek, Ingqilit yuungcaristiit.
Now, I also want to tahnk Marcelas williams who came from Native American territory downstates, a Native American healer.
Cali makunek qalaruciiqaakuk, tau͡gaam im’ Joe Albright-am mumigqurluki piciqa.
He will also talk to us about these, but Joe Albright will provide translations.
...villages along the creeks, that’s where these medicine things grow.
Tamaa-i-llu-gguq nunanun tagglermeggni kuiget ceńaitnun engelkartellruut, tua-i-gguq-wa iinruutulit tamaani kuigem ceńiini naulaata.
He siad that back when they were going inland to the villages, they settled on the riverbanks, because those medicinal plants grew on the riverbank.
When the white man found us there, they called us Cree Indians because we live by the creeks.
Makut-gguq qatellriit yuut nalkellermeggni aterpagtellruut Kuigem-wa Yuinek
He said that when these white people found them, they called them River People
Tamaa-i kuigem nuniini engelkaringallrat pitekluku.
Because they were setlled by the rivers back there.
If you have some children, infants, sometimes look at the base of the spine.
And if they got a blue spot right on the base of the spine, right along in here, then you and I are related.
Tua-llu-gguq mikelnguci murilkelaquvciki
Then, he said that if you watch your children
Maani tunuatni qukaat qul’araani aciqvani maani qiurrlugmek-gguq qiuqeggingalriamek tangerquvci
Here on their backs right above their midsection down there, if you see a blue spot
Tamaaggun-gguq nallunrilkiciu ilakuyucirput ellait-llu.
He said to know that we are related to them through that.
Don’t look mine. He’s too old.
Ca imna aturani tangrresqenritaa.
He said not to look at his clothes.
The little guys. Look at the little ones.
Everywhere, wherever you go, all kinds of people, black, yellow, brown, white, blue, green, or whatever
We all share something in common: we are either healthy or sick.
Tua-i-gguq cam tamiini nunam qaingani wall’ ellam iluani tarriskuvci-wa
He said that everywhere on the land, or if you go anywhere in the world
Qaillun-gguq tua-i yuut ayuqeng’e’rmeng, qaingit-wa tungunge’rmeng qat’nge’rmeng-llu
He said no matter what people are like, even if their skin is black or white
Tua-i-gguq ayuqluteng. Cali man’a ayquciat ayuquq nangtequtengqerraqluteng-llu ayuqluteng.
He said they’re the same. And what they’re like, they all suffer from sickness.
Even among white people, there are different kinds of white people within that group.
Makut-llu-wa qatellrianek pilangramceteng ayuqeqapiaranritut.
And even though we call these people white, they’re not exactly the same.
Ataucimek kangingqenritut. Ayuqenritut makut qatellrianek pilalput.
They’re not of the same origin. The ones we call white are not the same.
To ones in Washington, D.C., we call them from the Paper Tribe.
Everything is done on paper, [?] and all that.
Makut-gguq akmani nunarpagmek apqallranek kingunelget, tamakut-gguq Kalikat Tribe-artaitnek aterpagingalartut
He said that the people from the city downstates that he mentioned, they’re called the Paper Tribe
Tua-i kalikaq aturluku-wa calilaata.
Because they work with [official] paper[work].
There are some referred to as hillbillies, and they also have folk ways, folk medicine.
Au͡gkunek-wa ca au͡gna hillbilly-mek tuar piqaqii niiquralalput
It seemed that he called what we hear about a hillbilly
Tamatum cam iinrutulim-gguq ilakukai.
They are part of the ones who practice [folk] medicine.
[?] of mankind exist wherever they live.
They always learn something from their area.
Tua-i-gguq nunam qaingani tamiini ayuqluteng camek elicugngalartut nunameggnek.
He said that everywhere on the land, they are the same in that they can learn something of their land.
If all of my people moved over here in this part of Alaska, they’d all probably starve to death this next winter.
Tua-i ayuqestassiigutkaa. Tayima-gguq elliin ilakutai maavet nunamteńun pikuneng aipaagni-gguq paluyartut.
He gave an example. He said that if his people moved here to our lands, they’d probably starve to death.
And if you all came to my country, you might melt
And if you all came to my country, you might melt.
Nuniinun-llu-gguq wangkuta ayakumta aipaagni urugyalliakut.
And he said that if we went to his lands, we would probably melt.
But in this time, we learn to adjust, we learn to adapt, we learn to live off the land.
We learn for things that you can eat, things that you can use for medicine.
We learn for things that you can eat, thigns that you can use for medicine.
Tau͡gaam-gguq yuk alqunaq pinrilnge’rmi eliquratuuq cukavkenani.
But he said that even if it doesn’t happen right away, a person keeps learning slowly.
Nunam-llu qainganek nerrlerkani cali elicugngaluku
He can also learn what he can eat from the land
Wall’u-qaa iinrurkani-llu tamaaken elitarkauluku.
Or he will also learn what he can use as medicine from there
In the workshop we’ve been having, attending
Each one has some knowledge about the land, and we’ve been sharing this knowledge all week.
Maa-i-wa uumirpak quyurtaallemteńi yuut nallunrilkaitnek elitellritnek-llu niiqurtukut
Now, as we’ve been having these meetings, we’ve been hearing about what people know and have learned
Tua-i nunameggni tamakut uitalriit nallunrillritnek elilluki-llu.
The things people found out and learned about in their lands.
I’d like to just stay on for a long time and learn many of your ways.
For instance, we have lots of teachings in my tribe, similar to yours.
When a woman is expecting a child, when she goes out the door and changes her mind, we tell her not to turn around at the doorway.
Go on through, and then come back in.
Maa-i-wa ellii-llu akaarnun tua-i maancuumiryaaqeng’e’rmi eliterllerkani pitekluku.
Now, he wants to stay here from a long time so that he can learn.
Maa-i niicugniurallermikun cali kingunermini yum’i-wa ayuqucirtuutek’lallrit alerquatek’lallrit-llu iliini elitaq’larai.
As he’s been listening now, he sometimes recognizes his people’s teachings and instructions back home
Unaumek-llu cali elliin pillra-wa cali wangkutnun-am maani ciuliamta alerquutaitnun nall’arusngaluni.
And what he talked about today, it is in accordance to our ancestors instructions here.
Man’a ayuqeltassiigutekluku:
He used this as an example:
Waten-gguq akmani kingunrani-wa ilakutai alerquutengqertut:
He said that back at his home downstates, his people have this traditional instruction:
Neviarcar qinga’arqan irnivailgan anyugluni umyuarteqkuni, tua-i-llu anyugyaaqerrluni umyuani cimiraqan
When a young lady is pregnant before giving birth, if she things of going out, then changes her mind about wanting to go out
Tamana cimiqallra ilangcivkenaku egmianun anqertesqelluku.
Ignoring her change of mind, they tell her to go right out.
Tamatumek-gguq alerquutengqertut ciuliari.
He said his ancestors have that traditional instruction.
We have learned much from the white man, good and bad.
Maa-i-gguq wangkuta amllermek elitellrurtukut makunek qatellriartamteńek, assilrianek assiilngurnek-llu ayuqluku.
He said that we’ve learned much from these white people among us, good and bad all the same.
Among all people, there are some good, there are some bad.
Tua-i-gguq tuaten ayuquq, tamakut nallmegteggun tuaten ayuqevkenateng.
He said it’s like that, with people being different among their own.
Nunam qaingani-gguq yuut tuaten ayuquq au͡g’utun.
He said that people are like that, as he said.
If we look for something bad in other people, that will be easy to do. There’s something bad in all of us.
But it’s another thing to look for something good. It’s the better way.
Tua-llu-gguq wangkuta ilaput-wa tua-i [?]rrluki [?]lluulluki pikumta assiitellriamek ilamteggun nallunaillerkaanek
Then, he said that if we [?] those around us [?looking] for something bad to be shown in those around us
Tamana-gguq qacignarquq.
He said that’s easy.
Tau͡gaam assilriamek-wa tua-i pillerkaq pivigkartarluni cali.
But there is also a place for something good.
Another thing that we all have in common is destruction
By nature, and by man-made destruction.
Mat’umek-gguq cali maa-i tua-i nallunrirciqukut niilluta-llu.
He said that we will find out and hear about this.
Nallunairumalria-wa yuum qaillun piunrillerkaa cakun
It’s been shown that a person can be destoryed through something
Wall’u yuum taqellrakun-llu piunriryugngacia.
Or that he cane by destroyed by man-made things.
In nature’s destruction, there’s floods, tornadoes, hurricanes, earthquakes, fire, and things like that.
Mat’um-gguq ellam ayuquciakun yuut piunriryarait ava-i aperturai
He just mentioned the ways that people can be destroyed through natural phenomena
Imkutgun nunam pekterpallrakun-llu, ingrit-llu qagrallritgun.
Through those, earthquakes, and volcanic eruptions.
Tamaa-i wall’u ulerpagteggun, tamakutgun tua-i yuut piunriryugngaluteng.
Through those, or through floods, people can be destroyed through those.
Man-made destructions, there’s a lot of things. The list is too long.
There’s bombs, [?war ?].
World powers can’t live together. They must try to dominate one another.
Cali-gguq maa-i-wa yugteggun taqumalriit yuut piunriryarait ayuqevkenateng.
He said that there are different ways people can be destroyed by these man-made things.
Imukun-llu qagercetaakun, wall’u anguyaucarakun yuk amlleq piunriraqluni.
Many people are also destroyed through bombs, or through war.
Ilateng-wa tua-i tegungnaqluki cirlakengnaqlermegteggu-llu tamaaggun tuaten piunrilartuq yuk amlleq.
Trying to take over and dominate those around them, many people are destroyed through that.
This earth on which we live is known as a planet. It is a planet.
Man’a-gguq nunavut uitavigput, ava-i mumigtellerkaa nalluaqa.
He said that our land where we live, I don’t know how to translate it.
Tau͡gaam aperluku elitnaurani elitaqciqerci. Planet-aamek aterpagingauq man’a uitavigput.
But if I say it, you students will recognize it. The place we live is called a planet.
There are nine in what we call solar system.
There are nine planets in this area around the sun.
Tamaa-i qulngunritaraugut mat’umcetun ayuqellriit akertem avatiini planet-aat.
He said there are nine planets like ours here around the sun.
So far as we know now, this is the only planet that has life.
Tua-i-gguq yuvriumallermegteggun tau͡gaam tuaten amllertang’e’rmeng
He said that in all of their examinations, though there are that many
Una-gguq tau͡aam wangkuta uitavigput unguvanarqellriamek pitangqerrluni.
He said that where we live now is the only one that supports life.
With all the different people over our earth
We have a very unique place. This earth is very special.
The Great Ones above saw to it that this will be a special place for man to live in.
Tua-i-gguq man’a ellavut yuvriumallermini
He said that as they examined our world
Waten-llu mat’utun uitavimcetun planet-aatun allat planet-aaruyaaqeng’e’rmeng
And though the other planets like where we live now are planets
Tau͡gaam Pak’mum-wa murilkestemta nallunritaa man’a kiimi waten uitaviksunarqucia uitavigput.
But the One Above who watches over us knows that this place of ours is the only one viable to live in.
Many people refer to this earth as Mother Earth.
Amlleret-gguq yuut aterpagtelaraat man’a nunavut Aanaulriamek.
He said that many people refer to our earth here as a Mother.
My tribe has an endearing term. We call it Grandmother Earth.
Iliin-llu, elliin-llu ilakutain tamakut ap’lalliniluku Maurlurmek Nunamek.
And his people call it Grandmother Earth.
It makes us sad many times to see our Grandmother’s face all spot up, gouged out, without putting anything good back into it.
Tua-i-gguq waten man’a-wa tamana Maurluq imutun ilalkumalriacetun [?tugalleqtaarumaluni-llu] ayuqaqami
He said that when this Grandmother is mistreated and [?gouged]
Tua-i angniitnarqelartuq.
It’s sad to see.
Every little thing has life. Even a little blade of grass, a little weed has life.
Little tiny bugs, animals, birds, fish, everywhere there’s life all around, and we respect them..
Little tiny bugs, animals, birds, fish, everywhere there’s life all around, and we respect them.
Tua-i-gguq ca tamarmi maa-i nunam qaingani uitavimteńi tangllerput
He said that everything we see on this land where we live
Naunraunge’rmi wall’u yaquleyagaunge’rmi, caunge’rmi tamarmeng-gguq unguvangqertut.
He said that everything, even plants or little birds, everything has life.
Anerteqluteng.
They’re alive.
Tua-i-gguq wangkutni nallunritestaitni tamakut qigcignaqluteng.
He said that we who know about them treat them with respect.
I have learned much from the people from different villages.
They have learned much from this Mother Earth, something they can use in what we call Yup’ik medicine.
Maa-i-gguq quyungqallemteńi-wa amllermek-wa tua-i elituq yugteggun ayuqenrilngurteggun nallunairumalrianek
He said that as we’ve been meeting, he has learned a lot that has been demonstrated through different peoples
Maaken Aanamteńek Nunamek naumalriamek wangkutnun nunam eyirturtainun atuuyugngalriamek.
The plants that grow on Mother Earth that are useful for us who populate this earth.
The white man has a word called "poverty."
Makut wani qatellriit aipaiput-gguq qaneryarangqertut ava-i qaneryaraitgun apqaqii au͡gna "poverty."
He said that our white counterparts have a word that he just said in their language, "poverty."
Taringellemtun iqlutun taringumaksailkumku arrsaucimek kangingqertuq.
In my understanding, if I’m not understanding it wrong, it means to be poor.
Poverty usually means somebody without means, income, money.
Tamaa-i ava-i nalqigtellemkun poverty, arrsauyaraungan
Since poverty means to be poor as I just explained
Kina imna enuqlitellria-wa tua-i canek tamaitnek, enuqitellriim aprutkaa.
It’s a word used for someone who is short on everything, one who lacks.
But there is another poverty:
If you have no old people for many knowledge that they have, they don’t share and go on and
We are left without nothing, without guidance.
That would be a terrible poverty.
Cali-gguq nunamiutarteggun-wa tua-i tukuucitgun enuqellratgun yuk arrsauyaaqeciquq.
He also said that a person may be poor in worldly things, being short on [material] riches.
Tau͡gaa-gguq maa-i cali yuum arrsaucian ilii cali:
But, he said that this is another part of how a person can be poor:
Amlleret ciuliat kinguliateng nallunairvikumanritlermegteki camek eliyutkaatnek, nallunritarkaatnek.
When many elders do not explain to their descendants things that they should learn, that they should know.
Tamaa-i-gguq cali arrsaucim ilakaa.
He said that’s part of being poor.
If you sit in on meetings, you will find that you are very rich.
If you could sit in on our meetings, hearing these people share their knowledge
You will find that you are very rich to have people with this kind of knowledge.
Tua-i-gguq uumirpak quyungqallemteńi qallaquralriatgun niiqurallerput niiqu’rquvciki
He said that if you listen to the poeple who’ve been speaking as we’ve been meeting that we’ve been listening to
Tamaaggun-gguq tua-i nallunriryartuci wangkuta imutun tukuulriatun ayuqucimteńek.
He said that you would find through that it’s like we are rich.
Yuut elisngak’ngaarit nallunrilkengait-llu cat nallunairumallruut uumirpak ayagnirraanemteńek.
People have been explaining things they are knowledgeable about and know since we’ve started.
Tamaa-i tamaggun cali yuk elisngallermikun tukuulriatun ayuqeciqelliniuq.
Through a person’s knowledge like that, he will be like a rich person.
In sickness, it usually is in the body or in the mind.
Naulluunami-gguq yuk naulluulartuq aipaagni tememikun wall’u umyuamikun.
He said that in sickness, a person is sick either in his body or in his mind.
There is another part of us to make us whole, and that is the soul of man.
Cali-gguq tau͡gaam ataucimek pingqertukut wangkuta pimteńek-wa.
He said that we have one thing of our own.
Tayima nallunrilkuvciu elitaqa’arciiqerci ciuliartaq tarneq.
If you know the ancestors’ concept, you will recognize the soul.
Nalqigtelararput tuquyuilngurput tauna.
We explain that as the part of us that doesn’t die.
We rely great things upon what this soul tells this body and this mind to do.
Tauna-gguq tarnerput wangkuta amllermi cacetuqutek’lararput
He said that many times, we depend on our soul
Wangkuta-wa tua-i camek kepqutemteńek-llu umyuarteqaqamta.
Including when we think about the things we sorely need something.
We feed our bodies, clothe it, wash it.
We exercise our mind. But what about this soul?
Maa-i-gguq wangkuta temvut una wani caluku cayailkutacetun pilararput, nerevkarluku kenuggluku-llu.
He said that we do things to our body to protect it, feed and groom it.
Tau͡gaam-gguq tuana imna tuquyuilngurput qaillun piqatarta?
But, he said, what are we going to do with the part of us that doesn’t die?
This soul, in most every one of us, have experienced poverty
Because we don’t nourish it, we don’t feed it, we don’t exercise it.
Tua-i-gguq maa-i una wani tarnerput amllermi wangkuta imutun arrsauvkalriacetun-wa pilararput
He said that many times, we cause our soul to be destitute
Wangkuta tau͡gaam nerevkarinritlemteggun.
Only because we don’t feed it.
As I look around from the very smallest to the very oldest, all of us have souls, and you are beautiful.
As I look around form the very smallest to the very oldest, all of us have souls, and you are beautiful.
Tua-i-gguq waken tangvaurallermini mikelnguyagarpeceńek ayagluci ciulirneci tekilluki, tua-i-gguq tamarpeci tarnengqertuci.
He said that as he watches from here, from your very little children to your elders, he said that all of you have souls.
Cali-llu-gguq tangssunaqluci.
He also said you’re beautiful.
All of us have much to contribute, much to give, all of us
And be helpful to one another.
Tamamta-gguq ilamteńun tamiinun ikayuucugngaukut
He said that all of us can help those around us
Cali-llu tamamta cikiutekarluta ikayuutekamteńek ilamteńun.
And we all have gifts we can use to help those around us.
There was a story of a man who worked on the railroad, come home every other day.
Qanemcitangqertuq-gguq yugmek calilriamek nunakuarcuullugpiit tumyaraitni.
He said that there’s a story of a person who worked on the railroad.
Tauna-gguq yaaliaquaqan tau͡gaam kingunerminun utertetulriamek.
He said that that person only returned home every other day.
He had three children: one boy, a girl, and another small boy.
Tauna-gguq yungqertuq malrugnek tan’gaurluugnek, nasaurluq-wa-gguq pingayuat.
He said that that person had two male children, and a girl was the third.
The two older children, the boy and the girl, when they see their dad coming home
They run out into the field, pick pretty flowers to give to their daddy.
Tua-llu-gguq taukuk yugkenka ciuqlirraagket malruk tan’gaurluq nasaurlurraq-llu [?].
Then he said that when the two elders of his children, the boy and the girl, [?].
Atasek-gguq tauna iluvalliniaqan anqerrlutek paircularaak.
He said that when their father came into view, they’d go out to meet him.
Tua-i-llu-gguq naunrarnek tangssunarqellrianek qecukaullutek atasek tauna cikiqerluku.
Then he said that they would pluck out pretty flowers, and give their father [flowers].
The little boy was paralyzed from waist down. He could not walk or run.
Tauna-gguq kinguqliq tan’gaurlucuar uatek-gguq nal’aqringauk.
He said that that youngest boy’s waist was paralyzed.
Tarritesciiganani-wa ilagmitun.
He couldn’t walk around like the other two.
Muraggluarnek-llu.
And little pieces of wood.
When the older boy and girl get the flowers picked
They’d run to meet daddy. "Here, I picked this for you," and give it to him.
He said that because the first two were active and healthy
Naunrarnek tamaaken teguqauqaarlutek atasek paiqalaraak aqvaqurlutek
After taking flowers from there, they would run to meet their father
Qanrulluku waniwa cikirniluku, ellii pitekluku taukunek qecuutellrunilutek.
Telling him that they’re giving him [flowers[, that they had picked them for him.
When dad walked into the yard
This little boy that can’t run, can’t walk, wanted to give something too, little dirty stick, little dirty rocks.
But in his own way, "Here, daddy, here."
Tua-i-gguq tauna kinguqliak tuaten ilagmitun pisciigalami arenqiallugcami
He said that because their youngest sibling unfortunately couldn’t do as his siblings
Tua-i atani iluva’rqan paiqerpek’naku tuaten tamakunek teggalquyagarnek tayima muraggluarnek-llu avuqerluni.
Without meeting his father when he appreaed, he would gather those little rocks and little sticks.
Tekitaqan-gguq tau͡gaam yagutelarai tamakut elliin ataminun cikiutekluki.
He said that he only extended his hand to give his father those gifts when he arrived.
That’s why I say everyone has something to give one another
If that one thing that we can give is love from our hearts.
Taumek-gguq ava-i waten qanlugtellruuq:
That’s why he just said this:
Tamamta pinrilqurrunata qaqiarrluta cikiutekangqerrniluta ilamteńun.
All of us, with no exceptions, every one of us has gifts to give those around us.
Tua-i-gguq waniwauguq allamek-wa cikiutekailkumta: kenkaput tau͡gaam ilamteńun atuqumteggu.
He said that this [is what we can give] if we have no other gifts: only to treat those around us with love.
It is love that unites us together.
It iis love that unites us together.
Regardless of color, we eat.
When he pray, he pray to God, "Thank you for this."
When you partake of this food, each one, even a small portion, partake of it
We all became blessed as one people.
Tua-llu taringcetaarutkaa man’a, waten wangkuta ataucimurtelaucirput allakaqtaarluta piurangramta:
Then he used this as an example of how we are united, though we act as if we are separate:
Ukut wani neqkaugat amllellrulriit ayuqevkenateng-llu, ayuqenritqapiarluteng
There were a lot of different foods here, all completely different
Tau͡gaam piicalqa ava-i qanrutkaa Agayutmun quyatekluki atawaqercetesqumaluki ukut wani akurturpailemteki wangkuta.
But he spoke of my prayer to God, being thankful for this food and asking for the to be blessed before we received them.
Tua-i-ll’ ayuqenritkacagangraata tamamta tua-i uiggalriani tamamta ayuqluta tua-i tamana wangkuta akurturluku atawaqercecimalria wangkutnun.
Then even though they were completely different, all of us who partook in that received the things that were blessed for us.
Many times, I feel lonely. I’m not alone, but I feel lonely sometimes.
Many times, I feel lonely. I’m not along, but I feel onely sometimes.
I have a father that died first.
And then my son was killed when he was 17 years old.
My mother lived to be over 100 years old
And I buried her not too long ago.
They’re waiting for me.
But until that day comes when I will go to meet them
I want to make the most of this life while I’m still living here today.
Maa-i-gguq ellii akuliini aliayularyaaquq angniinani-llu.
He said that now, he sometimes feels lonely and sad.
Tua-i-gguq-wa ellii atangqellruami, atii-llu yuunrillruluni.
He said it’s because he had a father, and his father passed away.
Nalluvkenaku [?] nani uitanrilucia nallunritaa.
He knows [?], he knows that they’re waiting for him.
Tau͡gaam-gguq cali ilalqerluku qetunrangqellruuq tuqutaullermek ava-i allrakungeqerluni akimiaq malrugnek cipluku.
But, he said that what exacerbates [his loneliness] is that he had a son who was killed when he was 17 years old.
Tuamta-llu-gguq cali aanangqellruluni, kiituani-llu allrakunguq yuinarnek tallimanek.
Then, he said that he had a mother who eventually reached 100 years old.
Maa-i-gguq elliin tauna aanani tungmaggnerraraa, nalluvkenaku tau͡gaam nantenrilucia.
He said that he recently buried his mother, but he knows she’s waiting for him.
Taumek-gguq elliin neryuniurutkaa tamana cam iliiniku elliin taukut aliayuutek’lallni tangllerkaatnek.
That’s why he said that he awaits the day when he will see those that he misses so dearly.
Tamana-llu-gguq pitekluku elliin piyuumiutekaa piyunartacirramitun unguvallermini calillerkani nunam qaingani.
He said that for that reason, he has a desire to work as much as he can on the earth while he’s alive.
You have helped to fill the emptiness in my heart
And I am grateful, and I thank God for all of you.
Tua-i-gguq waniwa elliin man’a qanrutkaa:
He said that he speaks of this now:
Elpeci-gguq waniwa tuarpiaq imaitellranek imilriacetun piarci.
He said that it truly seems that you have filled what was empty [in his heart].
Tamana-llu-gguq pitekluku elliin Agayun quyavikaa tamatumek.
He said that for that reason, he thanks God for that.
God bless you, one and all.
Agayutem atawaqertellici tamarpeci.
May God bless you all.
Yaa, uumek wani quyurvallemteńek wani qaqiutellemteńek wani waniw’ piciqua.
Okay, now I will go over what we established when we held our large gathering.
Makut wani tua-i quyurtesqurluki qaqiutellruukut makut wani yuut tua-i-w’ qalarucistait quyurtarkaurrluki.
We established these meetings where the ones who would speak to people would gather.
Cali makut wani nunat wani makut wani tegganret wani qalarucisteksaurrluki pikumta
Also, if we in these villages start having these elders become instructors
Makunun wani ayagyuanun angutnun makut angukarau’urluut piaqluteng
These old men would speak to these young men
Makut-llu cali arnassagaat cali makut wani ayagyuat arnat cali qalarutaqluki makunek yuuyaramteńek-wa tua-i qalarulluki.
And these old women would also instruct these young women about our way of life.
Cali makut wani eitnaurviit wani cali pisqumaluki, man’a pinricetevkarpek’naku:
We also want these schools to do this, without refraining from doing so:
Makut wani yumta-wa tua-i yuullratnek tua-i elitnauresqumaluki.
We want them to teach about our people’s lives back then.
Cali makut taangam mat’um wani arenqiallugutii cali ukunun YKHC-nun tua-i umyuaqesqelluku tua-i angluku
We also want YKHC to greatly consider the negative effects of alcohol
Tua-i-w’ arenqiallugutnguan.
Because it is a problem.
Cali makut wani tegganret cali maani avatemteńi cali kitugikaaniisqelluki.
We also want to improve [the care of] the elders here around us.
Makunun wani tegganemteńun aulukellrat-wa tua-i assirikaniisqelluki maani avatemteńi nunani.
We want the care of our elders here in the villages around us to improve.
Cali makut wani aipanglalriit ilameggnek, cali irniangelalriit pikegtaunrilngurnek.
Also, these people marry close relatives and have abnormal children.
Cali taman’ makunun wani ilakessiyaalrianun wani man’a aipangyaraq pisqumavkenaku qaqiutellruukut.
We also met about how we don’t want these people to marry those to whom they are too closely related.
Cali makut wani tua-i quyurtaaresqurluki makut, mat’umek wani qaqiutellruukut.
We also met about how we want these people to keep holding meetings.
Tua-i quyurtaararkaurrluta makunek wani Yupiit iinruitnek piluta.
We will not repeatedly meet about these Yup’ik types of medicine.
Makunek-llu Yupiit tua-i-w’ qalaruciyaraat wani yugnek wani caliaqluku cali taman’ qaqiutellruukut.
We also met to work on Yup’ik instruction for people.
Quyaviksuganka ukut wani taillret wani.
I want to thank these people who came.
Yurartelput Cev’armiut quyaviksugluki cali piukut.
We also want to thank the people from Chevak who Yup’ik danced for us.
Ukut quyaviksuganka cali:
I also want to thank these people:
Kay Nukacuaq Qipnermek taillruuq
Kay Nukacuaq who came from Kipnuk
Edith Kawagley Akiarmek
Edith Kawagley from Akiak
Wassilie Evan Akiarmek
Wassilie Evan from Akiak
Betty Ontom Niugtarmek
Betty Onton from Newtok
Lucille Westlock Imangarmek
Lucille Westlock from Emmonak
Joseph Qilanaq Cevv’arnermek
Joseph Qilanaq from Chefornak
Helen Smith Naparyaarmiunek
Helen Smith from Hooper Bay
Joseph Olsen Naparyaarmiu
Joseph Olsen from Hooper Bay
Paul Beebe, Kuinerraq
Paul Beebe, Quinhagak
Annie Patsy, Mountain Village
Mary Andrews, Mountain Village
Phillip Foxy, Qerrullik, Kotlik
Jasper Lewis, St. Mary’s
Noel Polty, Pilot Station
And Gusty [?McKell], Stony River-aamek tailleq.
And Gusty [?McKell] who came from Stony River.
Cali quyaviksugluki makut KYUK-mi calilriit tua-i ikayurpiikut.
I also want to thank those who work at KYUK because they helped us a lot.
Cali allat wani yuut ikayurillret cali quyaviksugluki.
I also want to thank other people who’ve helped.
Quyanaqvaa niicugniluki makut Yuut wani iinrullrit.
Thank you for listening to these traditional Yup’ik medicine.