...llruut-qaa, iciw’ kinrumassiyaagluteng?
...did they [?], you know, dried too much?
Qaillun-wa imkut yullret take care-alallruit akluteng.
I’m not sure how people long ago took care of their clothes.
Ilait ak’anun pikumaaqluki mecungtevkaqsaunaki.
They would keep some for a very long time, keeping them from getting wet.
Mecungceteksaunaki, kucirceteksaunaki ellallugmek, camun mermun.
They wouldn’t let them get wet, wouldn’t let rain fall on the drip, any kind of water.
Kinqautelallrat-qaa navguvkalarai?
Does drying up make them break?
Cat?
What?
Tamakut.
Those.
Murilkenritaqaceteng cat arutuut.
When they don’t care for things, they deteriorate.
Rotten-aarluteng mecungtaarcetaqaceteng.
They become rotten when they let them get wet repeatedly.
Cat murilkurluki pitullrulriit yuut tamakut.
Those people carefully watched things.
Neqnek-qaa cali ayuqluteng?
Was it the same with food?
Neqet-llu kenkurluki, neqautait-ll’ assiraqluteng.
They treated their food with love, and their stores of food would be good.
Kitak’ ayagyuat camek nallunritesqumallerpenek tamalkuita umyuavni uitalriit
Now, whatever you want young people to know, everything that’s in your mind
Tamakunek, iciw’ arnat ayagyuat, iciw’ wangkugcetun wall’u-q’ ayagyuat...
Those, you know, young women, you know like us or the young ones...
Nutaan-llu adult-aurtellriit.
And those who’ve just become adults.
Ai?
What?
Camek maligtaqullerkamek qanrucukek’ngarpenek.
Whatever you want to say that they should follow.
Umyuarpeni uitallriit tamalkuita qaruteksukten piluki.
Say all of the things in your mind that would to talk about.
Adult-aurtaqa-w’ tua-i qanrut’lallrukait
When they became adults, they would tell them
Wangkuta ayagyuallemteńi alerquutengqellruukut not to make love with a man before you get married.
When we were young, we had the instruction not to make love with a man before you get married.
Angutmun pisqevkenata aipangvailemta.
They told us not to give ourselves to men before we got married.
Tuaten qanrutetulruitkut.
That’s what they used to tell us.
Maa-i, maa-i waniw’ tuaten arnat pilriit qaillun qanrucugciki?
Now, what do you want to tell the women who do that now?
Iciw’...
You know...
Amllerem-wa qanrut’laryaaqekai aipangvailgan angutmun kenkesqevkenaku.
Many probably tell them that before they get married, not to have a man "love" them.
Tau͡gaam maa-i waten-llu aipaqliupailegmeng aipaqsuitellruut ak’a.
But now, they didn’t get into relationships before getting married long ago.
Ciin-gguq tuaten pisqumanriceciu?
Why are they told not to do that?
Ai?
What?
Ciin-gguq tuaten pisqumanriceta?
Why are we told not to do that?
Maa-i-wa ilateng tangerrluki makut girlfriend-angluteng boyfriend-angqerraqluteng-llu pilalriit.
Now, looking at their peers, they get girlfriends and have boyfriends.
I mean, iciw’...
I mean, you know...
Ak’a tamakut yuut umyugiuyuitellruut ayagyuat.
Long ago, those people, young people, didn’t follow their every whim.
Kitak’ qanrutqerkut iciw’ ciin tuaten iciw’
Please tell us, you know, why [it’s told] that way, you know
Angayuqavet iciw’ qanrut’lallrullikiiten iciw’ anguciuresqevkenak wall’u-q’ piciatun.
You know, your parent probably told you, you know, not to flirt with men or various things.
Ciin-gguq tuaten iciw’...
Why [is it told] that way, you know...
Qanrutanga-qaa?
Why (s)he told me?
Iciw’ qanrutkeqerr’ kitak’ qaill’ qanlallruciitnek, im’u
You know, please talk about what they used to say, you know
Iciw’ aipaqilaqan qaillun piarkaucianek qanruyutaitnek.
You know, the traditional wisdom concerning what would happen if they’re promiscuous.
Tua-i-wa pisqevkenaki aipangvailgan angutmek kenkisqevkenaku.
They told them not to, not to "love" men before they get married.
Kasngunarquq-gguq irniangekuni aipaunani aatailngurmek.
They said it’s shameful if she has an illegitimate child without a spouse.
Tuaten qanrutaqluki.
That’s what they told them.
Cangakan-qaa maa-i amllessiyaagateng arnat irningellrat aipainateng?
Do you disapprove of the fact that there are too many women who have children without spouses?
Aipaunateng-qaa irniangelallrit?
How they have children without spouses?
Yuut-wa tamalkuita allayuurcata cangakengramki qaill’ qanerciigat’lalrianga.
Well, since all people have become so different, I can’t say anything though I disapprove of them.
Nuu, qaill’ umyuartequciki?
No, what do you think of them?
Qaillun umyuartequciki-gguq?
What do you think of them?
Maa-i iciw’ yuut ayuqenrilriit? Qaillun umyuartequciki?
You know how people are different now? What do you think of them?
Iciw’ ayagyuallerpeni ayuqutekluki maa-i, maa-i yuut ayuqellritnek, arnat ayagyuat ayagyuallerpeni ak’a imumi.
You know, comparing them to when you were young, what people are like now, how young people were like when you were young long ago.
Qaillun iciw’ compare-arlukek.
You know, comparing them somehow.
Ellait-llu-wa ayagyuat ayagaluteng piyaurcameng angayuqateng nayuqsaunaki.
It’s also because those young people have started traveling around, not being with their parents.
Iciw’ tua-i high school-amek graduate-arqameng avtelalriit, ellmeggnek pingluteng college-aarluteng.
You know, they separate when they graduate from high school, going off on their own, going to college.
Umyuateng cimirluki ellaita piyullmeggnek aturluteng..
They change their minds, doing what they want to do.
Tuaten pilalriit. Amlleq tuaten pilria.
They do that. Many do that.
Avtelaamegteki angayuqateng, iciw’ tua-i graduate-araqameng college-aanun ayagluteng elitnaurluteng.
It’s because they separate from their parents, you know, they leave for college when they graduate to get education.
Ellaita piyullmeggnek piluteng.
They do what they want.
Yuut ayuqenrilameng, ilaita angayuqameng qanellrit umyuaqaqluki
Because people are different, some of them remember what their parents taught
Ilii-llu angayuqami qanellra umyuaqevkenaku, elliin tau͡gaam tangvallni ayuqellrit ayuqengnaqluki ayuqluteng
And some does not remember what his parent said, instead trying to be like the ones that he’s watched
Yuut ayuqeksailameng.
Because people are different.
Ilii-llu amlleq taangaryugluni. Ayagyuange’rmeng taangaryugaqluteng.
And many tend to drink alcohol. They tend to drink even though they’re young.
Kitak’ angayuqaagpet grandparents-aarpet-llu qanruyutek’lallritnek qanrutqerkut
Please tell us about the traditional wisdom your parents and grandparents shared
Iciw’ alerqualu[ten].
You know, instructing you.
Grandparents-aagka wii tuqullruuq tamaa.
My grandparents died early on.
Qaillurraq tayim’ angtalua apa’urluqa tuquluni.
My grandfather died when I was at some young age.
Maurluma tau͡gaam keneklua
But my grandmother loved me
Kiimnuk-llu uitaaqlunuk parents-aagka uksuiyaraqagnek, wiinga elitnaurlua.
And we would stay alone when my parents went to winter camp, as I went to school.
I was only about maybe six. Six-aarngatua-ll’ tayima, six seven, eight.
I was only about maybe six. I think I was six, six, seven, eight.
Eight-aallemni tayim’ maurluqa tuqullrungatuq.
I think my grandmother died when I was eight.
Amllermek murilkessiyaangvailemni tuquluni.
She died before I could watch her do too many things.
Angayuqaagka-llu canun ayagayuitellruamek
And because my parents didn’t go to various villages
Yuut ayagaurayuitellruut watua pilallracetun.
People didn’t travel to many villages as they do now.
Ayagayuunatek tau͡gaam tua-i cangnatuglutek every day.
They didn’t travel to villages, but they worked hard to survive every day.
Ataka pissurluni.
My father hunted.
Una-llu aanaput cat aturkaput mingeqluki, neqkiurluta tuaten, neqkat-llu murilkelluki.
And our mother would sew our clothes, even made food for us, and attended to what would be our food.
Tangvallregka taukuk yugnun-ll’ ayagayuunatek.
The two I watched wouldn’t go to other people all the time.
Waten tau͡gaam ataka Paingarmiuni ilangqerrami, uncle-aangqerrami
But because my father had relatives, an uncle, in Paingarmiut like this
Yuraqataraqata ayagaqluta tuavet.
When they were going to hold dance festivals, we would travel there.
Yuut au͡gkut ciuqliit tangvalput yuralgullruut.
Those first people we watched long ago always had dance festivals.
Yuralriit arulaiqsaunateng. Uksuarmek ayagluteng yurangaqluteng.
They wouldn’t stop having dance festivals. They would start holding dance festivals starting in the fall.
Yuut-llu, Yupiat caciryarait amllerrluteng.
And people, Yupiit, had a lot of practices.
Qaariitaatuluta-llu October-aami.
We would also practice Yup’ik Halloween in October.
Qangvaq ayagnillrua tamana Qaariitaaryaurtelci?
When did your Yup’ik Halloween practice start?
Ak’a-w’ maaten ellangua tuaten pituluteng yuut.
In my earliest memories, people had already been doing that.
Atam Qaariitaarluteng, neqlilluteng-llu.
You see, they would practice Yup’ik Halloween, and would give out food.
Neqlitaqluki yuut irniameng atqestait.
They would give food to people, their children’s namesakes.
Neqlilluki waten qantamek cikirluki, imirluku assircaarluku.
They would give food by handing out a bowl like this, filling it well.
Merr’illuki-llu, mermek cikirluku mertelluki.
And they gave them water, they gave them water to drink.
Qantamek-llu cikirluku.
And give [the child] a bowl.
Cayarait amllellruut au͡gkut tangvallrenka, wagg’uq ukut Nunacuarmiut.
The people I watched back then had a lot of practices, the place they called Nunacuarmiut.
Tua-i-ll’ cali Ingularluteng.
Then they would also hold the Ingulaq dance festival.
Qasgiteng imlluku, kituggluku, kelgiluteng nunanek.
They demolished their community house, fixed it, and invited villages.
Nunat-llu tekicameng qasgiq wanirpak taqluku unugpailgan.
Then when the villages arrived, they finished the community house right away before night fell.
Atakuan-llu yurarluteng, ingularluteng.
Then they danced in the evening, the woman dancing slowly.
Imkunek yuarucirluteng cukailngurnek yuarutnek
They would sing slow songs
Cauyaq-llu cukaunani.
And the drumbeat was slow.
Arnaq una itraqluni qantamek tegumiarluni, tua-i-gguq Ingulautminek.
A woman would come in holding a bowl, what they called her Ingulaun [Ingulaq bowl].
Qantaq-llu qasgim qukaanun natermun ellirraarluku yurarluni arnaq tauna.
Then after she placed the bowl on the floor in the middle of the community house, that woman would Yup’ik dance.
Ingularluteng.
They held the Ingulaq festival.
Tua-i-llu Ingularraartelluki call’ kinguakun
Then after they held the Ingulaq festival
Waniw’ qenuqatarluku-gguq Elciluteng-gguq
They said that before it froze they would celebrate Elciq [beginning of Bladder Festival].
Qantanek tagulluteng qasgimun.
Bringing bowls inland to the community house.
Qasgit-llu hallway-nek tunnel-aanek amigluni.
And the community houses had hallways, [or] tunnels as entrances.
Arnaq cakmani elaturrami, waniw’ amiigni call’ arnaq, una-w’ call’ amigmi arnaq.
There was a woman out there in the enclosed entry area, then a woman by this [outer] entrance, and awoman here by the [inner] entrance.
Qantaq wani tun’urluku waken qasgim amiiganek.
They passed the bowl from here by the entrance of the community house.
Pim-gguq wanigg’ Elcitii qantaput.
They said that this is this person’s Elciq bowl, our bowls.
Atput aperturaqaki qantaput aqvaaqluku.
When they called our names, we would get our bowl.
Nunaniqluni.
It was a joyous time.
Elciluteng-gguq tua-i.
They called that the Elciq festival.
Caqtaalguluteng.
They always did various practices.
Tuamtell’ cali icivaumainanrani Kevgirluteng.
Then soon after, they would hold the Messenger Feast.
Kevgak ayaglutek nunanun.
The messengers traveled to villages.
Practice-aaqatarluteng uksurpak yuarutnek piyuutnek
They were going to practice requesting songs all winter
Canek agyunek, piyuutnek-llu.
[Songs for] things, requests from other things, and things they wanted.
Yurarluteng imkunek yuraraqluteng practice-aaraqluteng imkunek yurautnek cukalrianek.
They would Yup’ik dance, practice dancing with those fast Yup’ik dancing songs.
Fast, cukaluteng yuarutet, cauyat-lu cukaluteng.
Fast, the songs were fast, and the drumbeats were fast.
Arnat yuraquaqluteng, qavaruarluteng, tuntussuruarluteng, petmigcurluteng.
The woman would dance songs about sleeping, hunting caribou, setting pit traps.
Canguarturluteng yuratuluteng ancestor-aameng yurainek.
They would Yup’ik dance depicted various things, their ancestors dances.
Motion-aarinek yuratuluteng.
They would dance with their [ancestor’s] motions.
Allat-llu cali elitnaurluteng akiqliqellriik yuuk iciw’ imkunek yurapignek.
The the others, two people across from each other would learn, you know, those real [ancient] Yup’ik dances.
Tua-i-gguq tekiqata’arcuutekiurluteng.
They called that preparing the arrival dance for guests.
Tua-i-llu uksurpak tua-i pilnguameng upingariameng
Then when they were tired of doing that all winter and they were ready
Tunutekateng-llu agyuput, agyumta tunutekait upingariluteng
And when the thigns we were going to give as requested, when the thigns they were going to give as requested were ready
Yuarutet-llu upluki piyuutet.
They also prepared the requesting songs.
"Pinaurai-qaa kinakucim-qaa camek ima-qaa qaillun pilriamek?"
"Would some random person give them something as they requested?"
Tua-i anglanaqluteng yura’arqameng.
They would be fun when they danced.
Tua-i-llu tekiqata’arqata kel’kengateng tekicata
Then when they danced the arrival dance when the ones they invited arrived
Invite-alteng nunat allat tekicata
When the other villages they invited arrived
Angutet qasgivkarluki.
They had the men go to the community house.
Qasgim-llu ingelran iliit un’gavet elliluku qulvanun.
And they placed one of the beds in the community house toward the door high up there.
Taukut-llu angutet tamaavet aqumlluki payugarrluki.
Then they sat those men there and brought them food.
Tua-i-gguq payugarrluki.
They called that bringing them food.
Neqkaitnek payuggluki neqnek keniranek, wall’u, wall’ dry fish-aanek, yuurqerkaitnek-llu.
They would bring them cooked food to ear, or dried fish, and something hot to drink.
Tua-i-llu nernerrlugcetaariluteng nerngarcata tamakut allanret angutet.
Then when those male guests started eating, they sung ridiculing songs so they wouldn’t eat in peace.
Nerngarcata yuarutmek emengluteng nunat.
When they started eating, the [host] village would start softly drumming a song.
Tua-i-gguq nernerrlugcetaarluki.
They called that ridiculing them through song as they ate.
Apa’urluunka aqumlua tangvakenka.
I sat and watched my grandfathers and great-uncles.
Last one, that was the last one.
Murilkelluku tangvallruaqa atama uncle-aari Paingarmiut.
I carefully watched my father’s uncles from Paingarmiut.
Waten Nunacuarmiut atulriit atuulluki nernerrlugcetaarluki so they can choke, or can’t swallow, or something like that.
The people of Nunacuarmiut sung like this, ridiculing them through song as they ate so they can choke, or can’t swally, or something like that.
Atuuskait waten:
They sung to them like this:
"Talluryuyuilngurnun nalirrugcetaarilii.
"Let me give those with no shame a hard choice.
"Nalirriarrngualriit avukuulluki-qaa?
"Shall I lump together those who are undecided?
"Ata-ggem ukuni Akulurarmiuni aturyuktaalarmiut.
"Don’t these people from Akuluraq also like to sing?
"Cakegtaunriluciq calliggluku maavet aturyuktaarlarmiut."
"They also like to sing, scattering about unfavorable things here."
Imkuk-ll’ apallirtulriik angutek matarmek, uyamignek makurlutek, nasqurruterlutek, qerrulliglutek tau͡gaam waten elliurlutek.
And the two men singing the verses naked, with necklaces here, with headresses, but with pants, were doing this.
Tua-i-ll’ enipagluki
Then they pointed right at them
"Unagkurluut-llam pivakengraata."
"And though the poor people down there think highly of themselves."
Ala-i alingnaqluteng.
Oh my, they were intimidating.
Tua-i-gguq nernerrlugcetaarluki.
They called that ridiculing them through song as they ate.
Wii tua-i tangvakenka tamakut apa’urluunka, atama uncle-aari.
I watched my great-uncles there, my father’s uncles.
That was the last one. I never, nalluyagucuunaku-ll’ yuarutiit.
That was the last one. And I never forgot their song.
Elitnauryuyuama-ll’ yuranek yuaruteksularyaaqekeka.
And because I teach Yup’ik dances, I want to use that song.
Cangaknayukluku yuarutkeksailkeka. Anglanaksaaqaqa.
I haven’t used that song because they might be offended. I find it fun.
Atam yurat anglanakanka yuraliyaryunqellruama-llu.
You see, I find Yup’ik dances fun because I liked going to dance festivals.
Tua-i yuralrianun unegcuunii yuraliyaraqellrianga.
I would go to dance festivals and not stay behind [at home] for the dancing.
Tua-i-ll’ Kassiglumun upagluta Kassiglurmiut nunaurtellratni.
Then we moved to Kasigluk when Kasigluk was established as a village.
Last one-aamek Kevgilriit 1935.
The last Messenger Feast they held was in 1935.
Tua-i-llu yuramek taqluteng nunat tamarmeng.
Then every village stopped Yup’ik dancing.
Tua-i yurayuirulluteng.
They stopped holding dance festivals.
Elciyuirulluteng, neqlicuirulluteng-llu.
They stopped celebrating Elciq, and they stopped giving out food.
Cat taqluki.
They stopped those festivals.
Tua-i cat yuarnaqluteng.
I miss those things.
Imkut wani agayulirtet, Moravian people, taqevkarluki.
Those priests, Moravian people, had them stop.
Anagulluki-llu yurautelallratnek, tamakunek picirluteng taqevkarluki
And because they danced excessively for people, that was the reason they had them stop
Canek pilluarqelluteng pitullrat.
They way they gave out gifts.
Yurat yuarnarqellruut yurayuirutlermeggni. Wiinga-w’ yuallrukenka.
People missed Yup’ik dancing when they stopped dancing. Well, I personally missed them.
Tua-i-llu wangkuk
Then we
Calligtaalnguamnuk uksuiyaraqlunuk, up’nerkiyaraqlunuk, caqtaalnguamnuk
Since we were tired of moving about, going to winter camp, going to spring camp, since we were tired of doing various things
We start live in Bethel, 1943. That’s long time.
We start liv[ing] in Bethel, 1943. That’s [a] long time.
Mary-ll’ maani yuurrluni.
And Mary was born here.
Yuurtengraan aipaqa kiugg’ pissuryaraqluni uksuarmi.
Though she was born, my spouse in there would hunt in the fall.
Parents-aagemnun wii ayaullua.
He brought me to my parents.
Tuamta-ll’ up’nerkami up’nerkiyaraqluta.
Then in the spring, we would go to spring camp.
Tua-i-ll’ mikelnguut amlleriata elitnaungata ayayuirulluta tua-i.
Then because there were a lot of children, because they started going to school, we stopped traveling.
School-arluteng tau͡gaam kids-aat.
Instead, the kids went to school.
Aatiit tau͡gaam ayagaqluni, Nushagak-amun-llu kuvyayaraqluni, uksuarmi-ll’ pissuryaraqluni.
But their father would travel, and go commercial fishing in Nushagak, and hunt in the fall.
Kiituan-llu calituriuq,.
Eventually, he started working.
Ayagmek calilallruuq. Calinge’rmi tau͡gaam pissuryalallruuq.
He worked from the start. But even though he worked, he’d go hunting.
Wani-ll’ Mamterillermun tekiteqarraallemteńi nunakuarcuutek malruk,.
And when we first came here to Bethel, there were two cars.
Nunakuarcuutertaunani. Sidewalk-anek tau͡gam tumyararluteng.
There were no cars. The only paths were sidewalks.
Tua-i-ll’ piqerluteng nunakuarcuutet amlleriluteng.
Then there were suddenly an increase in cars.
NC-rullermini AC-rurpailegmi suuraqluteng.
When it was NC, before it became AC, they would show movies.
Tangercetaaraqluteng.
They would show movies.
Wii tangercetaaliaraqlua irnianka malikluki.
I would go see movies, taking my children with me.
Akikit’lallruut tangercetaat, 50 cents akiluteng.
Movies were cheap, priced at 50 cents.
Tua-i-ll’ call’ Swanson-aaq kipusviliami suurvililuni ikaggun bride-am akiakun angtuamek.
Then when Swanson’s became a store, they made a big movie theater across there on the other side of the bridge.
Suurnaurtut tang double feature from 7-12.
They would show a double feature movie, from 7-12.
Long movie. Anglanarqaqluteng-llu movie-t.
Long movie. And the movies would be fun.
Tua-i atakumi atakutarraarluta suurvigmun qerarluta suuraqluta atakurpak unugpak-llu.
In the evening, after we had dinner, we would cross to the theather and watch movies all evening and all night.