Yuunrillruuq agayulirtengqellemteńi [?Greens]-aamek. A long time.
She passed away when our priest was [?Greens]. A long time.
Up’nerkami-ll’ yuunrirluni Paaskaam nalliini nuliaqa wani.
And my wife passed away in the spring around Easter.
Caullrua atra?
What was her name?
Elena. Elena Andrew.
Hunter?
Andrew. (Andrew?) Yaa.
Andrew. (Andrew?) Yes.
Aa-ang.
Yes.
Ciumek ayagyuallerpeni-qaa qasgimi uitaqallruuten?
First, did you stay in the community house when you were young?
Tamana qalamcikeqaqvgu.
Please tell a story about that.
Waniw’ ayagyuallemni qasgimi angturrillruunga.
When I was young, I grew up in a community house.
Tua-llu iciw’ aatama caniani qavarturatullruunga qasgimi.
Then, you know, I would always sleep next to my father in the community house.
Yugugarni iciw’, you know, qasgiq nallunritan.
Among many people, you know, you about the community house.
[?Cuukvagtulirmi] pingqellruut. Qasgingqetullruut ingluktulput.
There was one in [?Cuukvagtuli]. Our competitors had a community house.
Atama caniani.
[I slept] next to my father.
Tua-i-llu quliini qavayarat waten inglengqetullruut two feet qasgit, two feet muragnek.
Then the sleeping areas above had two feet beds like this in the community house, two feet of wood.
Tua-i-llu pinarianga cali atrarlua natermun, floor, nacitnun iciw’ floor-amun.
Then when it was time, I would go down to the nateq, floor, to the floor planks, you know, the floor.
Qavaraqluta tua-i camek pivkenata.
We would sleep without thinking anything of it.
Aliimaksuaramteńek makucinek waten wall’u-q’ imkunek Yupiartarnek aliimatpianek akicirluta qavaraqluta.
We would sleep using these small mittens of ours like this, or those real Yup’ik gloves as headrests.
Cavkenani wangkutni wani ak’a tamaani, you know?
It wasn’t unusual to us a long time ago, you know?
Tua-i tuaten yuullruukut.
That’s how we lived.
Wii apa’urluma anglicallruanga.
My grandfather raised me.
Anglicarpek’nii waten: unuakumi qavarcecuitellruanga.
He raised me like this: he wouldn’t let me sleep in the morning.
Cunaw’ tang elluarrlua yuusqellua pillrullinikiinga.
It turned out that he had wanted me to live well.
Waten-llu qava’arqama waten, waten tupagyarturnauraanga waten ukugnun pilua.
Then when I slept like this, he would come wake my up by doing this here.
Tua-i-ll’ cailkamek maaken [?] pikanga, "Ani patagmek qagaavet ellamun."
Then when he [?] me from the floor her, he would say, "Quickly go outside."
Ellami-gguq atam assiriqerrniartua. Ellamun ankuma assiriqerrluni ayuquciqa, cegg’arlua qavarniyugnairrlua.
He said that I would get better outside. When I went outside, I would feel better, being awake with no more trace of sleep left.
Man’a-ll’ tekilluku maa-i qavayuunii unuakumi wani kesianek [?].
And to this day, I never sleep in the morning [?].
Kass’atun qanraqlua pikuma.
I should occassionally speak English.
Yaa.
Yes.
Nani tauna qasgi uitallrua?
Where was that community house?
Kayalivigmi. Kayalivigmi.
In Kayalivik. In Kayalivik.
Ilangqellruuten-qaa amllernek ayagyuanek tuani qasgim iluani?
Did you have a lot of young companions there in that community house?
Amllertut. Ayagyuat qasgimi tau͡gaam uitatullruut.
There were a lot. Young boys would only stay in the community house.
Qasgimi tua-i ayagyuat egkuani uitaaqluteng ayagyuat.
In the community house, the youth would stay in the back wall.
Enemecuunateng. Ayagyuat tau͡gaam qasgimi uitasqumaluki, you know?
They would stay in the houses. They wanted the youth to only stay in the community house, you know?
Makut-llu tegganret maani, imkut-ll’ angukara’urluut un’gani uaqvani, waten akiqliqluteng.
These adults and the old men would be here toward the door, across from each other like this.
Tamakut tamaa-i qanrucitullruut yugnek waten.
Those would speak to people like this.
Waten tutgarateng qanrutnaurait.
They would speak to their grandchildren like this.
Tua-i-ll’ qanruqaarluki, tutgaraq tuqlurluku qanruqaarluku qanpagaluteng. Alingnaqluteng qanpagaaqameng.
Then after speaking to them, after one addressed and spoke to his grandchild, they would speak sternly. They would be scary when they spoke sternly.
Tau͡gken assilriameng qanerturluteng, qanerturatuluteng.
Yet they would always speak about good things.
Ayuqucirtualuki qau͡gkut qavani egkumi.
They would instruct the ones inside on the back wall.
Yaa, tuaten yuullruunga wiinga.
Yes, that’s how I lived.
Angutngurrlainaullrullilriit-wa qasgim iluani.
They were probably all men in the community house.
Ii-i, yaa, tuaten anguterrlainaat pituut wani.
Yes, yes, only men do that.
Tuamtellu...
And then...
Nasaurlucuaraat, nasaurlurraat angturiqerrluteng cali aatameng caniitni uitaurall’ernaurtut qasgimi qasgimiut niicugniurluki qalartellrat assilriamek.
Little girls, little girls who had grown would also stay by their fathers in the community house listening to them speak about good things.
Tamakut tamaa-i ilait tuaten piqa’arqameng caqa’arqameng tuaten piuraraqluteng.
When some of those did that, they would once in a while.
Una nasaurlucuar qasgimcugtura’aqluni.
This little girl would keep wanting to be in the community house.
Cunaw’ niicugluni qasgimiut qalartellritnek.
Apparently, she wanted to hear what the men of the community house spoke about.
Yaa, angukara’urluut qalartellritnek. Yaa, tuaten pilallruut yuut.
Yes, what the old men spoke about. Yes, that’s what people would do.
Qaill’ tamakut tegganret tamatum nalliini ayuqellruat?
What were the adults like in that time?
Tegganret tan’gaurlurnek tau͡gaam kitugcingnaqluteng yuullruut. Ayuqucirtuagurluki assirluki yuusqelluki.
The adults lived only trying to improve boys. They instructed them, telling them to live well.
Kiingan tua-i caliaqaat tamana tegganret.
That’s the only job for adults.
Makut ilateng tan’gaurluut ayagyuat elluarrluki tau͡gaam yuusqelluki.
They only wanted their relatives, these young boys, to live well.
Qanllerteng-llu cagesqevkenaku. Niitesqumaluteng kiinga.
They did want what they said to be lost. The only wanted to be heard.
Assilriarrlainarnek qantullruut imkut angukara’urluut tangvallrenka wiinga.
Those old men I watched would only speak of good things.
Yaa. Ii-i, igautaqluki.
Yes. Yes, write them down.
Canek...
What...
Tang ata cukangnaqevkaavnga.
You see, because you’re making me hurry.
Nuu.
No.
Igaqautaqluki, igaulluki, ayagnerit-llu ayagluki nallunritarkaukuvki elisngakuvet tua-i.
Write them down, and start from the beggining if you are to know them if you are smart.
Ayagneritnek tua-i-ll’ taringluku.
From the beginning, then you’ll understand.
Tua-ll’ tamakut... are we ready?
Then those... are we ready?
Tamakut-qaa tegganret mat’um nalliinicetun ayuqellruut wall’u-qaa?
Were those adults like how they are now, or what?
Nuu, mat’um nalliinicetun ayuqenritut.
No, they weren’t like how they are now.
Tua-i-w’ anailameng, camek-llu uitavigkailameng, quyungqanriameng waten caggluteng pingengameng enemeggni.
It’s because they don’t go out, and they have no place, because they are not gathered anymore, but scattered in their houses like this.
Wii tau͡gaam kiima waniwa maani arenqilriit ilanka wall’u-q’ ilakenrilengramki tan’gaurluut qalaruquralaranka carraquinermek tua-i niitarkaatnek.
Now, only I speak to the boys, my relatives, or even if they’re not my relatives, who do well [to come] a little about what they need to hear.
Tua-i niilluki.
They listen to them.
Maa-i-ll’ mat’um nalliini ilait au͡gkut inerciigatellret qalaruquratullrenka egmian tua-i assiriluteng, assirluteng.
And these days, some of the ones who were mischievous whom I spoke to get better right away, are better.
Aklungluteng-llu, cangluteng tua-i, qaqicimariluteng tua-i, arenqiallugtenrirluteng.
They get clothes, get things, have everything they need, no longer in misfortune.
Canek, canek tamakut tegganret elicalallruitki ayagyuat?
What would those adults teach the youth?
Ayagallerkaatnek elicalallruit, imarpigmun-ll’ ayagalallerkaat.
They would teach how they would travel, and how they would travel in the ocean.
Tua-i ayagalallerkaat tamalkuan elitnaurluki qalaruqu’urluki pitullruit.
They would always speak to them to teach them everything about traveling.
Tuaten pitullruut.
That’s what they’d do.
Ayakatalriit tua-i tuaten qanrulluki tua-i. Tuaten yuilqumi arenqiallugeskaku-llu tuaten pisqelluku. Tuaten pilallruitkut.
They would speak to those we were going to travel like. They even told them what they would do if they came to misfortune in the wilderness. That’s how they [taught] us.
Elitnaulriacetun?
Like going to school?
Ii-i, elitnaulriacetun.
Yes, like going to school.
Tua-i-llu wangkuta Yupiaruamta
And then because we’re Yup’ik
Tua-i-wa neqkailkumta-llu wall’u pikangqerqumta, pikangqerqumta camek neqkailkumta, qassatukatgu tua-i qassarluku ner’arkauluku.
And if we have no other food, if we have something with no other food, if they eat it raw, we must eat it raw.
Tua-i-llu tuaten waniw’ ayuqucirtulallruitkut waten:
Then they would instruct us like this:
Ayakataqumta carrarmek neqrarmek, cakuine’rmek ayaulluta ayaasqelluta.
If we’re going to travel, they told us to travel with a little food, a little scrap.
Qanikciurun-llu imna shovel malikerrlainarluku.
And we should always bring a shovel with us.
Cali-llu qilak.
Also some cloth to work with.
Wiinga ellangellruama tua-i lumarrat amlleriluki qiliggarkaq tua-i malikerrlainarluku.
Since I grew up with an increase of cloth, I always took cloth to work with with me.
Neqraq-llu cali malikerrlainarluku.
And always bring fishing tools with us.
Tua-i-llu ellaqerruskakut egmian cali ayangnaqesqevkenata.
Then if the weather turns on us, they told us not to travel right away either.
Egmian ayagturaasqevkenata tua-i umyuaqellemtun.
They told us not to travel right away as we think to.
Tau͡gaam arulairesqelluta uqinrunrilngurmun waten, waten imna iciw’ nuna, man’a nuna.
Instead, they told us to stop where we’re not shielded [from the wind] liek this, you know, the land like this, the land here.
Wani wavet qanikcanrilkaku tua-i waten alaunaku waten.
If it hadn’t snowed here, and it was visible like this.
Tua-i tuaten arulairesqelluta, qilaput tuaten pisqelluku elliqerluku.
They told us to stop like that, and even to set up our tent.
Tua-i-ll’ cali caitqapigeskumta qilagkamek cali qanikcaq nayugluku waten.
Then if we have absolutely no tent, we should hollow out the snow like this.
Eneliluta waten nayugluku, iterluta.
Make a space hollowing it out like this, then go in.
Tau͡gaam cam uqinermun pivkenata cali nuna man’a im’ maa-i tua-i tuavet qanikcaq nayuulluku tua-i iterluta.
But we shouldn’t go into the leeward side in the land here, but hollow out the snow there and go in.
Qulvut-llu una waten ukilluku aneryaarcuutekluku.
And poke a hole above us like this as a breathing hole.
Qanikcaam atam makuni epsal[ngunarqucia] cakneq nallunritaqa wiinga.
You see, I absolutely know that snow is suffocating.
Atuqallruan?
Have you ever experienced it?
Yaa, atuqallruaqa. Epsalngunarquq. Kiircetuq cakneq.
Yes, I’ve experienced it. It’s suffocating. It’s very hot.
Epciquq yuk tuquluni-ll’ tua-i tuaten qanrucimanrilkuni.
A person will suffocate and die if he’s not told about that.
Epsalngunarquq, tuquluni-ll’ tua-i.
It’s suffocating, then he dies.
Alingnarquq qanikcaq tamana wani.
That snow is dangerous.
Cali kiskuvet, wiinga cali atullruaqa killua maatekiirlua waten.
Also, if you sink, I also experienced sinking to here like this.
Quunirluni ella nengllirluni-ll’ pacelluku waten.
The weather was calm, and it was cold and chilly like this.
Nuliaqa-w’ unilluku irniagka-llu pissurlua, hunting [?], imarmiutarnek.
I left my wife and children to go hunt, hunting, for minks.
Tua-i-llu man’a imarmiutacuar allayugtun pilria qamurturluni tua-i
Then this small mink that was acting strangely was dragging
Uumek piluni tallirluni, uumek kat’umek-llu iruluni.
It had its forepaws here, and its hindpaws were down there.
Tamatumek paqnayullemni kit’ellruunga. Tam’a’rqurluku tum’arrluku.
When I was curious about that, I sank. I followed its tracks.
Nunapik-wa una nunapik.
The tundra here was here.
Man’a cikuuluni.
This part was ice.
Tua-i tamana waten ayarungqerrsaaqlua, ayarurlua.
There, I did have a staff, I used my staff.
Tamatumek paqnayuglua piinanemni nunapiar waniw’ tekiteqatarluku igtua man’a-ll’ tekilluku.
As I was curious about that, when I was going to reach the tundra here, I fell and it reached here.
Nengllirluni-ll’ qakemna.
And it was cold out there.
Kenrenka wani plastic-aamek caqumaurluteng uitaluteng.
And my matches were here, covered in plastic.
Tua-i-llu takelriignek-llu waten pilua kamksagnek ayagassuutegnek-wa imkunek.
And I also had long fur boots like this, the ones used for traveling.
Killua.
I sunk.
Maaten kic’ama kamqertevkenii au͡gna ciunerkaqa kauka’rqa.
When I sunk, it didn’t reach past my boods, and I poked where I would go.
Waniw’ tua-i tekiciiqellinikeka man’a kiturpailemku nunaq.
I would reach the land before [the water] would go here.
Tua-i-ll’ taglua.
Then I went on the land.
Mayurlua tua-i ivrarlua. Tua-i kisngang’e’rmi taglua tua-i.
I went up wading. Though I had sunk, I went up on land.
Mayuama-ll’ egmian aturanka yuulaagluki tua-i patagpiarlua quunian-llu ella nenglling’e’rmi.
When I went up, I quickly took off my clothes in great hurry because the weather was calm though it was cold.
Ciulaagluki tamalkuita. Imkuk kameksak kuvluku waten-llu piaqlukek waten.
I quickly wrung them all. I poured the water out of my fur boots and would do this.
Tua-i-ll’ can’get amllerrata egmian aturalaagma canegnek tua-i man’a keviraqluku.
Then because there was a lot of grass, right when I put on my clothes, I stuffed grass in here.
Can’get pingualuruki ukumnun piaqluki, ukumnun piaqluki.
I bunched grass and put them here, put them here.
Tua-i-ll’ taq’ercamki maaten kiartua qakineyagaat makut.
Then when I was done with them, I looked around and noticed pale dry dead wood.
Imkut qakinret, you know iciw’ muraketukeput.
Those dry dead wood, you know, the ones we use for woodwork.
Tua-i-ll’ caaniggangqerrama puqlassuutet-ll’ amllerivailgata, puqlissuutet imkut pingvailgata
Then since I had a small kettle before there were a lot of portable stoves, before there were portable stoves
Keneq kumarrluku tuaken imuken mecungenrilriani wani kenernek, kenpianek.
I lit the fire with the matches from here that were no longer wet, real mathes.
Kenpianek waten [?].
[?] real matches like this.
Kumarrluku tua-i kenilua caanililua.
I started a fire and made a kettle of hot water.
Tua-i puqlangan caayumek tua-i yuurqaqcaarlua.
When it got hot, I sipped some tea.
Piama uruglua. Uruglua tua-i man’a nenglliurallra urugluku.
When I did, I warmed up. I warmed up from this cold.
Tua-ll’ taqngama umyuartequa.
Then when I was done, I pondered.
Tua-i-llu yuurqallma kinguani makuk irugka puqlangengiinartuk imkuk tua-i canegnek imillregka
Then after I had tea, my legs started getting warmer, the ones that I filled with grass
Man’a tekilluku tua-i kiturluku-llu.
Reaching here and past it.
Wii piyuagurlua pitullruama qimugcilleq, pitengnaqaqama-gga qimugcilleq assiksuitellruamku.
I always used to walk because I didn’t like mushing dogs when I was hunting.
Tua-i-llu ayaglua naspaalua.
Then I tried traveling.
Tua-i waniw’ qerruyingkanga utertarkaulua.
Should I’ve gotten cold, I’d have to go home.
Ernerpak piyuagua puqelvangluni. Kiiryunglua tua-i kiiryuglua. Cukangssaagarpek’nii.
I walked all day and [my legs] got very warm. I got very hot. I didn’t go quickly.
Imkut yaaqsilriit pissuutenka imkut iciw’ kapkaanat tekilluki nangluki uterrlua-llu.
I went to every one of my far away tools, you know, those steel traps, and went home.
Uterrlua-ll’ qaillun nenglliu...
And I went home in the cold...
Tua-i tang yuut imkut alerquutait assilriit cakneq, imkut ciuqlirmi ciuliarit.
You see, the instructions of those people back then are old, their first ancestors.
Waniw’ ciuliatgun wii yuugua.
I am living according to the ancestors.
Waniw’ yuugarkaugukut usvitungnaqelriani ciuliaput ak’a tamaanillaat aturluki.
Now, we who are trying to be mindful must live according to our ancestors’ wisdom of long ago.
Elluarrluta yuuciqukut tuaten yuukumta ciuliaput aturluki.
We will live well if we live according to our ancestors like that.
Tua-i-wa tuaten ayuquq.
Well, that’s how it is.
Ii-i, aptaqlua camek tua-i piyugaqavnga.
Okay, ask me something whenever you want.
Ilait tegganrurtellriit maa-i-rpak, ilait tegganrutellriit maa-i-rpak qanlartut, ak’a-gguq tamaani tegganret, yuut imkut naulluyuitellruut. Tamana-qaa piciuguq?
Some who are elders now, some who are elders now say that a long time ago, elders, people would not get sick. Is that true?
Yaa, piciuguq.
Yes, it’s true.
Naulluuyuitellruut imkut yuut wani.
People didn’t get sick back then.
Cayaqliqapiarluni tang atauciq naulluulalria.
Once in a great while, you see, one person would get sick.
Iliini-ll’ allrakurtaqluni, one year.
And sometimes one year would pass.
Tua-i-ll’ iliini tuquarkaullinikuni tua-i tuquyaqlirluni tuquluni.
Then sometimes if one is to die, he would be the first to die in a long time.
Tau͡gken tua-i tamana pellugluku cali iliini talliriluni tua-i tuaten.
Yet after that had passed, sometimes five years would pass [with no deaths] like that.
Cali-llu TB-lriit ikgenateng, TB.
And there were few who had TB.
Tua-i TB-lriit inerquutaqluki waten mallguri[sqevkenaki].
They admonish people against getting close to those with TB.
Makut-am inerquutaqsagutait Kass’at. Wangkuta TB-lriit waten pingraata cikiyuitaitkut.
Caucasians have started admonishing against this. Though we do this to those with TB, they don’t give it to us.
Cikiringaituq yuk apquciminek, you know?
A pesron will not spread his ailment, you know?
Tuaten ayuqelria umyuarteqelia camek uluryagpek’nani elluarrluni yuuciquq, camek, cam-llu agtuyuunaku.
One who is and thinks like that without being wary will live well, and nothing will touch him.
Yaa.
Yes.
Agtuyuunaku-ll’ yuum ca uluryakevkenaku qanrutkengraatgu.
Nothing will touch him if he’s not wary though they tell him.
Waniw’ tuaten wii yuugua alerquutemnek cali atamnek apa’urlumnek-llu.
Now, I am living like that through the instruction passed down to me by my father and grandfather.
Tua-ll’ ak’a tamaani-qaa tegganret ukvengqelallruut, camek-llu ukvengqelallruat?
Then, a longt ime ago, did the elders have beliefs, and what were their beliefs?
Angalkunek. Kiingan angalkuq.
Shamans. Only a shaman.
Imna-llu iciw’ Agayun-llu nalluluku, imna agayulirta.
And, you know, they didn’t know God, that priest.
Wii tamaani ellangellemni mission-aat tekitelallruut Kayalivigmun waten Cuukvagtuli-ll’ ingluku[llutek].
Back when I was growing up, missions would arrive to Kayalivik where they would compete with Cuukvagtuli.
Egmian tua-i yurarturluta-ll’ waten piqtaarluta, waten piqtaarluta, waten piqtaarturluta every year, every year too.
Right away, we would dance back and for like this, back and forth like this, back and forth like this every year, every year too.
Tuaten pituluteng.
They would do that.
Camek-mi ukvengqellruat?
But what was their belief?
Ai?
What?
Camek ukvengqellruat?
What was their beleif?
Yupiat? (Ii-i.)
The Yup’ik people? (Yes.)
Camek ukverunateng imkut waten qanernaurtut, imkut tamakut magic-aat-wa Kass’atum apeqmeggnek:
Without any belief, they would say this about what they call magic in English:
Ellam-gguq Yua. Ellam-gguq Yua.
They called it the Spirit of the Universe.
Cunaw’ Agayun.
Turned out to be God.
Ellam-gguq Yuanek qigciyugluteng tuaten pitullruut.
They said they would do that, respecting the Spirit of the Universe.
Cunaw’ God-amek.
Tuned out to be God.
Ellam Yuanek apraqluku God-aq.
They referred to God as the Spirit of the Universe.
Imkut-qaa yugurluut tuunrangayagmek qanlallruut?
Would the people of old speak about the devil?
Ii-i.
Yes.
Tuaten tuunrangayagmek qanyuitellruut yugurluut.
The people of old didn’t speak about the devil like that.
Tau͡gken angalkuugaqluteng tuunrituluteng wiinga-ll’ tangvagaqlua.
Yet they would be shamans who called on their spirit helpers, and I would watch.
Qaill’ tang ciin atak piaqluteng wiinga-ll’ qaillun piciitaqluki tamakut.
You see, they would do things for some reason, and I wouldn’t know what they did.
Tangvallruaten?
Did you watch them?
Tangvagaqluki.
I would watch them.
Qaill’ pilallruat?
What would they do?
Tua-i piluteng piaqluteng.
They would do [whatever] they did.
Tua-i taq’ertaqameng qalartaqluteng.
When they stopped, they would speak.
Ella-llu-gguq kitugtaqluku, ellaliuraqluteng-llu.
They said that they fixed and predicted the weather.
Iralurtaqluteng-llu-gguq wanirpapiaq tua-i.
They also said they’d instantly go to the moon.
Tang qaill’ yuut ayuqellruut. Ircenrrartun ayuqellruut yuut wani.
You see, people were strange. People were like legendary little people.
Yaa.
Yes.
Tuamtellu yuk waten cavvnaurait tamakut, akngirutii cakneq cavvluku.
Then they would feel a person like this, feeling for his extreme pain.
Tua-i-ll’ pegeskatni assiriluni.
Then when they let go of him, he got better.
Qaillun tamakut yuut? Irr’inarqut tamakut yullret.
How did those people [do it]? Those people of old are amazing.
Akilircetaarluteng-qaa tuaten pilallruut?
Would they ask to be paid to do that?
Nuu, akilircetaayuitait.
No, they didn’t ask to be paid.
Tau͡gaam imkut tamakut tuunritulit
But those people who called on spirit helpers
Tauna-ll’ yuk cateng anirtuusqumaaqamegteggu canek piciatun, Kass’artarnek akluitellruameng, Yugtarrlainarnek tau͡gaam pingqellruameng
When they wanted that person, their relative, to be saved, [they brought] various things, because they didn’t have Western clothes because they only had Yup’ik things
Camek, makliim-llu qecianek, maklaaraam-llu qecianek
Something, including a bearded seal skin, and a young bearded seal skin
Piciatun tua-i wani terikaniarmek, keglunermek
Various things, wolverine skin, wolf skin
Tua-i camek tuaten ayuqellruut tamakut yuut.
[Giving] something, that’s what those people were like.
Tua-i akiutekluki tamakut cam [?].
That was their payment, [?skin] of something.
Akiuteklu[ki]. Akimek nalluq’apiarluteng tua-i.
That was their payment. They knew nothing about money.
Tamaani-qaa ayagyuallerpeni ayagalallerpeni pissurluten wall’u-qaa natmun ayagaqavet
Back when you were young, when you traveled to go hunting, or when you traveled somewhere
Elpet-qaa camek irr’inarqellriamek...
Did you [experience] anything amazing?