Yaa.
Ready.
Yaa, kitek’ au͡gna kiuyullerpenek kiukiu.
Okay, please answer that how you want.
Nutaan kitak’ qanrutkiu.
Please say it again.
Ii-i. Man’a-qaa Yuut qanruyutait ak’anek, ak’a tamaakenirnek piugurallret cangallrunritut agayuvigtarni qanruyutni?
Okay. Is the anceint Yup’ik wisdom, the ones that have been since ancient times, no different from wisdom of the church?
Iciw’ igausngalriani Bible-aani?
You know, the ones written in the Bible?
Ii-i. Tua-i cangallruvken[ateng]. Maaten Bible-aani imkut, imkuuluteng tua-i qanruyuteput.
Yes. They are no different. We found that in the Bible, they were our traditional wisdom.
Agayuvigmi-ll’ wiinga, agayuyaryaqlirqama-llu qanruyutellrenka imkut elitaqaqluki qalarqura’arqata.
And when I was in the church, when I finally went to church, I would recognize the traditional wisdom passed down to me when they spoke.
Elitaqa’artaqluki qanruyutellrenka imkut.
I would recognize the traditional wisdom passed down to me.
Arnat-qaa uingvailegmeng qaillun alerquumalallruat?
How would the women be instructed before taking husbands?
Aren, angutet wangkutni alingnarqellruut.
Oh my, the men were scary to us.
Angutet alingnarqellruut.
The men were scary.
Aipaqnguayuunata-llu, tass’uqellriamek-llu tangssuunata.
And we wouldn’t play with each other informally, and we wouldn’t see anyone holding hands.
Uumi alingnaqpiarluteng angutet.
Long ago, men were very scary.
Wii tua-i alikellruanka.
I was scared of them.
Qingallerkaqa-ll’ tua-i niiqurluku tauggun wii aanamnek-wa.
And I would hear about how I would get pregnant from my mother.
Umyuaqenrilkemteńek-llu uingaqluta, umyuaqsugnailkemteńek.
And we would take husbands whom we never expected, those we did not expect at all.
Arnaurtellerkam-mi agleryaram tungiinun qaill’ qanlallruat?
What wouold they say about becoming a woman with first mensturations?
Agleryaraq-llu tua-i eyagcetaqluta.
And for first menstruations, they would have us abstain.
Tang arnaurtaqamta tua-i alingpiaqluta angutni.
When we became women, the men feared us a lot.
Arnaq-gguq tuquuguq.
They say that a woman leads to death.
Alingaqlua wiinga. Arniqevkariciqniluta-ll’ qanrutaqluta.
I would be scared. And they would tell us that we would make men crazed for women.
Maa-i arniqsuirutellriit.
Now, they don’t get woman-crazed.
Makut nasaurluut aglenrraraat aqumgavkalallruit qulni ernerni-gguq.
They said that they would have girls with their first menstruations abstain for ten days.
Aqumgavkarluki-gguq.
They called it aqumgaluteng.
Tamana-qaa elpet atullrunritan?
Did you not go through that?
Atullruaqa.
I went through it.
Aqumgalua tua-i canek, canek-wa tua-i at’ellua.
I abstained, and they had me put on certain clothes.
Tua-i kiarcecuunii-llu. Kiarteksaunii.
And they wouldn’t have me look around the area. I wouldn’t look around the area.
Kiartelallilrianga-llu-w’ iliini.
I may have looked around sometimes.
(Inerquutetarluni?) Inerquumaluta tua-i.
(Were there admonishments?) Were were admonished.
Tua-i-ll’ nangercamta atlinqigtelluta. Yagtelluta.
And when we stood up, they would have us replace what we were sitting on. They would have us raise our hands.
Meq tua-i alingcirarautekaqluku.
They would warn us about water.
Waten mat’um nalliini wii watmi aglellruunga.
During this time, I had my first menstruations.
(Ciin-gguq meq inerquutekluku?) Takvigituuq-gguq watmi?
(Why did they admonish against water?) They say can see you better at this time.
Qassaq-llu.
And raw meat.
Kiarceciiganaci-llu-qaa?
And you couldn’t look around?
Ii-i, canek kiartesqeksaitaqluta. (Ciin-gguq?)
Yes, they told us not to look around the area. (Why?)
Naamelliin. Iingiucara’arnayukluki-w’ pilallikait.
I don’t know. They probably told us our eyesight would go early.
Makut-llu-qaa tua-i tan’gaurluut pairqengaqavciki?
And when you were going to cross paths with these boys?
Ii-i, tuaten tua-i piaqluteng.
Yes, they would do that.
Qaill’ pisqaqluki?
What would they tell them to do?
Iciw’ uqritgun. Nalirnerteggun-wa kituusqelartatki.
You know, downwind from them. They tell them to pass in some direction.
Ciin-gguq?
Why?
Naam, ellaita-wa.
I don’t know, something about them.
Tua-ll’ tamaani-qaa yuut nunallgutkenrilnguut yugnek tangrraqameng akluitgun elitaq’lallruit camiunguciit?
And then, back when people who weren’t from the same village saw others, would they recognize where they were from by what they wore?
Qaralingqetullruut-gguq tuaten atkuit-llu.
They said they had decorations like that, including their parkas.
Tamakumiut tuaten qaralingqerraqluteng.
People from a certain area had unique decorations.
Elpeci-mi canek qaralingqellruceci?
What kind of decorations did you have?
Naamell’.
I don’t know.
Makut-qaa imkut...
Did these...
Qanemcitangqertuq-am tayima nani makunek elliranek.
There are stories somewhere about these orphans.
Niitelartukut Kass’at tainginanermeggni, natmun tainginanermeggni nataqutniluteng, aa, sandbar...
We hear that as the Caucasians were coming, as they were coming somewhere, that they found a, um, sandbar...
Qau͡gyaq-qaa?
A qau͡gyaq?
Elliramek unitellratnek yuut qikertam...
And orphan that people abandoned on an island...
That’s not how it... (Yaa, on a sandbar.) On a small island, I guess so, but it was on a sandbar.
That’s not how it... (Yes, on a sandbar.) On a small island, I guess so, but it was on a sandbar.
Tamakut-qaa ellirat allakaukelallruit yuut?
Would people discriminate against those orphans?
Elliraat tua-i inerquutekpiaraqluki. Inerquutekluki.
They had strong adminishments about orphans. They had admonishments about them.
Inerquagaqluta nakukengraitki-ll’ ilagauteqaasqevkenata elli’irnun, elliraat.
They would admonish us that even if others picked on orphans, never to join them.
Ciin tanem?
Why so?
Well, they had admonishments about orphans.
Inerquraqluta tangnerrlugnarqellrianun-llu iciw’ engelarturangraata ilagauteqaasqevkenata.
And they would admonish us that even if they, you know, made fun of people that looked funny, never to join them.
Kia auluk’lallruitki ellirat?
Who would take care of the orphans?
Elliraat imumi check-angyuitellermeggni tua-i arnam-llu uum aulukeqtararaqluku, tau͡gaam tungelqurrita tegutuyugnarqait.
Back when they wouldn’t get checks, a woman would take care of the dear orphan, but I think their relatives would take them in.
Tegutullruyugnarqait tuaten atairutaqata.
I think they took them in when they lost their fathers.
Tua-ll’ inuguangqelallrullilriaten-wa tayima.
And then, you probably had a small doll.
Inuguarcuutngullruunga wii. Inuguarturatullruukuk Caikaq-llu.
I was never without a small doll. Caikaq and I would always play with small dolls.
Tua-i-qaa canek taukut inuguat
And so, did your small dolls
Ayuqsuitellruut-qaa naanguaci uksumi aturcuutekat wall’u kiagmi?
Did you have different toys for the winter or the summer?
Yaa, uksumi yaaruiq.
Yes, there were storyknives in the winter.
Tua-i yaaruigura[raqluta]. Maa-i tang yaaruilriamek-llu tangssuunata, inugualrianek-llu tangssuunata.
We would always tell storyknife stories. Now, we don’t see anyone telling storyknife stories, and don’t see anyone playing with small dolls.
Caugat-mi inuguat irniaruat-llu?
What are inuguat (small dolls), and irniaruat (dolls)?
Irniaruat-llu tua-i cat tekitaqata yaqulget anutaqluki inuguat-llu.
When different things, birds, came, they would take out small dolls and dolls.
Ciin-gguq?
Why?
Anucuunaki uksumi, qemagngaluki tua-i.
They didn’t take them out in the winter, but kept them stored.
Tua-i-ll’ nutaan yaqulget, cat yungat tekitaqata pilliut, anulluki inuguat irniaruat-llu.
And then when the birds came, probably the jaegers, they would take out the small dolls and the dolls.
Ciin tanem?
Why so?
Naam. Kencikellruamegteggu-w’ ella.
I don’t know. Because they revered nature.
Niitelartua-llu manalrianek kanani Mamterillermi.
I also hear about people jiggin down in Bethel.
Cang’urluteng-gguq manarnaurtut, tua-i-llu-gguq-am catairrluteng neqet.
They say they would catch fish, then the fish would disappear.
Ilait qanlartut, "Aglenrrar-wam wall’u-qaa irnicuanerrar manaryallrullian tamaqallilriit." Tamana-qaa piciu[guq]?
Some say, "They probably disappeared because a girl within the first year of her menstruations or one who miscarried is jigging." Is that true?
Tamana piciuyugnarquq.
That’s probably true.
Allanek-qaa tuaten...
Were there others like that...
Tuaten tua-i maaten murilkua tuaten qanraqluteng inerquutnguluni.
When I observed them, I found that they would say that as an admonishment.
Tua-ll’ ak’a tamaani Kass’at pingssiyaagpailgata atrit’lallruyugnarqut mikelnguut ayagyuat.
And then, back before there were a lot of Caucasians, I don’t think young children had names.
Niitelallruunga waten: kituucianek una aptaqamegteggu kiunauraa waten: "Uum irniaqaanga," wall’u-q’ "Uum yuliaqaanga."
I used to hear this: when they would ask him what his name was, he would answer, "I am this person’s child," or "I am this person’s adopted child."
Tuaten-qaa niitelallruuten?
Did you hear about that?
Niitelallruunga. Atrit’lallruyugnarqut Kass’atun, Yugtun tau͡gaam.
I used to hear that. They probably didn’t have English names, only Yup’ik ones.
Qaillun-mi atenglallruat?
So how would they get names?
Acilallikait. Acilaqput-wa maa-i.
They probably named them. We name them now.
Nuu, tua-i-w’ iciw’ agayuvigmun agulluki angllurcelluki acilaqait?
No, you know how they bring them to the church, and baptize them with names?
Ak’a tamaani qaillun acilallruitki agayuvingvailgata makut Yuut Yupiarullratni?
How did they name them before there were churches, when Yupiit lived traditional lives?
Yugtarnek-wa acitullrullikai, acitukai.
They would give them Yup’ik names.
Wangkuta uani Qinarmi mission-aartarmek tau͡gaam tua-i agayuvingqellruukut.
Downriver in Qinaq, we only had a mission church.
Tua-i agayuvikluku kiingan naucan.
It was our only church when it was built.
Maaten ellangua wiinga agayuvigtaunani, tau͡gaam enetarluni mission-aartarmek.
When I grew up, I found that there was no church, but a mission house.
Tuani agayuaqluteng, qasgimi-ll’ agayuaqluteng.
They would hold services there, and hold services in the community house.
Tua-i-ll’ naulluku ak’allaq.
And then they built the old one.
Tua-i kiingan agayuvikluku.
It was their only church.
Ak’a-wa tamaani-llu makut yuut tuvqaku’urluteng pilallrullilriit ilameggnun.
And long ago, these people probably always shared their food with each other.
Tua-i tuvqakulluteng ilakuyusnganateng.
They shared their food with each other as if they were a single family.
Tua-i-w’ mat’um nalliini makut ayagyuat qaillun qaneryarateng Yugcetun nalluyagutengluku.
These days, these young people are started to forget how to speak their Yup’ik langauge.
Cali-llu Yuut, Yuut ak’a qanruyutait niicuirulluki.
Also, they don’t hear about traditional Yup’ik wisdom anymore.
Apqiitnek Kass’at saagarrluteng Yuut piciqnilarait qaneryuirutellriit wall’u-qaa kinkuuciteng nalluyagulluku.
As they call it, Westernization will spread among Yupiit who don’t speak Yup’ik or who forget who they are.
Wangkuta-qaa Yugni saagartellriatun ellirciqukut cam iliini qaneryuiruskumta Yugcetun wall’u-qaa niicuiruskumta Yugtarnek ak’allarnek tamakunek?
Will we Yupiit be as if we were scattered someday if we don’t speak Yup’ik anymore, or if we don’t hear about those ancient Yup’ik things?
Pillilriakut-wa.
We probably will.
Qaneryaraq tua-i man’a tamayunaicaaquq.
We shouldn’t lose this language.
Ciin tanem?
Why so?
Nutem qaneryarauluni.
It’s an ancient language.
I’d kind of like to get Nicholai to say something in...
I’d kin dof like to get Nicholai to say something in...
Nicholai-aq kitek’ piqerru, apteqerru.
Please ask Nicholai a question.
Camek-gguq-qaa piciatun qanqeryuumiituq ayagyuat atu’urkaatnek ak’allarmek piciatun qanruyutmek?
Ask him if he want’s to say any ancient traditional wisdom that young people should follow.
Qaillun ima?
What was it again?
Yaa, apteqerru waten: qanruyutmek-gguq-qaa piciatun qanqeryuumiituq ayagyuat atullerkaatnek watua mat’um nalliini?
Okay, as him like this: does he want to say anything that young people should follow in these days?
Qanruyutmek-gguq ak’allarmek ayagyuat qanruyutiitnek qanqaa.
He asked you to speak about ancient traditional wisdom concerning young people.
Wiinga tamaani tua-i tan’gurra’urluullemni
Back when I was a boy
Kanani enem, ena tauna yungqertuq angutngurrluni ayagyuarpek’nani.
Down in that house, there was an old man, not young, in that house.
Tan’gaurluut waten tuavet atakumi quyurrluki.
He would gather the boys there like this in the evening.
It’lallruukut.
We would go in.
Tua-i taum im’ angukara’urluum qanlallran ilii umyuaqela’arqa cali maa-i, cali ak’allaurcuunani.
I still remember to this day one of the things that old man said, and it doesn’t get old.
Tamaani tua-i taum angutem cunaw’ qanrut’lallinikiikut tua-i-w’ unguvallemteńi murilkelluta pisqelluta.
Back then, it turned out that that man would tell us to be careful in our lives.
Cali-llu ilaput kenekluki-w’ tua-i.
Also, to treat those around us with love.
Cunaw’ una kenekluki qanrumalria tamarmi yuum aturarkauyaaqellinikii-wa.
It turned out that the saying to treat everyone with love was to be followed by every person.
Nutaan-llu tangerrsaaqeng’e’rmiu qanellgutkekuniu, tua-i ilaliurluku pisqumaluni.
And even if he sees him for the first time, he wants to be spoken to and socialized with.
Taum tua-i angutem man’a qanrutkelallrua.
That man would speak about this.
Tua-i tau͡gaam caqerluni qanellra
But what he said one day
Cali wangkuta-w’ neqnek nertulini yugni piitenritengnaqesqelluta taum angutem unguvallemteńi utumakumta pisqelluta.
That old man also told us people who eat food to try not to run out, that we should subsist as we live if we are well.
Cunaw’ una neqem cataitellra assiituq neqnek nertuluni.
It turned out that being without food is bad for those who eat.
Tamaani tua-i neqkameggnek anglani’urlullrunritliniut makunek imkunek kuvyanek piilameng.
The poor people couldn’t afford to waste food because they didn’t have these Western nets.
Tua-i tau͡gaam qilaganek-gguq ilait qaillun tua-i kuvyangqerraqluteng.
However, he said that some would have nets made by knot-like tying.
Tuaten tua-i taum angutem, angukara’urluum qanrutkelallrui.
That’s how that man, old man, would speak of them.
Tamakut, pissuutnek-wa tua-i tamakut anglanillrunritliniut.
Those, they couldn’t afford to waste those tools.
Taumek tua-i-w’ iliini apqiitnek kailallrullini[lriit] nurutaqluteng neqkameggnek.
That’s why they would sometimes, as they say, starve with a shortage of food.
Ciku-gguq cup’uq. Wifey-q-gguq qanrullaku cup’uq-gguq un’a. (Cup’uq.)
They said the ice broke up. They told me to tell Wifey that the ice broke up. (It broke up.)
Tua-i-w’ nangqerrutellriakuk tape-amek. Quyanaqvaa.
Well, we have no more tape. Thank you very much.
Tua-llu-w’ qanenrulriaten.
You spoke more.
Quyana.
Thank you.
Yaa.
You’re welcome.
Uum-llu waniwa aanii...
And her mother...