...ayagalallrat
...in their travels
Kit’ellrianek niiqurangukut maa-i.
We always hear about people drowning now.
Cam, qaillun taukuk wani qalarutekniagken.
Please talk about what and how.
(Yaa.) Ayuqeltassiigullukek (Ii-i.) cukanrarluni cukaunani kit’ellrak, kit’elallrak naliak amllenrua ciin-llu?
(Okay.) Compare (Yes.) drowning when going fast and going slow, which one has more drownings and why?
Kitak’ tamana wani qanrutkeqerru.
Please speak about that.
Tamaa-i, tamaa-i tamatum nalliini ayagassuutengqertut qayanek.
Back at that time, they had kayaks for traveling.
Tua-llu anuqengararutaqateng qaspengqerrluteng-llu imkunek maklaaret qiluitnek.
Then when the wind suddenly picked up on them, they had thin pullovers made of bearded seal intestines.
Irnerrlugnek qaspernek all’uki pitulinek.
Seal gut pullovers that they put on.
Tamakunek qayam una painga, iciw’ uivenqellriit?
With those, the rim of the kayak here, you know how they’re round?
Qayanek-qaa tanglallruuten? (Yaa.)
Would you see kayaks? (Yes.)
Iciw’ uivenqellriit?
You know how they’re round?
Kinguqaminek qumigluku qayam painga.
[S]he would put the hem around the rim of the kayak.
Tua-i-llu nutaan pelacinaunrilngurmek tapengyaarmek pinevkarluku piliameggnek nemerluku. Tua-i-gguq ket’garluku.
Then finally, bind it, not with twine, but with binding material that they made by cutting sealskin in a spiral. They call that ket’garluku.
Tua-i qairem waten pilangraani iterciiganani qayaan iluanun.
Though a wave does this to him, it can’t go inside his kayak.
Tuaten pitulliniit, pitullruut.
They used to do that.
Qayaan iluanun iterciiganani meq qumikngani.
Water can’t go inside his kayak because it’s under his hem.
Tua-ll’ makut wani angyat kill’uteng-llu piksaitelaryaaqut.
Then these boats, they’ve don’t really sink.
Tau͡gaam mat’um, mat’um aturyulallrata atungnaq’lallrata picurlagavkalarai.
But this thing they tend to abuse, try to abuse, leads them to misfortune.
Picurlagatek’larai taangamek aterpagcimalria.
What’s called alcohol leads them to misfortune.
Tamakutaitellrani picurlalriartaitellruuq.
When there was none of that, there were no accidents.
Picurlalriamek niicuitellruukut kiagmi kit’ellriamek.
We didn’t hear of anyone in an accident, drowning, in the summer.
Maa-i mat’um, mat’um tua-i atuusqumanricaaqaat nunat tamarmeng yuita ayagyuat.
Now, people in every village don’t want the youth to abuse it.
Ayagyuanrilnge’rmeng-llu pilalriit.
They do it even if they’re not young.
Kanevtellriatun waten, kanevtellriatun ayuqluku.
Dying in great numbers like this, like they’re being scattered.
Tua-i tuaten wii ayuqekutela’arqa, kanevtellriatun.
That’s how I compare it, like being scattered.
Iciw’ kanevciaqamta tua-i kanvelalria. Imna-ll’ taryirissuutmek pilallerput kanvaqluni.
You know when we scatter things, they scatter. And what we call a salt shaker scatters [salt].
Tuarpiaq umyuartequra’rqama tuaten tua-i kanvutekluku man’a aturyulallrat.
It truly seems, when I ponder upon it, that what they tend to abuse makes them die in great numbers like that.
Tamakut camek nallullruut tamatutaitellrani.
They didn’t know of any [accidents] when there was none of that [alcohol].
Tamakutaitellrani picurlagayuunateng.
When there was none of that, they wouldn’t get into many accidents.
Tuaten tua-i. Angenricaaqut-ll’ au͡gkut ayagassuutek’lallriit. Qayat kiingita ayagassuutait.
Like that. Their means of travel back then also weren’t big. Kayaks were their only means of travel.
Man’a kitak’ cali waten maa-i niiqurangelriakut qanruyutet niitnaunrirniluki.
So now, we also hear now that we don’t hear traditional wisdom anymore.
Elpeni cali murilkellerpeni ciin qanruyutet qanruteknanrirpakartatki?
In your observation, why don’t they talk about traditional wisdom anymore?
Tua-i, tua-i au͡gkut, au͡gkut ciuqlimta, ciuqliput nang’ngata.
It’s because our elders are all gone.
Qanruyutet tamakunek ciuqlimteńek qanrutkestairucata. Qanrutkestairutut.
It’s because there’s none of our elders to speak of that traditional wisdom. There’s no one to talk about them anymore.
Ilaita-llu nallunrit’laryaaqellikait tayima.
And some probably know them.
Qanruyun ak’allaq niitelaryaaqellikii.
[Some] probably hear about the old traditional wisdom.
Tamaa-i qanrutkurtairucami.
It’s because there’s no one to speak about them anymore.
Atam tamakut tamaa-i angullrenka qalaruyutseng cimiqetaarpek’naku.
You see, the people I was born in time to see wouldn’t change what they were instructed.
Atauciq tua-i atauciuluku qalarutkuratuat.
They’d speak of one thing in one way.
Uum qalartaqami qanrutkaqluku.
When one instructed, [s]he’d speak of it.
Akaurpailgan allam uum qanraqami qanrutkaqluku.
Before long, when another instructed, [s]he’d speak of it.
Tamaa-i tamakunek tegganrurtellrianek qalarutkestairucameng
Because there are none of those who’ve become elders to talk about them anymore
Qanruyun man’a qanrutkuranriraat nang’ngameng tamakut qalarutkestek’lallri.
They don’t talk about this traditional wisdom anymore, because those that talk about them are gone.
Waten, waten cali makut wani ciuliaput waten qanerturalalriit
Also, our elders here say this
Qanerturalalriit-wa tuar, tuar qanruyutet pinrillrat ayagyuanun elliluku qanrucunairutniluta.
They always say, it seems, it seems that they put [the blame] on young people for the disconinuation of traditional wisdom, saying that we don’t heed advice anymore.
Ciin, ciin tamana cali tuaten piularta maa-i?
Why is it like that now?
Tua-i maa-i tang atungekvut tua-i tamana imna qanrutkelallrat.
Now, you see, we’ve started experiencing what they’d talk about.
Qanrutkelallrat atungekvut.
We’re starting to experience what they’d talk about.
Qanqauteng’e’rmi aturciigaliluku ilii.
Though one is given advice, [s]he cannot follow it.
Niicugnirraarluni tua-i-ll’ ayagluni tua-i unilluku.
After listening, then [s]he goes away, leaving [the instructor].
Tamaa-i tamana ciuqvaar umyuaqluku ilaita pilallruut.
With that, some would think of the far future.
Maa-i tua-i qanrutkelallrat.
This is what they spoke of.
Qanruyun atunrirciqniluku-ll’ wii niigartelallruunga.
I’d also hear that they won’t adhere to traditional wisdom anymore.
Qanrutestairuskata qanruyun atunrirciqniluku.
They said that when they have no more instructors, they won’t adhere to traditional wisdom anymore.
Avani ciuqvaarni niigartelallruaqa.
I’d hear that a long time ago back then.
Maa-i-qaa tamana niitelallren elpeni piciurtenguq qanruyun atunrir[ciqniluku]?
Now, to you, is it true what they said about how they’d stop adhering to traditional wisdom?
Ii-i, ii-i, piciurtuq tua-i maa-i.
Yes, yes, it’s come true now.
Tang au͡gkut yaaqvaq-llu tekitarkaq nallunrilngurtun pilallrulliniut, nallunrilngurtun.
You see, it was like people back then knew what was a long time to come, like they knew.
Camek wani elpet tua-i paiciryullerpenek
Whatever [wisdom] that you want to leave with us
Wangkuta ayagyuani wall’u niicugnilriani camek alerquutmek paicirluta.
Leave us young people, or those listening, with some traditional instruction.
Ii-i.
Okay.
Camek elpet paiciryarcikut?
What would you leave with us?
Paiciutekaqa, paiciuteksugyaaqek’ngaqa waniwa:
I leave behind, this is what I want to leave behind:
Kenkulluci, ayagyualriani kenkulluku.
Treat each other with love, young people, treat each other with love.
Ilaci cangayugcetaarpek’naki pisqelluci.
I tell you not to affront those around you.
Ilakelriatun ayuqulluci elpeceńek.
Treat each other as family.
Maa-i tang makut wani iqlutmun ayagarcukaarangelria
Now, you see, these people easily go astray.
Qanruyutni, wall’u cangayullni ayagneqluku.
Starting from traditional wisdom, or, being offended.
Ayuqlutek, ayuqlutek arnaunge’rmi tuaten ayuqliriuq.
[Man and woman] the same, the same, even a woman has become like that.
Cangayuutni iqlutmun ayagarutekarkauluku. Iqlutmuqrulluku, iqlutmuqrutekluku.
She goes astray because of being offended. She goes astray from that.
Tau͡gaam waten, waten atam cangayugcetaarpek’nani ilaci ayagyuallguceci.
But like this, do not affront your fellow young people.
Angutngurtengraan wall’ arnaurtengraan ayuqluku piurquvci
If you treat them the same, even if they’ve become a man or woman
Imutun tua-i uqisngauralriatun, uqisngauralriatun ayuqniartuci.
So it will be like you’re sheltered, like you’re sheltered.
Man’a maa-i umyuaqelarniaran catairut’nge’rma-llu wii.
Remember this even when I’m gone.
Ii-i, quyana. Quyana qalangssaulluta.
Okay, thank you. Thank you for speaking with us.