Tan’gurraullemteńi-gga tamaani imkut angayuqaamta
When we were boys back then, our parents
Angayuqaagma anerteqlermegni qaygimun tau͡gaam cinguqtaaralriatun ayuqetullrukiignga.
When my parents were alive, it’s like they encouraged me to go to the community house.
Qaygisqumaurelua.
They wanted me to partake in the community house.
Tau͡ga-llu niillukek taukuk narurrnanrilamkek-llu angayuqaagka taukuk.
And so I obeyed them, since I did not go against my parents’ wishes.
Tau͡gaam nutaraulkiilagnek ak’allaulutek piagnek narurtaarpegnakek cuungnatullruunga.
But since they were not young, since they were old, I lived without going against their wishes.
Tau͡gan’ pisqumatiik aturluku qaygimun tau͡ga ag’aqlua.
According to their request, I would go to the community house.
Qaygimun tau͡gken it’raqamta cugyakapiareluni qaug’utuumarmi.
Yet when we entered the community house, there was a great many people all the way inside.
Man’a-llu nakirnermeng pitukiit man’a kanaggun pugyarangqerrluni mayuryarauluni kanaggun.
And the area here that they call the side wall had an entrance from below where you would go up from down there.
Au͡gna-ll’ kialirneq egkumeng pituluku.
And they would call the area further inside the back wall.
Ukalirneq-llu ualirnermeng pituluku.
And they would call this area, the area toward the door.
Cugyakapiarnaurtuq man’a qaygim ilua.
There would be a great many people inside the community house.
Qau͡gna-llu waten atakuyartumi pilriani calinriqerrluteng qaygimun ag’aqata imkut angutet enmequrayuitellruameng-llu.
And the area inside close to the evening like this, the men stopped working when the men went to the community house since they didn’t always stay in the houses.
Qaygi tau͡ga enkepiarluku enekluku.
The community house was their real home.
Ukuk-gga angutngurtellriik, wanigg’ ualirnermi uani iqukacagarmi uitaluni
As for the two old men, [one] stayed here toward the door at the very end
Cali ikna iqukacagarmi cali uitaluni.
And [the other] across there was at the very end.
Taukuk qaneryarameng egelracilriik.
They brought forth traditional wisdom.
Civunerkiutulik taukuk tamarmeng una wani qanrraarcelluku ukalirnermelnguq
Both of those who instructed on the future, after having the one on this side speak
Ayuqucirkaat una qanrutkarkartek pavqaarluku
After bringing what they needed to say about how they should be
Waten cuullerkaat ayuqellerkaat qanrutekluku.
He spoke about how they should live, and how they should be.
Tau͡ga-ll’ taqngan ik’um call’ kituggluku akiqlian.
Then when he was done, the one across fixed it.
Waten cuusqelluku cuk. Qasgimiungermeng, ataunge’rmeng, irnialing’e’rmeng taukuk qaneryarakek canrilkenritait.
They said a person should live like this. Though they lived in the community house, were fathers, had many children, the didn’t disregard what they said.
Nepariataquq qaygi taukuk qanngaqagneng.
The community house would be quiet when they spoke.
Waten cuullerkaata tungii quyinginaqluki cuugusqevkenaki taukuk qantulik qantuuk.
About how they should live, the two speakers would say that they shouldn’t be haughty people.
Quyingnaqevkenata-gguq.
They said we shouldn’t be haughty.
Imna-gguq tau͡gaam un’a enqakluku nateq, nateq un’a waten caranglliraqelria tutmaqiit.
They said, however, to remember the floor, the floor down there where they trod that has grass strewn about it.
Enqakluku-gguq wangkuta cuuniartukut tamana quyingnaqevkenata.
They said that we should live remembering that, trying not to be haughty.
Tau͡ga-llu-gguq tau͡gatnaureluta pikumta
Then they said that if we do that
Cali makut civumteńi cuurtellret teggenrurtellriit makut cali tau͡ga-i ikayungnaqureluki uumeng piyuumiutiitneng.
Also, they said that we should try to help these elders that were born before us with what they want.
Qang’a-llu cali ukuk teggenrurtellriik nulirqelriit mermeng enuqitevkarpekgnakek ullakarlukuk nallunrilkumtekek cali mertarlukek.
Or also, we should not let an elderly couple lack water, go to them if we know them, and get water for them.
Cali cakmena amiiga kituggnarqekan kituggluku.
Also, if their door below needs fixing, to fix it.
Tua-ll’ imkut waten tan’gurrarnek atanqiyuitut ataurteng’e’rmeng maani qaygim iluani niitellrek.
Then, they do not await boys like this even though they’ve become fathers from what we heard of the two in the community house.
Tan’gurraat atanqevkenaki una ataurrnge’rmi-llu irniangqeng’e’rmi-llu malrugneng taukuk qaneryarak maligtaquqapiggluku maligtaquaqaat.
They didn’t wait for boys, though he became a father and had two children, they would completely follow their traditional wisdom.
Tau͡gamtellu ayuqenrilamta wangkuta cugni
Then, since we people are not the same
Ayuqenrilamta qanellrak taukuk iliin, cuum iliin tau͡ga-i imutun tangenrilngurcetun niitellrunilngurcetun-llu ayuqluku tau͡ga piarkaulliniluku.
Since we are no the same, some people would regard what they said as if they didn’t see or hear it.
Tau͡gaten-am tauna qanruteknauraak tau͡gaten ayuqelria.
They would speak like that about one who was like that.
Ingna-gguq tekilluku cuungaituq una, Cuugungaituq.
They said that he will not live to that day, will not be Cup’ik.
Tau͡gken imna qaneryarartek cali maligtaqustii tamana murilkeqapiggluku murilkellinivagaqluku tamaani qaygim iluanelnguum.
However, the one in the community house would closely observe the one that obeyed their traditional wisdom.
Qaneryarameng maligtaqustii, maligtaqusteqapiaraa waten ak’arrarnun anerteqerciqniluku.
They said that a person who follows traditional wisdom, completely follows it, will live for quite a long time.
Imumeng anernera uyungekanilriatun ayuqeciqniluku maligtaqulluni tauna pikan.
They said that it will be like his breath "squats down [more firmly]" if he is obedient.
Ilamineng-llu acivarciyuunani, ilamineng-llu waten upussakiyuunani.
And he doesn’t bring down those around him, and he doesn’t speak unfavorably about those around him.
Ayuqluki ayagyugarungraata, mik’lengraata ayuqluki tau͡ga pisqeńauraat tau͡gaten cuk tauna tukuk qanelriik.
The same for the young people, and the same for small children, those speakers would tell that person do be like that.
Tau͡ga-ll’ ilumuunganani tau͡ga ayuqaquq.
So, it seems that it’s true.
Tangrriu makut uka-i cuullemni Qissunameng ayaglua tau͡ga camaken imarpiim cińiineng Qissunameng ayaglua cuullemni
Look, in my life when I traveled from Qissunaq down there, when I traveled from Qissunaq on the coast of the sea in my life
Cali tau͡ga cuurtellrulrua tau͡gani.
I was also born there.
Ikamraquyaurrnemkun-llu agayulirtem angllurcicanga, tau͡gaken ayaglua angllullemneng ikamraquyaurrnemkun
As soon I started travling by sled when that priest baptized me, since my baptism then as soon as I started traveling by sled
Tau͡gaken al’rrakunka tau͡ga nallunaunateng taum kengliineng.
Since then, my age has been clear from that time.
Tau͡ga-ll’ tua-i taum cali atama qanrutnauraanga
Then my father would also tell me
Waten pairyartaqevkenaki pisqelluki angurrlugmeng waten nunat ukut.
He told me to never go to these villages like this.
Naugga imu cacuaqeratkut-llu ilait, ilait qenqerrluteng.
You know how when some do insignificant things to us, they get angry.
Waten tau͡ga kiumataqelriit taumeng caqertemeggneng tauna atuusqevkenaku.
They answer to those who do things to them not to use it.
Aturluku pisqevkenii, cuusqevkenii.
He told me to live without using it.
Nutaan cali arnaukan nutaan tau͡ga kiuqeryugnaipallaarluku tauna qaill’ eq’uklua pikan.
Especially if she’s a woman, I should not reply [badly] to her if she treats me badly.
Kiuqeryugnaunaku ulurluku pisqellua.
He told me to turn away from her without replying.
Tau͡ga-llu-gguq taum pitatma, wii pitatma pirrlainarpakaquma, pirrlainarpakaqanga tau͡gaten
Then he said that if my age-mate, if I do that from my age-mate, if he keeps doing that to me
Nialiak kinguvaralua, naliak-llu picuilkellua
One of them pushing me back, and one of them saying I’m not a good hunter
Kinguvaralua pikan, qang’a-llu caitnilua naliatneng tayim’ piciqanga picuilkellua, caitnilua-llu, carrlugaitnilua.
If he pushes me back, also saying I have nothing, one of them may say that I’m not a good hunter, and I have nothing, no little thing.
Arcaayaguskumteggu nutaan tauna kiusqelluku.
He said that if we can’t take him anymore that we should then reply.
Piyugtacimtun kiusqelluku uuma atama tau͡gaten alerquatullruanga.
My father used to instruct me like that, to reply with anything I want.
Tau͡ga-i-gguq taum pistellernaama taqciqaanga taum tau͡gaten kiukumni.
He said that the one who picked on me will stop if I answer him like that.
Tau͡ga-am murilkurallemni ilumuungatnaurtuq cali tauna.
In my observation, that would seem to be true as well.
Wangkuta tang ayagyugarni ak’a ugg’un tau͡gaam teggnemteggun eglerqurallrulriakut.
You see, a long time ago, we young people only went forth through our elders.
Taukuk tua pirpapaqiarelukek civunermeng qantulik.
They held the two who spoke about the future in very high regard.
Wanigga-llu tamana qaneryaraagneng ilii maa-i taiguralrianga au͡gaken yaaqvaneng taiguralrianga
And one of their traditional wisdom, I was coming here from far over there, I was coming
Kiitau͡gani makut maa-i waten ellirtuq: man’a kiartelqa eneneng allakauqapiaralrianeng makuneng pitangluni.
Eventually it became like this: when I looked around, there were completely different houses.
Nevurrlainarneng enengqerrluteng muragaq aturluku enmeng iluanun.
They had houses made completely of sod, using wood inside their houses.
Evek cali man’a aturluku. Nevuq cali aturluku enmeggnun maqarqutekluku.
They also used grass. They also used sod to insulate their houses.
Cameng-llu tau͡ga tamakuneng tua cali imkut arnait uitayuitqapiggluteng.
And their women were absolutely not sedentary.
Imkuneng caneng taququrluteng.
They made various things.
Waten enmi uitakuneng evegneng atlilirluki, curuqluki-llu caggluki.
If they’re in the house, they put grass underneath, and spread them out for matting.
Wagg’uq makut naqtat, imkut takliriluki curuneng pituluki.
They called those naqtat, the ones they made long and used for matting.
Tau͡gamtellu man’a enmeng ilua tamakuneng tangniqnaurtut kapuyukaareneng kapuqurluteng.
Then inside their house, it would be beautiful with those stuck in with little tack-like things.
Ena-ll’ tamana ataucimeng cungqerpegnani.
And there wasn’t just one person in that house.
Una wanigg’ cungqercecumauq akuliik una tamakucineng pimaluni.
And this part had those between it where a person would be.
Uatii cali tamakucineng pimaluni cungqercecumaluni.
And toward the door from there, it had those where a person would be.
Tau͡ga ataucimeng-ll’ cungqerpegnateng enet tamakut pituluteng.
Those houses wouldn’t have just one person.
Wanigga taigurallemni ukani taukut civunerkiutulit teggenrurtellriit makut
As I was coming, those who elders who would speak of the future
Taukuk cali nallunarikagneng cimiryuumarkaulriarulutek
If they become unnoticable, they can be changed
Makuneng tan’gurrarneng civunerkiuritulit.
The ones who speak of the future for these boys.
Makut tau͡gken kevgaraat arnat enaitni, enmeggni amani
These women who would serve [their elders], however, in their houses over there
Marrlugaita tau͡gaam caliaqluki.
Their grandmothers instead worked on them.
Cali taukugtun tau͡ga-i qaneryaraatun atauciuguq wii cumigartaqama.
It’s one with the [men’s] traditional wisdom when I look closely.
Una-wa maurluqenricaaqeka-llu, anaanaka una taukuneng al’qamneng qanerturaqeraqan
She’s not actually my grandmother, but when my maternal aunt spoke to my older sisters
Ayuqsarpenaqapiarluku iluarullutek tau͡ga qaneryaraak tamana ayuqelliniuq.
Their traditional wisdom is exacly the same and compliment each other.
Inerquutaat-ll’ atauciuluni, alarquuteklengnaaraat cali atauciuluni.
And their admonishments are one, and their instructions are also one.
Cameng alangaarnarqelriameng qaneryarameng niitnarqevkenateng.
We do not hear any surprising traditional wisdom from them.
Tau͡gamtellu maa-i makuneng qantuut taukut, qantuut tamakut teggenrurtellriit
Then now, they say, those elders say
Wangkuta-gguq Cup’igni Kass’aneng caneng imkuneng avungeciqukut.
They said that we Cuppot will get Westerners, other kinds [of people] among us.
Avungluta wangkucicetun ayuqenrilngurneng, wangkucicetun cuucingqenrilngurneng.
They said that there will be among us people different from us, people with different lives from us.
Cunagg’ makut Kass’at.
It turned out to be these Caucasians.
Tau͡ga-ll’ imkut Kass’am pekqaluteng pitullratni unani wangkutni yaaken Carvanertuliarmeng kingunerluteng Kuigpagmi
Then back when those Caucasians traveled among us who where from over in Carvanertuliar on the Yukon
Tamakut qantulliniut, "Maa-i-gguq makut amllericiqut, amlleriinarciqut."
They would say, "There will be more of these people, more and more."
Kiitau͡gani-gguq wangkuta imutun Cup’igni tamani uitalriatun ellirtukut tamakut amllenrureskata.
They said that we Cupiit would eventually be among different kinds if there are more of them [than us].
Arenqiallugun cali tamakut amllenrureskata
Also misfortune if there are more of them [than us]
Arenqiallugutellernaq man’a ellaitni pisqumatkenrilnguq anlirluni amlleriluni
What would cause us misfortune that they would not want upon us gets bigger and increases
Qaillun wangkuta Cup’igni piyungramteki pisciigaliciqaput.
No matter what we Cupiit want to do to them, we will be unable to [deal with] them.
Tau͡gaam wanigga assinguaraqua waten wanigg’ qaneryaurcama, qanerteńgurrlua qaneryaurcama.
But I am pretending to be good now as I started speaking, since I have started speaking as a teacher.
Pingraitkut tamakut acivanritengnaqluta. Wangkuta tamakut inglulingnaqluki pinertutacirramcetun piniaraput wangkuta.
No matter what they do to us, let us not lower ourselves. Let us try to work with them as much as we can.
Ellaita man’a nunavut pikenritaat.
They do not own our land.
Cali tamaani waten una Alaska-q una naken-lli pingraata, yaaqvaneng pingraata
And here in Alaska, not matter where they’re from, even if they come from far away
Tau͡ga elluarrluki ikayungnaqaqait taukut nunat pikngamegteggu man’a tamalkuan ayuqluteng.
They are trying to help those lands well because all of this belongs to each of them the same way.
Tau͡gaten tau͡gaam pinritniartukut wangkuta una nunavut pingraatgu.
However, let us not do that though they do that to our land here.
Ikayuulluta Cup’igglugarni wangkuta piniartukut.
Let us Cupiit help each other.
Ukegkut-llu tau͡ga cingumayaaqekenka kinguverkanka wii tau͡gaten tau͡ga pingraata tamakut akimatesqelluki.
I also encourage my descendants to come that even if they do that to respond to them.
Waten nayurrlainarngailamki cali qaneryarameng tamakut tan’gurraat ayagyugaanka ikani Cev’ami.
Since I will not always be with those boys, my young people, over in Chevak, I [tell them] my traditional wisdom.
School-arvia tumekluku waten qaneryaramkun piuratulqanka akaurtuq
It’s been a long time since I’ve passed on my traditional wisdom through their school
Akaurtuq BIA-m, BIA-m aulukellraniu school-arvigput. Civuqlikacagauluta wangkuta tegulqerput Chevak-armiuni school-arvigput.
It’s been a long time since the BIA took care of our school. We from Chevak were the very first to take our school.
Tau͡ga-i-ll’ tegukevut qaillukuange’rmegteggu-llu qaillukuarciiganaku.
Then we took it, and no matter what they tried to do to it, they couldn’t do anything.
Maa-i cali taukut ilallrenka imkut nallunarillret, icivaq-am caumatqallemni meeting-alrianun tamakunun Kass’anek inglulirluteng, school-arteńek inglulirluteng
And my former peers who are not known know, when I was recently in a meeting along with Caucasians, along with the school officials
Tauna kayukluki wii piamki tamakut, tayima [?] makunek [?ingllilrungraata] kayukluki wii keyirma.
Since those were my source of strength, though they [?] these, I was the only one who had them as my source of strength.
Tau͡gaam tutgarameng imumeng [?] elicarangqertua.
But I have taught one of my grandchildren.
Qanelqa tamana aturluku piuratuuq. Assirtuq.
He does the things I say. He’s good.
Waten tau͡ga piuralleq man’a, eglertengnaquralleq
Doing this, trying to keep going
Ilani makut imkurluteng pingraata eglertengnaquralleq cali ayagyugaulriani
Trying to keep going no matter what those around them do, to those who are young
He is called, they call him this: he is a good person, he is good.
Cameng ata aturyugciq...
What will [?] want to use...