...piqatallratnek.
...what they were going to do.
Piaqlua-llu, "Ila-i, TV-ni-wa wii pugngailngua."
And I’d say, "Oh no, I won’t appear on TV."
Cunawa-m’ makut tangerrluki ernemteńi arenqiatuq tua-i.
It turned out that looking at these [people] in our day, it’s distressing.
Qaneqsaunata uitakumta, we won’t done anything.
If we stay without saying anything, we won’t [accomplish] anything.
Apcugciqamken. Apciiqamken wall’u ayainantemteńi qanrutniaramken.
I will want to ask you questions. I will ask you, or as we go, I’ll tell you.
Waten maa-i qanelriaten ak’a avani cainata (Ii-i, ii-i.) cainata [?]. (Arrsauluta.)
You said that a long time ago, we didn’t have any [Western] things (Yes, yes.) didn’t have anything [?]. (We were destitute.)
Qaillun ilakutelput iciw’ ilakutellriani
How is our relations, you know, we who are related to each other
Tamatum Kassaurtessiyaallemta una ilakutelput agtuumaa? Tamakut wani...
How is has us being too Westernized affected our relations? Those...
Are we rolling? (Yaa.) Okay.
Are we rolling? (Yes.) Okay.
Qaillun atak’ apqerlaku?
Let’s see, how shall I say it?
Tua-i-wa murilkellerpeni ilakutelput-qaa, ilat wani family-t ukut ilakutellrat
In your observation, are our relations, how these families interact with [cultural] relations
Asiinaku agtuumaat tukuurtessiyaallrata, wall’u-qaa qaillun?
Is their abundance of wealth negatively affecting it, or how?
Kiingan tua-i murilkellerpenek. Umyuaqeksailkuvgu-llu qanrutkenrilngerpegu canrituq.
Just your observation. And if you haven’t thought about it, it’s okay if you don’t speak on it.
Ayuquciipakar.
I have no idea.
What was I saying again?
Oh yaa, cali tua-i callugtellerkamek enemi...
Oh yes, also [?to diligentely do things] in the house...
(Paniit uitaviit.) Oh, paniit. (Yaa.)
(Daughter’s places.) Oh, daughters. (Yes.)
Yaa, tua-i-llu waten-am qantullruata au͡gkut wani eneqeraqluki piunga:
Yes, then because those people back then used to say this, I remember:
Arnat-gguq irniamta wangkuta aanaulriani cauralput ayuqeliyugngaa.
Our female children can copy what we mothers work on.
Piciuguq.
It’s true.
Mingquratukuma panima ayuqeliyugngaat mingqaqluteng-llu.
If I keep sewing, my daughters can copy it, and sew.
Tau͡gaam-wa mat’um nalliini elitnauq man’a cavagta.
But these days, this schooling is such a conundrum.
Tua-i nanrarngaitanka irnianka. Cuqkuuryugngaanka cuqyutekluki.
I will not praise my children. I can use them as examples.
Ataucimek-llu maa-i irniangqertua college-aalalriamek. Allrakut-am tua-i maa-i amllerilriit.
I also have one child now who goes to college. It’s been many years now.
Apqiitnek drop out-araqluni.
[S]he would drop out, as they call it.
Tang makut-wa qaill’ piat?
Look at these, what’s going on with them?
Makumek-llu tang caliyaramek maani yuuluni nalluluni.
And, you see, [s]he’s living without knowing how to work.
Caliyuyuunani-ll’, naaqiq tau͡gaam.
And [s]he never wants to work, only read.
Tua-llu cali cuqku’urluku, cuqyutkaqluki-w’ canrilnguq.
Then also as an example, it’s okay to use them as examples.
Atauciq irniaqa elitnaunermek qessayulallruuq.
One of my children would be disinclined to go to school.
Cayunqepiaq. Caliyunqeggluni boy-aq, outside work.
He loved being active. The boy liked to work, outside work.
Nallunritaqa cikuciyunqektallrulria mikluni.
I know that he liked to pack ice when he was small.
Mer’icecuunii. Qessaitpiaq.
He never let me go without water. He was never lazy.
Wiinga-w’ pisqurqeka iciw’ kiingan pistek’lallruamku.
I would keep telling him to, you know, because he was my only provider.
Mat’um nalliini tangrraqa caliyaramek qagaani-llu nallunritqapiarluni tauna.
I see him these days, knowing really well how to work, outside too.
Ayagmek, angutngurrluni utaqaurpek’nani ayagmek tau͡gaam piuralria apqiitnek Kass’at train-arciqliniuq ellminek.
From the start, without waiting to become a man, but one who keeps doing it from the start will train himself as they say in English.
Taukun cali tua-i cuqyuteksugngaaqa yumkun ataucikun.
I can also make an example of that with one of my children.
Mat’um nalliini youngest, irniarugama youngest.
Now, he’s the youngest, the youngest out of my many children.
Cacetuqutek’la’rqa ellami caarkanek.
I depend on him to do outside chores.
Calinaurtuq tuar taqneq, nallunritqapiarluni.
He would work like an adult, knowing really well.
Tua-i tua-i.
There you have it.
Qanengssakanka makut cuqyutekluki.
I’m telling these stories as examples.
Iimteggun tangllemteggun canek elicugngaukut.
We can learn things through what we see through our eyes.
Iciw’ tua-i wiinga aanaka clean up-aatullrunrituq, mingqurluni tau͡gaam.
You know, my mother never used to clean up, only sew.
Clean up-aararkaitalna-wa enemta ilua.
It was because there was nothing to clean up in our house.
Tau͡gaam tua-i-w’ ava-i qanertua Cakayiinkugni Kassaungamek-wa tua-i [?cangaktullrulli?]
But I just said that at Cakayak and his spouse’s, since they were Caucasian, [?they’d find things amiss?].
Maanicetun tau͡gaam ayuqevkenateng. Phone-artaunani.
But it was like it is here. There were no phones.
TV-ngqellruut-qaa?
Did they have TV’s?
Taukugnek qaneryugngaunga taukugnek tamakunek elitellemnek.
I speak of those, what I learned of those from them.
Elitnaullemni tuar tang camek elitellrunrilngua. Ikgetellruami-w’ elitnaulqa, carraussiyaallruami.
When I went to school, it seemed that I didn’t learn anything. It was because my schooling was too little, too scant.
Egmian wani elitnauryuglua nangteq’nge’rma allrakunka, ikgelengraata-ll’ uingetullruameng imkut.
Even though I suffered wanting to go to school right away, my age, since they used to get husbands young back then.
Wiinga-am uingevkaqiitnga, ikgenateng-ll’ allrakunka.
They had me take a husband, and I was young.
Maani-llu marriage license-aamek piqatallmegni
And when we were going to get a marriage license here
Tauna-am commissioner-aamek aterluni marriage license-aanek cikiqengtuli.
That one who issued marriage licenses was called a commissioner.
Maa-i-am iliini pilartua, "Tauna-llam carpakayak iqlullinill’."
Sometimes now, I say, "That darned official lied."
Sixteen-aallruunga. Sixteen-aallruyugnarqua.
I was 16. I think I was 16.
Marriage license-aaq-am taitesciigatnirraarluku, igarraarluku taitaa.
After he said he couldn’t give us the marriage license, he wrote on it and brought it.
Wiinga 18-aaruartellua marriage license-aaq wangkugnun tunlliniluku.
He falsely stated that I was 18 and gave us the marriage license.
Allrakunka ilaluki.
He added to my age.
Maa-i tuaggun ayagtua allrakunka, allrakuma ilamallrakun.
Now, I go by that, how my age was increased.
Taumi younger-aanruyaaqua nallunailngurmek.
I’m certainly younger than that.
Tau͡gaam marriage license iciw’ prove-aqsugngalliniamegteggu tamakutgun kalikatgun kitugtellruit aipaqa yuunrillrani.
But since, you know, they could use marriage licenses as proof, they fixed it with those documents when my spouse passed away.
Tua-i tauna qanrutkela’arqa.
I talk about that.
Ilailallrulliniut-am allrakunek au͡gkut ciuqvani.
Apparently, the people back then would add years in the past.
Mat’um nalliini-wa arnassaurrluni wall’ angukara’urluurrluni nulirtulalria angun.
These days, becoming an old woman, or a man takes a wife as an old man.
Wall’ arnassagaurrluni arnaq uingaqluni mat’um nalliiini.
Or a woman takes a husband as an old woman these days.
Pirkakellruat-qaa tamaani ciuliamta uum irniam wani aipangllerkaa?
Back then, did our ancestors think it was important for a child to get married?
Probably because they thought it important, my parents would have others encourage me [to marry] as well.
Atam, tamaani aipairkiutulliniit aiparkaat una yuvriraqluku ayuqucia, qaillun-llu calitacia.
Look, back then, they would choose their husbands, examining their potential spouse’s behavior, and how much he works.
Iciw’ dumb man-amek pivkenateng.
You know, they wouldn’t choose a dumb man.
Mat’um-wa nalliini acirlaku "tamian."
These days, I should name it "tamian" [dumb man].
Ilii uingelartuq, uinga-ll’ taun’ canermek nalluluni.
Some take husbands, and their husband doesn’t know how to do anything.
Iqlunritua. Iqluunga-qaa?
I’m not lying. Am I lying?
Wall’ angun nulirturaqluni. Tua-i tua-i.
Or a man takes a [kazy] wife. There you have it.
Wiinga wani qanrutkenrilnguarngaitanka makut piciulriit.
I will not keep from talking about these true things.
Wiinga uikarcullrulliniagnga angayuqaagma.
Apparently, my parents sought a husband for me.
Au͡gna-am uikaqa cunaw’ ayagyuaqtarluni caneq elisngaq’apiarluku. Nick, Nick O’Nick.
It turned out that my groom to be was young and was an expert in doing things. Nick, Nick O’Nick.
Aipaqsagutaqa-llu young-apiallrulliniuq.
And when I married him, he was very young.
Marriage license-aamegni allrakurlunuk Nick-aa 22, wiinga-llu 18 married-aallemegni.
On our marriage license, our ages were, Nick 22, and me 18, when we got married.
Waten pilallruanga aanama: qessavkenii-gguq tauna pikilaku. "Castekaqerput."
My mother used to tell me this: I should work with him without being lazy. "He will provide for us."
Taum-gguq uima cascirciqaakut.
She said my husband will provide for us.
Una-wa anngaqa TB-rluni tua-i assiirulluni cayuunani.
My older brother got impaired with TB and couldn’t do anything.
Tua-i taumek-ll’ anngamnek umyuarniulallruama, tua-i tuqukan-llu... tang umyuarteqtullrullinilriakut wangkuta.
And because I would be worried about my older brother, and when he dies... you see, we would ponder.
Allrakunka-am ikgelengraata umyuarteq’lallrullinilrianga.
Though I was young, I’d ponder [upon such things].
Umyuarteqaqlua-ll’ waten: taum-am anngarma nulirran, "Pikina," qarutelaanga.
And I’d think like this: my older brothers wife, "Do it, okay," because she encouraged me.
Tua-i-ll’ umyuarteq’langua waten pingaitniaqlua, kenkiama allamek love-arlua.
Then I started thinking like this, that I wouldn’t, because I loved someone else, being in love.
Tua-i-w’ mat’um nalliini ap[qiitnek] qanrutekciqlikeka allamek loving-aarlua.
As [they] say these days, I’d probably say that I was loving another.
Assiqtarluni tauna alla. Wii tang tua-i kenkaqluku.
That other one was attractive. You see, I loved him.
Una tau͡gken uikaqa meet-aqallrukenaku takaqluku.
Without having met my groom to be, however, I was intimidated by him.
Tua-i-ll’ tuani aanama tang tua-i pilaanga-ll’ uum, "Castekaqerput. Tang castekarput tauna casciigalnguq."
Then because my mother, you see, would say to me, "He will proved for us. Look, our provider there can’t do anything."
Iliini tang...
Sometimes, you see...
Waten-llam pilallrukaitkut: aqumluta-gguq atam umyuartequraqa’aqluta.
They’d also tell us this: we should sit down and ponder for a while.
Wiinga atulallrulliniaqa.
I would do that.
Iliini tang umyuarteqeqcaarnaurtua waten: "Ingna-llam anngaqa tuqukan pisqestek’lalqa umyuarniurciqua."
Sometimes, you see, I’d ponder like this: "If my older brother over there who’d tell me what to do dies, I will regret it."
Iciw’ tua-i umyuarniuryaraq-llu nalluveknaki 16, nasaurlullraulua.
You know, I already know how to worry at 16, as a little girl.
Ceńirtaarteńgulua.
I’d go out to visit a lot.
Tuaten tang umyuarteqnaurtua. Tua-i-ll’ caqerlua angerlua.
You see, I would think like that. Then one day, I agreed.
Aren, maaten tua-i aipaqsagutaqa tang aipaqa takaqluku.
Oh my, when I married him, you see, I was intimidated by my spouse.
Inartaqlua waten aklutuumarma caniani.
I’d go to bed fully clothed like this beside him.
Iciw’ u͡gayarluten maa-i gown-arluteng caluteng inartelallinilriit.
You know, they apparently undress and put on gowns or something to go to bed.
Aklutuumarma wii inarrnaurtua caniani taum aipama.
I’d go to bed fully clothed next to my spouse.
Atang...
You see...
Ilamnun-am uani uanlata, kiani-ll’ taukut uika tua-i kiani, kiugumi village-arrarmi.
To my family downriver since they were downriver, and my husband upriver, upriver in a little village.
Iciw’ piani avtaalriit.
You know, they split inland.
Ilamnun anelrarqama meglartua, iciw’ utercuumiinii.
When I’d go downriver to my family, I’d be reluctant to go back, you know, I wouldn’t want to return.
Aanama pingnauraanga, "Ampi uterten."
My mother would end up saying to me, "Go home already."
Tua-i taqsuq’ngaqama anlua. Umyuaqa-w’ tua-i Kass’at apqiitnek smash.
When I’d get tired, I’d go out. My mindset was, as they say in English, smash[ed].
Itra’urlulalrianga taukunun uimnun.
Pity me, I’d go upriver to my husband’s.
Iteryartuarnaurtua tang nepa’itqapiarluni. Iternaurtua ak’a inartellrullin[ilria]. Takaipaa-ll’ wangni. Takaitellrullinivaa.
I’d start going in, you see, to absolute silence. I’d go in and he’d already be in bed. I was so shameless. I was so shameless.
Tua-i-ll’ tua-i nallunrilamku waniw’ aipaqa inangqiin canianun tua-i aklutuumarma-ll’ inarrlua.
Then since I knew my spouse was lying here, I went to bed fully clothed beside him.
Aren, aipaqsagutellemni-ll’ tua-i aqviitnga itertua tang...
Oh my, when I married him and they got me, I went in, you see...
Mat’um nalliini angun nulirtulartuq camek-llu tauna arnani cikirpek’naku, aipaa.
These days, a man takes a wife and doesn’t give anything to his wife.
Maaten tang itertua, ak’a pitullruyugnarqut.
I went in, you see, I think they used to do it long ago.
Ukuk tang yassigpallraak kalikaak.
You see, there were these two huge cardboard boxes.
Tua-i-ll’ tang au͡g’um nasaurluum taum uima anngaan yua, tuaken tang anciaqluni.
Then,you see, that girl, my husband’s older brother’s child, would take things out from there.
Taum aaniita, "Tang tua-i ingleten." Ingelret tang au͡gkut aklukegtaarait ulikegtaaraat nutararrlainaat.
Their mother [said], "Look, there’s your bed." The bed, you see, was good things, good blankets, all new.
Tua-i beginning-aaqatarlua.
I was going to start the beginning.
Tuaten pitullruut aklirluki.
They used to give them things like that.
Tuaken tang kalikagnek taum nasaurluum cikirtungkilia canek.
You see, that girl would give me things from those cardboard [boxes].
Cikiraanga-llam anciluni atkugmek, fur parka.
She took out and gave me an atkuk, [a] fur parka.
Iciw’ mat’um nalliini fur parka-t expensive.
You know, these days, fur parkas are expensive.
Takarnaqluteng.
They were overwhelming.
Atkugmek-am cikiqilia. Canimnun-llu elliluku tua-i wii quyavkenii.
She gave me a parka. And she put it by me, but I wasn’t thankful.
Iciw’ tua-i uingyuumiicaaqngama.
You know, because I didn’t want to take a husband.
Cali-am pirraarluni anciuq piluguuk, fur mukluks.
After that, she also took out piluguuk, fur mukluks.
Tegulukek canimnun ellilukek.
I took them and put them beside me.
Tang carugaat. Tuaten pilua.
You see, there were many things. [S]he gave them to me like that.
Tua-i.
There you have it.
Tua-i-llu aipaqa tuani ilamini tuaten pillrunrituq.
Then my spouse didn’t do that there in his family’s home.
Uksuarmi tegullruatnga. Up’nerkaquani ilamnun-am meglua.
They took me in the fall. The next spring, I didn’t want to go back with my family.
Tua-i tuaten pilallruunga.
I used to do that.
Megngama-ll’ tua-i taum aiparma upaucugyaaqlua up’nerkillernun. Pingaunii.
And when I didn’t want to go back, my spouse wanted to move with me to a spring camp. I wouldn’t.
Unillua tayim’ ayagluni.
He left me and went.
Tua-i-llu tua-i wii angnirilua ilamni.
Then I got happier with my family.
Tekilluni up’nerkami ukut qanertut, tauna-gguq, taum-gguq uima ullakataraanga move-arluni family-mnun.
When he arrived in the spring, these people said that my husband was going to come to me and move in with my family.
Tua-i tuaten pillrani wiinga iciw’ quyalua.
When he did that, I was, you know, thankful.
Ima tanem aanama pilallrukiinga, "Castekaqerput."
Now again, my mother used to say to me, "He’ll be our provider."
Tua-i-w’ move-arluni tailuni waniw’ aulukqataqiikut.
He was going to come and move to take care of us.
Tuaten tua-i nallunrilama iciw’ tua-i assirluku tang imkunga’arrluku, tunusngaurluku-ll’ uitalallruama.
Since I knew that, you know, I started [treating] him well, also because I used to always have my back turned to him.
Iliini-ll’ tua-i tangerrsaurrluku. Takarnaqpiarluni.
And I started looking at him sometimes. He was very intimidating.
Takaqutetullrulliut. Wiinga-w’ tuaten pillrulrianga.
They may have been reserved around each other. I did that.
Tua-i-llu move-arluni wangkutnun.
Then he moved in with us.
Aren-llam qinganrilngua egmian agturcecuilama tuaten inartelaama ellaka man’a eqluku.
Oh my, I also didn’t get pregnenat right away because I wouldn’t let him touch me, and would go to bed and shut out the world.
Iliini-llu unuakumi aanama pilaraanga waten: "Yagleralanrilu."
And some mornings, my mother would say this to me: "Don’t harshly raise your hand."
Aipaagni tang... iciw’ angutet nallunritut arnat yagiratulliut qaillun.
Probably, you see... you know, men know that women raise their hands a certain way.
Iliini waten tallini taitaqaku wiinga waten assiilkelluku piaqluku.
Sometimes, when he brought his arm like this, I would do this out of dislike.
Aanama, "Piyuitut tuaten." Nalluama-wa.
My mother [said to me], "They don’t do that." It was because I didn’t know.
Rule-angqelliniut cat tamarmeng.
Evidently, everything has rules.
Piyuitut-gguq tuaten.
She said they don’t do that.
Angun-gguq nulirtulartuq naanguarkaminek.
She said a man takes a wife to fool around with her.
Tua-i alingallagnaurtua.
I would get scared.
Tua-i-ll’ tang qingarlua Robert Nick, yuukamek pia-i.
Then, you see, I was pregnant with Robert Nick, my child to be inland.
Qinganglua. Qingangellemni tang nutaan uika tauna cauluku-ll’ caumayaurtellrukeka.
I got pregnant. When I got pregnant, you see, I finally started facing my husband face to face.
Aspiallinivaa-ll’ Nick-ami.
Nick is so wonderful.
Tua-i-llam tuaten qinganglua nutaan murilkessaurtellruaqa Bible-aanek, Bible.
Then when I got pregnant like that, I finally observed him [with] a Bible.
Una tang tauna uika calilgupiaq.
You see, my husband was always busy.
Tua-i cunaw’ hard worker-aarulliniami angayuqaagma cucukellrak.
It turned out that it was because my parents’ choice was a hard worker.
Bible-aaliurturyaur[tuq]. Bible-aanek-am naaqiurnaurtuq every evening.
[He] started always reading the Bible. He would always read the Bible every evening.
Malruurtuk-ll’ irniapuk, Robert, Margaret, piyugnarquq.
Then we had two children, Robert, Margaret, I think.
Pastor-aarurrluni young.
He became a pastor [at a] young [age].
Aspialliniuq. Qaneryugngaunga assillranek.
He turned out to be wonderful. I can say how good he was.
Aquiyuunani. Aquilallruukut.
He wouldn’t play out. We used to play out.
Maa-i aquivigtangqertuq like Teen Center, allat-llu.
Now, there are places to play like [the] Teen Center, and others.
Aquilallemni-ll’ tauna uikaqa tangerqayuunaku.
And when I’d go play, I’d never see my groom to be.
Tuaten tang ayagmek ayuqellinian angayuqaagma pikesqellrullinikiik.
You see, since he was like that from the beginning, my parents wanted me to have him.
Bible-aaliurturyaurrluni-am tua-i. Ak’anivkenaku-ll’ pastor-aarurrluni. Young-arluni pastor-aarurtellruuq Nunapicuarmi.
He started always reading the Bible. And not long after, he became a pastor. He became a pastor at a young age in Nunapitchuk.
Ava-i-ll’ tua-i pastor-aaruinanermini tuquluni.
And recently, he died while he was a pastor.
Nine, nine-aanek-ll’ irnianglunuk.
And he had nine children.
Angli-ll’ tang tuaten piyullrullinivaa.
Wow, you see, he had such passion for that.
Pastor-aarinanermini-ll’ ping’umek kipusviggarmek pililuni.
And while he was a pastor, me made that little trading post inland.
Pilivailegmi ciumek agayulirtet, Moravian-aat agayulirtait ullagnillrui, Kuigglugmi-llu-gguq cali agayulirta ullagluku.
Before makiung it, he said he first went to the priests, the Moravian priests, and he said he also went to the priest in Kwethluk.
Nallunritqapiaq elitna’ungssagaunani-ll’.
He was very knowledgeable, and he had absolutely no schooling.
Apqaullinii-am tamakut pastor-aarinenermini kipusvik inglukluku calillerkaminek.
Apparently, he asked them about working along with the trading post while he was a pastor.
Tamakut-llu tua-i okay-lliniluku.
And they gave him the okay.
Tamakunun tau͡gaam ellangcarraarluni pia-i pingna piliaruuq, Nick O’Nick Trading Post, agayulirteńun makunun elisngalrianun.
That [place] inland was made only after being advised by those, Nick O’Nick Trading Post, these knowledgeable priests.
Tua-i tuaten ayuqlunuk.
That’s what we were like.
Tua-i-ll’ ava-i tuaten irniapuk anglicarluki.
Then we raised our children like that.
Taangaq-ll’ ataucirquungraan waten piksaunaku.
And he never did this even once with alcohol.
Akmavet ayalallruukuk qavcirqunek kipusvingumariluku.
We went [to the city] over there several times after he’d gotten his trading post.
Elitna’ungssagaileng’e’rmi ilii smart-apialliniuq, elisngaq’apiarararkauluni.
Though some have absolutely no schooling, they are very smart, will be very knowledgeable.
Waniw’ wiinga nanrarpek’naku cuqyutkuurluku qalartua.
Now, I am not praising him, but speaking with him as an example.
Akmavet ayalallmegni Kass’at mat’um nalliini yugnikutek’lalliniat taangarraq.
When we’d go over there, Caucasians these days apparently use a little alcohol to make friends.
Tua-i una-ll’ itran, "You want drink?"
Then when this person comes in, "You want [a] drink?"
Akmani business-aalegni calillgutaini tarritelallruukuk.
Over there, we’d walk among his fellow workers with businesses.
Tua-i-ll’ igvaamnuk tua-i arenqiaqaarluni, "Nick, you want drink?" pilallruat.
Then when we appeared, after he was struggling, "Nick you want [a] drink?" they’d say to him.
"No." No-raqan atam sorry-lalriit imkut elisngapiat.
"No." When he said "no," those very knowledgeable people would say "sorry."
"I’m sorry, Nick."
Pirraarluku kinguneq taqluku, "Nick, you’re lucky."
Then after saying that, they’d end with: "Nick, you’re lucky."
Tuaten-llu piaqluku.
And they’d say that to him.
Qalarutkanka makut qanenrilnguarngailama assilriaruat
I’m speaking of these because I will not hold back speaking of them since they’re good.
Tua-i tuaten ayaglunuk.
That’s how we went [through life].
Au͡gna-am kipusvingellra kiturlaku. Canrituq. Qaillun, iliini qanrutkeciqaqa qaillun.
His tradin gpost, let me skip it. It’s okay. Somehow, I’ll speak about it sometime somehow.
Caliyuitellruuq Nick-aq. Nani-llu work-aqayuunani.
Nick never used to work. And he didn’t work anywhere.
Fur hunter-aarulliniluni tua-i, fur hunter.
He was a fur hunter, [a] fur hunter.
Melqulegcurteńguluni.
He was a fur hunter.
Tua-i-llu pia-i trading post-ani tamakukun ayagnillrua.
Then, he stated his trading post inland with that.
Qanellrulartuq waten, nalluyagucuitanka ilait qanellri wangnun:
He used to say this, I never forget some of what he said to me:
Taum-gguq nalliini melqulegtani tunellrui maani, fur buyer-aanun-wa pillikai.
He said that at that time, he sold his fur here, probably to fur buyers.
Seven hundred-llu-gguq akingluni, akingluteng.
He said he got $700 for them.
Tua-i-ll’ tauna aturluku carrarnek tekiulluni.
Then using that, he arrived with little things.
Tamana call’ kiturlaku?
Can I skip that too?
Tau͡gaam makut irniaput angayuqrit teacher-aarulliniut.
But our children’s parents were apparently teachers.
Arnam panian, ayuqsugngaa panian arnaq.
A woman’s daughter, a woman’s daughter can be like her.
Angun-llu cali qetunraan tangvaurluku callra ayuqsugngaa.
And a man’s son can watch him and do what he does.
Ukut waniwa angutet yum’a atateng ayuqenritaat.
My male children here are not like their father.
Iqlunritua. Qanrutkaqa iqluvkenii.
I’m not lying. I’m speaking of it without lying.
Ping’um tau͡gaam pia-i anngamta alerquutni-w’ tua-i atuamiu pia-i piqacaarqii pingna, pilallikii.
But our eldest brother over there, because he adheres to his traditional instructions, is working at [the trading post] inland, probably.
Qaillun nalluaqa ayuqucia.
I don’t know what he’s like.
Tau͡gaam assikpiaraqa wii tauna anngarput. Aspiartuq atam.
But I really like our older brother. He’s wonderful, you see.
Care-araakut atam.
He cares for us, you see.
Brothers and sisters-aani-ll’ care-apiarluki.
And he takes great care of his brothers and sisters.
Nanrarpek’naku qanrutkaqa family-t qaillun raise-allrat ayuqenritellra irniat-llu pitekluku.
Without praising him, I’m speaking of him to show how families are raised differently, and children.
Tua-i man’a arcaqerluku enemek clean up-aarillerkaq tua-i tang umyuamni uitapialallrulria uumirpak waten piqataama.
This cleaning up the home was especially prevalent in my mind lately as I was going to [be interviewed] like this.
Tamana-llu erurarkat kenilriit arnam, nasaurluum aanani...
And those dishes and what to cook, a woman, a girl, [?] her mother...