There were teachers and preachers, and tua-i yugyagluteng. Yugyagluteng. Kipusviliurtet-llu amllellruut.
There were teachers and preachers, and a lot of people. There were a lot of people. There were also a lot of storekeepers.
Kass’alillruuq.
There were a lot of Caucasians.
Yugnek tua-i yungqeng’e’rmi yugyagluni.
Though it was populated by Yupiit, there were a lot of people.
What’s going on?
Buzzing paper from the wind.
Okay, anytime.
Okay.
Ak’a imumi wani maavet nugtarteqarraallerpeni Mamterillermun qaillun murilkellrusiu? Man’a wani nuna qaillun ayuqellrua?
Long ago when you first moved here to Bethel, what did you observe? What was this land like?
Taiqarraallemteńi wiinga ketvut un’a kuigullruuq.
When we first came, the area toward the water down there was a river.
Ketvut-llu man’a bank-aq assirlun’ tua-i, willows-arluni-llu.
And toward the water from us, the bank here was good, and had willows.
Under the bank naanguarnaurtukut.
We would play under the bank.
Alingtallruama wii yaaqvanun ayagayuitellruunga.
Because I was cowardly, I wouldn’t go far.
Tua-i assirluni nuna tua-i yugyagpek’nateng.
The land was good, and there were not a lot of people.
Yugpalluuluteng-qaa?
Were they mostly Yup’ik?
Yugpalluuluteng Kass’anek tua-i ilaluteng. Kass’at tua-i amllerrluteng.
They were mostly Yup’ik with Caucasians among them. There were a lot of Caucasians.
Elitnaursitet, agayulirtet, kipusviliurtet-llu, makut-llu miners from mining camps and fishing.
Teachers, priests, and storekeeps, and these miners from mining camps and fishing.
Tamaani-qaa maani Mamterillermi makunek mud house?
Back then, [were there] these mud houses here in Bethel?
Mud house-amek qasgitangqellruuq, qasgimek mud house.
There was a mud community house, a mud community house.
Angluni qasgirpall’er.
The huge community house was big.
Elpenek-qaa enenek uitangenratgun...
From you, right when they started living in houses...
Enenek eneluteng, log houses.
They had houses, log houses.
Ukut-llu mission-aat kiimeng lumber-aanek eneluteng, ilait-llu cali makut yuut tua-i lumber-aanek eneluteng.
And these missions were the only ones with lumber houses, and some of these people also had lumber houses.
Tau͡gken tua-i makut ilait cali log houses. Amllerrluteng.
However, some of them also had log houses. There were a lot.
Mud house-amek tanger[pek’nii], tauna tau͡gaam qasgiq.
[I didn’t] see a mud house, except for that community house.
Yuungnaqengllerpeni tayima tamaani nerangnaqsaraq pingllerpegu
When you made your own living back then, starting to subsist
Tamatumek wani qanrutqerkut qaillun iciw’ uitayulriit uitanrilnguut-llu enuqlilluteng (Ii-i.) enuqlitevkenateng-llu.
Tell us about that, you know, how sedentary people and and active people don’t have enough (Yes.) and don’t lack things.
Tua-i-wa imumi ellangellemni wii yuut neqa cumigutellrukiit.
In my earlies memories long ago, people focused on food.
Tua-i neqsurnaurtut cumiggluteng.
They’d persistently fish.
Cat-llu meluit-llu kinercirluki, qamiqurrit-llu makut kinercirluki
And they’d dry their roe, and dry their heads.
Kuvyangqessuilameng taktuarpagnek maa-i mat’um nalliinitun.
Because they didn’t have extremely long drift nets like today.
Kuvyait nanilameng, cav’urluteng-llu pilaameng.
Because their drift nets were short, and they’d always row [when traveling].
Wiinga-w’ tua-i anaggluni yuulriamek tangellrunrilngua.
I didn’t see anyone surpassing that life.
Tua-i cavluteng kuvyaaqluteng, angyait-llu angevkenateng cav’ssuutnguameng.
They would row to go drift net, and their boats weren’t big because they were meant for rowing.
Kuvyait-llu takevkenateng.
And their nets weren’t long.
Tua-i neqet qellekluki pinaurait cakneq.
They would make great effort to conserve fish.
Qusuurnek ayagluteng qusuurnek qaluluteng nuvluki iniluki puyurluki-ll’.
Starting from rainbow smelt, they use dipnets for rainbow smelt, thread them through [grass ropes], hang them, and smoke them.
Qimugtet neqekluki ellaita-ll’ wangkuta-ll’ ner’aqluki.
They were food for dogs, and they’d, we’d eat them too.
Cat tua-i piqcaarturluki.
They steadily worked on things.
Maa-i imumi-llu neqa wani imumi-qaa neqa sagtelallruuq wall’u-qaa qaillun?
Now, and in the past, was fish strewn about in the past or what?
Wani sagtelallrat neqem sagtengellra qaillun enurnariuq-qaa qaillun? Tamatumek cali.
How they’re strew about, with fish getting strewn about, is it somehow getting harder to find? [Please talk about] that too.
Sagciyuitellruut neqnek murilkeqarraallemni.
They didn’t make a mess fish when I first became observant.
Cakneq kencikluki auluk’lallruit.
They cared for them with great reverence.
Tua-i sagtevkenaki tutmayuunaki-llu neqallret.
They wouldn’t scatter or tread upon food scraps.
Inerquutekluku.
They admonished against that.
Tutmaasaqevkenaki cat, yaqulget-llu cat, tua-i piciatun nertukait.
They told them not to tread upong things, and [all] kinds of birds, anything they ate.
Kencikluki cakneq auluktullruit.
They took care of them with great reverence.
Neqet-llu tua-i murilkelluki, puyuqumariata-llu qemaggluki.
And they tended to the fish, and when they’d been smoked, they stored them.
Qemaggluki cailkami uitavkarpek’naki.
They stored them, not left them in random places.
Camek wani kangililallruatgu tamana wani kencikluku neqa pisqelalteng?
What meaning did they give when telling you to revere fish?
Kencikevkenaki-gguq piaqata enurnarituut cat, neqet.
They say that when they don’t revere them, things, fish, get scarce.
Enurnarituniluki.
They said they become scarce.
Tuaten niitetullruunga.
That’s what I used to hear.
Maa-i-qaa murilkellerpeni maa-i ernemteńi wangkuta tayim’ neqallernek tanglalriakut qagaani.
In your observation of our days now, we see food scraps out there.
Tua-i-w’ maa-i qelkenrirluki arenqiatuq [?pili]vkenaki ayuqengameng.
It’s unfortunate that they’re not taking care of them anymore, because they [?don’t make them] anymore.
Kipusvignek akit-llu tekirqellriit pikaunrilata cikiutet amlleriluteng.
From the stores, and since money that is coming aren’t for things, there are now a lot of gifts.
Wangkuta imum’ elliraungramta cikiutmek nallullruukut.
Back then, though we may have been orphans, we didn’t know of gifts.
Cikiutmek aulukestaunata aanamta aulukeqcaarallruakut elliin calillmikun unatmikun.
Without having gifts to take care of us, our mother steadily worked to take care of us through her work with her hands.
Elliraat-mi, elliraat canek alerqualallruitki?
So, what would they instruct to the orphans?
Tua-i-wa elliraat, elliraat yuum, yuut takumcuktullrukait.
Orphans, a person, people would take pity on orphans.
Tangrrinarpek’naki ikayualuki, tungelqurrita-ll’ ikayualuki.
Without looking and ignoring, they helped them, and their families helped them.
Tuaten ayuqellruut.
That’s what they were like.
Maa-i tua-i yuk cayaaqeciquq neqkaunani, nalluciqaat yuut. Naklekngaitaat.
Now, a person may be in a situation without food, and peopl won’t know them. They won’t pity them.
Eyagyaraq-mi? Eyagyaraq-qaa atulall[ruat]? Murilkellruuten-qaa eyagyaranek piaqata?
What about abstinence practices? Did [they] practice abstinence? Did you observe when they did abstinence?
Yaa. Wii tang eyagyaraq nallukeka.
Yes. You see, I don’t know abstinence practices.
Eyagyarat wii nalluanka.
I don’t know abstinence practices.
Aanaka imna eyagyaranek pissiyaallrunrilan nalluanka wii amlleret.
Since my mother didn’t do much abstinence, I don’t know many of them.
Nalluamki-llu piyuilengraan tuaten pillininaurtua.
And because I don’t know them, though it wouldn’t happen, I’d apparently end up doing that.
Piyuicaaqelliningraata kinguakun nallunriraqluku eyagyarat nalluamki.
Though they actually wouldn’t, I’d find out later because I don’t know abstinence practices.
Kitak’ camek imumek elpet arcaqakek’ngarpenek qanruyukarmek qanrutqerkut.
Now, please tell us of something you think is important, a little piece of traditional wisdom.
Tua-i-wa arcaqalriit amllerrsaaqellriit.
Well, there are many important things.
Yuut tau͡gaam maa-i ilakutenrirluteng-llu pillrat wii assikenritla’qka.
But I don’t like how people today are no longer a community.
Wangkuta imum’ ellangellemteńi ilamta-llu tungayamta-llu, naklekulluteng kenkulluteng yuullruut.
Back when we were going up, our families and relaties, they lived with compassion and love for each other.
Tangrrutaqameng-llu tua-i tuar nakmiiqapiar ilakelalriit.
And when they saw each other, it seemed they were the closest of families.
Quyaluteng tangrrutellmeggnek.
They are thankful to see each other.
Pikangqerrucimegcetun-llu cikirrarluki piaqluki.
And they would give to them from what they could.
Maa-i tua-i tuaten ayuqenriqapiartut.
Now, they’re absolutely not like that.
Ilakengrateki tungayukengramteki-ll’ caperrsagulluki.
Though they’re our families and relatives, we hesitate with them.
Tuaten ayuqenrirluteng.
They’re not [loving] like that anymore.
Cali wii assikeksaitela’arqa ilameggnek teglegaluteng canek angengraata, angyanek massiinanek-llu.
I also don’t like when they things from their families though they’re big, boats and motors.
Tamana tua-i umyuama assikeksaitelaraa, akitulaata-llu cat.
In my mind, I don’t like that, also because things are expensive.
Tamakunek teglegiaqata yuut wii umyuarteq’lartua
When people steal those, I think
"Tuquqataqata-llu," wiinga-w’ umyuarteq’laama
"When they’re going to die," because I think
"Wii tua-i tuquqataquma cat assiilngillrenka umyuaqeciqngamki."
"If I’m going to die, I will remember the wrong things I’ve done."
Tuquqatanrilnge’r’ma-w’ tua-i maa-i umyuaqelaamki.
It’s because even if I’m not going to die now, I remember them.
Ilanka-ll’ tuaten pinayukluki umyuarteq’lalrianga.
I think that those around me might do that.
Man’a teglegyaraq ilaminek, cali navguiyugluteng ilameng caitnek.
This stealing from one’s family, they also destroy their families’ things.
Tamana cali wii assikeksaitaqa.
I don’t like that either.
Tuar ilateng cangqerresqumavkenaki assinrituq.
It’s bad that it seems they don’t want the families to have anything.
Wangni-w’ assinrilngat’lall’ tamana.
That doesn’t seem good to me.
Nangnermek wani camek, camek tayim paicicugcit ayagyuanun kingunerpenun?
Lastly, what do want to leave behind with the youth, your descendants?
Camek assilriamek paicicugcikut?
What good thing do you want to leave with us?
Tua-i-wa ayagyuat makut allayuurcameng maa-i nakukucugluteng-llu kenkulluteng yuukuneng assiryartuq.
Becuase these young people have become different and pick on each other, it would be good if they lived treating each other with love.
Alerquutngulria tua-i kenka una angtatailnguq.
This love that has nothing greater is a traditional instruction.
Qaneryarani-ll’ uitalaria kenka una ciuqlikacagauluni angtataunani-llu.
It’s in the Bible that love is the very first and there’s nothing greater than it.
Tamana tua-i wii umyuaqelaryaaqaqa waten ilanka kenkulluki yuusqessaaqluki-ll’ makut ayagyuat arcaqerluki.
I remember that when I want my family to treat each other with love like this, especially the youth.
Eq’ukutevkenaki, assikulluki, kenkulluki.
Do not scorn each other, treat each other well and with love.
Man’a-llu aturyullrat, arca tua-i cassuutngunrituq, cakaniutngunrituq.
And this [alcohol] they want to abuse, do not, it’s not for anything, and doesn’t improve anything.
Atuusqumanricaaqluku picurlagmek iqungqerran.
I don’t want it to be used because it ends in misfortune.
Tua-i camun ayagpek’nani picurlagmuun tau͡gaam.
It doesn’t lead to anywhere but misfortune.
Nunani aturyung’e’rmegteggu atunritaat iquggliqngan.
Though they want to use it in villages, they don’t because it ends badly.
Tamana tua-i wii umyuama ayagyuanun makunun umyuaqelaasqumalaryaaqekeka.
In my mind, I want these young people to remember that.
Wangkuta-llu pillrunrilengramta ayagyuallemteńi, inerciigatellrungramta tua-i.
Even though we didn’t do it in our youth, even if we were mischievous.
Tau͡gaam tua-i cat ilait anagulluk’ atullrunrilemteki, ilamta-llu cait takaqluki yuullruamta.
But, it’s because we didn’t excessively use somethings, and we respected the things of those around us in our lives.
Ii-i, quyana.
Okay, thank you.
Ii-i.
You’re welcome.
Kitak’-wa tua-i.
Okay, goodbye.
Aren, tauna-llam...
Oh my, that too...