Waniw’ uum Junior-aam yui three-aarulriit.
Now, Junior has three children.
Cama-i-aarnga.
Greet me with a handshake.
Ak’anek-lli tangerpaa.
It’s been so long since I’ve seen you.
Iluperatek-kiq tayim’ tangrruaqallerpetegni qavciunguarniartat.
By your estimation, how many great-grandchildren would you have?
Five-aaruciqut waniwa, five. Five-aat [?].
There are five now, five. Five [?].
Qaku ilait wani piniartat?
When will some of them [have children]?
Qavcirluten tuyuurtellrusit, tuyuni kevgiurellren?
How old were you when you became a pastor, serve as a pastor?
Maavet im’ move-aqarraallemteńi caullrua?
When did we first move here again?
Nineteen-sixty-nine maani.
Nineteen-sixty-nine here.
Tuyuurrlua tua-i.
I became a pastor.
Lay pastor-aaruluten im’un, reverend...
As a lay pastor, your, you know, reverend...
Kitak’ Nanvarnarrlagmek murilkellerpeni
Now, with your observation of Nanvarnarrlak
Qaillun taukut Nanvarnarrlagmiut ayuqucillratnek murilkestellren tangerrluku qanemcitqerkut.
Tell us a story about what the people of Nanvarnarrlak was like looking at your guardian.
Arulaiqsaileng’e’rma-qaa? (Ii-i, arulaqsaileng’e’rpet.)
Without stopping? (Yes, without stopping.)
Waniwa-qaa ayagnirlua? (Ii-i.)
Do I start now? (Yes.)
Yaa, quyana. Umyugiuqatalliniunga.
Okay, thank you. So, I’ll do what I want.
Yaa, umyugiuqatartuten.
Yes, you’ll do what you want.
Nanvarnarrlagmi tayima tau͡gaam allrakuq apqerciiganaku ayagyuaqapiarlua tamatum nalliini
In Nanvarnarrlak, but I can’t say what year when I was very young at that time
Elitnauraunrilama-llu tangvagluki tau͡gaam elitellrulrianga
And since I wasn’t a student, I only learned by watching them
Au͡g’umek tuyungellemteńi Neck, Uyaquq.
When we got that pastor, Neck, Uyaquq [in Yup’ik].
Lloyd Nick-auluni.
He was Lloyd Nick.
Nanvarnarrlagmi agayullrani tangvakarraallruaqa enemi.
I first saw him preaching in Nanvarnarrlak in a house.
Kinguakun tau͡gaam qasgimi tangvagaqluku agayuaqan.
But afterwards, I’d watch him preach in the community house.
Yuut quyurrluteng. Kuluk’uunailameng kelegtuuriluteng.
People would gather. Since they had no bell, they’d [personally] invite people.
Piyugngalriit nunanek quyurciaqluteng.
Those who were able would gather people from villages.
Uyaquq-llu igamikun...
And with Uyaquq’s orthography...
Tangerqercecugyaaqvaa-lli.
How I wish I could show you.
Uyaquq igamikun Bible-aanek naaqiaqluni.
Uyaquq would read the Bible in his own orthography.
Wiinga-wa niiteqarraalqa Bible-aamek, ciuqliinani-ll’
That was the first I heard of the Bible, and there was no one before him.
Au͡gkut-llu wiinga anglicartenka maurlurluunka-llu Bible-aarunateng.
And those who raised and my grandmothers had no Bibles.
Bible-aamek-llu naaqilriamek niiteksaunii.
And I hadn’t heard anyone reading the Bible.
Ciungani naaqivkarluku tangerpailemku unugmi elitnauraa tekitelliniluni.
Before I saw him reading, his pupil arrived at night.
Maurlurluma-am ukatmun ella maliggluku uivelaasqelluk’ qanemcikarcurlua-gguq.
My grandmother told me to turn clockwise this way in what she called looking for a story [forecast].
Ella tangelqa qanemciksarturluku, qanemcikarkauluku elliinun.
I would have to go tell her about the weather that I saw.
Naken-llu waniw’ anuqliucia nallusqevkenaku.
And she told me to know where the wind was blowing from.
Maaten waniw’ tua-i cukangnaqlua qanertua
When I was in a hurry, I said
"Anngama ukatmun waten kiarqu’rtua tallirpima tungiinun.
"When I went out, I looked out to the right like this.
"Tua-i-ll’ kuigem tunglirnera tangrraqa pelatekacuartanga’artellinilria unugmi.
"Then when I looked toward the river, and there was a small tent at night.
"Malrugnek tevvnerluni."
"It had two drapes."
Wiinga-ll’ tua-i kamilangqiima niugtenritua tayim’ atrallemni pelatekacuaraam amiiga tangerrsarturluku.
Then since I was barefoot, I didn’t make a sound as I went down to see the small tent’s entrance.
Igvaryaaqaqa kipullgusngaluni waten patumaluni.
When it came into my view, it was closed, the flaps crossing like this.
Tua-i-ll’ tangvakanemkun ciuqerranun nangerrlua yaaqvaariluku.
Then right when I saw it, I stood in front of it from a distance.
Uitaqanemkun qamna waten ayagnirtuq, nutaan-llu wii Bible-aamek niillua:
When I stood still, the person inside started like this, and it was the first time I heard the Bible:
"Ataneq qigcikellra elisngamun ayagniutnguarkauguq.
"Respect for the Lord will be the beginning of knowledge.
"Tau͡gaam ellakenrilnguut cakenritaat elisnganeq ayuqucirtuun-llu.
"But those without sense do not care for knowledge and teaching.
"Yum’a, niiskiu atavet ayuqucirtuutii
"My child, obey your father’s instruction
"Aanavet-llu picirkiutii unicaqunaku
"And do not leave your mother’s command
"Alngauciqngameng qamiqurpenun ilukegcinarqelriamek, uyamiuciqngameng-llu uyaqerpegun."
"Because they will be writing in your head that will bring you joy, and they will be a necklace around your neck."
Agayulirteńgurteqanemkun nalaqaqa Proverbs chapter 1, verses 7-9.
As soon as I became a priest, I found it in Proverbs chapter 1, verses 7-9.
Tuantellinilria au͡gna niitelqa.
What I’d heard was there.
Tua-i-ll’ taqngan qama-i aqvaqurtua utqerrlua.
Then when he was done in there, I ran right home.
Kamilangqiima niugtenritua. Tang niitenricugnarqaanga-llu taum.
Since I was barefoot, I didn’t make a sound. You see, he probably didn’t hear me.
Enevut-llu tua-i kitu’urrluku tumyaratgun tagqercama ilutuuralriamun tekicama arulairtua.
And when I went inland through the path past our house, I stopped when I reached a deeper area.
"Atak’ imna naspaaqerlaku camani niitelqa."
"Well now, let me try what I heard down there."
Nunapik caugarrluku, qungut-wa pia-i alaunateng, caugarrluku naspaagaqa.
I faced the tundra, while the graves inland were visible, I faced it and tried it.
"Ataneq qigcikellra elisngamun ayagniutnguarkauguq.
"Respect for the Lord will be the beginning of knowledge.
"Tau͡gaam ellakenrilnguut cakenritaat elisnganeq ayuqucirtuun-llu.
"But those without sense do not care for knowledge and teaching.
"Yum’a, niiskiu atavet ayuqucirtuutii
"My child, obey your father’s instruction
"Aanavet-llu picirkiutii unicaqunaku
"And do not leave your mother’s command
"Alngauciqngameng qamiqurpenun ilukegcinarqelriamek, uyamiuciqngameng-llu uyaqerpenun."
"Because they will be writing in your head that will bring you joy, and they will be a necklace around your neck."
Waniwa tua-i Bible-aaq tauna elitellrulliniaqa tuani ellami amiigmi, amiik tangvagluku qamna qalartellria niiqurluku.
I apparently learned the Bible outside by that door, watching that door and listening to the person inside.
Nalluyagutesciigataqa waniw’ unguvallemni maa-i.
I can’t forget it as I’m alive here.
Cali-ll’ nalaqellruamku Proverbs chapter 1, verses 7-9.
Also because I found it in Proverbs chapter 1, verses 7-9.
Tuani cali kalikaunaku elitellruluku nalaqutaqa.
I also learned what I [later] found without paper.
Waniwa ava-i amllerni allrakuni calligtaarlua agayulirteńgurcama pivkaqiitnga.
Now, when I became a priest, they had me move a lot over many years.
Ciungani tuyuulua cali ayagcetaulua pivkarlua.
Before that, they’d also sent me as a pastor.
Au͡gna tau͡gaam ataucirquunrilngurmek qaneryaraqluku pilallruunga eliteqarraarvikellruamku.
But I would use that verse more than once because it was the first one I learned.
Pektesteḿek tangerqarraalqa Akiarmiumek Robert-aaruluni.
The first [?pektesta] I saw was Robert from Akiak.
Yugtun-am atra nalluqaraqa tayima. Nallunritellruyaaqaqa.
I forgot his Yup’ik name. I did know it.
Tekilluni atama kelegniluku Uyaqum eniini uitallrani neryartuusqelluku.
He arrived, saying that my father invited him to eat when he was at Uyaquq’s house.
Puciinaaq, Puciinaaq qanertuq qantuami-llu, elliin-gguq maligciiqaa.
Puciinaaq, Puciinaaq said because [s]he speaks up that [s]he will go with him.
Tua-ll’ atama piyaaqaa, "Tun’ernarqeciquten nerkan. Qassayaarturcetqata’arqa."
Then my father said to him, "You’ll be embarrassing when he eats. I’m going to have him eat frozen aged whitefish."
Tua-i-ll’ Aalaaq tauna ungaulugtuq. Maliguciiquq-gguq. Tangerrsugaa-gguq enevut.
Then Aalaaq shook his head. He said he’ll follow. He said he wants to see our house.
Enepiaruluni nunamek ciuqlirnek enengqellruamta wangkuta, laavkaartaunani.
It was a sod house from the land sicne we had the first houses, with no wooden houses.
Tua-i-llu iterluni aqumluni.
Then he came in and sat down.
Kiatiinun nerellrani qanengssagaluni Yugtun qantuami Puciinaaq.
Then when he ate further in from him, he was speaking because Puciinaaq spoke Yup’ik.
Arturngaunani qanllerkaminek, Yugtun pillerkaminek.
He could manage to speak, speak in Yup’ik.
Tua-i-llu yuurqanermek taqngami Robert-aaq nererraarluni
Then when he was done drinking something ate after Robert ate
Taqngami kalikivini teguluku ikirtaa qanerluni, "Elitnauqataramken."
When he was done, he took and opened his book bag and said, "I’m going to teach you."
Chapter-aara aperturpek’naku Paaskaarcuutet tegumiaqluki ikirtai. Elliin tangvagluki, wii tau͡gken tangvagpek’naku.
Without mentioning the chapter, he held and opened the book used for Easter. He was looking at, but I wasn’t looking at it.
Tua-i-llu qanerluni, waniwa-gguq elitnauqataraanga nalluyagutarkaqenrilkemnek.
Then he said that he’s now going to teach me something that I shouldn’t forget.
Nangertesqellua-llu. Nangerrlua-llu tua-i caugarrluku.
And he told me to stand. So I stood and faced him.
Tan’gaurlullraulua tangelqa nalluyagucuunaku tau͡gaam.
But, I’d never forgotten what I’d seen as a little boy.
Tua-i-ll’ ikna, waniwa-gguq ayagniqatartuq elitnaurlua.
Then across there, he said that he’s now going to begin teaching me.
Chapter-aara verse-aara-llu aperturpek’naku.
He didn’t mention the chapter and verse.
Tua-i-ll’ ayagnirlun’ waten:
Then he started like this:
"Yiissussaaq-llu qayagaluni qanertuq, ’Wangnun ukvelria wangnun pivkenani, ayagtestemnun ukvertuq.
"Jesus proclaimed, "One who believes in me does not believe in me, but to the one who sent me.
"’Wangnek-llu tangellriim aata tangraa.
"’And one who sees me sees the father.
"’Tanqiulua nunamun tekitua wangnun ukvelria tan’geremtesqevkenaku.
"’I came to this land as a light so that one who believes in me will not be in darkness.
"’Qaneryaramnek-llu niitellria ukvekevkenaki-llu, tauna qanercetaartekangqertuq.
"’And one who hears my word and does not believe then, [s]he will be tried.
"’Qaneryaram qanercetaarciqaa ernermi nangneqlirmi.
"’The word will try that person in the last day.
"’Taumek qallataqama tuaten qallatelartua atamnun qanruyucimtun.’"
"’That’s why when I speak, I speak like that as my father told me to.’"
Nangluni-ll’ tua-i waniwa elitnaurutii.
And that was end of his lesson.
Taktaciatun elitellrulliniluku.
I learned all of it.
Kalikaunii agayuyugngarilua.
I became able to preach without a paper.
Yuarutmek-llu eliteqarraartua Uyaqurtarteggun igaumaluteng.
And I first learned a song written in Uyaquq’s orthography.
Waten aperyarangqerrluni, cali elitnaunrilengraatnga elitellruluku niicugniurluku:
These were the words, and without them teaching me, I learned it by listening:
"Quyanaqvaa elpeni, quyalartut pakmani
"We are thankful for you, they are thankful [in Heaven] up there
"Camek artuqailavet, naklegtaavet-llu elpet."
"Because you can manage anything, and because you are compassionate."
Cunaw’ tua-i igat elilluki tuani.
Apparently, I’d learned the writing then.
Naaqiturilua makunek Paaskaarcuutnek.
I started reading this book used for Easter.
Elliin-llu cali Uyaqum igai elilluki, naaqeturiluki tuaten.
I also learned Uyaquq’s orthography, and could even read them.
Cunaw’ agayulirteńgureskuma caliarkanka makut kalikaunii piyugngarilua.
It turned out that when I would become a priest, I could do my work without papers.
Uyaquq-llam igalliniuq ellii urenkutmek qanerluni waten:
Uyaquq wrote an intention saying this:
"Agayun qanellruuq, ’Alarcaqunak. Niicugnikina ciutegken angparrlukek.
"God said, ’Do not falter. Open your ears and listen.
"’Ca tamarmi pakmaken kingunengqertuq.
"’Everything comes from above.
"’Ciiskayuggaunge’rmi-llu nunami pakmaken tuaten taqumauq.
"’Even a tiny insect on the land is created from above.
"’Agayumalria, pegnem qanraqluten, pegnem-llu qenqertaqluten.
"’Oh Christian, be slow to speak, and be slow to anger.
"’Qaneryararkaten pingayurqunek ciumek elpet naspaarraaqiki.
"’First, test what you are going to say three times.
"’Yuum cangayuutekarkaunrilkaki anetniaten.’"
"’If a person will not take offense from them, speak them."
Ukut waniwa kalikaunii.
I [learned] these without paper.
Elitnaullrunricaaqlua tau͡gaam atanrem waten pitalriamek elitevkaraanga kalikaunii.
I wasn’t a student, but the Lord had me learn this much without papers.
Yuarutem au͡g’um makut mumigtallrit Moravian-aat elitevkarai, naaqetuvkarluki tuaten.
He let me learn that song, these [songs] that the Moravians translated, and even let me learn them.
Cali-llam emusngallemni hospital-aami Catholic-aat Bible-aaritnek, Revelation-aaritnek naaqiunga.
Also, when I was getting checked at the hospital, I read the Catholic Bible, their Revelations.
Makutgun qanrutkelallritgun nutaratgun igaumaluteng tamakut.
Those were written in the new orthography that they spoke of.
Cunaw’ tua-i tangrramki maa-i-llu makut kinguqliit mumigcilriit igaqngatki naaqetuluki tuaten.
It turned out that when I saw them, because they were written by the next generation of translators, I would also read them.
Maa-i tuani elitellrulliniluki Revelation-aanek naaqillemni.
I learned [how to read] them when I read Revelations.
Catholic-aartarteggun igaumalriit elilluki. Maa-i-ll’ nutaraurcata alangaarpek’nii naaqetuluki tamakut.
I learned the ones written by the Catholics. And since it’s updated now, I wasn’t shocked, but could read them.
Tuani tua-i elitellrulliniamki.
Because I learned them then.
Man’a cunaw’ caliarkaqa pitekluku atanrem waten makunek pinarqelrianek pillinikiinga.
It turned out that the Lord had me [learn] these things I needed to for my work.
Waniwa ciuqlirteggun au͡gkut ciuqliit cimirpailgatki kalikaqlemteńi
Now, when we had the first books before the changed the first ones
Kalikaunii-llu angllurceciyartua augturceciyarlua-llu tamakut aturluki ciuqliit.
Without any books, I would go baptize and lead communions using those first ones.
Waniwa tua-i piyugngayaaqengramki kinguqlirteggun tau͡gaam maa-i naaqeturiluki.
Though I can recite them now, I started reading from the later ones.
Man’a piuralqa quyatekaqa.
I’m thankful for all I did.
Cali-llu nalluqapiaryalrianga tuntulgurrlua qiayugngalua.
Also, I would know nothing, being able to cry having become a reindeer herder.
Tuntulgurrnilua miluqutamek ac’etaatnga maavet elliluku.
They said I was now a reindeer herder and had me put on a brand here.
Miluqutaq atanerruam ac’ecamiu waten qanertuq:
When the lower authority put the brand on me, he said this:
"Man’a ayallren tamalkuan miluqutaq ayauskiu. Neqnguuq."
"Everywhere you go, take this brand with you. It’s a fish."
Cauga tauna miluqutaq?
What’s a miluqutaq?
Ilavkuk tuntuliurcuun.
A rope for reindeer herding.
Tuntut tegukunegteggu milqerluku maagarkauluku kitumun pikucia nallunrirtelluku.
When they take reindeer, they would brand it with a mark to indicate who it belongs to.
Elitaqillerkarpeciuggun atauciq aperturnaurqa.
So that you will recognize it, let me say one thing.
Moravian-aat maangqellruut tuntum ciutiek kangriqerlukek yaaqvani teriiqan elitaqarkauluku.
The moravians had a mark by removed the tips of reindeer ears so that they would recognize it if it acts strangley from afar.
Wiinga-llu maagmek cali cikirlua elitarkamnek.
They also gave me a mark for me to learn.
Nalluyagucetevkenaku.
They didn’t let me forget it.
Tuamta-llu nuussimek naqugutmek pianga wavet agarrluku.
Then a knife, he gave me a belt and hung it here.
Tamana naqugun amiuguq qillernertarluni.
That belt was made of hide and had straps to tie it with.
Qukaqa-ll’ tua-i cuqluku taum ac’etesteḿa.
Then the one who put it on my measured my waist.
Waniwa-gguq qukama pitacia.
He told me my waist length.
Una-gguq waniwa pirciqan-llu wall’u ellarayauskanga naqugutaq-gguq aturluku tarritarkaugua.
He said that if a blizzard sets or the weather turns bad on me, that I must travel wearing the belt.
Pirciqan-llu maaggun ilumkun pirtuum iterngaunii. Tuaten piarkaulua.
And if there’s a blizzard, the blowing snow wouldn’t go in my [clothes] here. I would have to do that.
Tuamta-llu tamana pegcamiu naqugun, nuussiq wavet ellillerminiu waten qanertuq:
Then when he let go of that belt, he said this when he put the knife here:
"Ayallren tamalkuan ayautelaqiu.
"Take it everywhere you go.
"Nani unilluku ayakuvet, nalluyagulluku ayakuvet
"If you leave it somewhere and go, if you forget it and go
"Imkurciquq, arenqiallugciiquten, curulugkartessuutaunak-llu piarkauluten."
"It will, you know, you will have misfortune, and have nothing to gather grass for matting."
Tua-i-llu ayauqurluki taukut pingayun pik’nganka.
Then I would always bring those three things that I owned.
Taumek maa-i tunciullrunrilkuma Agayutem qusngii auluklemni ayuquciicartua.
That’s why had I not herded reindeer, I would be lost when taking care of God’s sheep.
Tamaani elitellrulliniunga Agayutem qusngiinek aulukillerkamnek.
Back then, I apparently learned how I could take care of God’s sheep.
Atanerruam inerquraanga; nangenruluku waniw’ qanernaurtua
The lower authority admonished; let me say this last thing
Tuntu-gguq akngirrngaitaqa. Yungqertuq-gguq.
He said I shouldn’t hurt the reindeer. He said it has a spirit.
Wall’u nutegluku piarkauvkenaku, wall’u qaill’ piluku akngirrluku piarkauvkenaku.
Or, I should not shoot it, or I should not somehow hurt it.
Yungqertuq-gguq. Yuan-gguq tangvagaanga, tangvagciqaanga.
He said it has a spirit. He said it’s spirit is watching me, will watch me.
Tua-i cunaw’ Agayutem auluklemteńi tamana umyuaqaqa.
It turned out that when we took care of God’s sheep, I remembered that.
Qigcikluki tuaten, piciatun-llu qalarutlerkaat alinguqluku piaqlua
I eve respected them, and feared speaking to them wrong
Yungqelliniata Agayutem qusngii.
Because God’s sheep have spirits.
I think it’s gotten long, so this is all I want to say.
Ii-i, yaa.
Yes, okay.
Amllermi niicugnikuvcia ikayuutnguciquq elpeceńun ayagyuaqapiarlua pillruama.
Many times, if you listen to me, it will be beneficial to you since I did it when I was very young.
Makut nalluyagutevkenaki nalluvkenaki tau͡gaam atullruanka.
I experienced these without forgetting them, but knowing them.
Quyanaqvaa. (Yaa, quyana.)
Thank you very much. (Yes, thank you.)
Au͡gna-qaa tauna Uyaquq niiteqarraallerpegu au͡gkunek Proverbs-aanek qavcirngatellrullinisit tamaani?
Back when you heard Uyaquq reading Proverbs, how old did you seem back then?
Wiinga tuntumun nangertellemni qiallruunga.
When I stood to the reindeer, I cried.