Atam itertuten tua-ll’ aqumluten. Kitak-wa
You came in then sat down. Let’s begin.
Ready?
Tau͡ga-q’ ayaglirlii?
Shall I begin?
Una yuungcautnguuq akaurtellrani yuungcauteput rosewort.
This is medicinal, our medicine from a long time ago rosewort.
Yugtun-llu... caulria im’?
And in Yup’ik... what is it again?
Nalluyagutaqa-am tayima.
I’ve forgotten it.
Maa-i makut yuungcautelput akaurtellrani. Wanigg’ uigtuaqataraqa kepluku.
This was our medicine a long time ago. I’m going to cut and taste it.
Makuksagaat-am nerellrit assiitqapigtut.
It’s terrible eating this little things.
Tua-i-llu wii igyariqellemni tamalkuan nerelqeka, iluka-ll’ assiriluni qama-i.
Then when I had a sore throat, I eat the entire then, then my stomach felt better inside.
Ilukaalriani-llu assirtut.
They’re good for stomach pains too.
Yuungcautelput makut akaurtellrani maa-i.
This was our medicine a long time ago.
Caqlat-gguq maa-i Yugtun, caqlat.
These are called caqlat in Yup’ik, caqlat.
Makut, makut neryuitait, makut tau͡gaam acilquit.
They don’t eat these, except for their roots.
Nallullruyaaqaput. Aanama qanruquratullruanga im’um Ceng’ulriim, my great-grandma, tamakuneng.
We didn’t know about them. My mom always used to tell me, Ceng’ulria, my great-grandma, about those.
Qaillun-llu maa-i-ll’ ayuquciit cimirluteng.
And they’ve somehow changed these days.
Kass’atun pingluteng, akaurtellrani pilteng aturpegnaki.
They’ve started living Western lives, not using what they did long ago.
Maa-i cimirluteng.
They’ve changed now.
Alingcetaarturluta-ll’ maa-i pitullruluta akaurtellrani.
They also used to try to scare us a long time ago.
Angutmun-llu nuliqsuguarluta caciqniluta. Tamakuneng tamaa-i aanama qanrut’tulqaanga.
They said that something would happen when we pretened to be a man’s wife. That’s what my mother used to tell me.
Cunagg’ maa-i ak’allaurcama enqaknauqa imna aanama qanellra.
It turned out as I’ve turned old now, I would remember what my mother said.
Aanaka tua-i qantulliuq terr’a tekilluku, tekitaqamku tau͡g’ enqaknauqa grandma-qa.
My mother would say, when I reached the bottom, when I reach the bottom I would remember my grandma.
Wii grandma-qa aanakpiksukluku pilqaqa.
I thought my grandma was my real mom.
Aquiqcaarraarlua-ll’ qagaani aquirraarlua itraqama qec’irluku emuugkeneng emutulua. Qayutun, 13-aq-ll’ cipesngaluku.
And after I played, when I came in after I played outside, I would embrace her and suckle on her breasts. How old, I was older than 13.
Tua-i tamaani wii piipiqellruamegteńga ingkut aanama.
It was because I was their baby, my mother’s [baby].
Piipiqlua tau͡g keyima arnaulua tau͡g keyirma.
I was the baby, the only girl.
Ilarugapuk tayim’, pingayurrauluta wanigg’ anertequkut.
Our big family, only three of us are now living.
Ukuk malruk angutngulutek, wii-gg’ atauciq.
These two are men, and I’m alone.
Tau͡g keyirma tau͡g ataucirraulua anerteqlua.
I am the only one who’s alive.
Tamakut TB-m tuqutellruluki al’qanka.
TB claimed my older sisters.
Wii tau͡ga aanama tau͡gaam piksuamia caqcaarlua tau͡ga anerteqevkallrullinianga, caqcaqapigglua.
Since my mother wanted me, she did whatever she could to make me live, whatever she could.
Makuneng-ll’ nerevkatulua miktellemni. Neqnialliq’nge’rma ner’tullruluki igluki-llu.
She also had me eat these when I was small. Though I thought they tasted made, I would eat and swallow them.
Akaurtellrani tua-i tamakut.
Those are things from long ago.
Tuamtell’ caqerlua-am qanrutaanga aanama
Then one day, my mother told me
Camineng? "Tutgarrluu." "Ai?"
What did she call me? "Grandchild." "What?"
Pakissaagkuma-gguq, pakissaakuma-gguq utngungssaraat neqaitneng pakissaakuma
She said that if I go search for vole caches, she said that if I search gor mare’s-tail plant tubers in vole caches
Pakikengkuma, pakikengkuma quarruugneng, needlefish
She said that if I uncover quarruuget [sticklebacks], needlefish, in a vole cache
Taukut-gguq ilaiqaqilaki ataucimeng tau͡gaam, just one.
She said I should take only one, just one.
Tuai-ll’ pakissaag[?] pakikengua ik’ikik’ pekluteng.
Then as I searched for vole cahces, I came upon one, so many were moving.
Tua-ll’ umyugartuqaqilii, "Ala, aanama-ggem pakikengkuma quarruugneng ataucirmeng neresqelqaanga."
Then I thought, "Oh my, didn’t my mother tell me that if I find sticklebacks that I should eat one?"
Tau͡ga nerqaqilii ataucirmeng.
Then I ate one.
Ayakataquma tau͡ga cailkamun-llu alarqurnauraanga tau͡gaten.
When I was going to go to the wilderness, she would instruct me like that.
Tuamtell’ caqerlunung, caqerlua aipaqa tauna pakikenguq
Then one day, my companion found a filled vole cache
Ignatius Black-aq-llu friend-aqellruamegnuk miktellmegni.
Because Ignatius Black and I were friends when we were small.
Pakikengami-am qayagpagaanga, "Ala, cat makut?"
When he found a filled vole cache, he called to me, "Oh my, what are these?"
Ala maaten ullagluku piaqa imkut ciissit.
Oh my, I went to him and found those bugs.
Cat imkut ciutmun itetulit meriit.
Those things that go into ears, meriit.
Ala-i tamakut pekluteng. Qaill’-kiq nernaqsartat?
Oh my, they were moving. I wonder how they could be eaten?
[?]anguaryaaqvimineng tau͡ga niiskilaku tauna aipaqa, "Quarruugunritut. Wii nerngaitua tamakuneng."
After he had [?], I heard my companion say, "They’re not sticklebacks. I won’t eat those."
Ayaglunung-llu.
And we traveled on.
Cunagg’ tecamegnung-am aanama taun great-grandma-ma apqangaqekiinga tamakuneng qaillun pillru[cimegnung].
It turned out that when we arrived, my mother, my great-grandma, asked me what we did with those.
"Tua-llu-q’ nerellr[uuten]?" "Nerqallruunga." Quyaklua-llu.
"So, did you eat?" "I ate." And she was thankful that I did.
Ala caullruat? Mayba aanama calqeńgatai. Calqeńgataanga.
Oh my, what were they? Maybe it was my mother’s doing. She seemed to do something to me.
Tau͡ga-q’ taq’uq?
Is it done?
Ala.
Oh my goodness.
Tua-i tamakuneng tau͡ga akaurtellrani pitullruukut.
That’s what we did a long time ago.
Cali imkunun qetunrayagaqa im’ piipiqa, last baby-qa keggluku, anngaan keggluku.
And my baby son, my last baby was bitten, his older brother bit him.
Ukuakun tau͡g keggsaaqluku, ukuakun keggsaaqluku malrugneng.
He bit him here, he bit him here in two spots.
Maaten alaqaqa makucimeng tegulluni
I found him and found that he took this kind of thing
Taukuk qamavet keggutain enait makucineng kevirturaqai.
He stuffed the places where the teeth were with this.
Kevirturluku nemerluku-llu.
He stuffed and bound them.
Maaten unuaquani manii ala mamqertelliuq tayima. Puverpalleq-ll’ imna red-aulleq tayima.
The next day, he showed them, and oh my, it healed. And what was red and swollen was gone.
Tau͡gani clinic-iurtet ellillakelqaat [?].
At that time, the clinic workers [?] him, [?].
Kapurarkauyaaqluni.
He was supposed to get shots.
Ayagyunrilami, atakuani wanigg’ unuaqu ayagciqluni makucineng kevirturallii nallumteńi.
Because he didn’t want to go, he was supposed to go the evening of the next day, he had stuffed them with these without our knowledge.
Tayima-ll’ mamlliniluteng. Caniluku tayim’ makuni piniyuunaku.
And they healed. And they never said that anything was wrong with this part.
Makuneng kevirturluku.
He stuffed it with these.
Alingtartuq atam ing’ piipiqa. Una-llu atam alingtartuq.
You see, my baby is always scared. These one is always scared too, you see.
Una im’um aatama ingna... uima ingna uum atii iluracunga’urluqaa.
My father... his father is my husband’s cross cousin.
Iluraqlutek tau͡ga ak’a, ak’a iluraqumalutek.
They are cousins, they’ve been cousins for a long time.
Tayima’urluq yuunrillruuq qayutun.
He passed away several years ago.
Yuunrallran kinguani wii wanigg’ keyirma ingkut qetunraanka anglicangnaqluki.
After he passed away, I’ve been trying to raise my sons over there by myself.
Qaniutellraneng, qanrtuutiineng qanruqureluki.
I always tell them about his precautions.
Aanama-ll’ qanellra unimyuunaku wii, qaniutellra.
And I never forget what my mother said, her precaution.
Tau͡ga-qaa?
Is that all?
(Yaa.) Quyana.
(Yes.) Thank you.
Okay.
Ii-i, quyana erneqegtaarmeng [?] today.
Okay, thank you for this wonderful day [?] today.
Tau͡ga-llu wii angayuqaagka maligtaqungnaqlukek miktellemni yuullrulrianga.
So, I tried to obey my parents when I was small in my life.
Aatama-llu qaneryaraa umyugamneng tamayuunani au͡gna qanrullua
And my father’s wisdom never leaves my mind, when he used to tell me
Assirpegnii cuukuma, nunanun ayakuma nunakenrilkemnun
If I do not live well, and I go to other villages that are not my own
Atqa niiskunegteggu tau͡gaggun inerciiganii wii callemkun nallungaitniluku.
If they hear my name, they will know that I am mischievous through what I’ve done.
Kaynguyugcetaarlua qanrutellrukiinga. Wanigga-llu umyugaqenriyuunaku tamana wii alerquutekellra.
He told me to try to make me feel ashamed [to be like that]. And now, I never forget his instruction.
Aanama cali ilanka naklekureluki pisqelluki qanrut’tullrulua.
My mother also told me to treat those around me with compassion.
Elpeci angayuqaci ayagyugarni niiyngaarkaugaci.
You young people must obey your parents.
Miktellerpecini-llu qanruyutelci unimeqaqsaunaki.
And never forget the traditional wisdom passed down to you when you were small.
Arcaqerluci enem iluani angayuqaci takaqerkaugaci.
You must especially respect your parents inside the home.
Qancurlagaksaunaci wall’u-qaa cat pileryagaksaunaki.
Do not speak harshly or do not do things harshly.
Angayuqarpeci umyugait pekcetenrilkurrluki.
Try not to upset your parents.
Angayuqaaci angayuqaarulriani iluteqaqut nalluvcini qaillun picurlagaluci piaqavci.
Your parents, those who are parents, are heartbroken without your knowledge when you cause trouble.
Taumeng tau͡ga-i assirluci uitasqumaluci qanruyutengqertua.
That is my piece of traditional wisdom, because I want you to be well.
Tau͡ga-llu ukuk angayuqaagma waten qanrut’tullqaagnenga:
Then, my parents used to tell me this:
Cameng mat’umeng puyumeng-llu wall’u-qaa naryalngunarqelriameng enemni pikuma
If I do something, smoking, or some other thing that smells bad, in my house
Miktellemteńeng ayagluta uqumeng qengaput iluitgun mingutulqai nasqulngunayukluta
Starting from when we were small, they would apply seal oil inside our noses because we might get headaches [from odors]
Tepmun-llu tamatumun assiirutnayukluta.
And because that odor might adversely affect us.
Ayuqluku maa-i kaassat. Puyuunrilnge’rmeng kaassat naryalngunarqelriit.
It’s the same with gas. Even though they’re not smoke, we get tired of smelling gas.
Qengaput mingugarkaugaput iluitgun, cali mikelnguut qengait mingugluki
We must apply [seal oil] inside our noses, and apply it to children’s noses.
Cali-llu cailkamun ayakuvci nangteqkuvci, cuungcautekaituci cailkami uitakuvci arenqiallugeskuvci.
Also, if you go to the wilderness and suffer, you have no medicine if you have an accident in the wilderness.
Uquutengqerquvci cakneq quyerluci, qamna assiilkan igyararci [?kapqelqilluni] uqu’urmeng [?]. Aanama pitulqaakut wangkuta.
If you have seal oil when you have a bad cough, if your throat inside is bad [?with prickling pain], you must [?take] seal oil. My mom used to do that to us.
Cali-llu quyeryuarassiyaakumta meq’ercilluta.
Also, if we had a persistant cough, she would have us drink it.
Aspirin-arkaitellemteńi tau͡gaten miktellemteńi pitulqaakut clinic-angqeyuitellruamta.
When we didn’t have aspirin, she would do that to us when we were small because we had no clinic.
Cali tau͡ga elluarrluta uitallerkarput nallunaituq.
It is also clear how we can live well.
Kitumun ukisqercitaarluta pingramta kia ukisqirciigataakut. Wangkutneng tau͡gaam qaillun elluarrluta cuuyuumaukut.
Though as for help from anyone, no one can help us. We alone can [have ourselves] live well.
Quyana cakneq.
Thank you very much.
Quyana. Aspiartuq au͡gna.
Thank you. What you said is very nice.
Henrietta, John, Carlton, Eddie.
Henrietty, John, Carlton, Eddie.
Seven?
Seven.
Wow, fourteen altogether? Tua-i two adopted?
Wow, fourteen altogether? Then two adopted?
Anerteqluteng seven-aat, right?
Seven are living, right?
Qavciugat-mi tutgaraten?
So, how many grandchildren do you have?
I don’t know. Amllertut tugaraanka qayutun.
I don’t know. I have many grandchildren.
Tua-i-q’ nutaan-qaa?
Ready to start now?
Man’a taangaq elpecinun assinritqapaireyaaquq atungnaqellra.
It is not good for you to use this alcohol.
Tau͡gaam taangaq man’a trouble-aamun tau͡gaam pinaqluni.
But this alcohol only leads to trouble.
Cali yuk taangarpakarluni iqlutmun piarkaqenrilkeńi tekilluku ellmineng picurlatuuq.
Also, when a person abuses alcohol too much, he comes upon something wrong that he’s not supposed to do and brings misfortune upon himself.
Cali man’a meluk aipaa...
And the other one, smoking...
Patuu.
Close it.
Aipaa tamana meluk man’a umyugamun taug͡aam ayatulria, man’a-llu tema tapulluku.
The other one, smoking, goes into this mind along with this body.
Wii atuyuicaaqaqa qaillun ayuqellra.
I don’t do it, [so I don’t know] what it’s like.
Tau͡gaam niitetuama wanigga tamatumeng melugmeng ayuqucianeng, umyugaq tau͡gaam navgutuniluku.
But I hear about what that smoking is like, that it destroys the mind.
Cali qavarturangluni tauna melugpakatuli.
Also, that person who smokes too much starts sleeping a lot.
Tau͡gaten niitetuunga tamatumeng melugaqata.
I hear about that when they smoke.
Iluumuuluni tamana pituyugnarquq, melugpakalria man’a qavarturangluni.
That is probably true, that one who smoke too much starts sleeping a lot.
Cali, you know? They forgot what to do.
Also, you know? They forgot what to do.
Ellirraarluki-llu cat wanirpaagaq nalluyagutaqluki.
And after they put things down, they immediately forget them.
Wii qetunrama iliit tau͡gaten iliit inerqungramteng tamatumeng iliini atuqeryutuata
One of my sons, though I admonish them, since they sometimes do that
Nunutuyaaqanka cakneq wii pirramneng, wangkugtun, wangkugtun... aipaqaqa una.
I do scold them with what I can, like us, like us... this is my spouse.
Patuu. Tailuten.
Close it. Come here.
That’s my husband right here.
[?]qiptaarpiiqnang
Stop [?].
Tau͡ga-qaa?
Ready?
Can I quit?