Watch me… wait.
Watch me as you [speak].
Wait.
It seems a little bright.
Or is it good?
It looks bright.
Have started it yet?
Yes, hold on.
Now, when you start it, ask me how they started getting ready in the fall for what they would need to use.
Will you be sitting like that?
Yes, I will be sitting like this.
Now, how did they get ready for the winter like this?
You mean how people long ago got ready for the fall like this?
Yes.
Our ancestors back then?
And so, I’m not extremely old
But I am now 68 years old.
I am from Tuntutuliak.
I have a Yup’ik name, Ackiar, that they called me.
An then when we became Westernized now, they started calling me Nick Lupie.
And so, you just asked how they got ready in the fall
Or, how they got ready for what they would need to use in the winter.
Now, I’m going to start talking, yes, about things I know and have seen.
Upriver in Kialiq in the fall like this when we were boys
Upriver at the mouth of Kialiq, they say that that creek is called Qukaqlircaraq.
We used to stay there.
Our caretakers here, however, were not sedentary in the fall like this.
Or, they didn’t travel without working like this either.
These things that are used for the fall
When they came from fish camps across there in the fall, they would gather wood.
And they didn’t have boats, only kayaks.
In the morning in the fall like this, because the tide gets very high
They would start traveling in the early morning when it was dark.
Yet sometimes, a kayak would sometimes come into view from Cingik downriver.
It would be pulling [a cargo of] wood.
Those people in the fall like this, when they were going to go to the headwaters of these rivers
They would gather those when they were going to go to winter camps.
Our elders who raised us were not like how we are here.
They would travel rowing with their own arms
Rowing [kayaks] on the water.
And when it was time, they would start going upriver
Bringing those pieces of wood with them.
And they would then load their possessions on top of them.
Those without boats would relocate using wood.
And then when they reached the headwaters of those rivers where they would spend the winter, they would bring up those pieces of wood.
They would then prepare the wood, preparing their fish traps that they used to catch fish.
Those who raised us back then used to struggle.
They used to prepare that wood to make fish traps, big fish traps.
Big fish traps were like this. Their openings.
They were wide, [and] long.
And then they were like this.
They called those their inner compartments [ilulirpiit].
And they would then make fish traps out of the centers too, inflating them like this.
And they would then put the third over there.
They used to call those old fish traps qamut.
This fish traps were not like, you know, blackfish traps.
You know, they were this far apart.
They made them equidistant.
Yes, they didn’t make those big fish traps haphazardly.
They measured these.
And then they put that split spruce there.
And then after doing this over from it
They used to make those big fish traps about this far from each other like this.
When they started working on them like this their hands would become raw.
These parts made like this were not made with twine.
Instead, they thinly split these pieces of wood.
They made them about this wide, but thin.
They wouldn’t work on those haphazardly either.
Their thicknesses had [set] measurements.
When they started doing that, their [hands] here would get raw doing this.
When they started bleeding, they would wrap these three with hide
When these got raw.
And these, these would also get raw where they held them.
Our ancestors back then were not like this as we are.
They had possessions, wooden possessions.
They used wood to make possessions, tools.
They used it for things, houses, possessions for their houses, and sleds.
They survived using this wood for things.
And yet when they started getting set, they would check them every day
And they would wake up early in the morning when the tide goes out after it came in.
They would get up at night, [check on] their fishing tools' stakes, go down, and drive them deeper after picking the ice around them like this.
That is what our caretakers back then were like.
They weren't like how it is now.
And then in the fall when it was time.
Their women would prepare tools that they would use.
The skins of these fish, including king salmon
They called it preparing fish skins for clothes.
They referred to those fish skins as amiriit.
Hold on.
Now, start again.
It’s time to start? Okay.
Those things I just talked about like this
Men’s work, how men worked to prepare their tools.
However, these women would [work] separately.
And before it froze like this, they would prepare tools and skin boots for their men.
And these fish skins like this, king salmon [skins]
They would call it neqairiluteng.
That’s what they would do when they prepared fish skins for clothes.
Also, they wouldn’t just stop at removing the flesh.
When they were finished removing their flesh, they wouldn’t work on them right away.
They also used to submerge those fish skins into urine like this.
They removed the smell of fish.
When they did this, what they called aging urine
Their men would urinate into those containers, their original containers.
They called that aging urine.
Those would be very stinky.
They used to soak fish skins in those.
And after they were soaked, they would then scrape them.
They would scrape them after putting them on boards.
They would then hang them outside to dry.
And then when those dried, they would make those into boots for their men.
They called that making them fish skin [clothes] that they would use to travel like this.
Their men would also prepare.
Even those blackfish traps.
When stopped using what they called big fish traps
When they were going to change those for blackfish too, they would also make those fish traps.
And then when they kept them set
These days, we use various things, boxes and sacks to put blackfish in.
However, those who raised us back then that I observed didn’t have those.
Their women also used to prepare grass to put them in.
Like this, yes, when they’re not green anymore, when they’re getting pale
They would gather a lot like this.
And in the summer like this...
I forgot something.
Women would prepare that grass, coarse grass, for their things.
They would be used for weaving.
Those who raised us back then always kept the future in mind.
They always prepared what they would need in the future even if it was a long way off
Because they didn’t have anything [pre-made].
They only had what [was made from] the land.
They would [work] because they couldn’t afford not to.
When the need for it was approaching, they would prepare them a long time beforehand.
They also used to use tall cottongrass from the summer for weaving.
When women started gathering those tall cottongrass, they would spread them to dry, nalacirluki as they called it.
And then when those had dried, nalaluteng as they say,
They wouldn’t gather them either, [but] weave them.
And then when they finished them, they would roll them up.
That’s what they used to do with grass that they used for weaving.
These days, when I think about those people back then
I’ve started becoming daunted about leading that kind of life.
And then when the men [worked on] their tools.
They would make mink traps that looked like fish traps.
They made them small, about this long, and something like this.
They would make traps depending on the creeks.
Those weren’t made haphazardly either. They also had [set] measurements.
Their inner compartments were not like blackfish traps either. They would be like this.
And then that part over there would be like a den.
When I watched my older sister’s husband like this
He would do this with his hands to measure the entrance
Doing that to what they called the throat.
That’s what they were like. They weren’t haphazard.
And then when he made otter traps like fish traps
Their entrances would be like this as before.
And then he would do this, measuring it with his thumb, determining the width like this.
Like that. Yes, they apparently didn’t make those haphazardly either.
These days, when I think about them back then
I wonder how their lives were.
When I think of them, I would be daunted [by their lives].
But because I [was born] when they started becoming Westernized
Our caretakers occasionally had Western things
But they didn’t get a lot.
They would get tea, flour, sugar, and pilot bread once in a blue moon.
And yet those things that they got
They would smell very strong when they were brought in.
And they don’t [seem to] have any scent these days.
When they took out the pilot bread, they smell strong from afar, they smelled nice and delicious.
These days, I can’t [smell] them anymore.
Once in a while, though, I smell them when they’re close.
That’s what those people back then were like.
So, how about, you know, admonishments when the men, you know, when they traveled in the fall like this?
And so, yes, they used to admonish them like this when it was dangerous as they traveled.
They also used to tell them not to make a lot of noise in the wilderness.
They said not to make a lot of noise like this.
Only those who get into accidents
They must make noise if they have an fall into the water.
They also admonished us against yelling in the wilderness in the fall like this.
They told us not to make a lot of noise.
They said that only those in dire situations would make noise like that.
And then if they heard anyone screaming, making noise, they would understand that [s]he’s gotten into an accident or fell into water.
Yet because they are not admonished anymore these days, they don’t know [those] anymore because we don’t admonish youpl.
They also make noise like this.
They yell in between villages here.
They used to admonish against those.
And then, I’ve done that once when I heard someone who got into an accident.
Before it was too long since Tuntutuliak was established as a village
When we were down in Kelliq, with people inland from us too.
You see this lake toward the water from this house.
In the day nearing evening like this, I heard someone screaming inland from us.
I had thought it was the people inland.
It turned out that someone fell into the water down there. [S]he had apparently fell into the water.
One of the people going down apparently saw the person just as [s]he was going to freeze to death
When there was no land here like this.
They had a lot of admonishments back then.
They used to tell them like this not to make a lot of noise.
And then this was especially important:
When they’re going to travel, they would always say that they’re going around that area.
And when they didn’t return, they would know where they had accidents.
Yet these days, when they travel like this with these boats, they don’t say anything.
And then when they don’t return, they don’t know what happened to them because they didn’t say anything.
It’s because they’ve started traveling without consideration these days.
Or they pretend to go somewhere then travel to other villages.
That’s what’s making us so addled these days.
They have no idea about these descendants like this or they think they’re in some place.
These days, even when they die in the wilderness, they have no idea about them.
You see, because there are now a lot of things bringing struggles these days
People back then were not like this, like this.
They always observed everything.
And in the fall, they would always talk to us boys like this
About our futures, what’s in store for us, that they are experiencing.
They would indicate what was dangerous, in the wilderness too.
These things on land, elevated hills, had names.
All of the creeks had names too.
Some of the lakes had names too.
They knew the layout of this land.
Yet these days, because we don’t point those out to our children
They don’t know the wilderness or what’s on it, rivers, and lakes, and these elevated areas.
And when something happens, when we ask them where it happened to them
Or a person these days would get lost, they get lost.
When they ask the people who saw it about the area where they saw it they don’t know its name either.
They would say it happened over there because we don’t point those out to them anymore.
We used to talk about everything, but we didn’t always experience them.
But when we reached them, we would recognize them.
Yes, a person should live through traditional wisdom.
Yes, [s]he evidently will not live well if [s]he does not adhere to traditional wisdom.
[S]he will also lack what their peers work on.
They used to tell us this back then:
If we adhere to this traditional wisdom, obey it while we live we will live well.
We should not be lazy or sleep too much.
They would promise us that.
However, yes, we wouldn’t reach what they indicated yet.
But when we reach it these days, we recognize it.
That’s why they used to tell us this back then:
They said to pay attention to our instructor yes, we should watch his mouth.
They said that if we look away from him, [we] won’t know what he’s talking about anymore.