Turns out, we have the same name.
Please speak to test it.
Okay, can you hear me?
Speak more.
How?
Any way.
Okay.
I think I’m going to be coughing.
Now, start.
What do you remember in your earliest memories?
Okay, growing up, my earliest memories are of downriver in Tagyaraq.
(S)he’s trying ot play with that.
Don’y play with that. Look [?]... hey!
Yes, growing up, my earliest memories are in Tagyaraq.
Our old village there was called Quuneq.
[It was called] Quuneq.
In my earliest memores, I, you know
We used to think we were alone.
And when my mom had me go outside
I would look around, and it would seem that the world extended to our vicinity.
You know, it seemed like we were the only people. And I would think we were the only people.
And my older brothers would arrive seemingly from the wilderness. I thought they came from the wilderness.
Apparently, they’d come from our home village, Qinaq.
Then my mother would travel.
He would bring back Western things he had purchased.
Apparently, he would go to the store owned by his male cross-cousin there in Ciun, also in Tagyaraq.
Some days, he would go.
When I wanted to go with him, he’d say that was going to go far away.
Then when I asked him, he’d say he was going to go to Eek.
It turned out, what did they call their resident Caucasian in Eek again?
He’d also buy Western things from there.
Then I became observant, and started going with my father.
We would go buy western things there in Ciun from his cousin. I would only go with him there, sometimes.
He didn’t bring me with him to other people. He wouldn’t take me though I was sad over his departure, only [took me] to the wilderness.
Then when I became observant, I had permanent long term memory.
And our fishcamp in Cuukvalegmiut, also right downriver from our old settlement
I also thought that place was always like that, and was in eternal summer.
I thought of them like that, that it was always summer there.
There would be many staying there.
And I don’t think I remembered them when they left, when we moved.
Then I became observant.
And we went upriver.
Back then, the two of us would get younger siblings.
[My sibling] downriver and I lived as lone [siblings] for a long time.
Then right when we went upriver to Qinaq, we got a younger siblings.
When we’d started going to winter camp in Qurrelvak, we, you know
We got a younger sibling, the one downriver.
Then that’s how it went.
Then I, you know
We’d be in Qukaqlircaraq, and when we went upriver then, we would go inland to our winter camp, Qurrelvak.
But when a school was built in 19...
When thye started going to school in 1951 downriver at Tuntutuliak
We stopped being nomadic ever since then.
But we would also be told
And our father used to instruct us like this:
"Always clean off debris in the house. Clean everything, the floors.
"And though things feel gross, dump them out."
He also said to think as we dumped them
That we want to be good hunter-gatherers, or live long, or live well without getting sick.
Or, he also said to put the debris in our front flounces and take them out.
He said to pu tthem here in the front flounce, and take them out.
Look, he said, back then, the people who wanted to have light
Those ones who wanted to have light would always clean up
The ones he said wanted to be spiritually pure.
He said that osme of those who always did that, those people wouldn’t get sick.
And on their hems, he said that though they weren’t baptized, they’d emit light from their hems, and the tips of their sleeves, and here from their neck openings.
They’d emit light like this. And though they walked around outside, it wouldn’t be too dark for them.
That’s what he used to tell us.
And those people weren’t baptized, but they knew.
Then he said that we shouldn’t be averse to the sick, but help clean them up though we get dirty.
He said that impurities do not affect people.
He said that a person who serves does not become impure.
But even though those around him are sick, (s)he will not get sick.
There you have it.
Then, those who serve
You know, cleaning skins though they get dirty
He said they come off with washing, but they don’t stick to a person.
Well...
Then these bowls
These bowls, you know, always wash things.
They would also always discard food scraps where they wouldn’t be tread upon.
Also, all of us are forgetting much traditional wisdom.
And we, we Yupiit, have forgotten the traditional Yup’ik wisdom.
We’ve forgotten them.
Then like this
Recently, I also heard someone from Napakiak speaking.
And I remembered the traditional wisdom passed down to me like this:
Try to have that person remember, try to have them remember.
My father also used to tell us this:
"Though they know them, they always tell them to have them remember."
That’s why he said we should never tire of traditional wisdom or our instructors, but we must listen to them, watching their mouths.
They also used to tell me this, because I was woefully bad
Since I was woefully bad, they would tell me what was apparently traditional wisdom
"A person has a very good appearance."
And wood, what that person from Napakiak was talking about.
Wood is not only used for jealousy.
He said that a person has a very good appearance, very nice to look, cute as you call it.
However, he said that a man may come upong a great [looking] piece of wood.
"What a great piece of wood."
He said he will split that good piece of wood, and the inside will be all twisted.
He said that a person, all of us people with bad minds are like that.
Also, a man or a woman is like that.
Then he said one may come across a very twisted piece of wood, the wood all twisted.
He said it looks like a bad piece of wood.
Then he said one will try to split it open to find that only the outside is twisted, and the inside is good and straight.
He said that though a person is ugly, has an ugly face, and is like that twisted piece of wood
He said that if (s)he has a good mind, they are like that twisted piece of wood with the straight grained inside, very good on the inside.
Then a straight piece of wood looks good, like it’ll be a good piece of wood
He said they’d try to split it open, and the inside would be all twisted.
He said that’s what a person is also like.
Though they look lovely, have a good face, [acts] good, or seems good like this
He said that the inside of a person with a bad mind is like that.
Because of that
These are things we must remember.
Also, do not treat people badly.
They’re different, and their minds are different like that piece of wood.
Apparently, we people are like wood.
I was also told that.
Since I was pitifully twisted and bad, I would hear traditional wisdom.
Then when they would tell me that
I would sometimes ask, "Why? Why is one like that?"
They said a person is like that.
They said one with a good appearance looking straight, has twisted insides.
All of them like that
The ones [who look] good, and the ones who look bad though their appearances look twisted, have good insides when they have good minds.
Those are the things we must remember.
Also
Though a person does anything to us, we shouldn’t retort.
And we shouldn’t defend ourselves, and not think that we’re good people.
And as we walk here, we should never think we’re better than those around us
But remember our own faults.
But also, we should remember our own faults
And do not stop interacting with people because of our faults.
Evidently, we must live socializing with other people.
Then we would also be told this:
They said that when we go out
They said that right when we go out, we should look in the middle of the [Spirit of the] Universe.
They said that the Spirit of the Universe is grateful by nature.
They said to always check the weather, always look around, including at the navigation stars.
Then people also used the sun to measure time.
And back when I started using these clocks
My father, you see, never used clocks, only the sun.
Then after coming in from outside, after he went out and came in, he would say
"It’s noon. It’s time to eat."
I would look at my clock and find that it was noon, yet he never saw a clock.
Then sometimes, when the sun appeared in the windows, he would say, "It’s one o’clock."
I would look at my clock and find it would be one o’clock.
It can also be used to measure time by watching how it moves.
That is clear to them, and confusing for us.
Though thye seem confusing, those who are observant do that.
When I recently heard that, when I heard that
I remember how I was told this
About what a person should do.
Then they also used to tell me
Though these are shameful and embarrassing, they must be told.
You see, they must be told.
Then they would also speak to them though they were very shameful [topics].
Then they used to tell me
I forgot what I was going to say.
You know, when I had too hard of a time
After I struggled too much, I apologize, I sometimes forget what I’m going to say.
But also, though one struggles with mental health
Though people struggle with mental health
We must remember them.
I just said, I was just speaking about to say that, and I forgot
When I struggled a lot, since they were all my relatives who passed away last winter over the course of one week.
But let us have this mindset
Though we struggle, all people experience it.
All people experience it.
And a person shouldn’t think they’re the only one, since all people struggle with mental health
Sometimes having great troubles.
Also, this was said, people said this:
They said that one who thinks they’re alone become severely depressed, until eventually they go insane.
They said it’s because he thinks like this: "I am the only one struggles with mental health."
However, all people in the world suffer here.
That’s why we should think that we’re the only ones struggling with mental health.
Instead, we should remember others with mental health problems, but pray for the ones who are also struggling with mental health like us.
Now, some days, a day comes where it is very hard.
You call it, having a hard time with your mental health.
That’s what that is.
Now, let’s not think we’re the only ones who think that.
Instead, let all of us people consider each other
And let us consider each other in prayer.
This is all from me.
Like that [?].
Since I have nothing to say
Since it was all I had to say, I talked about that.
Its mouth. Its mouth.
Oh my, you’re late and ended up fixing the camera for the dog.