Hello, I’m Hazel Lincoln, and my Yup’ik name is Qang’allugaq.
Thank you for joining us on our Delta Review.
This eveneing, an elder for Kwethluk, Jimmy Chimigalrea, will join us.
We will also be showing the others who Yup’ik danced in Mountain Village for the dance festival this past Sunday.
First, let’s listen to what Chimigalrea has to say.
If you understand Yup’ik, listen closely.
To all people, we who are listening, all of you people
They are asked to be like this, we need to hear one of them.
It says in Philippians 2:12
It says this: "As you obey the one whom I love as you are together now
"Even though I am not your relative, work on your salvation out of respect and fear.
"For it is God who works in you. He gives you fervor and has you follow his will.
"Work through all of them.
"Do not grumblr, and do not say unfavorable things. Do not make yourself need admonishment.
"So that you will be God’s people without drawing attention.
"You shall have no ailments among the false and the sinful.
"And so that you shall shine like stars among them in the world."
It showed the wisdom concerning life. I started off with that.
It’s time we people hear that, without leaving anyone out.
You know, we shouldn’t [?], and stop lying.
Also, we must stop thinking malicious things about those around us, and do not think bad things about people in secret.
That’s all for that.
It’s time that we hear this.
Then this, started from a long time ago in those years that have passed
Some people tell me that I should talk about this here on KYUK
So that my voice would spread out more like this.
Some people up there, far away from the Yukon, have also been telling me for many years.
But since I found it daunting to go to KYUK, I wouldn’t go to them before this.
Also, I used to look for someone to who could speak about this better than I could.
However, some of them would say to me
Oh my, they said that there is no one who can say it better than me. They said that I should speak about it instead.
Now, I am finally going to speak about it.
You see, when they used to speak about the end of the world, I was born in time to see the ones who spoke about the end of the world.
Well, I was born in time to see the ones who spoke about the time of famine far in the future.
Then, you see, what that one person said always comes to mind now.
Then since it always come to my mind, I’ve become wary of this world, thinking that it would end badly.
And I’m not the only one. Some others have become wary of this world.
Back then, you see, I realized when I became observant that some old men and women would walk, supporting themselves on their knees like this
Yet some couldn’t walk anymore
When they had old women and men.
They would carry some out of the community house to take sweat baths
And when they were done, they brought in the ones who couldn’t walk anymore.
Then when they spoke about the end of the world, some of them said this:
They said that those who are the oldest there under the earth
Those who lived, the oldest ones, under the one we used to hear about
They said, "A person lives for quite a long time. (S)he will not live another [life]."
They also said this:
You see, they said, a long time ago... when they used to speak about the end of the world a long time ago
You see, they said, some of these great hunters
After this old man was laying in the community house, he said listening to the one by the wall near the door say
They said that one of them got up, "Ah, it should happen already while we are [doing well]."
They said that it was apparently when the one who would [?take] them was getting close.
They said that when people, you know, apparently waited for others to act, you know people sometimes wait for others to act
When they ask to be set free when what they’re about to do is approaching.
Then at that time, at that time
I also used to see those days. I think those happened over one winter.
Day started breaking after dawn like this further upriver, past where the day breaks toward the north.
The wonderful day became night.
Some of those men say that the day has become false, without any further explanation.
Then one day, we were playing excitedly, and it got dark.
I went into a house that was not of those who raised me.
Then right when I went in, that woman came in after me.
Then when she came in, she said before she sat down there, "There is now day out there."
The the old man of that house said
"When this world is on the brink [of ending], it doesn’t leave its people in the dark.
"But, you see, it gives them notice first.
"Look, it is giving notice to them about the lesson it’s going to teach them.
"It sees its people, sees the people on this earth because it’s time for them.
"Look, it is showing it to them, and will [correct] them through that."
Then he said, "People will wait expectantly.
"Watch, as they are eagerly waiting, they will stop waiting eagerly, then there will be no one left who is wating eagerly.
"And watch, they will stop hearing anyone say the world is ending."
We now coincide with what he said.
He also said that there would be no more snow, that is, when [the world] starts putting it into one place.
Now, what he said always comes to mind.
I am not wary of this world. I don’t know what this world is doing.
Then, they also said this:
"Fish roe," it was the only one they mentioned.
They said that fish roe would be in the land year after year. They said it wouldn’t spoil.
It will not become dangerous inside a person though it spends year after year in the land.
That was the only one they mentioned.
Then these days, there are now freezers.
But there are two things, there are two things [that don’t spoil] in freezers.
But when I think about this salted fish, it may also spend year after year if it is salted well
It may take on years, but that will not spoil either.
There are two things [that don’t spoil] in freezers. What it does is irregular.
And these days, our [Caucasian] counterparts are [?] in this current day.
But as they go, it’s hard to know when I think about it.
Look, I’ve started hearing since a long time ago, since quite a while ago
In those lands way over there that I do not see where there are a lot of people
It started getting cold where they do not know cold; it started snowing where they do not know snow.
That is negatively affecting crops.
It is also negatively affecting animal young, whatever wildlife there is.
Maybe the people of the lands that I do not see
They are trying, trying [things] with their crops.
When I think about it and pretend I’m there
They will not turn their back on their lives and consider Alaskan people more important.
I was also told this, I was told this that was untranslated from a knowledgeable person:
"Those with crops must [survive] with their crops. Those with food [from animals] must survive with their foor [from animals]."
Then he also said this:
"Watch, when the false day that wilts plants is nigh
"Watch, people will start fighting, acting crazy. They will no longer await anything."
You see, we are corresponding to what is like this in these current days.
They care nothing for their families anymore.
Oh my, it is clear these days that their grandmother is not a teacher.
Also, you see, we poor grandfathers of their are also not teachers in random places here.
It truly seems that the chidlren of the next generation, it truly seems that we watch them with levity.
We have no [?affection] these days.
Then when I ponder
When the world is on the verge of doing this, though it is on the verge of going through this winter
It will not tell it’s people that it’s going to do it now.
It turns out it was all of that.
It had already shown its people through that, without leaving anything out, that it would do that.
Then, that old man also said this:
"Watch, when that time of famine is nigh
These two, sheefish, Bering cisco, watch, they rivers will be filled with those two fish."
He said that when a person runs out [of food] like this, one of those two will be his source of food.
He said that he will eat a lot of one of those two. He said that despite that, he will grow skinny, his flesh falling off.
Those to healthy and good fish that are also fatty
"So," he said, "so those two are the fish of famine."
I haven’t forgotten this. Since it always comes to mind now, I’ve become wary of this world.
Then, people back then also said this:
"These three, king salmon, chum salmon, silver salmon, those don’t run out."
That’s why they gave this piece of traditional wisdom to the children of our descendants today like this:
While those are swimming, if a person is able, he should not be lazy, but take as much as he can from them.
They admonished against [?being unprepared for] fall.
They said that if it is going to have that kind of winter, all of the things that come after them will be gone.
This always comes to mind now.
Then when that famine comes upon them
I was also told about that. It’s been quite a while.
It also moved my mind when the one who told me told this to me
It also moved his mind as he said this:
He said that he dreamt he was drift netting.
He let the current carry him, however we drift net, you drift net.
Then when it was time, he rolled up his net.
As he was rolling up his net, a fish appeared down there, entirely covered in bones yet was moving.
Then when it appeared, it said to the one who caught it
"Wait a second. I have two things to say."
Then it said to the one who had caught it
"After a few years, the time of famine is going to come
"And the spirit of theft is going to be active."
Look, though the people I was born to see had talked for a long time
You see, that was the first time I heard about the spirit of theft.
Then after that person spoke to me
It seems that every year, people get worse. They seem to get worse.
They do not share with their families. They steal from them, even take their food away.
When I ponder upon these people now
If these they desire what was taken away from their stomachs, how far will they go?
They will also take from their families.
Or, these people are not like long ago anymore.
Some have no more inhibitions, and some have gotten dangerous.
And one of them will be killed because he has a little food.
It’s getting to long. This is all I will say about it.
Thank you Chimigalrea.
Now, the dancers of Emmonak recorded a video when Mountain Village held a challenge feast.
Thank you. I am Qang’allugaq.
Join us next time for our Delta Review.