Ready?
Now, [tell us] a piece of traditional wisdom, or something that you want to leave with us...
I have trouble saying the word "paiciluki."
Pleae talk about one thing that is important to you that you want to leave with your children, or something you want people to remember.
Now, there is one thign that is important to me that I want you to remember.
If I want you to remember it, I would tell you now
This is one thing you should remember, you know, if you want to live a good life:
You shall not be your own master, even if you live as an adult like that.
You must have a mind, you must think of some belief.
You must believe in God’s will.
Then if you can’t do that, you must believe in Yup’ik instructions.
It’s because if you live by yourself like that without faith, thinking you’re smart, thinking highly of yourself
I don’t know how you’ll end up.
Especially if you drink alcohol like that, or even if you smoke marijuana
Especially with you, I don’t know how you’ll end up.
However, if you live believing in one of those two
Believing what you hear from the Bible, knowing and believing that there is a god
If you’re going to live of your own accord like that, you will be hindered by the one who watches you.
But if you don’t want to follow the church, listen to traditional Yup’ik wisdom.
If you try to obey and believe them as you live
And their traditional wisdom says that they revered the Spirit of the Universe, that [the Spirit] presided over everything
And they didn’t speak of God, but spoke of the Spirit of the Universe.
And of something wrong, they also said not to take anything that was not theirs behind a person.
They said that one like that would get into worse things.
They also said that a liar would also get into worse things.
That is traditional Yup’ik wisdom about what is dangerous.
However, they said that one who tried not to do wrong does well and has a good future.
That’s why if you live with faith, you will live with strength.
So how was that? (Good, thank you.) Okay. How was it?
Were they over 20?
A little short, uh, they wer over twenty.
Haven’t you had great-granchildren? Do you have great-grandchildren.
I have two great-granchildren.
Okay, and where were you born?
Sheldon’s Point, at Nunam Iqua.
Here at the mouth of the Yukon.
So, when...
I probably am. I still have the lifetime certificate that I got.
You know, it’s not shown.
But, you know, when someone asks me, as I said, when someone asks me, I’d try to help.
Even to the people here who are like that around me, [?] when I can, I go to them.
Okay, that's probably enough.
More? (Mhm.) Okay.
You are a speaker when invited here, and YKHC also invites you when they have workshops.
With those, are you still active?
Since they didn’t invite me here to YKHC
I think it's going to be three years since they've invited me.
Since they didn’t, I didn’t go. But I did go on the news by myself.
I’ve probably gone twice.
And once here, when KCC across there had an event...