...they say she’s become an old lady.
They say they don’t refer to one who can walk by themself as an old man or old woman.
But call someon an old man or an old woman...
We who know them will not keep our ancestors’ wisdom to ourself
Because they help us stand here on earth for a long time.
Do we want our people whom we love to have early deaths?
If we love them, we must tell them especially of our ancestors’ traditional instructions.
Then, we Yupiit have the traditional instruction to warmly welcome all of our fellow people
We must cooperate without discriminating against them.
Anyone, even the people of Alaska, are asked to stand with one mind in accordance.
Some of them here, some religions say this:
"Our religion is good and powerful."
That's not the cast. That's not what it's like.
We shouldn't destroy our ancestors' tradition of community, and we shouldn't do away with it.
Our ancestors have spoken of this traditional of community, that it's a form of love starting from a long time ago.
If we don’t practice love while we’re alive how, what will we do to be saved? We have no other salvation.
Our ancestors practiced love.
And they went in salvation because they practice that will all of their fellow people without discrimination.
Though different religions try to have us discriminate against each that, that discrimination is bad and leads to unrest.
Only if we practice our ancestors’ instruction of community will we stand [together] in peace
And our faith will be complete.
And through that love, we shall be saved.
We must have our descendants especially be knowledgeable about our ancestors
And how to take good care of our land.
We who know this traditional wisdom shouldn’t hide it.
They say, you see, that our ancestors were like this:
They said that in the community house, a young man would be waking up to an old man in the darkness already speaking about a person can live well.
The same way in a house out there, they said an old woman would already be speaking.
In the darkness, she let those she loved wake up to traditional wisdom and instruction.
Do we do that? We haven't done that.
We must keep up what our ancestors were like to our descendants here.
We have no other salvation. We only have salvation through community.
Jesus came down only to establish community among all the land.
Let us know this:
And that sense of community of ours will teach us how to live well, be strong, and live long lives.
It’s a great thing how our ancestors stood [together] as a community.
That’s why even if they say other religions are better, don’t believe them.
One God who has no potential for being exalter higher [among denominations], be greater, or lesser, who is always as he is.
We believe in one God and in Jesus
To one who cannot be exalted higher [among denominations], be higher, or stronger, who is always as he is.
For that reason, let us Yupiit start this sense of community, especially with our descendants.
A youth here is like this these days:
When [s]he learns to speak English, they become proud thinking they’re smart.
And yet [s]he doesn’t know how to survive, and doesn’t know what they will come to.
We must make available to our youth and have them be knowledgeable about our ancestors’ way of life
Especially their sense of community.
I’ve [come to] say this much though it wasn’t a lot. Thank you.
Those people speak little.
What’s goin on? Is it time to start? (Yes.)
Okay then, let’s talk now.
Yes, a long time ago, and when I became observant
We became aware in our early childhood, and we heard about those that my spouse just talked about.
But for us young people, those first Caucasians were scary.
We’d occassionally see several Caucasians.
Absolutely without [?] them, when they came once in a great while, we’d see Caucasians.
There were those.
Then one day when we were living here in Anuuraaq, they built a school here.
They built a school right in the middle of us, then they started going to school.
Then we tried going to school. Our parents didn’t want to part with us.
They told us not to go to school whatsoever.
They said that it starts something mischievous. Now, they said that those schools make them coddled.
They were scary back when we went because they admonished us.
And after I tried going to school, after I tried going to them once...
Wait, that fell.
Is he your spouse?
It might be because we were too loud.
No.
Then after we tried going to school, since they told us to stay, we went home.
These people kept saying, "These schools are distressing."
Later, their mischief will have bad outcomes.
They said they’d become foolish far in the future, not thinking of what chores they should be doing
When they start bringing in these mischievous things.
We didn’t go to school, but these poor young people and our children started going to school.
They started knowing things and wrote for us.
Even those Caucasians... and they didn’t seem to mistreat Caucasians in any way.
But the work of those shamans were also like that.
They would have fun [causing mischief] with them because they had malicious intent.
And among them here, among the many pieces of traditional wisdom from our instructors, one who wanted to [cause mischief] was part of the traditional wisdom.
They said that jealousy
They said that out of a joulesy of a poor person making their own living, a jealous shaman
[S]he places a curse on him to make him unable to catch animals, or destroys the great wealth of one who was going to live well.
Those had very malicious intent.
Then these pieces of traditional wisdom
They said that among the people around them, though they find us poor young people improper or lazy
When I was a girl here, at night, and since I lost my mother at a young age, because I would stop going out at night when it got dark
These people would threaten me that if I were a lazy person, that I would be a begger like this.
And they said that that [begging] would bring me misfortune after I was lazy when my peers took husbands, out of [my] desire to have things like them.
But our thorough instructors would tell us that.
And among our peers, we shouldn’t misbehave, shouldn’t [? as you know], shouldn’t be inadequately observant, shouldn’t be fooling among our peers.
When they got up, they’d always tell us
"When you young people have children, though your child seems small, or if you admonish them when you put on their boots
"’Now, if your peers do anything to you, respond by getting away from them.’
They said the little ones pay attention.
They said that these things our elders heard in their earliest memories are theirs [to remember and pass on].
Now, when I remember that, and how I was reluctant to accept that they’d become more mischievous later
And since I didn’t speak English, and didn’t hear them speak English, I remembered them.
And when we had children, when we got married
They told us to treat our spouses with love, take care of our husbands.
And we shouldn’t commit adultery.
And if we poor woman go to various places without our husbands’ knowledge
They said that eventually, we’d become pregnant with someone other than our husbands.
Back when in our childhoods, we found that when they instructed us, no matter how socially unacceptable it was, they’d pry it out and tell us.
And when they looked at us, we who were listening would think like this:
"Oh my, it turns out the one across know knows us, has seen us."
It seemed they knew everything about us, like they’d indeed seen us.
It turned out that those who instructed well would empty their heard of what they’d experienced.
The dear ones would instruct us, wanting a person to go [through life] well.
And when we bear children, they told us never to bring them to various places [with people].
And if we hold their hands to visit other houses with them, the dear ones will become bad.
They say their improper behavior exacerbates a mother’s destitution who looks after the home.
They said our household’s father would travel to try to provide for us.
They said that when he arrives, we women should be thankful for whatever he catches.
Or if he earns a little money, we women shouldn’t be angry wanting beautiful dresses or some beautiful shoes.
They said it’s because we have nice clothes, because we’re standing with what they provided.
They say those will destroy our spouses.
What little they obtain, they said we should be dextrous with what little they obtain, helping our dear spouses.
They said not to be frivolous with them.
We shouldn’t grab what money he made and go.
And later as we go, if we come across mischievous things, or we drink, or other things
They admonished us against all of those dangerous things, not to be like that in front of our children. They said we’d teach them [how to be like that].
It turned out that when they got enlisted en masse, and since we have a lot of male children
We start living with a hopeless mindset because they [?tended to drink].
May a person live like that without exacerbating anything these days.
And their warning of a terrible ending
They said that if we start being mischievous, when our parents, instructors, and elders instructed us
They said that if we become mischievous, we [won’t] be sensible anymore.
We don’t pay any more attention to our advisor, our instructor, who tells us to live right, without being a hindrance among those around us.
Instead, they said that we would do well to look presentable sitting at home, so, they said, that our home would be peaceful.
And if some guest who feels helpless comes in, we should make them feel at peace if we don’t, you know, live mischievously.
When they said that, though we wanted to [be like that], yet we’d sometimes come across [extrenuating] circumstances.
We're unsuccessful when we wanted to be good.
And because these people are now in great need of instructors like this
These young people, our descendants, because there’s now a lot of people who want to hear traditional instructions
That’s why I’m daunted by it.
When we’re grown like this, we’re supposed to listen well to their traditional wisdom.
I’ve already started through here on KYUK, with those who are instructing, and those women giving traditional instruction.
And those, when women didn’t have husbands, when they didn’t think anything of it, it was their kneeguards.
Through that, we didn’t have children with various [fathers], except through our very own dear husbands.
They said we should have our spouses’ children without adding any from other [people].
They said they were very beautiful [families].
Poor me, I would wish for that, oh my goodness.
Apparently, we might have accidentally gotten pregnant.
And the thought of becoming pregnant at a young age was very scary, bringing forth a child.
They said children out of wedlock were very embarrassing. It had been an admonishment.
Apparently, that was how they’d become mischievous as our ancestors talked about.
That is an important instruction they have now.
These Caucasians are so good. Oh my, they sound nice, these Caucasians are pleasant.
When we watch them, and when we watch showsand other things, when they inject rowdy people and women, they’d become very strange.
They would become like, and to me, it seemed they had no more rigidity.
If some rowdy person came upon them, it seemed that they wouldn’t have the strength [to apprehend them].
Young people, it’ll be good if you don’t do these bad things that are admonished against.
Don’t follow what Caucasians tell you to do too much.
Also because they say they start marijuana, and that has negative effects.
Don’t abuse those.
But, you see, our lives are short like this.
Our youth and childhood may seem close, yet we become weak, unable to do strenuous things.
That’s why you should be careful, not only following those bad things.
We will be very thankful if you do housework, make your own living, and try to earn money enthusiastically.
But, use the money you earn for yourselves and your houses to help you, for your things.
And now, because I don’t know how to speak English, don’t hold it in high regard since I don’t use it
Only when they absolutely want me to, and when my spouse across there comes with me, I take something when he comes with me, because I know nothing of how to buy it.
I’m very thankful, I’m thankful that I don’t know because I stay in peace.
Since the ones we watch say little, we’ve probably spoken enough.
Should we stop here? Our long talk hasn’t been much.
Is that all?
I want to stop here.
Had we not been mourning, we wouldn’t have [hunted] that animal that was eating.
We ate it last, finished it [?].
We eat the meat.
We ate it. We ate that [animal] that had been eating.
Since we had no other food, we ate it.
There are many hunting grounds up in the mountains.
Here’s the first: Evsairniik is a hunting ground.
And next: the hunting grounds at Nacarkiarniar where it takes a long time to climb.
Then the third: Ilutuqacuk. It’s a land under my name.
Yes.
And Naqerpak, and Nurtuucaraq.
Lots of camps [?] upriver.
And Qanirtuum Qagatii.
Way up there [?].
They call it Nakerpak, the route that goes here to Kuinerram Qagatii.
And here on this side of Kuinerram Qagatii, inland from the lake, Equgniilnguq is also a hunting ground.
And here at the end near the mouth is another hunting ground, a place where they hunt for a long time.
And the people from Kuiggluk go there in the fall until there’s no more men.
They only return when Christmas is nigh.
And up there where they call it Naqailnguq, that’s also a hunting ground.
They hunt there for a long time.
I know all of the hunting grounds up there.
Its name is Ingriu͡rluq. The mountain is called Ingriu͡rluq.
And downriver from there, it’s called Elngurtuliar.
Across from these are Qikertat.
These two inland from Elngurtuliar are called Napanguliik, two boulders standing upright.
On the other side of them, there’s what they call Ingrilukaak.
And so, those are also hunting grounds.
And up there across from that is Iluvaqtuq. They call it Iluvaqtuq. That’s also a hunting ground.
Then upriver from there over there, they call it Ulurrugnaq.
The mountain is slanted, slanted towards the water.
In the middle is a grassy plain, the grass growing up there.
And in the middle of where they grow, the elders say:
They said that a person climbed.
Then, they said that in the middle, he was nervously wary, and squatted beneath himself out of nervous wariness.
He couldn’t do anything, couldn’t go.
They said that up there, the center of the mountain is a grassy plain to this day.
Then upriver from there, upriver is what they call Atsartulriar, a small mountain that’s not big.
It’s also a long time hunting ground.
Then inland from that small mountain is a small river, a small river going inland with the name Kuignayugpak.
Now that’s a hunting ground, a long time hunting ground.
And then...
[The] Eskimo name is like the mountain here.
I’m about to reach Qanirtuq River now.
On the banks of the Qanirtuq River... what was the mountain called again?
Ulurrugnaq
That’s also a long time hunting ground.
And upriver from there... what was it again? Cayagtuli?
No?
I don’t know them. Is that all?
No, that’s not all. That’s far from all.
Then up there, Ircaqurrnaq.
That’s also a hunting ground, with the name Ircaqurrnaq.
Then here toward the water is a similar mountain with the name Ircaqurrnayagaq.
Then over there upriver from there are Evsairrsugaak.
They also hunt not far from there.
And here is Qerrirtaq.
In Qerrirtaq there, it’s also a hunting ground. You see, it’s a very long standing hunting ground.
Then inland is Cingikeggliq.
The mountain is named Cingikeggliq with a sharp upward summit.
Then on this side, the mountain going down to Kuiggluk is Canirngalria.
Then on the other side of that is Qupun. It’s named Qupun.
Over there at the end, it’s named Canyon, and Kuignayuggaq.
And here on the other side is Nacarkarniarun.
Now that’s a long time hunting ground for those who are staying up there.
Then on the other side of Nacarkarniarun...
Don’t wave your hands.
Evsairniik. They call them Evsairniik.
Those are also a hunting ground for a long time.
He’s tired.
Yeah, so you can take a break, rest, stop for a minute. Yeah, stop.
Yes, you’re tired.
I spoke about all of those hunting grounds.
I don’t know how to [?] English.
Has he mentioned any stories of big creatures?
It has big fish.
Yes, he just talked about it. She already [did].
Did he talk about, anything about the skeleton, ribs, skeletons on the beach?
It’s [been a] long time.
Yeah, did he talk about that though? (Yes.) The skeletons on the beach? (Yes.)
[?] the father, her father, long time, the bones, [?back] bones?
Yeah, yeah.
She get big hole on it.
Right.
In and out, the kids are playing.
Yeah, that’s what I heard.
Yes.
She’s at long grass, that place on ground, place, that old place.
Do you know which side of the lake those were on? North side?
No. (South side?) Kwethluk side.
Kwethluk side of the lake?
That’s east side?
No.
South?
Yes.
Facing this way like this, yes.
Kiillaraliin, Heart Lake, Kwethluk, this side.
This side, that’s where the bones were?
Yes.
Yes. Where’s your map? I’ll show you.
Where’s your map?
Okay, Jerry can you get that? It’s back in there, top one.
On the next map, you know how it goes toward Kwethluk like this?
Right or left? Right?
Where’s Kwethluk?
Look, here’s Kwethluk.
Yes, it’s this side.
We always stay [on] this side.
Kuikayuk is over there.
Can you say this aloud?
Here’s Kuikayuk.
Yes. Crooked Creek Mountain, yes, here it is.
Where’s Kiillaraliin? Here it is.
(Kiillaraliin is on this side.) Here’s Keligceńaq.
Upper Fall, Igceńaq, Qurrlurtaq.
Yes.
Eskimo name, Qurrlurtaq.
Here’s Taryaqvagtuli.
[?] here.
Down there on this side. It’s on this side.
It’s on this side there.
[?]
Evon Qugg’aq [?].
You know stories, or?
No, it’s older than [?].
She’s teaching for hunting, walking. No stove, just tent in winter.
When you went to Heart Lake, did you walk?
No, by plane.
This time? Long time ago, though, you walked?
Dogs.
Dog team.
Do you went to Heart Lake in the winter?
Spring. (In the spring toward the fall?) Beaver hunting that time.
Now is, it was in the fall instead this year.
How many years, since long time. Her daughter went up too.
I didn’t go up because I’m sickly.
They flew up this year?
I’m getting old.
Is the lake, the lake’s good now? There’s no big fish in the lake? It’s good? No...
She got lots of talaarit [rainbow trout]. [?] What are talaarit again?
What do they call those fish again?
(Who?) Talaarit. (Who?) Trout in the lakes.
Lake trout.
Small ones. (Yes.) We’re fishing. (Yes.)
[?] small one.
But no creatures in there, like, no stories anymore?
Sometime, her youngest brother... but we’re from mountainside.
He saw the something bubbling the water.
And then he saw lots of spots.
Down, way down, it’s clear. You know the clear water?
Clear water?
Yes, way down there, he saw the spots, [?black].
When was that?
Almost jump up.
This time? This trip?
No, long time.
Oh, long time?
Her brother, when she was like... she’s in hospital now.
So, did people get scared and stop going there, or people always went there?
But me, I’m scared I might eat airplane.
Really, I’m scared we might eat.
You ever, you or Wassilie ever hear of a stone face on top of a mountain by Kiseralik?
Stone head, face?
No, I never go Kiillaraliin.
Can you ask him? A stone head by Kiseralik, does he know? Can you ask?
What head?
Stone, rock, on top of a mountain.
You never heard, huh? (I don’t know. I don’t know it.)
Did you know a Old Man Reed that a mine up on the Kiseralik?
No.
I always went up [?], always [?] ’cause I would...
Only went up to...
’Cause I would, yeah.
One time, he went up to Kiillaraliin, but always raining.
Summer stories we’ve had, the people go up to Kiseralik all the time, but they were afraid to go to Heart Lake
’Cause there’s supposed to be a creature over there, so they never did go to Kiseralik, I mean, to Heart Lake.
We talked to Fanny, Fanny.
Yes. (Yes.)
When she was young, her brother, David Jackson, long time, she went up that way.
Look, I’ll show you Kiillaraliin Lake.
Where?
In Bethel.
I heard about them recently.
(I don’t understand them, you see.) Yes, I don’t understand them.
Yes.
We’ve probably started rolling now.
Wait.
William, please quickly say where you were born, and how old you are now.
Okay, I was born in 1915 long ago
When the Kuskokwim here was peaceful, and people traveled by rowing.
And they’d row to go fishing. There were no boat motors.
How old are you now as you remember it, as you know it?
I think I’m 75.
Also say your name in Yup’ik.
Callerkuaq.
Callerkuaq? (Yes.)
I see.
Also, please tell us about your first job when you were young.
I was part of the Elders of the church. I was a preacher in church.
And to the young people, I was a leader for the Young People.
And after that, I went into the could, IRA Council, back around ’43.
And from then on, I never stopped working with the tribal council regulations.
And as we Yupiit live here, I especially know that traditional instruction too.
And these too... I wasn’t a student.
And the federal government, the Territory of Alaska, I also observed its laws.
And I would study those by watching those who knew the laws.
These days, about the problem of us Yupiit, alcohol
What it was like back then, it’s still closed now in Bethel or in villages.
Please talk about what it was like, and how it’s different today.
In 1930, I first heard about someone having an accident in the water.
And I saw that alcohol had gotten him.
Then after that, I also heard about someone who shot himself under the influence of alcohol.
It was long after. I think it was a year after.
Also, for a long time after that, I also heard about a person who was missing in the spring when the ice broke up.
And when they found him in the summer, we went downriver to go see him.
Those were the first victims of alcohol.
Then from here on out to now, it happens a lot.
These boys are [dying] at a very fast rate.
And when it was open, it really was like they were dropping rapidly.
Especially now, it’s especially awful in our current day.
Sometimes, I sleep in fear because these young people are distressing.
What can you instruct us about that, and how we can help someone with that addiction?
For those with that problem, addiction, they say this is the first: love.
And even if they heavily abuse it, don’t condemn them.
Instead, treat them no different with the love of our ancient way of life, our ancestors’ tradition.
It turns out, we can’t completely eradicate that as we live.
Some think that people won’t socialize with them.
We must also talk to them like this about their lives’, you know, traditional wisdom.
Now, when someone with an addiction says this: "I want to quit. I don’t want to drink anymore,"
Some of us answer them like this: "I do admonish you. You don’t listen."
How would you, how would you instruct us to answer that person who is eager [to quit] like that?
One who is eager [to quit] like that must believe what I said.
Sometimes, I see someone who truly does end up quitting.
But now, some can’t quit.
I work with alcohol [addiction] through the tribal court. Sometimes, there are nine boys.
But we work with them through our court.
It’s very good. l like it.
But also, those small students who are this big
I can bring them in together there without any sentence, but talk to them as was our ancestors’ custom.
But these, an older one at 20 years, who’s 20 years old
To me, I cannot work with him as those children there in our Yup’ik court.
But we will not ignore one who needs that, but bring them downriver if we’re wary.
Now, I can speak about what I know and what I’ve experienced.
You just said that you tell the children or young people about the traditional wisdom that you used to hear.
Please bring forth that traditional wisdom you used to hear.
This, this is what it’s like: "My son, obey your father and mother. Obey them, so that you will live."
That’s traditional wisdom for those [children] who aren’t big.
Also tell them this: when the time to go to bed has come for them to go home right away.
They say that after midnight, in our way of life
They say that after midnight, a person’s behavior splits.
Their mind will get an idea, [s]he will go into a house.
[S]he will have nothing [but mischief] to do after midnight.
That’s something that our ancestors also spoke of.
Any other important thing that you want to say
It may be traditional instruction, an admonishment, or from our Yup’ik culture, the culture of [our] people long ago.
Please speak about it now. Say what you want.
Back in our ancestors’ culture, there was nothing except for the community house.
They would instruct us there in the community house.
But also, when I’d go into a house, I’d stand back at the door.
Someone from here would say, "Dear one back there," calling me by an endearing term.
And from the handle at the exit, we couldn’t step anywhere or run out.
Now, I don’t come across anyone giving instruction anymore.
In our current day, I don’t come across that anymore.
Why is that the case?
It’s an ancient traditional from long ago.
Like this, our traditional Yup’ik instructions
Even over a hundred years, it doesn’t change, and doesn’t sow discord.
Instead, you can speak of peace, you can admonish a person to be peaceful.
Also, villages like this, small villages would have leaders, one elder who was an advisor.
[S]he was like a great leader.
Every village, I used to see them back then including downriver in Napaskiak, these villages, even what they call Ayalpiit downriver.
You also just said that young people don’t hear traditional wisdom anymore, that these people don’t [instruct them] anymore.
Why is that the case?
Since’ it’s like that, this state is going to take over us, superceding us like this.
We started this, what is called the Yup’ik Nation.
I call it the Ancient Way of Life.
I can say what I just said, "Obey your father and mother. And quit living according to your every whim."
Now, it’s becoming stronger and better to me downriver in Akiachak.
It was almost lost.
Then Willie who is a boy, I’m not sure how far apart you are, probably the same age as you.
We’ve [gone over] our language and traditional instructions with his peerson, his peers are also in my council.
In my mind, I don’t worry about them now.
But I still haven’t taught them about the stars and winds for survival.
Much of how to survival has still not been brought up.
You’ve made me curious about survival with the stars and winds. Please talk about it.
I know about [these] four winds very well. They are the harbingers of fish.
I know when the fish are coming int he summer through these because I would always fish.
And I know if they’re going to be abundant.
One wind direction heralds no fish: the one they call [?kanavaq].
You may fish, but they won’t bite.
Those are [the winds].
You must also observe the stars up there.
Up in the middle of the sky, there are seven rotating stars to measure time.
When these seven rotate like this, if it faces the day[break] over there, if it stops and faces it
A star will rise, the only biggest and bright one, pulling up Erenret [Days - constellation?].
Then when it ends, Erenret appear.
That was when our ancestors would start stirring.
They said it was time [to get up] now. Also, it was because they had no clocks, wouldn’t see clocks.
Also, if there are a lot like this, it will be windy. They are connected to the wind.
And even if it’s windy from that direction, if the star goes past and there’s a falling star, the wind will shift to there.
These people they call scientists who are knowledgeable about fish.
Though we didn’t have those, we are knowledgeable about them. Since I always fished, I know them.
And I also know the ones who’ve stayed downriver in the currents. They are easy to tell.
Those are things I was taught, what I learned.
Also, when there kept being strong winds int he spring, they said it brought fish.
How was that?
Those were things they observed back then. It’s good to observe the world, our world.
Okay, if you want to say anything else, or if you have nothing left to say...
I’m very thankful now. I yearn to join you like this to speak about our ancient traditions.
And that guy, you know, who is he again? Twitchell.
He wanted to record me, but since I didn’t go downriver, he didn’t.
Willie...
Willie, what’s your view on the unification issue?
The unification issue has been a topic of discussion on AVCP’s convention, I would guess for the last four to five years.
I think it has made a slow progress, but nevertheless, it takes time to work on issues of relevance that affect the whole region.
Just recently, prior to the convention, we had what we call a Unification Forum Meeting in Emmonak where the regional non-profits were invited.
And at that time, we discussed with Nunam Kellutestii, Ceńaliulriit, YKHC, AVCP, and Yupiit Nation
About the unification process that AVCP has undertaken based up the directions that they received from Kipnuk’s convention resolution.
At that time, we also understand that not many of the people in the villages really understood what the unification meant.
The unification that we’re talking about is the development of the regional tribal government.
So at the recommendations at the Emmonak forum meeting was that
The non-profits each shall adopt a supporting resolution in concept.
And we did receive commitment from the organizations that were represented there.
I believe one of the things that this convention will talk about, how to select people to sit on what it’s called, the Constitutional Committee.
The Constitutional Committee’s task would be to review how the other Indigenous people in the United States, for that matter the whole world, organize under their own types of government.
As stated, as I stated earlier, not everybody understands the tribal government issues.
So, one of the tasks of this committee would be to educate the people.
By that, I mean they will be traveling to regional centers to conduct series of public meetings
To get people to understand and up to speed of what we would like to achieve under the unification plan.
I think one important thing about the unificationplan is
That the organizations and their boards are not the individuals and the authority to develop this government.
Ultimately, the people in the villages, those that have the voting rights will be the ones to vote on the issue
And then proceed with the development of a government.
You think you’re going to see lot of support after this unification forum?
I believe so, based on some of the comments that I heard.
There’s still a lot of questions that needs to be brought out and answered
And we had a little bit of taste of that yesterday when I gave the Yupiit Nation report.
I think especially the elders have already understood the concept
But it’s, from some of the comments that I’ve heard from the elders is that
These young people that are bilingual aren’t too sure whether to go with the old ways or the new ways.
I think in developing a regional government under the unification process
Both the old ways and the new ways needs to be incorporated
So that whatever comes about would best represent the people, and work for the people.
One other question...
Even if you don’t prepare? is it ready?
I don’t think AVCP is boycotting not to rejoin AFN
And, it’s on the agenda.
I think what AVCP wants is true representation of our desires
If we are to go back to AFN.
And, I think using the example of the 1991 process
AVCP had some specific issues that we wanted AFN to address.
But, on the 11th hour, our concerns weren’t heard.
And for that reason, we did not go back to AFN, among others.
That was the primary reason.
If AVCP is to rejoin AFN
The AVCP leadership needs to sit down with AFN leadership
And discuss how representation would have to occur.
And, AVCP needs to be involved in such a statewide organization.
Do you have any additional comments you want to make?
I guess as far as the convention here, the 25th Annual Convention of AVCP
This, I view as a turning point where our people are beginning to understand
That we need to work together as a united group of villages.
Whatever form the unification comes out of, we need to support it individually and organizationally in order for it to succeed
For our desires.
Thank you.
You should’ve spoke Yup’ik.
It’s okay, [s]he just covered it.