Were we not sad over our loss, we wouldn’t have killed that animal that ate.
Afterwards, the people ate the rest of it.
Way in the...
We also ate what had been eaten. We ate it because we had nothing else to eat.
There’s a lot of places to hunt up there in the mountains.
Here’s the first: Evsairniit is a place to hunt.
And the next: a hunting place is going up from Nacarkarniar.
And the third: Ilutuqacuk, my lands.
(And from Kangerpakmailiat.) Yes.
Then Naqerpak. Then Nurtuutaraq.
Lots of camps [?] upriver.
Then Qanirtuum Qagatii.
Way of up there, [?].
They call it Naqerpak where it goes it goes here to Kuinerram Qagatii.
And on this side of Kuinerram Qagatii, inland from the lake, Equgniilnguut is also hunting grounds.
And then downriver near its mouth, there’s a hunting ground that they hunt in for a long time.
And then every single man from Kuiggluk goes there in the fall.
They would only return when Christmas was nigh.
And up there where they call it Naqailnguq is also a hunting ground where they hunt for a long time.
I know all of the hunting grounds up there.
It’s called Ingriúrluq. The mountain is called Ingriúrluq.
And downriver, it’s called Elngurtuliar.
And across from them is Qikertat [Islands].
And these two inland from Elngurtuliar, the upright boulders are called Napanguliik.
And beneath them, they call them Ingrilukaak. That is also a hunting ground.
And then up there across from it is Iluvagtuq. They call it Iluvagtuq. That’s also a hunting ground.
And then upriver and to the side, the moutnain Ulurrugnaq is steep.
It’s slope goes toward the water.
And in the center is a grassy area. The grass grows upriver.
In the center of those plants, the elders say
They say that a person went up.
And then when he reached the middle, he became wary. He was wary and squat down below.
He couldn’t do anything, couldn’t go on.
They say that the center of that mountain up there is a grassy area to this day.
Then upriver, they call the small mountain Atsartuliar. It’s also a hunting ground.
And the the small river inland from that small mountain, the small river going inland is called Kuignayugpak.
Now that is a hunting ground where they hunt for a long time.
And then, I’m going to go to the Qanirtuk River.
On the banks of the Qanirtuk River... what do they call the mountain again?
Ulurrugnaq. That’s also a hunting ground.
And upriver from there... what is it again? Cayagtuli? No.
I don’t know them. Is that all?
No, there’s more. There’s a lot more.
And then up there is Ircaqurrnaq.
That’s also a hunting ground. It’s called Ircaqurrnaq.
And then toward the water, there’s a similar mountain. It’s called Ircaqurrnayagaq.
And then over and upriver are Evsiaksugaak. They also hunt not far from there.
And here is Qerrirtaq.
Qerrirtaq is also a hunting ground where they can hunt for a long time.
And then upriver is Cingikeggliq.
The mountin with a sharp upward summit is called Cingikeggliq.
And on this side, they mountain going down to Kuiggluk is named Canirngalria.
And then on the other side is Qupun. It’s called Qupun.
And then over at the end, it’s name is Canyon, Kuignayuggaq.
And on the other side here is Nacarkarniarun.
Now that place where they go up is a hunting ground.
And then on the other side of Nacarkarniarun...
[?Don’t use your hand.]
What?
Evsairniik. They call it Evsairniik.
They also hunt there for a long time.
Yeah, take a break, rest, stop for a mintue. Yeah, stop. (Okay, you can stop.)
I’ve just talked about all of those hunting grounds.
I don’t know how to talk in English.
Has he mentioned any stories of big creatures?
It has big fish.
Yes, he just talked about it. He already did.
Did he talk about, anything about the skeleton, ribs, skeletons on the beach?
It’s long time.
Okay, did he talk about that though? (Yes.) The skeletons on the beach? (Yes.) Okay.
[?] the father, her father, long time, the bones.
White bones? (Yes, yes.)
He get big hole. (Right.) In and out, the kids are playing there.
That’s the story we heard.
She said long grass, that’s he’s on ground place, that old place.
Do you know which side of the lake those were on? North side?
No. (South side?) Kwethluk side.
Kwethluk side of the lake?
That’s east side?
Yaa.
It faces this side. Yes.
Kiillaraliin, Heart Lake, Kwethluk, this side.
This side, that’s where the bones were? (Yes.)
Yes, where your map? I’lls how you. Where’s your map?
Okay, George can you get that? It’s back in there, top one.
Toward it on the map, you know it goes like this toward Kwethluk?
Right or left? Right?
Where’ Kwethluk again? Here’s Kwethluk.
Yes, it’s this side.
We always stay this side.
There’s Kuikayak over there.
Can you say this aloud?
Here’s Kuikayak.
Yes. Crooked Creek Mountain. Yes, here it is.
Where’s Killalin? Here it is.
The river over there... (Here’s Kuigceńaq.)
Upper Fall is Igceńaq, Qurrlurta.
(Yes.) Eskimo name, Qurrlurta.
Here’s Taryaqvagtuli.
Yes, here it is down there on this side.
It’s on this side. (Yes, it’s there on this side.)
Evon Qugg’aq, [?].
You know stories, or?
No, it’s older than.
She’s teaching for hunting, walking.
No stove, just tent in the winter.
When you went to Heart, like, did you walk?
No, by plane.
Oh, this time? Long time, a long time ago, though, did you walk?
Dogs. (Dogs.) Dog team.
She went Heart Lake in the winter?
Spring. (In the spring for the thaw?) Beaver hunting, that kind.
Now it’s, only in the the fall this year.
How many years, that was long time. Her daughter went up there.
I think [?] sickness.
They flew up this year?
Is the lake, the lake’s good now? There’s no big fish in the lake? It’s good? No...
She god lots of talaarit [rainbow trout]. What are talaarit again?
What do they call those fish again?
Who? Who?
The trout in lakes.
No big... (Citegnat.)
Small ones we’re fishing. (Citegnat.) We’re fishing, we’re eating small ones.
But no creatures in there like the stories anymore.
Sometime, her youngest brother, but way up from the moutnainside, he saw something bubbling the water.
And then he saw lots of spots.
Down, way down, it’s clear, you know, the clearest water?
Clear water?
Yes, way down there, he saw the spots, black.
When was that?
Almost jump up.
This time? This trip?
No, long time, her brother, when she was...
She’s in hospital now.
So did people get scared and stop going there, or people always went there?
But me, I’m scared I might eat airplane.
Really, I’m scared. We might eat.
You ever, you or Wassilie ever hear of a stone face on top of a mountain by Kiseralik?
Stone head, face?
No, I never go there, Kiillaraliin.
What head?
Stone, rock, on top of a mountain.
I think, no, I don’t know it.
Did you know Old Man Reed had a mine up on the Kiseralik?
[?] I always went up, always [?].
Only went up to...
One time, he wen tup to Kiillaraliin, but always rain.
Some stories we’ve had, the people go up to Kiseralik all the time, but they were afraid to go to Heart Lake, ’cause there’s supposed to be a creature over there. So they never did go to Kiseralik, I mean, to Heart Lake.
We talked to Fanny, Fanny. (Yes.) Yes.
When she was young, her brother, David Jackson?
Look, I’ll show you Kiillaraliin. Take it.