You see, we were like this…
…some of it from Oscar and the other.
Let me speak about it like this.
I can’t ignore part of the Bible that I learned.
There is a lot I don’t know.
One of the men confessed to me.
When I was a lay pastor, one of them said in a confession
That he had a dream the night before.
He didn’t like his dream.
He said that he saw himself as very fat like this.
He was strong, tough, and fat.
And then, he said that he saw one of children whom he loved,
the eldest son, after looking at himself.
He said [his son] was very skinny.
He was pitiful.
And his bones were only covered by skin.
He said that he envied himself because he loved him so much.
Envying himself,
“Why am I fat? He should be fat.”
Do youpl understand it? Youpl might not understand it.
And then the one who had the dream understood this:
You know the entire Bible, and you know how
one should be on the earth.
Yet even though you’re like that, you don’t instruct your children
They’re skinny because you don’t instruct them.
You are fat in your knowledge.
Well? I digressed with that.
Am I in accordance with what they’re saying?
And then, I don’t know English.
I took Anitia’s place.
How is “promote” translated?
I don’t understand what “promote the heritage” says here.
(To bring it forth.)
Please explain it to me.
I’m hard of hearing.
(To bring it forth.)
To bring forth a way of life, right?
Okay, let’s [cover] a small part of it.
We, us for me personally
One of them told me yesterday, it may have been Ayapruca’ar
From our time, it seems that starting from us, where a Yup’ik
is going is changing. Right?
Our descendants here are becoming Westernized.
They’re becoming Westernized, and some
understand Yup’ik anymore.
They’ve started only speaking completely in English.
And then even if we [teach] what a person must be like
living a Yup’ik life
How are we going to teach those who’ve learned English?
Will our dear children be able to enthusiastically begin
[living] our lives where we struggled?
We would travel with dog teams, and we would gather wood
by pushing sleds in the Akula region.
We also used to travel without dogs.
Also, our shovels were not convenient,
and our axes were not convenient.
We, yourpl elders
And when I imagine our elders, they probably struggled a lot more.
As we became more Westernized and using their tools,
it seems that things have been getting easier.
And now, they’ve started reaching far places right away
where we used to strive to reach starting early in the morning.
Well? Do youpl understand this?
I might speak too excessively.
Later… let me tell you this:
I’m not fluent in English. I’ve received a letter
from here concerning entertainment.
George [?] wrote asking if I wanted to entertain
here at the Elders’ Conference.
Because I didn’t know what it meant,
I thought they would give me one of these to say
“Following our legacies in our future.”
Thinking that I was going to be given one of these to say,
I agreed to the one who asked me.
This is probably what it is.
And now, I understand that it’s a form of fun.
As I’ve been watching those before me
when it comes to this entertainment
They sing, and even Yup’ik dance.
I don’t sing. I have a bad voice.
Also, I used to Yup’ik, but I don’t now.
But if I have to do something funny later at 2:00,
I can make youpl smile.
That’s all from me. It’s enough.
…years have passed.
I had started understanding our ancestors’ traditional wisdom
as I’ve gone in life.
Now, they’ve also started referring to the Spirit of the Universe
as [the Christian] God.
This qilak is now also the name of [Heaven] above.
…when villages started going the wrong way,
that shaman would steer them the right way.
But because I started being afraid of myself…
It used to be called a water offering a long time ago.
Also, this way of food or water offerings…
…we evidently used to offer food or water for the deceased.
That’s what I started to understand.
I’ve ended up talking about them since I’ve held them for so long.
Our belief…
…for that reason, [we do that] to our young people.
We have apparently stopped insetruction them
because we might teach them something bad.
Because some of us here have different beliefs,
our traditional custom…
…but since we’ve started holding meetings since last year
Priests who have different beliefs meet and have started understanding
our ancient way of life more and more.
Including abstinence.
Youpl know me.
In my earliest memories of the Kuskokwim here,
the Kuskokwim was our main river.
Alciq is my Yup’ik name.
And then from what I know, I talked yesterday about
using it for support.
We people of the land have this extremely ancient instruction
as our support.
And our support should be respected, and should always be respected.
For us elders today, that cause for respect is there.
That thing we must respect supports the people of the earth.
They also know who supports them.
Because we have always been supported by this ancient thing
And it supports our lives, we dear healthy ones here
are standing.
And the way we are towards a person’s name,
we consider his Yup’ik name important.
We also consider the Yup’ik language important
because we are Yupiit.
I’m very thankful that we call each other [by our Yup’ik names]
among ourselves.
And then, we Yupiit know this:
Welcoming each other, and treating each other
the way we should treat each other well.
That’s why this way we are is extremely important among us.
It’s need for respect is always like that,
and it should always be respected.
That’s why for our descendats, the young people here
From they education, they learn how to speak English to each other.
And indeed, what they have learned later
Does one first learn from what he has been taught
by his parents?
And then they learn to be Westernized later.
That is also in that young Yup’ik person.
It’s in him since he first learned from his parents.
This Westernization is also in him since it was taught to him.
We know this:
When a person takes another, he takes him and his hands…
…we [always] exercise as we were taught.
When they follow their Yup’ik dancing tradition,
they’re happy, thankful, and they laugh.
There you have it.
Truly, these knowledgable people [must use]
what we are living now
They must work to oppose these Caucasians with what they learned.
They must work for the good [of our people].
And truly, it’s exciting and good to work for the good [of our people].
This bringing forth [goodness], even if they didn’t
get it right away a long time ago
But when they know later, all of us people are thankful
when they find out [about this goodness].
And now, some of us are preparing good things
that they will use.
And we elders [must do] that
And when two, three, or several men are together
When we discuss what they are preparing,
it’s like we’re spreading it
Because their work inspires others.
And then we must prepare those good things
that we will use so that they will inspire others.
Thank you.
…[some of] these people these days are not like
those in my earliest memories.
They even have a shorter life span.
Back in my earliest memories, I used to see old women and men
Ones who only walked supporting themselves
with their knees that didn’t stretch out.
Yet they had no walking staffs.
How old would they be?
They were certainly over 100 years old.
Several who are over 100 years old that I used to see
are not like those.
Their [legs] can stretch, and they walk with canes.
They don’t support themselves with their knees when they walk.
I wonder what makes us lack old men these days?
The Bible very clearly tells us this:
Because we disobey our parents, mothers, and fathers,
our lives get cut short.
We only do what we think is fun.
Our parents and mothers back then talked to us as if they were
scolding us because they wanted us to live long lives.
Turns out, they talked to us like that because they loved us.
Let me touch on what I heard about food and water offerings.
They used to do that a long time ago, and I used to see it.
However, my parents would not make food or water offerings
like that because they had already understood.
Food and water offerings were evidently done like this:
they prayed to that person who had died.
They prayed for good lives, lives without sickness,
or they prayed to and entreated a dead person
Because they were not instruction on [religious] entreaty.
But when Jesus arrived, he said that he had become the way.
If we entreat through him, he will give us what we want.
That’s what it was like, a form of prayer.
Our ancestors know God as the Spirit of the Universe.
But because Jesus appeared recently,
our ancestors didn’t know him.
They said that when they first heard about Jesus,
they would say in reply
“Why is that person’s life so important?”
It was because they didn’t understand it.
That is how I understand it.
And because we’ve stopped doing one thing that makes us
live longer, especially these days.
Our ancestors back then, when young women or men wanted to live
long lives, they would watch over their land here.
They didn’t leave garbage in it, and they cleaned up
the areas in settlements.
They would dump that garbage in one place
where no one had trod.
That was what our ancestors instructed too.
Cleaning up the land here was [one of] their instructions.
That is the meaning of our ancestors’ long lives back then.
Because God owns this land, he doesn’t want us to
leave it trashed or polluted.
It must be left pristine like our ancesotrs.
And if we’re like that, we have traditional wisdom from our ancestors
They said that if we’re like that, we will live long lives.
Our bodies will also be standing strong.
And they said that even if those around us are sick,
that sickness will not affect us if we’re like that.
That is God’s gratitude for people keeping his land pristine
that he has lent us.
They say that God’s gratitude toward that person
is having him live a long life.
And on top of that, what they call great hunters or those who are good
at catching animals, both men and women.
God apparently rewards a person like that
who cleans up this land.
It’s an ancient traditional instruction to this day.
And we heard, “Honor your father and mother so that you will
live long in this land that Jehovah your god has given you.”
If you are obedient like that, we should not hide this
from our children…