Is that my mic? It is my mic.
This one’s yours, this one. (Oh, I see.)
Ready? (Yes. Maybe, well, yes, okay.)
For the record, talking to Johnny K. Guy from Kwethluk.
Qavarliar? (Qavarliaq, yes.)
Alright, Qavarliaq, okay.
It starts with a K [in the old orthography]. [?] (Okay. Okay.)
Now, when you were young back then… (You mean what we used to eat?)
No, what did youpl go to the mountains for?
Our late father, Guy, used to work with reindeer in the mountains.
He would work herding reindeer.
Did those people have their own reindeer that they owned themselves?
Did those reindeer also have identifying marks?
They used to say those reindeer belonged to the government
But they would mark reindeer ears in the fall.
They also got paid for [herding] reindeer.
They would get paid, but they would never appear [in person].
I see.
Were there a lot of reindeer back then?
They said there weren’t too many at first, then they increased later and got dirty.
The [herded] government reindeer.
They also got blood from these caribout coming here from Nome.
Why have they depleted now?
I don’t know. Wolves probably depleted them.
There are now a lot of reindeer that have come over from Nome.
Because they’ve increased over there, they’ve come here.
And then, please talk about these… I can’t.
What you were born in time to see, the community house.
They used to have Yup’ik dance festivals here with a huge community house in Kwethluk, over there in the middle upriver from the old church.
They had a huge community house and would have Yup’ik dance festivals.
Would the old men talk about traditional instructions there?
I haven’t heard them.
But they would also go to dance festivals in Akiachak from here.
At least in the winter and summer.
Would they invite them?
They invited them. The people from Akiachak invited the people from here to go make a community house.
And then they made a huge community house in Akiachak tying it with [?].
What would they do when they went to the community house?
They Yup’ik danced. They would have a feast that evening, bring in various things like this
Hides, hides for containers, and caribou.
They brought those to dance festivals, including animal traps, various things, and cloth.
Have you heard about wars a long time ago?
I used to hear about them, but I don’t know them.
They say they had wars here against their fellow Yupiit even going upriver on the Kuskokwim.
But because I’m not knowledgable, I don’t know about them because they didn’t talk about them too much.
Were you born in time to see Aavaaq who used to live here?
I was born in time to see him. Aavaaq used to have a house downriver across and downriver from the fishcamp on the riverbank.
Well, was he a healer?
He didn’t speak, but he talked with gestures.
He didn’t know how to talk.
Was he not a shaman?
He wasn’t a shaman.
He liked to make little things. He even made wooden hairbrushes.
He always made little things.
Yourpl river Kuiggluk here, where did youpl come up with that name?
I don’t know from where, but I heard it’s always been called Kuiggluk.
They say that these houses are on the old Kuiggluk [river path]
That old river inland from Kwethluk.
They say it was an old river.
When you were young, would they instruct you on things you would need to use in the wilderness when you were going to go hunt?
They used to instruct me to dress warmly
That I had to travel in warm clothes. They also said I would be cold as I wandered in the wilderness.
Did they also tell youpl to bring things that would save youpl?
Yes, we would bring things, and have some food provisions in case anything happened as we traveled in the wilderness.
What about walking staffs that some people talk about?
We always had staffs too. They said that we should cross rivers prodding it like this in case we should fall into the water.
Yes, these days, those old pieces of traditional wisdom
The people back then used to adhere to them.
Yes, our ancestors who were born before us used staffs.
They also probably hunted with staffs because they were quick on foot.
What about these young people, children, these days, should they listen to those pieces of Yup’ik wisdom?
They should hear about them, and walk around with staffs.
But they don’t seem to do that. Some don’t have staffs.
To you, these young people these days
These children that you are seeing these days, are they more mischievous to you than before?
They’re not like before.
They look like they’re getting more mischievous.
They don’t obey their admonishments like before.
Why does it seem to be like that?
I don’t know. It’s probably their minds when they have the idea to do that.
They’ve also probably become like this because their parents, mothers, and fathers do not teach them anymore.
Probably.
They don’t teach their children too much anymore.
They sometimes admonish them against doing that and against using those.
They admonish them, but they don’t listen.
I wonder why these young people are getting disobedient?
It’s probably because they don’t listen to traditional wisdom and refuse instruction.
Even though they are told not to do it, they do.
These schools are probably exacerbating that for them.
These schools also get destroyed.
These descendants of before were not like that.
But now, they destroy even schools, various things.
They’ve also started destroyed unoccupied buildings.
Some of the young people from here probably do not understand Yup’ik anymore.
Because the little ones now always speak English.
Consider that [they spoke] Yup’ik before, not knowing English and then they started going to school.
And then the people from upriver do not speak Yup’ik too much because they’re Upper Kuskokwim Athabascans.
But even though they speak English, do they really understand when they speak English?
For you, should our speaking in Yup’ik, our Yup’ik language not be lost?
Our Yup’ik language should not be lost.
Couple it with English, translating what is said in English into Yup’ik
Because they ask us to translate like that, and these Caucasians who aren’t Yup’ik like us ask for translations.
And some Yupiit ask for others to speak to Caucasians for them.
Some of the old people say this:
They said that when these churches first came, they ended up reading these written Qaneryarat, what they call the Bible.
They said they read and started understanding them.
They realized that they were not different from the old Yup’ik wisdom and traditional isntructions.
Is that true for you?
It’s true for me.
When they obey those instructions that the ancestors taught
When our earth here was not heavily populated back then, the land was probably thin
Or the people probably talked gauging the weather.
Should we not forget passing on traditional wisdom, our Yup’ik way of passing on wisdom to our young people here?
A person should not forget traditional wisdom from his father or from other people.
They should talk about it, traditional wisdom about nature, traditional wisdom about nature.
They’re probable the voice of [nature].
Okay, we’re rolling. (Rolling, rolling, okay.)
The people of old talked about these great hunters.
Are there scarce any great hunters these days?
These days, they’re not like [traditional] great hunters.
And they don’t go hunting at night, early in the morning, anymore.
They’re not like great hunters anymore.
Back then, they probably called those who were good at catching animals great hunters.
They would travel to the wilderness, and go early to far away places on foot.
They probably referred to those who were good at catching animals great hunters.
And then, you know our subsistence way of life?
It seems that the laws of our Caucasians counterparts is destroying it.
Is that not good to you?
It’s because these Caucasians who are not Yup’ik are partially destroying it somehow.
They even have laws against hunting too many animals.
They have laws against [hunting] some animals we eat.
And they sometimes [punish] many who catch a lot.
For you, would it be good if we Yupiit who live on our lands started governing ourselves?
They have leaders like this:
They are governed by leaders from out of state who tell these villages to elect leaders
And they tell those other villages to elect leaders too.
They tell them to meet and govern what they should do.
These school that have started appearing in villages.
They’ve already started [appearing].
For you, are they helpful for Yup’ik youth?
They will be helpful if they don’t speak or understand English
Because it won’t be helpful if they don’t understand what they should do.
When they don’t understand, they don’t know what to do.
What about this Yup’ik language?
Our Yup’ik language, we Yupiit speak the Yup’ik language.
And then these Caucasians ask to be taught Yup’ik like us
Or they ask for translations from a Yup’ik speaking the Yup’ik langauge.
They say there a lot of people who don’t speak the same language.
And then… what was I just going to ask you?
Can you stop it for a second? I forgot what I was [going to ask].
Now, this is the last question I’m going to ask you:
These young people from here, or even from other surrounding villages
Do you want to tell them anything that they should remember for the future or that they would use now?
I’m not sure what I should say to them.
I don’t really know since I’m not knowledgable.
I thought you might want them to hear something from their parents.
Parents must admonish their children against doing [bad] things
Or even if they’re not parents, they say they should teach them even if they’re not young.
Is speaking Yup’ik beneficial?
This Yup’ik language is beneficial for Yupiit like this.
Caucasians ask to be taught Yup’ik, and Yupiit ask to be taght English.
That’s why they have school to teach both Yup’ik and English.
This is all the questions I have. This is all. (I see.)
Thank you for agreeing to go on camera. (You’re welcome.)
Okay. (Thank you.) You’re welcome.
Please take this off [of him]. There you go. (Sorry.) Poor guy.
Thank you very much. (Thank you very much.) You’re welcome.
Did [I] [?]. (Yes.)
I didn’t speak very well. (It’s okay, it was good.)