...what they were going to do.
And I’d say, "Oh no, I won’t appear on TV."
It turned out that looking at these [people] in our day, it’s distressing.
If we stay without saying anything, we won’t [accomplish] anything.
I will want to ask you questions. I will ask you, or as we go, I’ll tell you.
You said that a long time ago, we didn’t have any [Western] things (Yes, yes.) didn’t have anything [?]. (We were destitute.)
How is our relations, you know, we who are related to each other
How is has us being too Westernized affected our relations? Those...
Are we rolling? (Yes.) Okay.
Let’s see, how shall I say it?
In your observation, are our relations, how these families interact with [cultural] relations
Is their abundance of wealth negatively affecting it, or how?
Just your observation. And if you haven’t thought about it, it’s okay if you don’t speak on it.
I have no idea.
What was I saying again?
Oh yes, also [?to diligentely do things] in the house...
(Daughter’s places.) Oh, daughters. (Yes.)
Yes, then because those people back then used to say this, I remember:
Our female children can copy what we mothers work on.
It’s true.
If I keep sewing, my daughters can copy it, and sew.
But these days, this schooling is such a conundrum.
I will not praise my children. I can use them as examples.
I also have one child now who goes to college. It’s been many years now.
[S]he would drop out, as they call it.
Look at these, what’s going on with them?
And, you see, [s]he’s living without knowing how to work.
And [s]he never wants to work, only read.
Then also as an example, it’s okay to use them as examples.
One of my children would be disinclined to go to school.
He loved being active. The boy liked to work, outside work.
I know that he liked to pack ice when he was small.
He never let me go without water. He was never lazy.
I would keep telling him to, you know, because he was my only provider.
I see him these days, knowing really well how to work, outside too.
From the start, without waiting to become a man, but one who keeps doing it from the start will train himself as they say in English.
I can also make an example of that with one of my children.
Now, he’s the youngest, the youngest out of my many children.
I depend on him to do outside chores.
He would work like an adult, knowing really well.
There you have it.
I’m telling these stories as examples.
We can learn things through what we see through our eyes.
You know, my mother never used to clean up, only sew.
It was because there was nothing to clean up in our house.
But I just said that at Cakayak and his spouse’s, since they were Caucasian, [?they’d find things amiss?].
But it was like it is here. There were no phones.
Did they have TV’s?
I speak of those, what I learned of those from them.
When I went to school, it seemed that I didn’t learn anything. It was because my schooling was too little, too scant.
Even though I suffered wanting to go to school right away, my age, since they used to get husbands young back then.
They had me take a husband, and I was young.
And when we were going to get a marriage license here
That one who issued marriage licenses was called a commissioner.
Sometimes now, I say, "That darned official lied."
I was 16. I think I was 16.
After he said he couldn’t give us the marriage license, he wrote on it and brought it.
He falsely stated that I was 18 and gave us the marriage license.
He added to my age.
Now, I go by that, how my age was increased.
I’m certainly younger than that.
But since, you know, they could use marriage licenses as proof, they fixed it with those documents when my spouse passed away.
I talk about that.
Apparently, the people back then would add years in the past.
These days, becoming an old woman, or a man takes a wife as an old man.
Or a woman takes a husband as an old woman these days.
Back then, did our ancestors think it was important for a child to get married?
Probably because they thought it important, my parents would have others encourage me [to marry] as well.
Look, back then, they would choose their husbands, examining their potential spouse’s behavior, and how much he works.
You know, they wouldn’t choose a dumb man.
These days, I should name it "tamian" [dumb man].
Some take husbands, and their husband doesn’t know how to do anything.
I’m not lying. Am I lying?
Or a man takes a [kazy] wife. There you have it.
I will not keep from talking about these true things.
Apparently, my parents sought a husband for me.
It turned out that my groom to be was young and was an expert in doing things. Nick, Nick O’Nick.
And when I married him, he was very young.
On our marriage license, our ages were, Nick 22, and me 18, when we got married.
My mother used to tell me this: I should work with him without being lazy. "He will provide for us."
She said my husband will provide for us.
My older brother got impaired with TB and couldn’t do anything.
And because I would be worried about my older brother, and when he dies... you see, we would ponder.
Though I was young, I’d ponder [upon such things].
And I’d think like this: my older brothers wife, "Do it, okay," because she encouraged me.
Then I started thinking like this, that I wouldn’t, because I loved someone else, being in love.
As [they] say these days, I’d probably say that I was loving another.
That other one was attractive. You see, I loved him.
Without having met my groom to be, however, I was intimidated by him.
Then because my mother, you see, would say to me, "He will proved for us. Look, our provider there can’t do anything."
Sometimes, you see...
They’d also tell us this: we should sit down and ponder for a while.
I would do that.
Sometimes, you see, I’d ponder like this: "If my older brother over there who’d tell me what to do dies, I will regret it."
You know, I already know how to worry at 16, as a little girl.
I’d go out to visit a lot.
You see, I would think like that. Then one day, I agreed.
Oh my, when I married him, you see, I was intimidated by my spouse.
I’d go to bed fully clothed like this beside him.
You know, they apparently undress and put on gowns or something to go to bed.
I’d go to bed fully clothed next to my spouse.
You see...
To my family downriver since they were downriver, and my husband upriver, upriver in a little village.
You know, they split inland.
When I’d go downriver to my family, I’d be reluctant to go back, you know, I wouldn’t want to return.
My mother would end up saying to me, "Go home already."
When I’d get tired, I’d go out. My mindset was, as they say in English, smash[ed].
Pity me, I’d go upriver to my husband’s.
I’d start going in, you see, to absolute silence. I’d go in and he’d already be in bed. I was so shameless. I was so shameless.
Then since I knew my spouse was lying here, I went to bed fully clothed beside him.
Oh my, when I married him and they got me, I went in, you see...
These days, a man takes a wife and doesn’t give anything to his wife.
I went in, you see, I think they used to do it long ago.
You see, there were these two huge cardboard boxes.
Then,you see, that girl, my husband’s older brother’s child, would take things out from there.
Their mother [said], "Look, there’s your bed." The bed, you see, was good things, good blankets, all new.
I was going to start the beginning.
They used to give them things like that.
You see, that girl would give me things from those cardboard [boxes].
She took out and gave me an atkuk, [a] fur parka.
You know, these days, fur parkas are expensive.
They were overwhelming.
She gave me a parka. And she put it by me, but I wasn’t thankful.
You know, because I didn’t want to take a husband.
After that, she also took out piluguuk, fur mukluks.
I took them and put them beside me.
You see, there were many things. [S]he gave them to me like that.
There you have it.
Then my spouse didn’t do that there in his family’s home.
They took me in the fall. The next spring, I didn’t want to go back with my family.
I used to do that.
And when I didn’t want to go back, my spouse wanted to move with me to a spring camp. I wouldn’t.
He left me and went.
Then I got happier with my family.
When he arrived in the spring, these people said that my husband was going to come to me and move in with my family.
When he did that, I was, you know, thankful.
Now again, my mother used to say to me, "He’ll be our provider."
He was going to come and move to take care of us.
Since I knew that, you know, I started [treating] him well, also because I used to always have my back turned to him.
And I started looking at him sometimes. He was very intimidating.
They may have been reserved around each other. I did that.
Then he moved in with us.
Oh my, I also didn’t get pregnenat right away because I wouldn’t let him touch me, and would go to bed and shut out the world.
And some mornings, my mother would say this to me: "Don’t harshly raise your hand."
Probably, you see... you know, men know that women raise their hands a certain way.
Sometimes, when he brought his arm like this, I would do this out of dislike.
My mother [said to me], "They don’t do that." It was because I didn’t know.
Evidently, everything has rules.
She said they don’t do that.
She said a man takes a wife to fool around with her.
I would get scared.
Then, you see, I was pregnant with Robert Nick, my child to be inland.
I got pregnant. When I got pregnant, you see, I finally started facing my husband face to face.
Nick is so wonderful.
Then when I got pregnant like that, I finally observed him [with] a Bible.
You see, my husband was always busy.
It turned out that it was because my parents’ choice was a hard worker.
[He] started always reading the Bible. He would always read the Bible every evening.
Then we had two children, Robert, Margaret, I think.
He became a pastor [at a] young [age].
He turned out to be wonderful. I can say how good he was.
He wouldn’t play out. We used to play out.
Now, there are places to play like [the] Teen Center, and others.
And when I’d go play, I’d never see my groom to be.
You see, since he was like that from the beginning, my parents wanted me to have him.
He started always reading the Bible. And not long after, he became a pastor. He became a pastor at a young age in Nunapitchuk.
And recently, he died while he was a pastor.
And he had nine children.
Wow, you see, he had such passion for that.
And while he was a pastor, me made that little trading post inland.
Before makiung it, he said he first went to the priests, the Moravian priests, and he said he also went to the priest in Kwethluk.
He was very knowledgeable, and he had absolutely no schooling.
Apparently, he asked them about working along with the trading post while he was a pastor.
And they gave him the okay.
That [place] inland was made only after being advised by those, Nick O’Nick Trading Post, these knowledgeable priests.
That’s what we were like.
Then we raised our children like that.
And he never did this even once with alcohol.
We went [to the city] over there several times after he’d gotten his trading post.
Though some have absolutely no schooling, they are very smart, will be very knowledgeable.
Now, I am not praising him, but speaking with him as an example.
When we’d go over there, Caucasians these days apparently use a little alcohol to make friends.
Then when this person comes in, "You want [a] drink?"
Over there, we’d walk among his fellow workers with businesses.
Then when we appeared, after he was struggling, "Nick you want [a] drink?" they’d say to him.
"No." When he said "no," those very knowledgeable people would say "sorry."
"I’m sorry, Nick."
Then after saying that, they’d end with: "Nick, you’re lucky."
And they’d say that to him.
I’m speaking of these because I will not hold back speaking of them since they’re good.
That’s how we went [through life].
His tradin gpost, let me skip it. It’s okay. Somehow, I’ll speak about it sometime somehow.
Nick never used to work. And he didn’t work anywhere.
He was a fur hunter, [a] fur hunter.
He was a fur hunter.
Then, he stated his trading post inland with that.
He used to say this, I never forget some of what he said to me:
He said that at that time, he sold his fur here, probably to fur buyers.
He said he got $700 for them.
Then using that, he arrived with little things.
Can I skip that too?
But our children’s parents were apparently teachers.
A woman’s daughter, a woman’s daughter can be like her.
And a man’s son can watch him and do what he does.
My male children here are not like their father.
I’m not lying. I’m speaking of it without lying.
But our eldest brother over there, because he adheres to his traditional instructions, is working at [the trading post] inland, probably.
I don’t know what he’s like.
But I really like our older brother. He’s wonderful, you see.
He cares for us, you see.
And he takes great care of his brothers and sisters.
Without praising him, I’m speaking of him to show how families are raised differently, and children.
This cleaning up the home was especially prevalent in my mind lately as I was going to [be interviewed] like this.
And those dishes and what to cook, a woman, a girl, [?] her mother...