Take $25 and send it.
[?] first, this one doesn’t seem like an elder.
Sometimes, they say to me...
Where’s your mom? What?
Where’s the payment?
Wait.
Okay.
Now, how did your caretakers choose your husband?
My caretaker had me take a husband that I didn’t choose. You know, I didn’t pick my own husband.
How did they choose?
They said the way they chose was their parents would speak to each other about their children.
They said their parents would choose their daughters’ husbands, their son’s wives.
When there were a lot of suitors, would they look at their characters?
Yes, they said that because people are different, their parents would choose the husband they preferred for their daughters.
Did you say nothing, only obeyed?
Yes, they said that back then, the young people, boys and girls, wouldn’t play with each other.
They said that they didn’t play with each other and didn’t get into relationships. You know, they weren’t too forward. They were respectful.
And they wouldn’t walk around holding hands like they do now.
How can you be a good wife, one with a husband?
How I can be a wife?
Stop.
How can you be a good wife?
They said that those who could be good wifes would respect and defer to their spouses, their husbands.
They also said that if a woman takes a husband even if he has an ugly face, she will treat her husband with respect and deference.
Not disparaging him
What else?
As just now, one who can be a good wife will treat her husband with deference.
And she doesn’t mess around without his knowledge, and obeys him out of respect.
Should she always prepare food for him?
Yes.
And before they go home?
They also said that when they were in the wilderness a long time ago, their wives would wait for their husbands, only eating when they arrived.
Can you tell us anything about the things women worked on a long time ago?
They said that a long time ago, the women were not like how they are now.
And boys, they didn’t have boys, greatly respecting each other.
They also said that when they played, the girls were separate, and the boys played separately over there, not interacting with each other like this.
That’s why they said they didn’t get pregnant, and there were scarce any pregnant young people a long time ago.
How did that lack of proper social conduct seem to start?
Recent, it seems to me in my observation, that we started lacking proper social conduct when we start going to school.
When we went to school, I would be withdrawn when I went to school.
It was a place to conduct oneself properly.
The teachers would admonish us against being withdrawn.
Now, however, they have no more sense of proper social conduct.
How did those teachers try to stop you from being withdrawn?
When we used to go to school, they would tell us not to be withdrawn
Yet we would be withdrawn [by proper social conduct] a long time ago.
You see, they lack proper social conduct now.
It seems, in my opinion, that those who hold themselves with proper social conduct are good, respecting everything before them.
And when people went into houses, they said they would stay put out of respect. Only when a person told them to come in would they come in.
Those who hold themselves with proper social conduct are good in my opinion.
Those without proper social conduct, however, are not good.
But now, they all lack proper social conduct because they’ve started doing various things at school.
What kinds of various things would you do?
We, you see, when I went to school, we didn’t do various things.
When they first built a school in Nunapitchuk, I was small when I went to school.
There was scarcely any various things to do.
We didn’t do various thigns, didn’t play basketball, didn’t do anything, didn’ t cheerlead.
Now, you know, they have scant clothing, with no reservation about their legs, and they embrace. They have no reservations.
We didn’t know those back when we were small.
How did your mother, or your caretaker ["aulukutestevet"], how did your caretaker...
"Aulukestevet." [Your caretaker]
How did your caretaker [?raise] you to be a good wife?
My caretaker did not instruct me on how to be a good wife like that
But when old women sometimes spoke to me
Because I didn’t know since I was an orphan, they would speak to me about how to be a good wife, and mother to my children.
I learned from them.
What did they teach you?
They taught me that my spouse, that my spouse and I should be a peaceful couple.
Also, if I raise my children, they told me not to shout at them when they first wake up in the morning.
That is admonished against.
They say we shouldn’t shout at our children in the morning.
Why?
Probably because it’s not good. I don’t know the exact meaning of it.
I want young people to hear what I’ve said.
They’ve started speaking mostly in English in their youth. And many young people probably don’t understand me.
Why do married couples get divorced?
They say that being married is a big responsibility.
Being married is a big responsibility and should be treated with respect.
They said that disparaging one’s spouse is admonished against like this.
I [will not disparage] my husband, and my husband will not disparage me. He should not treat me with disrespect.
We do disparage each other when we harshly say something bad. They say that’s how we disparage each other.
Then they said that one is the greatest way to disparage one’s spouse.
A man, or if a women fools around with men without her husband’s knowledge, if she lets a man fornicate with her
They say that’s the greatest disparagement.
Or if a man fornicates with another woman without his wife’s knowledge
They say he disparages his wife.
They say those are the greatest ways to disparage one’s spouse.
What can we young people focus on to, you know, stop doing that, to keep from doing that?
If one wants to keep from doing those, they must listen to their ancient traditional wisdom.
Even if you go to school where they do various things and you are smart, there probably won’t be anything written about how you can be a good wife.
Or, there is nothing written about how you can be a good husband.
Though a person is very smart, he will not learn in school.
But through these from our Yup’ik elders, and even though I am not an elder, I am instructing you now.
If you want to be good wives, respect your spouses.
Or a man must respect his wife.
Without committing adultery.
One who wants to be a good wife or husband will not "love" others, but will be married to their spouse.
But now...
Did you ask about how to be a bad wife or husband?
If a person is a bad wife or husband, they will not respect their spouse
They said that if one fornicates with others, that married couple will not be together.
You know, this is admonished against.
Many do not heed admonishments these days.
There is a multitude. Every little thing has admonishments.
You know, if they follow good [advice], they will not do what is admonished against if they follow good [advice].
You know how you said that you and your husband started off not loving each other?
What caused your love for each other to grow?
You see, I...
I didn’t choose my own husband.
My caretaker chose for me.
Because people respected and deferred to each other, I don’t know what made my love grow.
But they told us to work in accordance with our spouses if we want to be good spouses.
I’ve been on the verge of coughing.
As you watched your husband, what do you like about your husband?
When I took care of them?
As I watched my husband, or as he was my husband
I like that we treat each other with mutual respect, not disparaging each other.
And before my husband started working, I would try to take good care of what little he caught
The animals he had caught.
In your opinion, are some of the people who get divorced now include those who abuse alcohol or other mind-altering substances?
Yes, the good thing that I just talked about at first was what people practiced.
Now, however, how they get divorced
The young people are no longer doing right because they take husbands they’ve chosen themselves
Because their parents don’t choose for them, and they take wives they choose.
They reason for their getting divorced is because they [marry] whom they want, not deferring to their parents.
What about this alcohol?
About this alcohol, in my observation, there has recently been an increase in alcohol.
For married couples, if her husband drinks alcohol, and his wife doesn’t drink alcohol
His wife wants her husband to get better.
She tries to have her husband stop abusing alcohol.
If a person, a woman, a person knows God and prays
God will hear her desire, and her husband will stop drinking alcohol.
Or in a married couple if her husband drinks alcohol, and the wife joins her husband after she didn’t drink, they will destroy themselves.
They destroy each other, fight each other, then get a divorce.
If they understand that they’re destroying each other if they both drink alcohol, what can they do?
You know, if they realize that they’re destroying each other.
Now, we know that they stop drinking alcohol, you know, fix themselves and get better.
If married couples who drink alcohol understand themselves, understand their [situations]
If they give up their abuse of alcohol when they want to, they can give it up through that.
There is no one who can’t. Anything can be done.
What about the children who were hurt in their minds or hearts when [the parents] drank alcohol
When when they stop, how can the broken mental health or hearts of those children be fixed?
When these alcoholics are drunk, their children are probably hurt very deep inside.
If these parents stop doing that
Their children, well, if they start having the mind to take good care of their children to make them better
You know, that will probably be a long-standing hurt in a person’s heart.
But if they try to heal, they will heal.
You mean only if those two who were alcoholics worked with their hearts?
Yes, the alcoholic [parents] these days, you know how alcoholics have help here now?
They can get better with the help of their counselors.
And married couples, I see many who are in good marriages, and they love their children.
But that one thing is the worst thing that destroys married couples these days.
When they’re drunk, you know we watch them doing unacceptable things, and they have no self-restraint.
And they do things with this woman, "loving" others.
Because they have no more self-restraint.
If those people give it up, believing with their hearts, if they give it up in their hearts, they can get better.
And they can become better than us who have never drunk alcohol in our lives.
When couples separated a long time ago, what would these elders do or say to those who separated?
What did they say to them?
You see, I’m not too knowledgeable about the distant past.
But when I was growing up, married couples were married couples, and they didn’t seem to separate.
They didn’t seem to separate to me.
You know, they respected each other before these [Western things] became a lot, and we lived well in little villages.
And we didn’t have a lot to do here in the house because our houses were small.
We didn’t have a lot to do.
Do you have anything else to say?
Anything important or what?
I have something important to say about what brings people to destruction.
If a person wants to live well, he can live well by obeying his parents.
We parents will not instruct our children like this:
"When you go out, be bad." No, we will not tell them that.
We want all of our children to be good.
Also, these young people who are getting married these days
Their husbands, or when a man has too little respect for his wife, or a woman her husband, it destoys them.
They disparage themselves, making themselves more important.
I used to hear this when I took a husband:
They said that even if our husbands are ugly, or walk with a limp, no matter what they’re like, we must respect them and not disparage them.
The reason that married couples are no longer good these days
They choose and take their own husbands without examining their characters first
They do that because they have pretty faces, yet their characters are bad.
That’s what makes them have rocky marriages.
They apparently used to instruct them a long time ago, to marry a person even if he has an ugly face, saying that he will take care of her well.
It turned out to be true.
Now, because married couples disparage their husbands too much, or they disparage this boy, they are not good anymore.
Because they don’t hear these pieces of traditional wisdom, they don’t know.
When a small child goes out from his parents’ when he starts going to school
He’s gone all day long, then goes home tired at night.
He can’t learn much from his parents.
Only through school...