That’ll be useful.
Yes.
Right, we’re ready.
Okay.
Okay, for the record, speaking to James Guy, Kwethluk.
Were you born in time to see those who lived in the community house?
I was born in time to see them.
And I always went to listen to them speaking right after they took fire baths.
I would go listen to the words of the old men the men I thought of as old because I was a small boy.
I thought it was fun when they spoke. They would speak as they were.
And even when they knew what he was talking about his peers would listen to him.
And then when he made a small mistake, they would tell him that he had made a mistake.
Yes.
Whatpl did they used to talk about?
Various things, those who were shamans, shamans with some power.
They would talk about those, even how they held running races.
And how warriors attacked, because there had always been warriors that shot each other with arrows.
They would talk about those.
I see.
You see…
Were those community houses like schools?
They weren’t like schools.
Also, when someone misbehaved like this down there what we call those who’ve stolen people’s tools
When these elders were done taking fire baths, they would get him telling him that there had been trouble in their village.
They wanted to try him, to assuage [the situation].
And then they brought him, then admonished him together not to do that again.
Saying that stealing is bad.
That’s what they revealed to me.
Also, my wife and I last winter, because I can’t work very hard ever since I became weak
We2 would get salted fish last summer telling my children2.
And then last winter, we2 went to get it because there were three [containers of] salted fish.
Two of them, and half of this barrel, someone had taken half, and only a little [was left].
I was sad because they wouldn’t be returned. I didn’t say anything.
That’s why I really want to say something now because people will hear it.
This is what it’s like,
It’s also in those ancient commandments, [the] Ten Commandments, it’s in there: “Thou shall not steal,” “Teglegyaqunak.”
Yes, that’s why I’m admonishing all of the people of the land now
I’m admonishing them that even if they see a person’s things or even if they come upon fish camps not to take anything.
But if they want to take anything, do this:
Write on a piece of paper that a person is taking that much and write his name.
If [s]he does that, the owner will be grateful.
[S]he will also say this: “[S]he probably let me know because [s]he’s lacking. I’m thankful that [s]he did that.”
Let the owner know with a piece of paper even if [s]he’s gone.
And when I was young and healthy, that person… You know Pinky.
When I was lacking up in the mountains, because I lacked sometimes
When I came upon his camp, even if I wanted to use something, I never did.
And then when I saw him, I would tell him that even when I lacked even though I came upon his camp that I didn’t touch anything.
He would instruct me like this:
The next time I am lacking something important his provisions are put inside the barrel.
He said that I should open it, look for what I need, and take it
And he said to write my name, and how much I’ve taken from that barrel.
But I never did that.
I haven’t completely lacked anything important
Because I always traveled in the wilderness over there when I was young.
Also...
What about these, were you born in time to see Aavaaq?
Yes, I was born in time to see him.
I’ve heard, I’ve probably heard wrong, that he was a shaman.
The poor guy wasn’t a shaman.
Poor guy, I see.
But he was, you know, treated by a shaman [in utero], yes.
People said that he was treated by a shaman [in utero].
They only say that he was treated by a shaman.
How?
That he was treated by a shaman.
He was named Taqukaq to keep him clinging to life. (Shamans used to treat them in utero by giving them names.)
He didn’t [treat] himself?
Yes, shamans did that to him.
They say that that’s why when he was crawling when he did this, eating plants, grass
This part where he ate grass would turn green.
And they say that his mother never admonished him [against that].
The poor guy wasn’t a shaman, but he was treated by one like that.
Were you born in time to see these…
What are reindeer in Yup’ik again?
You mean tuntut?
Tuntut. (Yes.)
Were those…
I was born in time to see them. (Please talk about them.)
Yes, because I liked to go with my father to mark reindeer
I used to go with them to herd reindeer in Akiachak.
In the morning, they would go up from Akiachuk to mark reindeer.
They said that they would corral them from a massive meadow over there.
And from there, they said that they would take them to the waiting area so that they could look around.
The fences had names.
And from the waiting area there, they would bring them in through the corraling path.
The corraling path wasn’t long. It was narrow.
The reindeer would go through there one at a time.
Those who were fast were dangerous.
They would even suddenly stand and tread over the others.
And one person would count them.
[S]he never made a mistake, holding large papers, calling out.
And over there, there were four wrestlers coming out of that corraling path.
When it was overflowing over there, the wrestlers would wait to catch them across from each other like this.
And then when its head appeared, they would take it right away, wrestle it, and mark it.
However, they would let out those that were marked.
They would only mark the ones that weren’t marked.
What do you mean maagluki?
Mark them on their ears. Yes.
With a knife?
Yes, with a knife.
You see, the callers knew the reindeer.
[Belonging] to that person…
I never forget something.
I was amazed at that extremely white one.
How did this reindeer get white?
One day, it went through that corraling path through what they call the nutek.
When it arrived, someone over there called it.
I’ve never forgotten this, what he said:
“Qayaksuk’s there.”
That reindeer apparently belonged to Qayaksuk.
The callers knew them by their ears.
And when they took them out of that wrestling area over there
They brought it out again to the fence.
They wouldn’t let them go about right away either.
When that last [area with a] fence was full
They would open them and let those reindeer out.
And they closed it when they were all through.
They freed them, except for those that were still to come.
It was fun watching them have fun.
The workers [on the field] also had workers down in the camp.
They had cooks.
They probably paid their cooks with reindeer.
When I went down, I would see that they used half of a tank as a cooking pot.
They probably put the entire reindeer herd in.
And so, because that multitude would go along with women
The [women] with less responsibility who were not taking care of children
The people would finish that huge pot, half of a tank, when they had lunch.
In English, they would have break time, lunch break time.
There were no Caucasians.
They would say it’s time to eat at 12 o’clock.
Were they the only ones…
They used to in Akiachak.
But when they did it towards here up on Akulikutaq Corral, that’s where they went.
But because I thought it was far since I was small, I didn’t go with them.
It was also because I was a student at that time.
But when they went to Akiachak, I would go along since it was close.
Back when youpl herded reindeer, were there wolves?
Yes, there were.
There always used to be wolves.
There were always wolves in my old man’s stories.
He would say this:
“It drove the reindeer and killed one, those wolves.”
But when the reindeer declined, when they were taken under the governement
When those reindeer were taken under the government
He stopped herding, he stopped herding.
They also said that reindeer would sometimes go, go over a hill, and they disappeared from the end.
They think that the legendary little people took them.
Eventually, they said that the reindeer…
It had become covered in reindeer all over, up in the marsh, mountains, and across there.
But that happened; wolves aren’t the only ones that depleted them.
But that said that they were quickly depleted when they vanished like that.
This is what I heard:
They said that the government brought those reindeer herding places here.
And then they said that they had teachers from outside
They brought a Saami person here to teach people how to herd reindeer.
And then they said that when they left, Yupiit took care of reindeer herds and they were depleted because they didn’t take care of them well.
Is that true?
No, that’s not true.
They weren’t taken care of badly.
That old man of mine used to talk about them like that.
He said that wolves weren’t the only ones that depleted them, but they vanished.
When they go out of view like that behind hills, they vanished.
They say that’s mostly what depleted them.
They were extremely dirty.
After they were taken under the government, they say that were extremely dirty.
And then they were depleted.
One day when they were depleted, I started traveling up there.
Also, I dropped out of school by my own choice when I was going to turn 15 years [old].
I started helping my father make money from the wilderness.
There were no jobs in the villages, only by [trading] fur.
Villages didn’t have donated money, what they call grants.
People only got [money] mostly through [trading] fur.
They also worked on lumber in the summer.
They worked hard to get money.
They would even carry loads of wood down from the trees.
But my daddy traveled a lot.
We2 would go right after fishing in August up to the mountains to hunt for squirrels
Because squirrel skins were expensive.
Back when I first started, one coat cost $15.
But because we would be short [on money], we would go hunt squirrels.
I see.
And so to you, the young people these days
Even outside of here, they’re starting to be mischievous even in other villages.
Yes, the young people, our descendants,these days are becoming mischievous.
And they have nothing to do at night, and tend to wander about.
They’re not like us.
In our time,
And when the child of this one who spoke before me enjoyed each others’ company, we went home early at nine [o’]clock and ten [o’]clock after playing.
These days you see, at night, and after midnight
Because they have vehicles, they’ve started going around with snow machines and even fourwheelers these days.
Also, these young people, these little Yupiit
Their mothers make the mistake of raising them without speaking [in our language] as we were.
They learn, these children learn to speak English in school.
Some days, here and over there outside of the school
I admonish these little Yupiit speaking in Yup’ik like this.
Those big boys would answer me, “I don’t know what you’re talking about.”
It’s not right that we should lose, start to lose our language.
And then sometimes, they would answer when I speak to them
That that is not written in their high school books.
They’ve started converting to the Westerne ways in our region.
It’s probably because they always speak English to them.
They’ve also started losing their traveling ways.
They can’t walk a little ways over there either
Saying that they don’t have that [vehicle].
Back when we were boys, when the land [became walkable] like this
Even though we had dogs, we left them behind and traveled with packs on our backs.
But we always had walking staffs as we were instructed.
We always had walking staffs even here in the village.
Even when we walked through the village, we held a walking staff
Because we were instructed to.
In Yup’ik instructions, Yupiit have a lot of instructions and traditional wisdom.
For you, what is the most powerful of those instructions
Or the most important traditional wisdom of the people back then?
I just talked about the most important one: do not take other’s things. Do not steal.
That’s the most important because we all get disappointed from loss.
That's the most important.
Next, if we go anywhere, even inside the village, do not leave the walking staff.
And if we should go on ice, we should [test it] with a pointed tool.
Even in the village, make a long walking staff out of wood and hold it.
Even in the village, and even when we went up mountains
We always walked around holding a walking staff.
That's the next [piece of wisdom].
And sometimes, it would save us.
When we’re going to fall, we upheld ourselves with a staff.
And sometimes, when we cross streams
That staff lets us know which parts are deep and should not be crossed.
We look for another path instead.
Even streams are dangerous up in the mountains.
The snow, as our ancestors back then used to say, if we travel without [?probing], we will fall into hollows in the snow.
Sometimes when we poke what looks good here, the [hollow] beneath does not close in.
They told us to always have staffs because we might fall into those
What they call neruinilluta.
The area beneath, though this is all snow, the area beneath [?has a large hollow].
Because we might fall into those, they told us to always have a staff even in the village.
And when we’re going to cross, always examine it even if it’s narrow.
Was there also…