In the winter, when I went with my late father to the wilderness when it was cold
I got frostbitten and I didn’t realize it.
When he saw me, he said that my cheeks got frostbitten.
He took snow from there, pressed it against my cheeks, and the snow melted.
When it had been some time, he stopped.
And then the skin from my cheeks didn’t, you know, peel off.
But that’s what I know about how that happens.
But I think it would be good to be submerged into cold water if they get frostbitten on their feet or hands.
It probably won’t be any different from getting it here on the cheeks.
It probably won’t be any different if they get frostbitten on their hands or feet and they are submerged into cold water.
They will probably be good if they are submerged.
They say it will suddenly get cold when that happens.
They say that the sun is "ready" when it’s going to be cold.
When it’s cold, when it’s going to get cold, that’s what they said it was like.
It would be as if it were wearing an outer parka, and wearing gloves on the outside with white parts.
They said that it will get cold. That probably happens when it’s going to be cold for a while.
For a long time?
I think it's like that. They said that it would be like that.
Don't they also say that they would use the mountains for weather forecasts?
The mountains also, since some of them were observant
Because I'm not observant, when those mountains across there do something, when there are mirages on the horizon
They say that it's a sign of some kind of weather.
But when the mountains across are high, and some of them have sharp summits, I think that’s a sign of warm weather.
I see the mountain across there with the sharp summit, and it’s visible from here.
And when I used to live up in Qanirtuum Qagatii over there, it would be visible with a sharp summit.
When it’s going to be warm, I use it as a sign.
When the summit seems to get sharper and rise acting strangely, it seems to do that when it’s going to get warm.
The observant ones back then would know, the people of old back then.
When they used to survive with various tools, because they were always outside
And those who use them know to use the stars at night as signs of incoming weather.
There is probably no one who does that now.
I’m not sure. Some young people who were told can probably do that.
Those observant ones were indeed like weather forecasters.
They knew through their signs, how they gauged the signs
Through the stars or how the weather was like.
They knew what the weather was going to be like.
Some of those who believed in them would follow them.
And then the squirrels in the mountains across there, one of them also told me a story
He said that when the weather is going to be bad for a long while, their cheeks have a lot in them.
They fill them with berries or other things they eat, go to their dens, then eat from the stores in their cheeks for as long as the weather is bad.
They stay there in the den with food.
What were storyknives made of?
I had a storyknive made out of ivory, tuluq, ivory.
And I’m not sure who made it.
I would never stop telling storyknife stories.
And since we had friends, we would only tell storyknife stories with our friends when we weren’t in school.
We would tell storyknife stories, and the villages from my friend’s and my storyknife stories would have names.
They had names as we pretended they were inland.
We had them pretend to be a family.
My playmate would name these the inlanders.
These would be the Tundra People, and she would have the Coastal People always be over here.
She would name that village and the people the Tundra People.
We would make up families and give them houses.
Would they have things? Would they have names?
We would pretend that they would have things like what we’ve seen. They would have normal things.
And when we didn’t tell storyknife stories, we played string games.
But they would admonish us against playing string games for too long saying that an elf would enter to whomever is playing string games.
We wouldn’t do it for long, but stop after playing some string games.
Why?
I don’t know.
And in the summer, we would play with small dolls.
We had small dolls, almost every girl.
They would have a lot of small dolls. These would make up a small family.
And then these other dolls. Those were the toys we had.
When my father was going to travel
My mother would prepare food for him, tea, sugar. They always had things to cook with.
But when the weather was good, those men would cook outdoors.
Would they hunt for their own food?
Yes.
And then I would find that they would make drift nets out of string.
My father would also carve wood for fishing tools. He would make blackfish traps.
The men I’ve seen would also make conical traps for land animals, adding in steel traps.
When the other villages they invited arrived, they would take the men to the community house.
And they would place one of the benches and put it high up near the exit.
And they would seat the men there and bring them food.
They would call it bringing them food.
They would bring them cooked food to eat, or dried fish along with tea.
And then they would try to disrupt their meals when they started eating.
When those visiting men started eating, the village would start drumming a song.
They called it disrupting their meals.
I sat and watched my grandfathers and great-uncles, the last one, that was the last one.
I observed and watched my father’s uncle from Paingaq.
The villagers would sing for them like this to disrupt their meals
So they can choke, or can’t swallow, or something like that.
They sang to them like this:
"Let me make those who do not get embarrassed become undecided
"Do I lump in everyone who’s undecided?
"Don’t these people from Akuluraq also want to sing repeatedly, scattering nothing of value here?
"They also want to repeatedly sing."
But the two naked men who sang the verses, with necklaces here, headdresses, but with pants, would do this.
And then they would specifically point them out, "Even if those out there think they’re important."
Oh my, they were frightening.
They called that disrupting their meals.
I didn’t choose my own husband.
My caretaker chose for me.
Because the people were respectful and deferential to each other, I don’t know to whom I was starting to love.
But they told us to obey our spouses if we wanted to be good spouses.
When I took care of my husband, or when I was married to him
I like mutually respecting each other, not treating each other badly.
And before my husband started working, I would try to take good care of what little he caught
Well, the animals that he caught.
Divorcing now, however, the young people are getting worse because they marry husbands they chose themselves
Because their parents don’t choose for them, instead marrying whomever they want.
And they divorce because they choose their own without listening to their parents.
What about alcohol?
And this alcohol, in my observation, there is more alcohol recently.
And for married couples, if the husband drinks alcohol and the wife doesn’t
The wife will want the husband to get better.
She will want her husband to stop drinking alcohol.
If a woman knows God and prays
God will hear what she asks for, and her husband will stop drinking alcohol.
Or with married couples, if the husband drinks and the wife doesn’t
If she joins her husband, they will destroy each other, destroy each other and fight each other, then divorce.
I see many married couples who also love their children.
That one thing is what is destroying married couples these days.
You know we see people do various things when they’re drunk. They are not ashamed, and make love to this random woman.
It’s because they’re not ashamed anymore.
If they give it up, believing in their hearts, if they give it up in their hearts, they can get better.
And they can become better than we who have never drank alcohol in our lives.
If a person wants to live well
He can live well by obeying his parents.
We who are parents will not instruct our children like this:
"When you go out, misbehave." No, we will not tell them that.
We all want our children to be good.
Also, these young people who are married today
When they don’t respect their husbands, or the men their wives, or the women their husbands, it destroys them.
They disparage each other and consider themselves as more important.
I would hear this when I took a husband:
They said that even if our husbands are ugly or crippled, no matter what they’re like, we must respect them and not treat them badly.
And how married couples are getting worse these days, they also choose their own husbands without examining what they’re like
It because they have good faces, but their dispositions are bad.
That is what keeps them from having good marraiges.
Long ago, they used to instruct people
They said that even if a person was ugly, to marry him even if he had an ugly face, saying that he will take good care of her.
It turned out to be true.
These days in married couples, they are becoming bad because they treat their husbands or these boys very badly.
They don’t know because they don’t hear this traditional wisdom.
They told us to be careful of our mouths towards those around us. They also told us not to live by saying harsh words just because we have mouths.
They said that those who are bad people come to shame many times along with those who say too many harsh words.
They say that they are seen in different ways, and then as they want to be.
And then they would tell us to try to stay quiet even if we are blamed if we didn’t do it.
That was also an admonishment.
And then we would be admonished against going after people too much.
They said that we would come to times of mental hardship or keep hearing of bad things.
This is what we were told.
Also, they told us not to invite our families into saying things about them because that also brings discord.
I would be told that I am no longer a child, that I’ve become a woman.
But they said that I should always take things to wash them.
And then they told me never to step over men’s clothes no matter what they were, nor fish.
They told me not to step over even food.
They say that we, you know, scatter impurity on them.
And then they told me not to keep my hair untied. They said that we drop and scatter impurity.
And these two old men, one was at near the door at the very end
There was also one across there at the very end. They were bringing forth traditional wisdom.
Both of those who were talking about life ahead, after having the one toward here talk
After bringing up the things they had to say about how they should be
They talked about how they should live and be like this.
And then when he was finished, the one on the other side would correct him.
He said a person should live like this.
Even if they lived in the community house, were father, or had a lot of children, they didn’t disregard their traditional wisdom.
The community house would be quiet when they spoke.
And then when I had a child, I was told to teach that child.
They said that chidlren do not forget.
And then they would admonish me against asking him questions, or asking him about what his peers are like.
Also, do not defend them. You know how some are defensive?
And then they told me not to defend him but to admonish him.
They said that if I defend him, I will encourage him to lie and say false things.
And then they would also admonish me against physically punishing them too much.
They said that I would make him unstable.
They said that we make them unstable by physically or verbally abusing them. They say that we make them impertinent.
They say that they make them impertinent like that.
It turns out that we must raise children to make them feel like we do not defend them.
They say that those who are defended and spoken to without thought make discord among their parents.
When they were done taking sweat baths and the fire down there had gone out, one of them would place the cover on the smoke hole of the community house.
And then after they close it, the men would sit naked like this without having put on clothes when we come in. They were probably drying off.
The people of Aagurmiut and Urucararmiut had one community house.
Sometimes in the winter like this, when the people of Aagurmiut wanted to take sweat baths
They would go to the community house together with sleds filled with wood though Kepenkuk down there when it used to be called Kepenkuk.
They would go to the community house over there because Urucararmiut and what was Aagurmiut had one community house.
It’s actually called Aagurmiut down there.
I started off completely prepared to be married.
But my late grandmother, and my mom, and my father would tell me
That I should be careful with my spouse.
Also, even if people say bad things about him, they told me not to tell him
Also, I have a companion, a male younger sibling.
They also used to tell him that even if people say various things about his wife not to believe them if he hasn’t seen it with his own eyes.
My father also used to tell me that.
He said that I should not suspect my spouse of various things if I haven’t done them.
I also shouldn’t accuse him of being with other women.
He said that, you know, that brings discord.
I was also told not to excessively tease my husband.
And then they would also tell me this:
Even if I have nothing or am short on things not to say that I have nothing.
They said that I would make my spouse’s mind be in turmoil.
This is what I was told.
We were also admonished against always being suspicious of each other.
They said that those who are guilty are the ones who suspect their spouses.
I just told you about what I observed, that the community house inland was down toward the water from the Joe Lomack Building.
The place they called Urucaraq wasn’t a lake, was dry, but had a river.
And the river had a bridge down there.
And the first school upriver, upriver over from the Moravian church, the old church.
There were boardwalks made of plywood all the way to Aagurmiut down there to where they called Luqinquq.
Luqinquq had a store there.
He had a Caucasian companion with a house toward the water from him. He was probably his partner at the time. They called him Kassaussaaq.
It was because those people back then would give them whatever names suited them.
I grew up at the time without a lot of Caucasians here between Aagurmiut and Urucuaraq.
They also talked about Kenirkauyar over there.
And Kenirkauyar was a Western dancing hall here.
But it wasn’t at any time, only on Saturdays.
They also went until 12 o’clock.
That was when they stopped, and they didn’t let them do it all the time.
They would have us go back to our villages at midnight and admonish us against wandering about.
You see, the first Caucasians back then also seemed to help each other like Yupiit.
Even if we were Yup’ik, even the Caucasians would admonish us.
They say that those who are defended and spoken to without respect bring discord to their parents.
That’s what I used to be told, and that’s what my mother told me.
And no matter what, when I sometimes was fed up, she would admonish me not to talk about those.
She said that I would be the cause of discord among people.
And then she said that no matter what they do, she admonished me against coming home crying.
And then even if I never did that
When my children would come in crying when they were small, my father would tell me that because he said I needed it.
And then I would not run away, but stay because I thought that I did.
And then when children are admonished like this for the benefit of their futures, it turns out they do not run away but stop when they are told to.
And do not say this to them: "I will take care of him."
Children who are treated like that learn to go home crying.
And then the ones that they keep defending
That’s why it’s admonished against, because it leads to lying and saying things without consideration.
They also told us to help those who looked destitute and who were unable.
They also told us never to make fun of anyone even if they look funny.
That is probably bad.
Instead, they told us to help the older ones who were unable.
They say a person’s mind is powerful.
Also, even if we enter another house, my teacher would tell me to never take even a single match or nail from that house.
How much more time?
He also said that even in the wilderness, a person doesn’t forget what he put, even in the wilderness.
That must be true.
He said that a person doesn’t forget what he put even in the wilderness.
And when we were in the marshes over there in the summer like this
When our feet wouldn’t get cold and we started walking around barefoot
When our feet were itchy at night, we would take out our feet to our bedding and they would start bleeding.
And we didn’t use them as an excuse when they told us to travel.
When we stepped into water, they would sometimes sting.
This was the only way we walked, and they became raw, and they became raw between the toes.
When we went to the wilderness, we would pull something out and bandage the part that was bleeding too much.
And we lived without making any excuses but were quiet.
We lived without any discord in the house.
And then when we and our younger siblings almost made too much noise having fun, they would admonish us against acting foolish.
There were four in what is called a family in English.
That big family had that house as they were supposed to.
Also, when they stayed in that house like this
These food to eat, those familes weren't the only ones to have them, but everyone in the house would eat from what food they had.
Some of them have houses, and the ones trying to survive would stay in one house that they own.
But they always had a lot of people.
These familes with several members would live in a house, only those families.
That’s what they were like.
And their food that they get from the wilderness, blackfish, saffron cods, or whatever food they get in the winter and fall for frozen raw fish
The yweren’t food for only the ones in the house or the ones who caught them, but for everyone in the house along with the men in the community house.
These days, because the old life of the people long ago has changed
Since it’s like we Yupiit have started living a new life unlike our traditional life
Because our young people are going to completely forget our original lifestyle
We show them the kinds of houses that we used to have when we were growing up that the workers have finished
Because we absolutely should not lose the original lifestyle of our Yup’ik people.
Also, we absolutely should not leave our young people in ignorance, because it is our ancient way as Yupiit.
Because it is so sad.
Now, we look at our young people and want them to return and learn it.
And even though we only instruct them with words, because they seem to doubt it because they’ve never seen it
Let them see these houses they used to have long ago as true
And the thigns we were born in time to see before Western things became available.
Now, they are working to show our young people so that they can learn from them.
When thye went to their winter camps like this
When they were finished, they would split wood to make fish traps out of stright-graned pieces of wood.
That’s what they also used to do.
Since these young people of ours, even if they’re not young, are too ignorant about what to do, lashing fish traps, and making fish traps
We don’t want their lives to be like that anymore now.
Lashing fishing tools for blackfish and loche.
They measure, you know, the size of the fish, and lash traps for sticklebacks.
Their women would also make grass baskets to hold fish, but not out of empty sacks.
They would gather wheat grass to make baskets to hold caught fish so them wouldn’t be without containers.
That is what the people I was born in time to see were like.
The people back then would gauge it by the snow.
When there’s a lot of snow, and also when there’s a lot of ice where the snow is partially frozen
When it freezes as it periodically warms up.
They say that when there’s a lot of snow also upriver from us, there’s a lot of water. They would say there’s a lot of water.
Did you see the snowiest time when there was a lot of snow?
There used to be a lot of snow here back when we were small. There was a lot of snow.
And the houses down there, the mission house was the only elevated one.
It would reach their roof and slope down.
We would go up there and slide.
And they would shovel tunnels to the doors of the porches like this.
Did you observe a lot of snow on the Yukon or anywhere?
Yes, there used to be a lot of snow in the 1930’s when I was a boy.
Sometimes, when it keeps snowing with repeated southern winds, they say that the marsh freezes, cirmiggluni as they say.
Now, even though there’s snow, the tundra here is not frozen.
Even though there’s a lot of snow like this, there’s not a flood of water even though there’s a lot.
But the melted ice is slow to flow out.
They say that the water will be gone probably when it repeatedly freezes.
But when there’s a lot of ice that can’t do that, then there is a flood of water.
Also, when these rivers have a lot of snow, the ice isn’t thick.
Because it’s not as thick as it usually is, even if there’s a lot of water, I don’t think there’ll be a flood for that reason.
With how February is ending now, how would they prepare to go to their spring camps?
When they were going to go to their spring camps, they would start preparing in April.
And prepare food supplies for the entire spring
And setting up their tents, and...
See, I’ll slip into English a lot.
And, you know, they would bring their boats and canoes.
They brought the things they would need in the spring camps.
And then when the middle of April had passed, we would relocate.
We would arrive to our settlement. It was nice and wonderful.
This was the traditional wisdom passed to us: they told us to respect especially the land and water.
Respect it.
This is what our instruction was like: respect it as much as our bowls.
It’s not like that these days. It’s different.
What does it mean, "as much as our bowls?"
This is how I understand it:
Our bowls when we eat, at least back then, it’s probably because a person long ago would have only one bowl and personally kept it.
he treated it with love and respect.
I think that that’s a metaphor, to respect our land and water as much as our bowls.
This is part of the traditional wisdom of the people long ago.