Do you want to start?
Okay, is it time to start? (Yes, yes.)
Look, can we just introduce ourselves?
Okay, these people. Their names.
Ann [?].
From? (From Bethel.)
Are you a teacher, or what?
No, I work for [?], and I work for YKHC.
[?]
I’m Lucy Sparck and I work here at KCC.
Introduce them. We can’t hear [?] their names.
Okay, over there…
…for animals.
These, back when we were young and [did not watch them] well
Before we watched the ones working on them who were alive.
Our caretakers, however, had instructions for these animals of the wilderness.
They would instruct us until we would not waste it.
They also told us not to delibirately hunt something we would not use, saying that it would get wasted.
Instead, they would respect animals they hunted in the wilderness.
Those who respected them also [passed] those on to us because our ancestors took good care of them
Not wasting or polluting with them because they gave us those instructions.
And then afterwards, we started seeing those pieces of traditional wisdom that were given to us
If we’re not going to eat it, not to deliberately kill it.
But if we're going to eat it, they told us to [hunt it] and not to pollute nature with it.
Also, because it’s warm in the winter
If we kill that [animal] as we’re somewhere in the wilderness
If it starts to smell, they told us not to throw it on the ground.
Instead, after digging into the land, cover it.
We had that instruction.
Also…
One moment. That’s going to be translated.
What’s the matter? Is it too long or what?
No, finish what you were saying first. (Okay.)
You know, how they told them only to dig and put those.
Yes, dig into the ground.
Don’t throw it on the ground, but after digging into the land, cover it there.
Also, if we have some of this food that has gone bad which we won’t eat
They said to put it where people have not and will not tread upon.
Those were our instructions from those who raised us.
We also had instructions for the wilderness because we hunt these things on the land
Because our familes and we used animal traps.
They also told us to respect what that person had caught because it’s not ours.
We also had instructions that if that one was going to go or if we see an animal to kill it
And hang it there so that when the owner comes to it before leaving
That person will be thankful that someone had done that to what he had caught.
They told us not to steal it because it’s not ours. We had that admonishment.
They say a person can learn to do this.
One can also learn to talk another person’s possession that is not his own.
Those had admonishments for us.
But, they said that we should only use what we caught withought taking another person’s.
These are the instructions we had from those who raised us back then.
That is all from me.
Okay…
…we didn’t have instructions concerning [their days].
But, we hear that from the direction of the ocean or if it suddenly gets foggy
If the water suddenly gets foggy, we upriver people sometimes say
“So, someone has caught something in the ocean.”
When it gets foggy like that, we say that they caught something, that we think they caught something.
He said that…
…here.
Upriver here? (Yes, land animals.)
These land animals…
Hey, if you know, please explain about some of those, how the land animals [are treated].
Our ancestors back then took care of revered land animals.
You know, they didn’t pollute nature with them.
They and the ones I saw took good care of them.
They also instructed us not to throw their bones in places with heavy traffic out of reverence.
They revered and loved the animals that the men caught.
And they didn’t[carelessly] throw even their bones away.
They always dug and covered their bones.
They used to have people dispose of them like that a long time ago.
There was no mess in all of the land.
Before there were these cans, these various Western garbage materials, there was no [waste] on the land.
There was no visible mess or paper materials.
The land was good with no mess.
The people revered their land.
They revered their land, including the areas around them.
They also used to instruct us.
The places we women subsist, our berry picking lands, where we tread, and our egg hunting lands
They told us that if we stop at those not leave it messy.
They also told us never to leave our food scraps, whatever leftovers we had, in open places as messes
Instead, always dig and cover them.
The people back then, including their land, was not like now.
They respected this land. They respected it in their lives.
Well, she said that…
Truly, I do not leave anything when I pick berries. (Did they tell youpl?)
When we [pick] berries… (I wouldn’t leave berries when I picked them.)
I even take a single little seed and put it in my bucket.
And the place I picked berries has nothing because I think like this
I always think like this:
“God put this here. He made it grow here.
“I will not [gather] without being thorough and scatttering them.”
These days, since we’ve recently gotten this [religion], this is how I think when I pick berries.
I also take a single berry all the same without saying there are bigger ones.
And sometimes, there is a single seed growing on a stem.
I also peel that off and put it in even though it takes up my time.
I am honestly talking about my personal custom.
Okay, she’s answering it, this, from…
At that time, there were a great many birds.
There were also a great many ptarmigans.
Before there were these governement workers with laws
People used to hunt in the spring for birds and ptarmigans.
But what they caught, because salt came early in our time
We would preserve those birds with salt before they spoiled.
They would also hang ptarmigan meat to dry.
We [preserved] those like that.
Also, because they would sometimes have shortages back then before these [Western] nets appeared
Because we had nets and deteriorated back then that needed to be replaced every year
Sometimes, it couldn’t catch a lot of fish.
When we [hunted] those, because we didn’t have an abundant supply of guns
Because we hunted ptarmigans first, we would trap ptarmigans with snares made from twine.
We used to do that because there were a lot back then
Before these Caucasians these things with their work out of state.
And before Alaska was covered with these numerous coats that are filled with fur
They were filled with bird feathers because there was a lot back then.
We used to preserve some of those birds in salt during the spring to eat them over the summer.
They also told us, [you know] we gather eggs in the spring like this.
Because they observed these eggs
They would have us stop when the fetuses developed in the eggs.
They told us not to take eggs again because their fetuses had developed and would become birds.
We also had admonishments like that for those.
Those who raised us would also tell us this
If we also polluted nature with those things we gathered, they would tell us this:
If we keep polluting nature with them, our caretaker will remove those.
We had that traditional wisdom.
They said that if we pollute nature with them, he will not give them to us anymore.
They say that after that person is a good hunter and catches a lot, he can no longer catch anything because he pollutes nature with what he catches.
Okay, he mentioned [Forest] and asked him a question.
How did you show respect to those?
And how...cure them?
Cure them? How did they cure them?
You make them last through the winter or…
Would you eat them all winter long?
How did you preserve them, you know, without discarding them?
How did you take care of them? Yes. (I see. How do take care of them?)
The habit for birds in the fall
When they start swimming, because the people back then observed them
They said that when bird chicks are small, they are not food because they’re too small before they grow.
Only when they are grown and start flapping their wings, they treat them as food only then.
A person can then [hunt] them if he wants to, and because he wouldn’t catch a lot
Only once in a great while, people who are able to travel [hunt] those.
Because they travel to the wilderness in September when the berries are [ready], and at the end of August
Those chicks grow at that time.
But when people hunt during the time of opportunity when the chicks are good before they can fly
When the people back then caught some, they would preserve them in salt to prevent spoiling.
If they don’t have any and they woould spoil, they would give them to their families before they spoil like that.
He’s saying that when birds are, when little birds are small, he said they’re not much of food for them.
But only when they get bigger, people then go after them.
And he’s saying that, you know, from being around here, he said not everybody went after them.
But those who did, went after them and then salted them again. And if you…
…she asked if [they stored] those, or did they eat them right away?
Back then, when some gathered eggs, when they gathered more than they needed
They don’t dig them into the ground raw, or store them, only after cooking them.
They’re only done and won’t spoil after cooking like that.
They only stored them after cooking them.
To where? To what?
I’m not sure where they stored them.
Some froze them, cooked and froze them, then stored them all together.
And because they had seal oil containers a long time ago, big seal pokes
They would store some of them in those to prepare for uncertainty
Only submerging them in seal oil after cooking them.
When it was time, they would reach in and take those eggs out.
Okay, he’s saying that if people take…
What do these people [work as]?
[S]he works, caliluni, at Fish and Wildlife. (I see.)
And this one at YKHC. (I see.)
You asked me about who [we store] these seals when we catch them.
Yes, before there were freezers. (Okay.)
They want to know how they [stored food] before freezers.
(I see.)
No.
Their spirits when they catch seals down from the ocean (For their spirits.)
How do they [show respect] to their spirits?
What will happen to the spirit of that [seal] when it’s caught and dead?
No, didn’t you say that you did something to them, giving them water to drink…
Oh, those. Oh, yes.
Back when they caught them, even if it was a small ringed seal or even a bearded seal
When they caught them in the spring, brought them to land, brought them into their homes.
When they catch even a small ringed or even a bearded seal
For some reason, [s]he would [do this] here with his hands
After pouring water on his hands, open its mouth even if it’s skinny
Even if it’s skinny, pour that leftover [water] in its mouth.
Even though its dead? (Yes, even though it’s dead.)
Even if that bearded seal is butchered inside that house.
And then, the first thing when a boy had his very first catch of everything, even a bearded seal
When one who went on his first hunting trip caught his first bearded seal
After doing that, pouring [water] with his hands here…