Oh my, I was going to make frybread so that we would have some when I was done.
Let's stay here for a while.
Yes, I prepared, yes.
Yes, I'll make (?) so we can drink something hot.
And, you know, Kakianaq wanted you to walk outside.
Yes, oh my, I don't want to go out.
Or do you watch something out from the patio?
You soend leisurely time.
It'll probably be broadcast on TV.
You know, you wanted your Waves of Wisdom recording to be translated?
Really?
Then when it's translated, we will use it.
What's your Yup'ik name again?
Elena, oh, Narull'aq.
Now, please tell us stories about people would go to pick berries long ago when you were small.
Okay, I used to go berry picking when I was a little girls in Nalqigliq, going along with them.
I used a square five-gallon gas can as, you know, my berry container,
Because we poor people use square gas cans.
Then I filled it full and brought it home.
Then when I went home, my mother made Yup'ik ice cream with all of it and fed it to people.
We would pick berries like that, but did you just ask how they would be kept all winter?
Yes, how did people store them before they had freezers?
I used to see... see, I don't know how they picked berries.
In barrels, they would be in the porch.
You know, our food would be in the porch and they would be cold.
I used to see our store of berries in the porch in a wooden barrel.
When you made Yup'ik ice cream, before there was shortening, what type of fat would you use?
My mother used to make Yup'ik ice cream out of tunut, you know, tallow, tunut.
Reindeer tallow.
She dried them, then after drying them, when she was going to make Yup'ik ice cream, she would them into a frying pan,
Then she would heat them on the stove, you know, like bacon.
Then they would boil, sizzing, then it would render.
And those pieces she cut up would bunch.
Then she removed them and, you know, wrung them like this.
She took them out, then that tallow, you know how bacon renders grease?
She would add the fat, you know, the real fat, tallow.
They would get snow, you know, that snow, little hailstones.
That kind. Then she would make Yup'ik ice cream, you know, periodically adding in that snow.
And when she made Yup'ik ice cream, she would tell us not to make any sound. I wonder why?
We would stay quietly.
That's how she made Yup'ik ice cream. I'm not sure at what stage she would add berries.
That's how I used to see that.
What else did they use? Would they sometimes add oil/fat?
Well, if it's all [solid] tallow, it would be very hard. You know how hard tallow gets when it's cold?
Then when it's added and mixed with oil,
It can probably be whipped into Yup'ik ice cream. I don't know of any other.
Do you know when they started using shortening?
Oh my, I do know. It was recent.
I was making my own living in Nunapitchuk.
I tried to make my own living. Then my male cross cousin who moved over there, Iilgayaq, Bristol Bay.
When he came as a guest, I said I had no Yup'ik ice cream.
I make Yup'ik ice cream out of tallow, adding in oil.
I used to do that without any knowledge of shortening.
Then that man instructed me when I said this, "See, I don't have any Yup'ik ice cream."
He said that if I want quick Yup'ik ice cream to use shortening.
Then when I took out my shortning
He took nothing but shortning like this into a mixing bowl
He told me to whip it into Yup'ik ice cream occassinally adding water.
They also add in Wesson oil.
I personally do it with milk.
Yes, it seems to be different in these lands.
Then ever since then
I never used kaugaq, tallow, but only shortning.
It's really quick.
Would they add in anything else like this, like tall cottongrass tubers or sourdock?
Yes, tall cottongrass tubers, one with sourdock. The one with nothing but tall cottongrass tubers,
By itself, I used to see it with nothing else added.
And this sourdock, they would add in berries, mixing them.
Is it here around Bethel or on the Kuskokwim,
Would you gather tall cottongrass tubers?
I don't know about them here on the Kuskokwim, but in the Akula region, inland in Nunapitchuk.
We had a place to gather tall cottongrass tubers over there, you know, there would be some there.
Well, what were the tubers' plants again?
Places with those have those tubers. Tall cottongrass, places with tall cottongrass.
Do you know how different villages have slightly different ways of making Yup'ik ice cream?
People from the Yukon, or other places?
Maybe. I know, I think it's people from up there on the Yukon.
They like to make Yup'ik ice cream, I mean, they also make Yup'ik ice cream with meat, you know, meat
White fish meat, after cooking it, then deboning it, then taking off their skins
Then wring them, then make Yup'ik ice cream.
You know, it's like they use them as snow.
Then this, what does it do? It rises, rises.
Well, I don't know those.
Except for the people up there, Yukon.
Then recently, that person invited me to go eat.
I had Yup'ik ice cream with meat, you know, with whitefish meat added. They do that.
But how do they make aged salmon egg ice cream?
In the past, did they made salmon egg ice cream when you were small?
They made salmon egg ice cream with, you know, fish roe from the Kuskokwim.
You know they hang them to half dry?
Then they encase them. (Only king salmon?) Any kind, dog salmon, they would hang any kind of roe to dry.
Then my spouse and I had a lot of fish roe when he had a lot of dogs.
When he made food for the dogs, he would add in roe from there into the meat.
Then when we wanted to make salmon egg ice cream, the roe beneath inside.
He would take some like this.
Some say, "Just like cheese." They say they are cheese.
They say it's like Western cheese.
They would make aged salmon egg ice cream out of that soft part that wasn't hard.
And now, they make fish egg ice cream out of whitefish roe. It's very good.
That's the first time I heard that.
Whitefish roe is very good, you know, crushing them.
They have no odor. Those [others] are, you see,
Roe from the Kuskokwim have an odor, you know?
They are, you know, rich.
These whitefish roe is very good, but after crushing them.
Then remove those things that look like hair.
They have things that look like hair. It's porbably the membrane from the roe.
They'd also make fish egg ice cream with those.
Do you happen to know any legends from long ago about Yup'ik ice cream?
I don't know. You know, I don't know legends.
You know, I didn't find anything fun.
Since I'm the one who visits others the most, I get suffocated easily.
Now, I don't know about any legends.
How did you go berry picking long ago? With kayaks?
We rowed boats.
One time from Nalqigliq downriver, at the old village sites across Napakiak.
You know, they're all gone now.
And my friend from Kasigluk died.
Tinker's wife.
She and I always played together, and liked to go with each other.
We went along with those who went to pick berries in Nunapitchuk.
We kept rowed, you know, rowing like this.
Well, they rowed.
We rowed up to Nunapitchuk, very far away.
Would you camp?
But we would camp, how many [several] days.
Then my friend and I would watch over our containers, you know, the berries we picked.
Those, it was probably a five gallon bucket.
That's what I used for a container.
The other had a hole in it.
You know gas had metal [containers]?
They had [those] containers, five gallon. That kind. We didn't know of any plastic.
But after picking crowberries, how did you store them until you used them?
I would see them put into those things,
They stored them in empty flour bags.
Then they submerged them in water. You know, they used the water like a freezer.
It's because they would be good there where it's cold.
And I know, my husband and I did this.
We let that sink across from us in the water.
Into the river?
Into the river.
But it was a major river.
Somewhere across there, I think it was in Nanvaryugyaq where it wasn't a path, where the boats wouldn't go through.
Then when it got cold, we raised it, took it, and put it in a container.
What about blueberries? Would they do that with blueberries too?
Blueberries, well, I didn't have any blueberries, you see.
But we do get blueberries and eat them right away.
We only ate them right away.
We didn't do that with them because they spoil easily.
But they don't spoil in freezers now.
Would they make Yup'ik ice cream with anything else? Other things?
Cranberries? They also make crushed whitefish roe ice cream with cranberries.
Whitefish roe ice cream. Do you know about it?
How do they make it again?
We would make crushed whitefish roe ice cream out of whitefish roe, also crushing it.
Then after crushing it, we would also crush, you know, the cranberries.
We crushed them without adding anything.
But salmon egg ice cream takes a lot of work. Do you know about it?
When they were made into crushed whitefish roe ice cream back then, wouldn't they be like yogurt?
Yes, and they wouldn't add anything to that crushed roe ice cream.
Crush it, then after crushing it, after taking out those things that look like hair
Then add berries and crush the cranberries.
After crushing it, mix it, adding sugar.
Does crushed roe ice cream have fish roe?
It is made of fish roe. They make crushed whitefish roe ice cream out of roe, whitefish roe.
I only know that they only make crushed whitefish roe ice cream out of those.
Then, you know, it would be fluffy. Then when it became like that, they finished it.
But they would eat it with seal oil, a little bit of seal oil.
Well, thank you for your stories.
We're finally done.
Stop.
I’m shy.
Did you pick these crowberries from here?
Yes, when they picked berries here last year.
[?(S)he gave me food], I think two five gallons, all of them.
Because she loves to pick berries, she would bring them probably because she had no more room.
Your mom loves to [?].
When she was a girl, would go travel together like that? (Yes.)
That’s what [?] has always been like.
She finds everything, you know, enjoyable.
And recently, in Fairbanks...
I wonder if she can do it in English?
Something for Caucasians to lsiten to. I don’t want to keep translating what you said.
Yes, but [?Napaskiak] today.
They came to sew very [?]. She and my sister sewed.
[Sewed] what?
The grant we received...