...he became my husband.
Then that person said to me
"Now, go in. I will bring your clothes upriver later."
Upriver, we lived downriver upriver from Keggukarmiut in a place called Kelliqucirmiut.
Oh my, then I went in when these people woke up in the early morning
When they didn’t use stoves, when they made kettles of hot water outside in fireplaces.
Oh my, when I went in and these people watched me, I would go more quickly and look away from them.
Oh my, when I went it, I undressed because I was hot, and because those before me didn’t do anything to me.
I undressed because my mother didn’t do anything and didn’t say anything to me.
I undressed.
I lay down because I was sleepy and ended up falling asleep.
It turned out that I wouldn’t know that I had gotten married for a long time, until eventually we arrived back home.
It turned out, they said, that that man purposely wanted us to go before him to make me respectfully withdrawn.
That’s how I found out.
I lived without knowing that I had a husband.
You see, during the fall, when the people of Chefornak over there where I grew up used to use hookless lures when dipnetting.
Were you born there?
I wasn’t born in Chefornak.
They said that I was born in the spring in Isrimiut, a spring camp, in May.
And they said that near evening, there was someone who found eggs when I was born then.
How far is Isrimiu? Isrimiut, which direction from Chefornak?
Toward the water down in the mountains. Haven’t you seen the mountains? (I see them.)
Toward the water from the mountains. Toward the water from the mountains across from Kipnuk.
Was that a village or a winter camp?
They were a big village. There were a lot of houses with sod for their spring camps.
And toward here, Nuuteqerrmiut also had houses, and they had a community house.
Over from them was the populated place of Chefornak. There were also a lot of people in Qikertaarmiut.
They were close together. And the baying dogs were visible, and people wandering were visible.
Oh my, their summer camps were very close together.
They said that the place I grew up would set up spring camps on this where they called in Isrimiut, in Isrimiut.
Oh my goodness, they were at spring camp.
You see, there were a lot of legendary little people around them.
And one with a signaling gaff would appear.
And when the one with the signaling gaff was going to reach the village, it would disappear.
And after it disappeared, there would be some amount of sleds going to the water beside them.
After they went to the water, those legendary little people would keep ahead of the people from that spring camp settlement.
They kept ahead of them.
After those sleds went to the water, they would go inland. Their sleds were read, filled full with animals.
Then right when evening came, those sleds would go here toward the mountains.
In the evening, there would be one with a signaling gaff who was from this spring camp settlement.
Then there was a community house outside of our house here, a huge community house.
Our dear grandfather, the one they said was Evnguq’s father, would come and sit up there on the above-ground entrance of the community house
He sang to the one withe the signaling gaff who was coming inland toward here.
And we girls and boys would embrace him like a nest, embraced and listened to him.
Oh my, we even eventually learned his song.
You see, he would sing like this, watching that one with the signaling gaff:
"One with the signaling gaff-raya-yarra-ii-ya
"Aa-ii-ya [?the many blades of grass]
"Spotted seal-spotted seal-spotted seal-spotted seal, bearded seal-yaa-yarra-ii-ya
"Aa-ii-ya [?the many blades of grass."
We who listened to him completely learned it.
When the one with the signaling gaff arrived, when he stood in front of him with clear intent
He stuck his small gaff in the ground, put it here, and told a story.
He told the ones who would get [the animals they caught].
Oh my, the same number of legendary little people would go to the water in front of them every day.
It turned out that they would show beforehand how many there would be.
Oh my, the same number that would go toward the water everyday would go get the animals they had caught.
Oh my, in the winter, the ones who were at spring camp would fill the walls of their houses, and excess would go on the floor.
The huge walls in there, the walls of their spring camp houses would be filled with animals, and the excess would go on the floor.
Oh my goodness.
That’s what the people I was born in time to see back then were like.
Hold on, please. This ran out of battery.
...my grandchildren’s children, my great-grandchildren.
The eldest sister of Pangall’aq’s children, Nura’ar, you know, Qussauyaq, Arnaaquq, Tikaaq
Their youngest sibling downriver, Nanugaq.
I see.
And Uyangqalria with her five children, pregnant with their sixth downriver.
And Miisaq’s three children.
And Ciulluk’s one child, what would be their younger siblings being miscarried, coming out undeveloped.
There are now five who’ve come out undeveloped, the ones who’d Ciulluk’s child’s younger siblings.
And over in Kwigillingok, Akat’aq’s children are my great-grandchildren.
Their oldest sister is here, you see.
The next younger one has also married as a daughter-in-law in Chefornak.
But she comes to her parents.
The one over there...
They were visible long ago during your time.
There were a lot of shamans in my time.
Please tell us stories about them.
We hear this now: good shamans, and bad shamans.
Or however. I might be speaking nonsense. You know them. Please tell stories about them.
Some of them, I noticed that some people on the verge of death would hallucinate seeing those shamans that I observed.
And some of the people on the verge of death would hallucinate seeing that shaman.
Some on the verge of death would do that, saying that he was going after them.
They hallucinated on the verge of death.
Even though some, however, were said to be shamans, they would be shamans without every having any word said about them.
They would be like ordinary people, with no word said about them.
However, there were bad ones among them.
Looking at his female cross-cousin, I also caught a shaman, you see.
I caught a shaman in my dream.
One time, I found myself, let me tell you the story, I found myself in the wilderness, sitting all by myself on the ground.
When I heard something, I turned my head this way and saw a door here.
There was a right arm, you see, touching the ground as it approached.
I thought, "Oh my goodness, this is not a good things."
Then before it reached me since it was a little far, I prayed in my sleep down there.
I asked the Lord to help me, and that I knew that I couldn’t think of anything to combat this thing approaching that was going to reach me.
I said I had nothing to combat with the same power, but asked to give me strength.
I asked to be given strength for this situation.
Because I was nervous as it was going to reach me
When I was finihsed, I opened my eyes as I was sitting with my legs stretched out to find my huge woman’s knife between my legs.
How did that come? Yet I was in the wilderness.
I took it.
When I took it, I saw that it was going to reach me here.
You see, I turned to face it straight on.
When I faced it as it was going to reach me, I knelt here like this.
I took the knife with its handle like a [?weapon].
After I prayed then, I opened my eyes and didn’t feel like myself, and I felt strong.
And so, when this right hand reached here
I did this with the knife and set it down.
Then it started crunching. I shut my eyes fast as it crunched.
As it was crunching, you see, [the knife] stuck into the ground.
Then something screeched, and it seemed like metal screeching. It withdrew into silence.
Oh my, I looked back and the arm was gone.
Oh my, I thought to myself, while this knife stuck into the ground all the way to its handle.
Oh my, it seemed to [?], but I think I wounded it.
When I got up and looked around my, oh my, I saw these hands springing up around me.
The ones that sprang up didn’t stay still, but would jump.
I chased them and would chop them.
Eventually, they stayed still. When they stayed, I chopped them up.
I threw these fingers in random directions, threw them in random directions so they wouldn’t be gathered.
When I had nothing left to do, I stood up and kept that knife with me.
I made my way home over to Kwigillingok. I made my way home.
I started to dream about those kinds of things in various ways because of Cegg’aq.
Cegg’aq here.
Cegg’aq said this to me:
"Oh my goodness, you," he was drunk
"Hey you, let me heal you."
He said that he had healed Ayagina’ar over there, the one who made it this far.
"Let me heal you.
"When you wash yourself, when you bathe, if I heal you, you would bathe adding in your bathwater with saltwater from down there."
He said that he would add on who should be healed, then heal them
Like Ayagina’ar there.
Oh my, since my mind didn’t want that
I told him that it would be fine if I continued to wash this way.
I told him it would be fine if I continued to wash like this. I said I didn’t want to do that.
He started making me dream since then, because I didn’t accept his offer.
Since then, I stopped dreaming about him.
But I would dream about those strange things like that.
I made my way home and arrived.
Oh my, I looked around after I cut those hands up
At that time, spring was nigh
And they had celebrated Christmas. It was long since they’d celebrated Christmas.
The ground surface had melted.
And these lakes were melting, but their ice hadn’t melted yet.
And the area between rivers had started gtetting water.
I looked around with the land like that.
When I went home and arrived, when I went into our house, I realized that I was sleeping, tried to awake myself and opened my eyes.
When I woke up and their poor father asked what happened to me, I told him.
I told him that I had that kind of dream.
If my dream was true, I said that I would watch all spring for what nature out there was like.
I told him this without reaching the point.
Then I kept watch.
And a long time ago, did you know that they would set up a lot of tents at the mouth of the Kuigilnguq River?
I was only born in time to see Tengmiarsuk and family. I think they were the last ones.
On this side of Kuigilnguq, there used to be a multitude of tents far downriver.
There were also a lot of tents here upriver from them.
And across from them, there would be a lot of tents.
When they used to go downriver en masse to the mouth of Kuigilnguq.
Oh my goodness.
That’s what they did.
We went downriver and stayed across on the other side. There were a lot of people.
And my cousin, [?]’s mother and I were neighbors, back when she was alive and well.
As we stayed, you see, they started catching a lot of animals from down [in the ocean].
I made "little feet [?]" trying to finish them all, the ringed seal skins I had to make into "little feet."
As we were doing that, you see, a person out there opened the door.
We had a black tent, with a white part in the middle to let in light.
That’s what we were like.
The person said as he came in behind me, Qayuq’s father when he was alive.
Then he said to their namesake, he said to Acill’aq
"Cousin, you should go to them across there."
He said that he wasn’t going to them because he was having stomach problems.
Then I noticed those things.
Oh my, he said that Cegg’aq passed away.
Oh my, nothing was wrong with him, nothing was wrong with him at that time.
Oh my, I said, "What happened to him?"
They said that when we coughed up what he coughed up, he passed away
Because he’d started coughing up [blood].
Oh my goodness.
Then they crossed [the river] together.
When they crossed and I didn’t want to work anymore, I dropped what I was working, went out, and look around the land
Remembering what I had dreamt the last winter.
That person passed away right at that exact point.
And the river down there was getting watery, both sides of the riverbank were getting watery.
Oh my, it was exactly what I had dreamt.
Oh my. I was so scared at that time.
I was scared.