...when they’re green, freshly grown.
After putting them into a bowl, pour seal oil onto them, add in dried pike, then eat them.
They are very good.
She said that she used to use those things to eat [?], and they mixed them with seal oil.
And then they also...
They were healers.
Because I’ve never gone to shamans, I don’t know about them.
They said that shamans... I don’t know them because I didn’t see shamans around.
I’m not telling them about what I don’t know, but only what I do know.
I say I don’t know what I don’t know. I don’t know how shamans work.
She said she didn’t go to any shamans, so therefore she can’t tell you.
And she can’t really talk about something she doesn’t know.
I used to hear about urine.
To someone on the verge of freezing, someone who is very cold in the wilderness on the verge of freezing, on the verge of freezing with his whole body cold
I heard that the person who found him would immediately have him drink his urine.
His urine?
The person that came would give his urine for the one on the verge of freezing to drink.
She said that the one example that she knows is when urine was used
Was when a person almost freezes or goes through hypothermia, when the body is already cool
She said the person who rescues that person or comes up to them would pee and let that person drink that urine.
Nass’, I heard that for the...
I heard that he gives him his warmth, that person who is well would help him by giving him his warmth.
She said that it was usually the one who...
...through that urine, the warmth, let it go through their body.
Back then, urine was also used medicinally.
Urine in those days was also treated as medicine.
How would they use it?
Now, you see these days that there are not a lot who do that.
But since people are cleaner, they have stopped breaking out with sores that they would call impetigo.
People are cleaner these days.
The germs from dirt can no longer penetrate the body and cause it to break out because they consistently wash.
Back when they didn’t consistently wash, urine was used medicinally.
Some children’s, and even some adults’ heads would break out with impetigo.
And some of their scalps would get hardened crusts from those stores.
But urine would make them better.
After soaking them in seal oil to soften them, you know how the discharge from inside those sores would harden
After soaking that in seal oil to soften it, then when it softened
Finally, they would use aged urine, not fresh, that has become potent to wash their heads.
And after washing them, they would warm up less potent urine and was their heads again, taking off the scabs.
And then after removing them, they would apply a little seal oil to keep them from drying out.
They said that those washed with urine would not break out again for a long time.
Go ahead and translate it now. You’ll forget what it’s about.
[?] Let me mention something about what I know.
Affter translating this.
After translating it.
She says the other use for urine was, she said you see nowadays that nobody uses urine...
Yes.
Those willows are native to the Akula region.
Then out here on the Kuskokwim, the big trees on the Kuskokwim have completely different names.
(Yes.) You know some of the willow shoots (Yes.) [?] you know their insides are delicious. (Yes.)
And do they add their branches into soups?
You know we add them in the summer? (I never have before.)
We add them in the summer before they harden.
Did you mention them?
I didn’t mention them.
Because you’re talking about trees.
Then two weeks ago, I’ve never gathered them before, I went to Anchorage and my daughter said this to me:
”Mom, why don’t you make food out of trees?"
"Out of what?"
"And why don’t you make food from the leaves of willow shoots?"
I said to her, "I don’t know them."
And then my daughter told me that her friend fed her the leaves of willow shoots in seal oil from Unalakleet.
She said they were very good.
And then I said, "Wow, there’s so many willow shoots on the Kuskokwim."
Now, I’m preparing to put willow shoots in a jar with seal oil when summer sets. My daughter really wants me to.
It turns out we don’t know what we can eat.
I just talked about what food we can prepare.
This is Elena Nick and their cousins. She says, you know, there’s so many different...
They take care of frostbites by trying to thaw them out. Frostbites don’t thaw right away.
They would take care of them by trying to thaw them.
How exactly would they do that?
Leave me and don’t ask me about that. I don’t like it.
Her husband got really frostbitten. He almost died. She doesn’t want to talk about it.
That reminds her of...
[?] there is treatment for frostbite.
Well, they, when I was younger, we used to have frostbites on our cheeks when we played too long outside.
And then the old people would let us put a little bit snow on the frozen part for a while and then let it go.
And stay in the hosue and try to thaw it out with our hands, not by the stove.
Because they say when you put something warm on it, the cold part will go inside, and that’ll rot the skin.
So, that was the only thing we knew.
Do you know how the snow is supposed to help them...
I don’t know. They said it’s supposed to bring out the frozen part...
We can go into another break, fast ten minute break.
Today, they...
I apologize. (It’s okay.)
You can go to the bathroom. (Okay.) Okay.
My husband went out looking for that boy that was missing since Saturday, George Guest Jr., I mean, George Guest.
He was gone since Saturday, and then my husband went out looking for his three-wheeler yesterday by plane.
And then he found a three-wheeler somewhere between here and Atmauthluk.
Then they started looking for him.
Every time when George landed, he was right there. He takes off, he didn’t see him, he was right there, close to the three-wheeler.
They found him this morning. And they went out, and George brought him in, and he’s not supposed to carry passengers.
He could hardly move.
Poor thing. He’s still alive?
He was still alive.
[?] to Anchorage?
I don’t know.
He said she was still there, his mom and his sister were there.
Ran out of gas or something?
Something wrong with his three-wheeler.
He was gone since Saturday. Saturday, Sunday, Monday, Tuesday.
Three days? (Poor thing.)
Those tall cottongrass, you know that we eat the insides of tall cottongrass? We split them and eat what’s inside.
Cloudberries would be contained in woven bags out of those, big woven bags. They were big like this.
After she picked berries in the summer, my late mother would put them into one of those.
Then she would make a deep pit, digging into the tundra all the way to the permafrost below.
And after digging it, it would get filled with water.
And when it was filled, that woven grass container filled with cloudberries
They would weave tall cottongrass into containers with gaps of a certain size circling them around like this, weaving them into circular patterns like this.
And then closing off the bottom.
They were like those sewn things you call baskets.
But they had wide gaps.
And then they would fill that with berries.
After filling it full, they would tie it there, then weave a cord into by weaving grass.
They closed the rim off tightly.
And then after doing that, she would put it into the pit she dug filled with water.
Then after putting it in, she would line the sides with trees, then close off the mouth with dirt.
It would stay there all summer.
And then in the fall as it was going to freeze close to winter, she would take it out.
Before it froze and got stuck, she would take it out.
She would take them out and they were very good. They were like freshly picked berries in that woven grass container.
They were very good.
And the other ones, the sourdock, you know those green sourdock.
She boiled them, and when they were cooked, she would ladle them out, cool them off, and put them into a woven grass container.
The same way, she would bury them into a put like that so that they would be submerged.
And she left them. Then it froze, and as they were going to get stuck, she would take it out like that cloudberry container.
She kept them cool, kept them frozen.
That’s what they did to their winter food supply.
Would you make a sourdock-berry mixture here?
Would you make sourdock-berry mixtures?
Would you add blueberries to the sourdock?
We didn’t do that.
They would make sourdock-berry mixtures up north.
They cook the sourdock.
After they’re cooked, they mix blueberries with it, and then let it [?] she described in the ground.
And when it’s cooled off in the fall time [?]. And that’s another way of preserving the blueberries because the blueberries are harder to keep than the salmonberries.
So are you going to translate that?
She was talking about her mother that...
What?
The seal blood...
Tell him I don’t live where there’s seals. I live here. Tell him I don’t know about seals.
But the coastal people, tell him to ask the two old men that joined us this morning.
Tell him they’re coastal people.
Please tell them. Tell them over there.
We’re not from the place where there’s lots of seals or those things.