Now, you know how children play with toys.
You know in old times, they would play with small dolls, and tell storyknife stories that we don’t see now.
Which do you think is more fun:
The children who do not tell storyknife stories or play with dolls, or the ones who played with dolls and storyknives?
Because these children play with Western toys
They’ve started watching TV, and stopped playing with the toys that we had back then.
You see, back when we were girls, we liked to tell storyknife stories.
We always had a storyknife with us.
What were the storyknives made of?
I had a storyknive made of a little ivory, ivory.
Ivory, and I’m not sure who made it. I would never stop telling storyknife stories.
Since we had friends, when our friends and we weren’t in school, there was only storyknife stories.
We would tell storyknife stories, and my friend’s and my way of telling stories, those villages had names. We preteneded they were Inlanders.
Some of the ones you talked about were the Inlanders?
What kinds of things would you tell stories about?
We made them a family. We said that this village
She would call the partners Inlanders.
These was Nunapigngiar and family, and this was Ceńaqviuksuk and family were always the furthest over there.
She named those people Nunapigngiar and family.
We made up families and made them houses.
Did they try to be the greatest? Did they try to be the best?
She gave them little things like us that we’ve seen. She would have them do as she did.
And when we didn’t tell storyknife stories, we would play string games with string.
But they would admonish us against playing string games for long, saying that a legendary little person would come in on us.
[It would come in] to those playing string games. We wouldn’t play string games for long, then quit.
I wonder why?
I don’t know. And in the summer, we would play with small dolls.
We had small dolls, almost every girl.
They would have a lot of small dolls. This would make up a small family.
And these dolls, we had those toys too.
What other toys were there?
We had small dolls.
And dolls, but when winter set, we would store away the dolls.
We only played with small dolls in the house, not dolls, but we went outside [to play with the dolls].
Only when the birds came in the spring would we then start playing with dolls.
Why wouldn’t you bring them out? What would they say?
We wouldn’t bring those dolls out.
They said that if we bring them out, the weather will, you know
Summer would set late, constant blizzards, they said it would be strange. We wouldn’t bring dolls out.
Would you pretend to cook?
Do what?
Pretend to cook.
We always played, and we played outside making houses out of grass.
We wove grass into caches. We would play, pretending to have children and mothers.
We pretended to cook, pretended to do things.
Would you pretend to have women’s knives?
Yes.
Out of what? What kinds of women’s knives would you have?
What kinds of women’s knives did we have?
We would also make clothes for them out of sourdock.
We used grass for them. We would have fun when we played.
And back when I had grown a little, I stopped playing with small dolls and didn’t tell too many storyknife stories anymore.
But in the summer, I always paddled with a canoe.
I never stopped going to the wilderness every day because the weather would also be good.
Did you teach your children to play like that, to make small dolls?
I didn’t make my children small dolls, but they had dolls.
Dolls, and I tried to have them tell storyknife stories, and they would pretend to tell legends.
What about the children [?who do not] do that today?
My grandchildren now only play with Western toys.
When they don’t play, they watch TV.
Do you think they’ll have fun if they tell storyknife stories?
They would have fun if they told storyknife stories.
It was also fun when we told storyknife stories.
When the men were going to travel, how would you prepare food for them?
How would you prepare things for them, you know, when you were small for your father or
Or when you took a husband, when your husband was going to go for several weeks?
When my father was going to travel, my mother would prepare for him
Food, tea, sugar for him. They always had portable stoves.
But when the weather was good, those men would cook outside.
Would they get their own food by hunting?
Yes.
Then I would notice that they would make drift nets out of [a certain type of] string.
My father would also make a fishing tool by carving wood, making fish traps.
The men I watched would make fish traps for blackfish, and they added steel traps.
My spouse did too when we got married. We always went to winter and spring camp.
Then I realized that back when I lived with my family, my parents, when I lived with my parents
Every spring, we would move in March.
We would set tents on the snow.
And yet we weren’t cold. And we put the stove on the snow.
We would live in the tent starting from March.
When we moved, we would camp, then after we camped
After we took our supplies ahead, after our father took our supplies ahead
We would then reach where we would stay. It would be wonderful.
And because the weather would be good
Even though we stayed in the tent, we wouldn’t be cold.
We were used to it since we had always done that.
In March, we would live in a tent.
Would you be hit by strong winds?
It would be windy sometimes.
But we would be able to use [the tent] in the wind.
And as summer was approaching, it would be rainy.
It would be wonderful with sunny weather.
So what would you women do when you traveled?
When we traveled?
Going with them, you know, in March.
In March?
You know, you just told us that you would travel, right, in March?
Living in a tent, what would you women do?
You see, I liked to gather wood.
Early in the morning, right after dawn
I would get up and gather wood
’cause I was the oldest one, because I was the eldest sister in the family.
I always gathered wood, enjoying gathering wood.
So what would your mother do?
My mother never stopped preparing things
Everyhing my father would need, and she would make them waterproof skin boots.
And all of us had waterproof skin boots, handmade water boots.
We would use those waterproof skin boots in the spring.
What were they made of? What were they made of?
We had waterproof moose skin boots, large caribou skins.
There used to be a lot of moose a long time ago.
All over, there were a lot of caribou.
And then in 1941, a lot of caribou died.
They also said wolves ate them.
Then the caribou were gone, no more caribou.
What would the parents do to lazy women, the lazy women?
They probable told the lazy women to do things.
What traditional wisdom would they have for lazy people?
For me, mostly only my father taught me.
He told me this: if I am lazy, to see that someday
I will try to make my own living.
And then if I am lazy, I won’t have anything.
He told me not to be lazy but to continously work, looking at the way these people do things.
And when berries grow in the summer, to pick berries.
And he said that if I have a provider, if my provider catches fish, to take care of the fish.
I should treat them with love, not be disinclined to do them, and not make a mess of them.
The people I saw back, my parents
They didn’t make a mess of fish, never made a mess, out of reverence for the fish.
Even if they’re bones, they told us not to put them on the floor out of love.
To revere them. He said, you see, that if we do not revere them and tread upon them
We won’t have things.
Or our drift nets will not catch anything, or our fish traps will not catch anything because we don’t love them.
They told us to revere everything, and to even treat our clothes with love.
And now, to this day, I do not make a mess of anything.
And even though there’s a lot of things, I do not make a mess of them out of love, but revere them.
And you know that fish have poison, fish have poison. How would you tell them apart?
The people I watched a long time ago would revere fish
They would not let the fish they worked on be exposed to the sun.
And on the net, what had been caught in the net that had been exposed to the sun
They would prepare the ones that had bloated to be food only for dogs.
That’s why they never had food poisining. I’ve never seen any person have food poisoning.
And when I had grown up, not many people died.
Once in a great while, a person would die. And the people I saw wouldn’t get sick too often.
And I never saw anyone drunk.
But when I was 16, I saw someone drunk for the first time.
Now when girls are 16, you know, they become adults.
I became a woman late because I became a woman when I was 16.
And I got married to my spouse when I was 18. My parents chose my spouse.
What about those who sewed grass?
I didn’t grow up with those who sewed grass, but they would weave grass.
And then women who had gotten older would make mats out of coarse grass
They would tightly weave them. They wove great things.
My grandmother died back then. I think she died when I was about eight.
That why when we weren’t playing, we would go to the old women.
I would have fun when they worked weaving grass.
Then it’s been recently that the Mikelnguut Elitnaurviat wanted old teachings.
Old things. When my mother was alive, they asked my mother to make things.
They asked her to make things in the old way, grass mats for kayaks, earrings, and I think necklaces.
Then my mother said that she wouldn’t. She said that I should try.
Then I wove grass, replicating the old women that I used to watch.
I wove grass like they did, making small warp strands with course grass.
I used some of them to thread through. The things they wove would be like this: these going this way, and these going this way.
They had small warp strands that were this thick. They wove grass like this.
Look, the little woven grass bag across there. Give it to me.
This one?
There, no, there it is, yes, that too.
They would make mats like this.
They made warp strands like, and made the gaps this size.
I made grass mats for kayaks.
Then my mother watched and said to me, "Look, twist them this way like this."
Then when I started doing that, they started becoming like this.
You see, the small grass mats for kayaks I made are inland in Mikelnguut Elitnaurviat, and my name is there, Elena Charles.
Then when they asked me to make a woven grass bag, I made a bad out of tall cottongrass.
I made it like this, but pretty big.
But the bottom down there got long, and I braided the end.
This is done well.
And the bottom here?
This is made very well.
Please hold it, connecting the bottom parts, showing the bottom.
They would also weave grass to make fish carrying bags.
When they didn’t have paper boxes, they always made bags for fish.
And the dry fish they made would be good.
They would weave grass with this close pattern.
They called those kuusqulluut.
Their openings would be woven, the grass would be woven to make ropes.
Would the aged herring be in them as well?
We didn’t have aged herring. I’m from [the] tundra.
And caches, every family would have a cache.
Fish cache, and it would have wooden posts.
It was airtight up there, and the wall was airtight.
But their floors had holes.
And the fish in them wouldn’t spoil.
And the frozen fish inside the fish bags would be very good.
And the dry fish in them wouldn’t get mold. They’d be good.