With houses, we want them to take advantage of that good weather.
Down there, I also tell those young people down there.
Some of them, I’m not sure what they make of me.
Some of them listen until I am completely finished.
The boys and the girls listen extremely well.
And those poor people out there, I tell them about what I have just said.
I do talk to them about how they should be.
Because though wouldn’t do anything or talk back, the poor things listen to me.
One of them also took me around here yesterday
He stays at the house of someone who’s about to give birth.
He says he stays at their house.
Look, those struggling people that I was born in time to see, I never saw anyone else like them after.
See, it’s been a long time since I became aware.
You see, I am now 93 years old.
If I make it safely to May, I will turn 94.
My age past 90.
It’s unfortunate now. I really wish to be strong for you, especially you young people.
I wish that I could be strong for what I just said.
I want you to become good people, and do not disregard the wisdom passed to you. Become obedient people and see.
You, see if you become obedient people, you will become good people, if you become people who follow the wisdom passed to you.
You will become good people.
You see, even though one is not always obedient like this, being obedient and faithful leads to a good life.
Now, you see, in your poor state,
And before I saw anyone who wronged me, I’ve become like this.
Here I am.
Before anyone said harmful words to me, I’ve become like this.
I treated everything the same through having you watch me.
It’s good to treat everyone the same without thinking them of them as children, and encouraging them.
You see, only a person who is like that will go through life well.
And like that, he will not come to anything, or accidents, and he will keep going without coming to being treated badly.
Only one who is just, who is obedient.
An obedient person who does not disregard traditional wisdom, but applies them, will be like that.
My dear husband and I were married without being abusive.
He did break my heart, but I didn’t, you know, do the same to him.
It had turned out that it would be a good thing if he passed before me.
It’s a good thing I was like that even though he had broken my heart.
It’s a good thing that I wasn’t like that even though he had broken my heart.
I still think that’s a good thing to this day.
See, here’s another thing:
The first here, when I hear about people putting down others and treated them badly,
You see, that first one is not untrue, it’s definitely not untrue.
You see, I remember what Jesus said when I hear about people doing this, when he said this:
He said that he did not come to destroy this commandment, but to fulfill it.
You see? See that the one with the authority to destroy it, did not destroy even a little of the first customs and commandment.
It was not destroyed in the least.
I think of it now very clearly.
Well, is it time for me to stop, cousin?
It’s time for you to stop.
Okay, please stay now that it’s time to end.
Please stay. Let me tell these young people about the traditional wisdom that I know and think of, okay?
Okay.
Okay now. Understand this truth:
If we intentionally sin, our sins will have no more chances of forgiveness,
But in our future there is a great trial,
And a frightening fire for the destruction of the sinners, Hebrews 10:26.
Now it’s done.
Yes, thank you. (It’s done.)
That’s all, no.
He did not go out for twelve hours.
When she walked around the house, she would always walk with a tube attached here.
Here's my spouse and I.
But the one who was like that lived for three months without our knowledge.
??It’s been a long time since those who are in our lands fish salmon for money.
Through the fish in 1976, here is what they studied here on the Kuskokwim and near the mouth of the Yukon.
These Causcasians do not tell us because we’re Yup’ik.
It also says this:
It says that what they call mercury, down in the rivers...
Matthew, we asked you to speak about this: waste and spills (?)
It’ll be fine if you do that later.
Our time is running out.
It won’t take long.
I first wanted to explain that means, what my work means.
I am now alone like a piece of debris on the sand on the shore.
When I explain it, people doubt me and try to stop me like this.
But if we understood, our people probably would not be like this.
They say that because our fish now, since our fish are like this unbeknownst to us
When we eat them, especially their livers
When a woman eats salmon with those bad things we don’t know about
Our counterparts who do not understand
I travel working with people
I repeatedly leave my wife despite our children.
That’s the reason I’m bringing it up.
It still hasn’t stopped now.
If I get that, it will be like I have gotten something.
With the destruction of our salmon without our knowledge through the pollution of those looking for profit
They say that because this fetus inside is upside down, it destroys his brain.
Yet he is born underdeveloped.
And now, I am going to speak so that our survival will improve.
Because of that, I started traveling a lot without stopped and rarely sat.
But ONC and AVCP paid for my lodging and meals here in the city
And I didn’t think of money for myself.
It was only so that people here would get better.
And then when a child is born like this, he is underdeveloped.
It turns out its inside in his brain.
Now, when we admonish these children, they’ve started thinking:
"I wonder why he’s admonishing me against that?"
We probably don’t explain the origin of that, curious about how that is harmful.
When they are curious about it, even alcohol and marijuana, they will wake up with a slight headache and be wide awake that evening.
That is what destroys our young people.
But now, it’s as if I am going forward.
Because even though I bring it up to our people here in Alaska and to the governement, they don’t listen to me.
I went to another place out of state to ask for help from my former fellow teacher.
He will take care of us.
You’ve probably also seen one of you up there in October and in December
Here on KYUK TV, and you’ve seen it in January and the beginning of February
They said that they would show that again between 12 and 8 on KYUK.
It is important to them.
And now, these two dear people are recording me with that in mind.
It will probably show sometime again.
In order for our people to go forth well, I am not sitting for this anymore.
We have unknowingly allowed it to become like this.
Since that is harmful to the mind in different ways
Since people live with varying strengths, some of them are strongly affected, and some are not harmed much.
I am not speaking of our ancestors right now, but especially what our people, our people, are harmed by
To try to help you understand.
So that we they will become better in our future, I want to see them go forth better before I am gone from this earth.
Now, we are only working to encourage those who have been mentally hurt from the beginning.
Many Caucasians do not have any enthusiasm for that, only we Yupiit, because they profit off of us.
You see, they have a lot of workers, social workers, police, interrogators, planes, and health care workers all gathered.
They say that now, alcohol is the only one, not other ailments
The state has lost over $300 million to those working for the people.
They are not enthusiastic because they would lost a lot with their work.
Here, you know that they cannoy stop those who sell
Since the police down there do not work hard on them since it is a source of income.
That’s why, there may be a lot of explanations on this paper
Since I am not working here anymore, I am personally not sitting for my young people, our young people.
Maybe if you teach and push your young people toward science
If it does not hold meaning for a single Yup’ik, it will get worse.
See what the Caucasians have brought forth: they are not readily available to listen to us, only telling us to quit.
They only listen once in a while.
From what I see now, they are not getting more peaceful, not getting easier.
Becuase of these salmon, those of us here between Akula and the Yukon are the most harmed than our fellow people here in our state.
Because our salmon are eating the pollution from those making profit unbeknownst to us
And between us, the animals probably choke on things and eat the salmon among the plants when the main river floods inland then goes out.
I do request them for researchers for those, especially how those are taken care of.
It I think we will get help from Switzerland.
This summer, they will present taking care of the earth in relation to our ailments.
It’s going to be two years since they’ve come to Bethel and researched for two weeks
Also going inland to nature aroudn us and examining the plants.
Do not tire of the sources of our work to improve us going forward, but continue them.
They only listen once in a while, especially our counterparts.
Here is what they strive for: our riches down in our pristine lands.
That is the main reason that they do not cooperate with us.
You who have gone to school also know that they shot arrows and guns at the Native Americans and reduced their populations.
Now, they utilize those, the destruction of the nature and land around us, to reduce our population.
And our population isn’t increasing.
We also don’t reach a million.
You see, I traveled to a place that reached a population of eight million, a single city.
As a Yup’ik, it was as if I were a single piece of sand on the shore.
Because I was helpless, I said that first.
I have peers who would like to speak. Thank you for listening.
Because I wasn’t like this a long time ago
Also because I would regret what I said after I speak.
It turns out that becoming this age, it gets less difficult to speak.
Poor me, I just listened to what I was like.
But my teacher back then, because I stayed on the floor on a mattress
Before I went out, my teacher would speak to me even if it wasn’t all the time.
He would mainly speak to me about how I should live.
But I would listen to what we shouldn’t do and I wouldn’t be able to move.
He would speak to me about how I should live.
I just talked about what we shouldn’t do. I used to listen to him.
When he spoke, he would say that the people long ago would have no sicknesses.
Also, he said that when someone passed away once in a while in faraway villages, if there was a nimble person
He said that when that visitor arrived and said that someone from a faraway village had passed away
He said that that village would cry and grieve loudly over him.
I wonder why he said this? I recognize it now.
He said that later when the world is going to be no more, people will pass away more quickly.
He also said that they would start hurting themselves.
He said that they would stop grieving over them, but laugh at them.
He said that when the world is close to being no more, we people will become foolish all the same.
I used to hear this. It’s probably true now. I recognize it.
When I used to hear of the far future, my heart would skip a beat.
And I was worse than those doing wrong by abusing alcohol.
I heavily abused alcohol, and it would be the only thing in my mind coming from the wilderness
I realized that I was destroying my old body of my own volition.
My regret to this day is doing that in front of my children.
It turned out that I had taught them.
Today, that is my greatest regret.
And I cry
Becuase I had taught them something bad that would destroy me when I reached this age.
It is amazing how true what those people said long ago.
He would also especially talk about this:
"Never take another person’s possessions, and do not covet him.
"Also, if you enter another house, do not take even a single match or nail from that house.
"Or even if you travel in the wilderness, no matter what you see, do not covet and take it."
He said that a person never forgets what he puts even in the wilderness.
Because I am not fluent in English, what I had to say was about my teacher.
Alcohol destroys this body. And today, it’s accompanied by medicine and marijuana...