I advised them this, the elders, my peers:
This way, these school age children our children who are called the young people who are just starting,
Not to discourage them.
Don’t tell them that they are crazy, also don’t call them names, names that aren’t theirs.
If we do that, us elders will be creating enemies for ourselves.
They will be against us elders if we repeatedly hurt them.
But to tell them our way of life, our struggles in years past.
Hoping these things will be helpful to them.
Because while we are still alive as I have been watching, things have changed.
Everything is changing.
It’s not the the same as before. Even these people are changing.
Even our children are changing.
They now go to school.
They now go to highschool and to college. Back then we never saw these things.
These never happened.
We should not oppose the Kass’aq people so much even though they are doing these to us.
They are trying to help us through our children.
But sometimes we do not understand and view it as oppression.
We say that they are “breaking” our children,  these other people.
They need to learn. Through the education they have received, our children, our young people
Are helping us elders of today. We cannot do these things.
Even here with this Elders Conference, these young people obtained money for our travel
They let us see each other, we who have no other way to get together
Our children are able to do this.
My own children don’t always follow advice.
Waniwa tauna elluarr[luku]...