Please try again.
Let me try speaking. Can you hear me?
Now, let me speak of the traditional wisdom when I was growing up.
I grew up where we had a settlement in the wilderness inland, or we had our own settlement at the mouth of Tagyaraq.
But in the summer, we were be at the fish camps when I was a girl. We would stay in the wilderness inland in the fall with no one around us.
And downriver in Tagyaraq during the winter, there was no one around us.
But when we went to fish camps, we’d finally start seeing people.
Then I would stay with my grandmother because she raised me, because my grandparents raised me.
However, I had two other women with me. We were a family.
Then my grandmother would tell us, and she would admonish us in the morning when we wake up against fighting, that we shouldn’t fight.
We small family, we small family in that house did not fight.
She would tell us this: we should always be busy and help each other without fighting.
Then when we went to populated places, she would also say this to me when I was going to go out in the morning:
If they pick on me, and if they pick on me as we’re playing, that I should run away. She told me not to retaliate.
Then she would also tell me this: no matter what a person does to me, I should not retaliate, but always treat my peers with love. She told us to treat each other with love.
She also said to treat all of our peers with love.
Back when I was a girl, when we were girls, she would talk to us about how we should behave all day.
That’s why we feared her since she spoke to us as if scolding us.
When we disobeyed her traditional wisdom, my grandmother would speak to us very sternly as if scolding us.
That’s why we were afraid to go against her traditional wisdom.
The would instruct us to treat each other with love like that, and not to pick on our peers.
And no matter what a person does to us, we should not retaliate.
But they would say this to us: we shoudl always be busy, and not visit each other too often.
She said that if we visit other people too often, we’ll eventually be offended. She said that if we visit too often, we’ll eventually be offended.
Then she said that if we visit too often, we will lack things. She said that when we will lack things when we should have worked.
Then she talked about grass since we were all women
Back when I was growing up, people always took grass and wove them.
They made fish containers in the summer.
And they would pair king salmon with tall cottongrass, then cover them with tall cottongrass.
They said that if we do not gather, it will be clear what we would do. We would ask for things from our neighbors over there.
If we do not gather tall cottongrass to pair them with, we will ask for things.
She said that if we do not save things, we will be beggars. That’s what she told us.
We were poor. There was nothing when we were growing up.
Then she would tell us, well, it wasn’t like how it is now when we were growing up.
I haven’t become a very old lady yet.
But because I grew up around those old people, it seems they lived a very old life.
That’s what she told us, that we’ll be beggars if we do not save things.
And she said that if we’re going to sew, see how it’s not scarce these days, if we’re going to sew and we don’t save things, we’ll ask for thread from our neighbors over there.
Or, she said that we might borrow or ask for a needle if we don’t store things. That’s how poor we were.
That’s why our traditional wisdom warranted respect.
Then after telling us that, she would tell us that if we see a fish, this fish is the first thing.
If we see a fish, we should welcome it without thinking it’s too little. We should hang and dry it.
She said that would become food if we hand and dry it.
In the summer like this, she said we should cut even a single fish and hang it.
Then she said that when it dries, we can make it into dried and boiled fish.
However, she said that if we ignore it saying it’s too little, worms will eat it.
Worms destroy it, flies lay eggs on it and worms infest it until it’s no longer edible.
That’s why se said to store even a little fish. She said it becomes food even though it’s not a lot.
That’s what she would tell us.
Then, should we have providers, since we’re all women
Though there’s a lot of food [to prepare], a woman should not be overwhelmed by it.
Instead, she said she should not do a sloppy job on it. She said she should do it well and dry it.
Also, she said not to dump fish guts to where people have trod, but somewhere that no one has trod.
She said that fish guts are an eyesore when scattered on the ground here.
She said that being without food and an empty stomach is unbearable.
This is the traditional wisdom passed down to us.
They said that it’s worse having an empty stomach than any ailment or sickness.
That’s why a fish, these are our traditional wisdom.
That’s why they said not to despise a fish, to keep it even if it’s bad.
They said we won’t dislike anything if our stomach is empty.
These are the traditional wisdom passed down to us when we were young.
They also told us not to scatter food waste, but to throw it away where people have not trod.
And if we work on fish, they told us to throw away the waste where no on has trod.
They said that a fish that a person [?] should not be [?].
They also told us not to dislike our food.
They said that if there’s no food, we will not dislike or reject anything, since a person truly will not reject anything if he’s hungry.
These are our traditional wisdom.
Then, they said that should we marry and take care of a child
They said we should not push him to our husband. They said that that man travels.
That’s why they said we shouldn’t push that child to that man.
They said that if we are in a bind, he must play with him to entertain him, since a couple should help each other.
But they said he’s a traveler. We shouldn’t let him take care of the child.
They said that he would be sad over his leaving. When his father leaves, he would be bad missing him.
Eventually, they said that in his travels, he would be worried over him back home, and have bad travels if the child misses him.
They would admonish us against pushing our child to the man like that if we have children.
THen they said that when we raise our child, we will stay with our child in the house since we’re the caretakers, unlike the men who travel.
They said that we must watch our children in the house.
They also said not to react excessively when they misbehave.
They said that they get worse when they react excessively when getting tired of their misbehavior.
They also said that if we scold them, that we don’t need to add to our voices. We shouldn’t raise a hand on our children.
They said if we raise our hands on them, he’ll be impertinent.
They also said that if we excessively shout at him, he’ll be impertinent. They said that we’ll make our child impertinent.
That’s included in the traditional wisdom for women.
They said that we’ll make our child impertinent if we excessively shout at him.
He’ll be bad and disobedient though we admonish him.
Also, if he’s mischievous and we react excessively, he will get worse.
That’s why they said it’s okay to encourage a child instead.
Then they said that if we scold, every person can be irritating. They said they don’t always treat their children with love. They scold them when they get tiring.
They said that if we scold, we will scold him.
They said that after scolding him, do not laugh at him but leave him alone.
Leave him alone and don’t say anything [else] if we scold him.
Only when he gets better, treat him well after scolding him.
And if he cries, do not laugh at him after scolding him.
They said that if we laugh at him, he will become bad. They say that children who are laughed at also become bad.
That is also included in what we should do when we raise children in the house.
It’s because raising a child is not easy.
It’s hard work. We worked hard to raise our children back then.
And it wasn’t like how it is now when we raised our children.
We didn’t have disposable diapers.
That’s why we had a lot of traditional wisdom.
They said that if we sleep to much, we’ll get urine on us. Our child will urinate on his bed and get it on us. It will smell like urine.
Now, you like to be very clean.
They said that if we sleep too much, our house will smell like our child’s urine
Because we don’t have them urinate at night.
We would wake from our sleep, and have our children urinate in urine buckets at night.
And when we got up, we’d take the urine container, go out, and dump it.
They had diapers we’d need to wash.
We would always wash them since they didn’t have a lot of diapers and would run out. We who didn’t have a lot would wash their diapers later in the day.
That’s why we have that traditional wisdom, to look after little things.
They said that a person who doesn’t care for things doesn’t have anything.
He throws things away thinking their insignificant.
They also said that storing something does not [?].
They said that the time to use it comes when they put and keep it, then the time to use it comes.
That is our traditional wisdom, at the traditional wisdom I grew up with.
Then this love is an important piece of traditional wisdom.
No matter what our peer does to us, never retaliate.
Then if a guest arrives, socialize with him even if you don’t know where he’s from.
I was very shy.
I would be very daunted when they said this to me: "Even if you see him for the first time, socialize with him.
"And even if you see a guest for the first time, if there’s none for him, welcome him by mouth, talking to him, or feed him if there’s enough for him."
Here, I was very shy.
They said that socializing with a person by mouth or be feeding him, a person makes close friends.
He becomes friends with those he socialized with.
They say that some people are daunted when arriving in a village, and it’s true.
Those things that they talked to us about are true, that it’s difficult for a person to arrive where he’s never gone before.
That’s why we must give a hearty welcome to someone we don’t know or haven’t seen anywhere before.
They said that he’s daunted because he doesn’t know where he’s going. He’s daunted by that village because he doesn’t know where he’s going.
That’s what it’s like. When we go somewhere we’ve never been before, we’re daunted.
That’s why you young people should remember this.
Also, no matter what your peers do to you, never do anything because they did something to you.
We were also told to respect our parents.
That’s why to you who still have parents, this is the traditional wisdom passed down to me.
We must defer to and respect our parents, and try to adhere to their traditional wisdom.
That’s what we were told.
THat’s why we had to respect those who raised us.
THis is the traditional wisdom passed down to me when I was growing up.
There is a lot of our traditional wisdom, Yup’ik wisdom. There’s traditional wisdom for everything.
If we talked about them, we’d talk for a long time. There’s traditional wisdom for everything.
These are the important traditional wisdom passed down to me, looking after fish.
And to treat our peers with love no matter what they do to us, and not to retaliate no matter what someone does to us.
And how to take care of a child if we raise him.
What else?
Leaving us a legacy?
I would leave you, my grandchildren, with something that will never end if you remember it, I would leave you with traditional wisdom.
I just said now, "You must treat those around you with love."
No matter what anyone does to you, treat them with love. And do not do anything if they do something to you, but love them all the same.
This love is to be your bequest.
Then, love those around you, and depend on your God.
That is what I bequeath to you, my grandchildren.
Then my grandchildren down there, your relatives, I tell them at the dawn of every day to teach them, so that they will inherit the traditional wisdom.
So that you will remember it though I leave this place and you no longer see me.
I tell them at the dawn of every day to treat their peers and what siblings thye have with love, of even if they’re not siblings, or not to retaliate no matter what their peers do to them.
I also tell them not to speak harshly, you know, not to speak without thinking.
If you speak without thinking, you will come to regretful times.
That is my bequest that you must remember.
Though I leave this place, you must remember it, as an inheritance.
You know, about being lazy.
If a person is lazy, they also tell us this:
"There is no one without a lazy inclination. Every person is lazy [sometimes].
"But if a person lives by ’breaking’ his laziness and does things in spite of his laziness will be called one who is not lazy.
"However, a person who follows his laziness and is sedentary is lazy."
Truly, someone who does things in spite of laziness, who does things without laziness, eventually becomes eager.
Eventually, he remembers his chores, and knows what he needs to do, knows how he needs to serve, and knows them despite not being told because he does them.
He knows what he does, and knows how to do things.
That’s what a person who’s not lazy is like.
He knows them because he does them despite his laziness. Then even when he’s lazy, he raises his hand, is no longer lazy, and is eventually eager.
He starts wanting to do things, wanting to do things, doing chores. That’s what someone’ who’s not lazy is like.
He starts thinking of his chores, knowing his chores.
Yet since a lazy person follows his laziness and is sedentary, though he knows what he needs to do, he’s lazy.
They say that one who follows is laziness like that is called a qessanquq.
Yet one who is not lazy, they also tell us this: "There is no person completely without laziness.
But one who lives by ’breaking’ his laziness and does things in spite of his laziness is called one who is not lazy."
That’s true, that if he does things in spite of his laziness, he’ll know his chores, know what he needs to do.
He knows the chores he needs to do for others.
You also like to clean things. He’ll no longer be lazy to clean, but become eager.
Now, you clean everything.
He’ll become like that, eager to do his chores.
Yet if he’s sedentary out of laziness, he puts up with being sedentary following his laziness.
They say that one who obeys his laziness will start to be called a qessanquq.
Then, this is the wisdom I pass down especially to your relatives down there, my grandchildren down there:
"There’s no person completely without anger. Every person, even if he’s not great, gets angry."
I’m not great, not a good or great person, yet I am easily angered, my inclination to become angry right here.
Indeed, my inclination to get angry is right here.
That’s why a person shouldn’t be proud of being angry. Every person, even if they’re not great, experiences it.
He also shouldn’t be easily angered because he’s angered easily.
Someday at the end of our life, we will not experience anger.
I end it with this to them down there: "We will not progress to salvation through anger."
This is what I bequeath. You shall inherit it. I pass on this wisdom to you down there, "We will not prgress to life through anger."
When the lord is going to throw us into that bad place, we will not go there saying this: "I won’t go there because I’m angry." We won’t say that.
Because I am easily angered, I remember that we will not experience my anger there at the end of our life.
So, let us who are easily angered remember it.
This is what you must remember. Even if you’re easily angered, think like that.
Also, what it’s like for you to be lazy, to obey laziness.
Yet doing things in spite of laziness makes you keep doing it in spite of laziness.
Also, after being very daunted, even after being daunted by [preparing] a lot of food, they are finished with continued work.
Also, try not to keep whatever articles of clothing in a mess, because when they’re worked on even if they’re a lot, they’re eventually finished.
Then before they’re infested with worms, they’re finished when worked on in spite of laziness, before they "bump into laziness" as they call it.
That’s what being lazy is like.
They also say that laziness makes one have nothing, and makes them lack things.
So if you ask me anything else, I will answer if I can, but will not answer if I can’t.
Yes.