Now, it hasn’t been a long time since our old lives, but...
Okay, since I was asked to speak, I’m going to speak.
What we did when we first got married
And I was asked to speak about the traditional wisdom passed down to us.
And now, it hasn’t been too terribly long since our old lives.
But I was completely prepared on how to be married when I started.
But my late grandmother, and my mom and father would tell me
That I should be careful with my spouse.
Also, they said that even though they speak badly about him not to tell him.
Also, I have another with me, a male younger sibling.
They also used to tell not that no matter what people say about his wife, not to believe them if he didn’t see it with his own eyes.
That’s what my father used to tell me to. He told me not to suspect my spouse if I hadn’t done anything, and not to accuse him of being with other women.
He said, you know, that brings discord.
I was also told not to tease my husband too excessively.
Then he would also tell me this: even if I have nothing and I am short on things, never to say this: "I am without."
He said, watch, I will affect my husband’s mental health.
This is what I was told.
We were also admonished against being suspicious of each other.
They said that only those who are guilty are suspicious of their spouses.
Then young people, girls and boys who are young now
There is also traditional wisdom saying that we should be careful with our mouths toward our peers.
They also told us not to live life saying harsh things just because we have mouths.
They say that wicked people and those who say harsh things come to times when they are ashamed.
They say that they see things differently as they are told to.
Then, they also said that even if we are accused, to stay quietly if we hadn’t done it.
That is also an admonishment.
Then we were also admonished against going to people too much.
Watch, they said, we would come across things that affect our mental health, or hear bad things.
This is what we were told.
They also told us not to invite our relatives to eat by treating them, well, you know
No matter what they do to them, do not be quick to say things, because that also leads to discord.
Then, my late grandmother and father would also tell me
They said that if I am too mischievous, people will speak about me, and people in other villages will know what I’m like.
Now, all people give that piece of wisdom.
Also, well
We need to admonish those who are mischievous and try to start a commotion.
Also, it truly is something admonished against.
My father also used to tell me this: that I shouldn’t try to come up in other villages.
Then, if I travel to where it not my home village, I shouldn’t [?misbehave].
Also, if I were in another village, they told me not to be the source of commotion.
He also told me to live as a stepping stool for those around me.
The traditional wisdom, they also used to tell me this: even if I don’t experience them, if I remember them, it’ll be like I experieced them.
Also, these days, there are now very many things that cause people to misbehave.
Then now, even when I wander around villages
What my father and late grandmother said sometimes come up on my mind.
That’s why even though I travel to other villages, what’s right in front of me, if a person focuses on what’s in front of him and doesn’t mess around, it would be good.
Anything else?
What else? Wait.
Okay.
Just now, you know, I just said that saying speaking harshly to one’s spouse makes things go wrong.
Then they would also tell me this:
They said not to tell a spouse, a husband, things that would negatively affect his mental health.
Then I was also told when I had children, that I should instruct that child.
They said children don’t forget.
Then they would admonish me against asking him things, or asking him what his peers are like to him.
I was also told not to verbally defend them. You know how some are verbally defensive.
Then they said not to verbally defend him, but to admonish him.
They said that if I verbally defend him, I will encourage him to lie and slander.
Then they also admonished me against excessively raised a hand against them.
They said I would make him stubborn.
They say they make them stubborn when they raise their hands against them too much or shout at them. They say they make them insolent.
They say that’s how they make them insolent.
It turns out, we must not be verbally defensive over these children.
They say that those they defend and those who slander other to their parents cause commotion.
I was also told that.
I was also told by my mother
No matter what they do to me, and when I sometimes got tired, she would admonish me against talking about those.
She said people would start a commotion starting from me.
Then no matter what anyone did to me, she admonished me against going home crying.
And even though I was doing those things, when my children would come in crying when they were small
My father would also tell me that, saying that I needed to be told.
Then I would try not to leave, but stay thinking I had done it.
Then children like this in their future, when they’re admonished
And they do not run away, but stop when told to stop.
And don’t say this to them: "I will get him."
The children who are told that learn to go home crying
Including the ones they verbally defend.
That’s why it’s an admonished, because that makes them liars and slanderers.
Then my late grandmother would also tell me when we were inland back then, that I should eat when my husband is gone, but to wait for him.
Then, because I liked to be with only old women, and older adults
When my late grandmother told me that, I’d ask her why, "Why?"
Then she said to me that should there be a food shortage, I would pretend there’s not enough for my family and eat alone, and my family will starve, and I will let my husband starve.
Okay, ready?
Okay, since I was a bad person at that time
I would ask questions like this and ask them why.
I would as Aana and mom why, but I couldn’t [ask why] with my father like that.
But all of them used to tell me that if I am too wicked of a person, and if I [stop taking care of] children after receiving money
My husband will decide to leave me because of my character.
Then, they said that when a man is too disobedient
They also leave those who stop taking care of children after receiving money, and who do not heed advice.
Then [the family] breaks up. They can’t take husbands anymore. Then the man cannot take wives because people found out [what he’s like].
They said that some who do not heed advice
They said that some...
Well, I also knew what my father would say to my younger sibling.
Then they said that some men
They said that some men, though they can change their ways, are disobedient for a long time.
And they say that some change their ways when they’re old men.
They said that women, however, many do not change their ways.
However, they say that men change their ways more easily, so they change their ways.
They said that women, however, do not change their ways.
That’s why they said we women should try to live sensibly.
As we just heard at first, though we do not do them, if we remember them, we will end up not doing them.
Now, they said, that we should live quietly.
Then when I became a woman, I would also be told
Now, they said, I’m not a child anymore; I’ve become a woman. But, they said, that I should always wash my hands before taking anything.
Then they said that I should not step over men’s clothes the same way, clothes and food.
They told me not to step over them, including food.
They said we scatter impurities on them.
Then they told me not to leave my hair untied. They said we pour, we scatter impurities on things.
Then, since we were all by ourselves, since the two of us grew up alone
Then they would tell us not to play with each other, saying that I’ve become a woman.
They said they’re careful around men when they become women.
They’re also careful with their breath and saliva.
Since we were together and with each other at the same age, my father would speak to us like that.
Then they said
They said that if I pass a man who id downwind from me, I should hold my breath and let him pass.
They said he might inhale my breath.
Then, my companion also, my younger sibling
They also told him that if he passes a woman that he should pass upwind from her, and if a woman goes upwind from him, that he should hold his breath as she passes.
They said that he might inhale her breath.
Then what would happen if they inhaled it like that?
Apparently, people had very strong restrictions a long time ago.
And women, men and women wouldn’t interact with each other.
They said that those who submit to men too much drive them sex crazy.
They also say that those who are sex crazy die, their groins rotting.
They say some die when they stop eating, and some suddenly get overwight.
These are the things they talked about that are dangerous to people.
That’s why people a long time ago didn’t get sick, because they weren’t unclean.
And the men and women only had single bowls [for each]. They were the same, and they didn’t exchange their bowls.
And the women wouldn’t have disheveled hair.
Just now, my father and paternal uncle kept a very close eye on my hair. I couldn’t ever go without braids.
They said it was because I might scatter impurities that would cause sickness.
That’s what they’d tell me.
Then they said that some women who think too much about men have imaginary husbands.
They also stop eating, and always imagine having lovers.