There were teachers and preachers, and a lot of people. There were a lot of people. There were also a lot of storekeepers.
There were a lot of Caucasians.
Though it was populated by Yupiit, there were a lot of people.
What’s going on?
Buzzing paper from the wind.
Okay, anytime.
Okay.
Long ago when you first moved here to Bethel, what did you observe? What was this land like?
When we first came, the area toward the water down there was a river.
And toward the water from us, the bank here was good, and had willows.
We would play under the bank.
Because I was cowardly, I wouldn’t go far.
The land was good, and there were not a lot of people.
Were they mostly Yup’ik?
They were mostly Yup’ik with Caucasians among them. There were a lot of Caucasians.
Teachers, priests, and storekeeps, and these miners from mining camps and fishing.
Back then, [were there] these mud houses here in Bethel?
There was a mud community house, a mud community house.
The huge community house was big.
From you, right when they started living in houses...
They had houses, log houses.
And these missions were the only ones with lumber houses, and some of these people also had lumber houses.
However, some of them also had log houses. There were a lot.
[I didn’t] see a mud house, except for that community house.
When you made your own living back then, starting to subsist
Tell us about that, you know, how sedentary people and and active people don’t have enough (Yes.) and don’t lack things.
In my earlies memories long ago, people focused on food.
They’d persistently fish.
And they’d dry their roe, and dry their heads.
Because they didn’t have extremely long drift nets like today.
Because their drift nets were short, and they’d always row [when traveling].
I didn’t see anyone surpassing that life.
They would row to go drift net, and their boats weren’t big because they were meant for rowing.
And their nets weren’t long.
They would make great effort to conserve fish.
Starting from rainbow smelt, they use dipnets for rainbow smelt, thread them through [grass ropes], hang them, and smoke them.
They were food for dogs, and they’d, we’d eat them too.
They steadily worked on things.
Now, and in the past, was fish strewn about in the past or what?
How they’re strew about, with fish getting strewn about, is it somehow getting harder to find? [Please talk about] that too.
They didn’t make a mess fish when I first became observant.
They cared for them with great reverence.
They wouldn’t scatter or tread upon food scraps.
They admonished against that.
They told them not to tread upong things, and [all] kinds of birds, anything they ate.
They took care of them with great reverence.
And they tended to the fish, and when they’d been smoked, they stored them.
They stored them, not left them in random places.
What meaning did they give when telling you to revere fish?
They say that when they don’t revere them, things, fish, get scarce.
They said they become scarce.
That’s what I used to hear.
In your observation of our days now, we see food scraps out there.
It’s unfortunate that they’re not taking care of them anymore, because they [?don’t make them] anymore.
From the stores, and since money that is coming aren’t for things, there are now a lot of gifts.
Back then, though we may have been orphans, we didn’t know of gifts.
Without having gifts to take care of us, our mother steadily worked to take care of us through her work with her hands.
So, what would they instruct to the orphans?
Orphans, a person, people would take pity on orphans.
Without looking and ignoring, they helped them, and their families helped them.
That’s what they were like.
Now, a person may be in a situation without food, and peopl won’t know them. They won’t pity them.
What about abstinence practices? Did [they] practice abstinence? Did you observe when they did abstinence?
Yes. You see, I don’t know abstinence practices.
I don’t know abstinence practices.
Since my mother didn’t do much abstinence, I don’t know many of them.
And because I don’t know them, though it wouldn’t happen, I’d apparently end up doing that.
Though they actually wouldn’t, I’d find out later because I don’t know abstinence practices.
Now, please tell us of something you think is important, a little piece of traditional wisdom.
Well, there are many important things.
But I don’t like how people today are no longer a community.
Back when we were going up, our families and relaties, they lived with compassion and love for each other.
And when they saw each other, it seemed they were the closest of families.
They are thankful to see each other.
And they would give to them from what they could.
Now, they’re absolutely not like that.
Though they’re our families and relatives, we hesitate with them.
They’re not [loving] like that anymore.
I also don’t like when they things from their families though they’re big, boats and motors.
In my mind, I don’t like that, also because things are expensive.
When people steal those, I think
"When they’re going to die," because I think
"If I’m going to die, I will remember the wrong things I’ve done."
It’s because even if I’m not going to die now, I remember them.
I think that those around me might do that.
This stealing from one’s family, they also destroy their families’ things.
I don’t like that either.
It’s bad that it seems they don’t want the families to have anything.
That doesn’t seem good to me.
Lastly, what do want to leave behind with the youth, your descendants?
What good thing do you want to leave with us?
Becuase these young people have become different and pick on each other, it would be good if they lived treating each other with love.
This love that has nothing greater is a traditional instruction.
It’s in the Bible that love is the very first and there’s nothing greater than it.
I remember that when I want my family to treat each other with love like this, especially the youth.
Do not scorn each other, treat each other well and with love.
And this [alcohol] they want to abuse, do not, it’s not for anything, and doesn’t improve anything.
I don’t want it to be used because it ends in misfortune.
It doesn’t lead to anywhere but misfortune.
Though they want to use it in villages, they don’t because it ends badly.
In my mind, I want these young people to remember that.
Even though we didn’t do it in our youth, even if we were mischievous.
But, it’s because we didn’t excessively use somethings, and we respected the things of those around us in our lives.
Okay, thank you.
You’re welcome.
Okay, goodbye.
Oh my, that too...