Please start talking about how people, you, moved here to Atmautluak again.
And when, what year, did you move here?
Yes, these ones first moved here to Atmautluak in 1969.
Then in one year in ’71, I moved here.
A person, it’s because a person, we Yupiit, historically only to places where there is fish since a long time ago.
It’s because we’ve always eaten fish starting from our ancestors.
So they moved to get food from here.
Yes.
Yes, had we not moved, the people of Nunpitchuk across there would have nowhere to be now.
We live on the coast.
And on the coast, those who go to the wilderness have traditional instructions
Or when they go to the ocean, they have traditional instructions in the ocean.
How, here as you grew up here deep in the wilderness, how did your elders instruct you when you started traveling?
How did they instruct you so you wouldn’t get hurt, or so nothing would happen to you?
We had traditinional instruction back when we were young, especially [to take] a shovel or ice pick, a walking staff.
They also talked about that staff, saying it is life for a person.
These are also the important things they instructed:
Those seal gut rain parkas, we Yupiit, back before these Western things came, they used to use those seal gut rain parkas.
Then for us who were born after Caucasians had come
Our parents used to instruct us to especially keep those rainproof clothes with us even if the weather seems good.
Because sometimes, the weather doesn’t relent like this in the spring or fall
Those were the things that they especially told us to have with us.
Because if we don’t have a staff, we won’t know things, and we won’t know that something is dangerous.
Or, they also told us that when we travel in the winter, to always have a shovel in our cargo even if the weather is good.
If we get into misfortune, it turns out, in the wilderness, or if a blizzard his us, or the weather changes on us, they also instructed
They told us not to stop at a small snowbank.
But also, if we have no tarpaulin, if we have a shovel
A snowbank, dig into an already formed snowbank.
They told us to stay inside of it, but to also get a piece of wood to poke [the ceiling].
When it gets hot, poke it to ventilate it.
Those were our important traditional instruction from our elders.
Also, since I am thankful for it, I want to give one quick traditional instruction to our youth.
Also, when I got married, when I got married
Or when I also had children, since my father wouldn’t hold back when advising me back then
He used to speak to me like this: a child, should we have children
Even if [s]he comes in crying that we shouldn’t as questions, or ask what’s wrong or who did it.
He said not to be defensive over them.
Watch, he said, if we defend them, that little child will be able to make us believe [anything].
As we go, [s]he can make us upset with our friends.
Then when it’s time for him, since they’ve also started going to school
He said that even if people admonish them, [s]he will not obey.
He said it’s because [s]he has us to defend them.
Since I especially yearned to say that because I'm thankful that you came, I spoke about it.
Now, those who drown, there are now a lot who drown in the summer.
What about in the past... they say there’s a lot, and I hear that it’s like we’re dying in great numbesr in our day through the river.
What can you instruct those who travel, boys or others, so that they wouldn’t do that?
Yes, especially what they said about this, they weren’t actually completely without it.
Back when we were born, because we were born when there’d been Caucasians
But having gotten these fast boat motors
Those especially, starting to use these vehicles especially is what’s causing people to die in great numbers.
And abusing this mind-altering substance is probably what’s making do that.
Long ago, and in my time, all of the stores down in Bethel were all liquor stores.
But since they didn’t have sophisticated vehicles back then, though they [drank] like that, they didn’t know [of people dying a lot].
Now, we do instruct our children, and I also advise my children
But these days like that, and me, like my parents
I used to watch my late father and myself
But I cannot [instruct] them exactly like he did.
I did that because they may feel offended or may go in the wrong direction. It turned out I made a mistake.
Yes, if I love them, I must not hold back speaking about everything dangerous like this
So that they will remember them.
Now, [unspecified] know[s] many times...
Those who [?break apart] their parents evidently do not live well.
Also, those who don’t follow the traditional wisdom passed down to them like this, are like those who’ve ended up on the ground.
Also, though [s]he tried not to be heard of in other villages
That person is like something waving on top of a pole when [s]he doesn’t follow their traditional wisdom.
However, one who follows their traditional wisdom seems absent, and they seem absent even here in neighboring villages.
Lastly, how would you, Fred Pavilla
Something important that you want to leave the next generations
What would you [pass on] to us, should we, by happenstance, live after you, who do live, who will live
How can you instruct us? What can you leave with us?
I can leave with you young people
Like this, no matter what a person is like, even if they’re bad, socialize with them
Or if you have none, offer a small conversation like that, or if you have some, feed them.
It’s because no matter what a person is like, what they seem like, all of us people are faulty here on this earth.
They said that a person who is [nice] like that is never without help should they get into misfortune.
A [nice] person like that.
Also, how [s]he would be seen, how [s]he would be talked about
They say people are excited to see them.
Like that, or people are excited to help them.
One who lives socializing like that, one who lives treating everyone they see with love.
That was my most important traditional instruction from my parents.
No matter what one is like, or an orphan, or even if [s]he’s not an orphan, they told me to help a person in misfortune all the same.
I see.
Thank you.
Yes.
Girls had traditional wisdom specific to them.
What traditional instructions from back what you were very young do you most remember now?
The traditional instruction I was given, there are many for women.
Boys also [had] separate ones, it seemed they were separate.
Even if they weren’t separate, they had traditional wisdom specific to them.
And the traditional wisdom passed down to me have been revelead these days.
Lo and behold, they were revealed these days.
In my earliest memories, we were baptized, they’d been baptized.
I became aware, and later here, when our baptist came to us, we were baptized.
To me, it’s been quite a while since I was born.
Then, we were given traditional wisdom
Even if our fathers and mothers don’t harshly speak to us, even if they don’t shout at us like this
It was like they were scary even if they weren’t scary, even if they didn’t harshly react to us, raising their hands against us.
We women had traditional wisdom saying not to wander in the evening, and not to have many visitors.
This was important from my mother, my mother and father, like this:
They said that I shouldn’t listen to people speaking of something bad.
Then if I see someone giving instruction, if I see someone giving instruction
They said to go to and listen to one speaking of admonishments.
They were peaceful back then.
But these things the Bible spoke about
As we’re coming to what was foretold, you must live carefully.
Try to be careful.
So when this comes [to pass], you will not be surprised but recognize it, and even if you dislike it, you will not think it amiss.
And this man or woman who tends to speak harshly, speak loudly, they don’t like that.
And harshly speaking to a young boy in his presence like this, with people listening, without regard for how he might suddenly react
They say that causes them to be a certain way [makes them hardened].
These days, our traditional wisdom, I’m starting to remember it since I’m starting to struggle with my grandchildren or my children.
Since I’m starting to struggle, I’m remembering it.
They do not think that person who shouts, speaks loudly, is good
Or those who react [badly] to those who instruct them.
This is what I tell you young people to make you steadfast
Also, do not merely look at something bad, and one who doesn’t merely need to be told like this like us.
Us too, some of use were also disobedient.
From our mother, just the two of us, she would tell me that.
Also, you may know these days.
These days, you only here it inside these churches.
But, having no one to instruct you in random places like that has probably done that to you.
One who doesn’t need to merely be told and scatters is like an orphan.
And eventually, [s]he comes to misfortune.
We, your elders, are sometimes weak.
Though these young people are admonished, look, they drop their admonishments.
This is as much as I remember.
So, when you were going to get married, how were you instructed about how to be a spouse?
I was finally instructed when I was going to get married.
And before I was 13, I lost my arm like this to a misfire.
Then I wasn’t expecting to get married. It turned out my mother took care of me.
I didn’t think I’d be with a person without an arm like this.
But she finally instructed me when I was going to get married.
She covered everything.
She talked about everything.
And the admonishments against harshly replying to my spouse like this
The admonishments
She finally told me of the admonishments.
It was daunting. It was daunting to do something like that in their presence, or even if wasn’t in their presence.
And they’d let them imaging their mother and father were watching them.
That was what my admonishment was like when I was going to get married.
And I shouldn’t go to various places. And when I first saw a child, now there was a lot of traditional wisdom.
These days, however, those who get married or have children, it seems that they do whatever they want.
They do whatever they want.
Then a man gets married later. Then they also instruct him like that.
They told me not to treat my spouse harshly.
And do not use my mouth against him, and don’t reply harshly when he treats me harshly.
Then when that last man gets married, they’d also instruct him.
They’d tell him to make sure his spouse is in peace.
And to say that he will stop after being upset.
Please wait a short minute.
Okay.
That down there is going to be replaced.