When we were boys back then, our parents
When my parents were alive, it’s like they encouraged me to go to the community house.
They wanted me to partake in the community house.
And so I obeyed them, since I did not go against my parents’ wishes.
But since they were not young, since they were old, I lived without going against their wishes.
According to their request, I would go to the community house.
Yet when we entered the community house, there was a great many people all the way inside.
And the area here that they call the side wall had an entrance from below where you would go up from down there.
And they would call the area further inside the back wall.
And they would call this area, the area toward the door.
There would be a great many people inside the community house.
And the area inside close to the evening like this, the men stopped working when the men went to the community house since they didn’t always stay in the houses.
The community house was their real home.
As for the two old men, [one] stayed here toward the door at the very end
And [the other] across there was at the very end.
They brought forth traditional wisdom.
Both of those who instructed on the future, after having the one on this side speak
After bringing what they needed to say about how they should be
He spoke about how they should live, and how they should be.
Then when he was done, the one across fixed it.
They said a person should live like this. Though they lived in the community house, were fathers, had many children, the didn’t disregard what they said.
The community house would be quiet when they spoke.
About how they should live, the two speakers would say that they shouldn’t be haughty people.
They said we shouldn’t be haughty.
They said, however, to remember the floor, the floor down there where they trod that has grass strewn about it.
They said that we should live remembering that, trying not to be haughty.
Then they said that if we do that
Also, they said that we should try to help these elders that were born before us with what they want.
Or also, we should not let an elderly couple lack water, go to them if we know them, and get water for them.
Also, if their door below needs fixing, to fix it.
Then, they do not await boys like this even though they’ve become fathers from what we heard of the two in the community house.
They didn’t wait for boys, though he became a father and had two children, they would completely follow their traditional wisdom.
Then, since we people are not the same
Since we are no the same, some people would regard what they said as if they didn’t see or hear it.
They would speak like that about one who was like that.
They said that he will not live to that day, will not be Cup’ik.
However, the one in the community house would closely observe the one that obeyed their traditional wisdom.
They said that a person who follows traditional wisdom, completely follows it, will live for quite a long time.
They said that it will be like his breath "squats down [more firmly]" if he is obedient.
And he doesn’t bring down those around him, and he doesn’t speak unfavorably about those around him.
The same for the young people, and the same for small children, those speakers would tell that person do be like that.
So, it seems that it’s true.
Look, in my life when I traveled from Qissunaq down there, when I traveled from Qissunaq on the coast of the sea in my life
I was also born there.
As soon I started travling by sled when that priest baptized me, since my baptism then as soon as I started traveling by sled
Since then, my age has been clear from that time.
Then my father would also tell me
He told me to never go to these villages like this.
You know how when some do insignificant things to us, they get angry.
They answer to those who do things to them not to use it.
He told me to live without using it.
Especially if she’s a woman, I should not reply [badly] to her if she treats me badly.
He told me to turn away from her without replying.
Then he said that if my age-mate, if I do that from my age-mate, if he keeps doing that to me
One of them pushing me back, and one of them saying I’m not a good hunter
If he pushes me back, also saying I have nothing, one of them may say that I’m not a good hunter, and I have nothing, no little thing.
He said that if we can’t take him anymore that we should then reply.
My father used to instruct me like that, to reply with anything I want.
He said that the one who picked on me will stop if I answer him like that.
In my observation, that would seem to be true as well.
You see, a long time ago, we young people only went forth through our elders.
They held the two who spoke about the future in very high regard.
And one of their traditional wisdom, I was coming here from far over there, I was coming
Eventually it became like this: when I looked around, there were completely different houses.
They had houses made completely of sod, using wood inside their houses.
They also used grass. They also used sod to insulate their houses.
And their women were absolutely not sedentary.
They made various things.
If they’re in the house, they put grass underneath, and spread them out for matting.
They called those naqtat, the ones they made long and used for matting.
Then inside their house, it would be beautiful with those stuck in with little tack-like things.
And there wasn’t just one person in that house.
And this part had those between it where a person would be.
And toward the door from there, it had those where a person would be.
Those houses wouldn’t have just one person.
As I was coming, those who elders who would speak of the future
If they become unnoticable, they can be changed
The ones who speak of the future for these boys.
These women who would serve [their elders], however, in their houses over there
Their grandmothers instead worked on them.
It’s one with the [men’s] traditional wisdom when I look closely.
She’s not actually my grandmother, but when my maternal aunt spoke to my older sisters
Their traditional wisdom is exacly the same and compliment each other.
And their admonishments are one, and their instructions are also one.
We do not hear any surprising traditional wisdom from them.
Then now, they say, those elders say
They said that we Cuppot will get Westerners, other kinds [of people] among us.
They said that there will be among us people different from us, people with different lives from us.
It turned out to be these Caucasians.
Then back when those Caucasians traveled among us who where from over in Carvanertuliar on the Yukon
They would say, "There will be more of these people, more and more."
They said that we Cupiit would eventually be among different kinds if there are more of them [than us].
Also misfortune if there are more of them [than us]
What would cause us misfortune that they would not want upon us gets bigger and increases
No matter what we Cupiit want to do to them, we will be unable to [deal with] them.
But I am pretending to be good now as I started speaking, since I have started speaking as a teacher.
No matter what they do to us, let us not lower ourselves. Let us try to work with them as much as we can.
They do not own our land.
And here in Alaska, not matter where they’re from, even if they come from far away
They are trying to help those lands well because all of this belongs to each of them the same way.
However, let us not do that though they do that to our land here.
Let us Cupiit help each other.
I also encourage my descendants to come that even if they do that to respond to them.
Since I will not always be with those boys, my young people, over in Chevak, I [tell them] my traditional wisdom.
It’s been a long time since I’ve passed on my traditional wisdom through their school
It’s been a long time since the BIA took care of our school. We from Chevak were the very first to take our school.
Then we took it, and no matter what they tried to do to it, they couldn’t do anything.
And my former peers who are not known know, when I was recently in a meeting along with Caucasians, along with the school officials
Since those were my source of strength, though they [?] these, I was the only one who had them as my source of strength.
But I have taught one of my grandchildren.
He does the things I say. He’s good.
Doing this, trying to keep going
Trying to keep going no matter what those around them do, to those who are young
He is called, they call him this: he is a good person, he is good.
What will [?] want to use...