How old are you?
About 78.
(Who are you in Yup’ik?) Seventy...
Seventy-eight?
Who are you in Yup’ik?
I’m Ayagina’ar in Yup’ik.
Okay, so what kinds of admonished did you hear or find out about the river down there when it first freezes like this?
When it first freezes in the fall like this before it gets thick, the ice is dangerous.
Parts of it also freeze late, they freeze late.
It freezes late when it warms up periodically, and some freeze late even when it’s cold.
Also, it’s still dangerously thin when it freezes.
A person cannot tell where it’s thin and dangerous.
But if he has a staff and examines the ice with that staff, he will know.
We were instructed on how to use this staff
That we should not be without it, especially in the fall when it’s dangerous like this, to examine the ice with.
Even if he’s in a hurry, after stopping and examining the place he’s curious about with that tool
He will know where it’s thin. He will know where it’s dangerous. His ice pick will show him.
So how cam a person who accidentally falls through the ice help himself?
This is what my father and other people used to tell me:
If he suddenly falls into the water and is floathing, that he should not go out right away, but try to keep the hole from closing up.
If it closes off and he tries to go out of the water right away, he will become weak.
But they said that he needs to be careful.
This is what my late father used to tell me: if it’s cold and I have gloves
After placing them on the ice here like this, slap them on the ice up there and let them freeze.
He said that a person can hold those and pull himself out.
Also, he should take his legs out first, then hold this and roll, he must roll out of the water.
He can also save himself if the ice didn’t close in on him.
But if it closes in on him right away, he will suddenly become tired
If he tries to get out right away.
But, you know, they would instruct us to try to keep the hole from closing in on us.
But what will save him if he gets out safely?
In the cold like this before there is snow
When he gets out, he should take off his clothes right away if the land is close and there is grass visible.
He should take off his wet clothes and wring them.
And put them on again, lining his body with grass.
Also, he must make calculated decisions if he’s getting cold
If he tries to urinate and drinks his urine, his own urine if he’s alone, or if there’s two of them, if he drinks his companions urine, whoever needs to urinate
They say a person will not freeze to death if he does that.
These young people must know that.
If he’s not repulsed and drinks his companion’s urine, they say he will not freeze to death.
Many used to do that. Those who used to do that would instruct that.
Does it also help to tell families before traveling?
What?
You know, telling people that he’s going to go to that place. How can that be of help to people?
Yes, a person can tell his family if he’s going to travel somewhere that he’s going to travel to someplace there.
If it’s past the time he should’ve came back, the people from his hometown will go first to where he wanted to go.
If they happen to come upon him without any misfortune if he doesn’t wander about
They will find him right away
If he doesn’t stray anywhere.
Anything else...
If people, these young people, know these instructions and adhere to them
These young people, especially now, do not know what they should do.
That’s why their parents must teach them about those
Always talking to them about dangerous things especially now in these dangerous times.
Also instruct them on these rivers.
Even though some rivers were thick, they quickly become dangerous when it warms up.
Then this staff as well, a person must not be without a staff when he’s traveling.
If he has a staff like that, he will know what parts are dangerous.
He will know which parts are dangerous with that staff he uses on the ice.
There are a lot of instructions that these young people are supposed to know.
But because we don’t speak abou tthem, our successors espcially do not know them
Because we do not teach them.
Long ago when we who are this age were growing up
Because they men would be gathered in the community house alnog with the young boys
That’s why observant young people know those instructions.
A person uses these instructions as forewarning.
If he knows them, even if he gets into misfortune, he will be better and will not get into too much misfortune.
These young people should know them.
These elders talk about what they’ve experienced
They also talk about the things they’ve heard their elders say long ago so that these young people will use them well, so that they will live well.
So that they will live well including when they make their own living.
If a young person knows it liek that, if he knows the instructions, he will be helping his life in the future
If he keeps examining those dangerous things.
These snowgoes do not know which way to travel, and they don’t know what’s dangerous.
But back when we had dogs, the dogs knew which places were dangerous.
That’s why when they’re traveling with snowgos, they should always examine it when they’re going to go down to the river.
It’s also easy to tell when previously unfrozen holes have frozen over.
And where it froze late if there has been windy for a long time, the places where the unfrozen holes splash out in the wind, their edges in the river are rough and higher.
Also, we should always check the good smooth ice.
They shouldn’t try parts of it because they may fall through the freshly frozen parts.
But they should always examine it with that staff first.
Always examine it first even if he’s in a hurry.
This was also our instructions when young people would travel like this:
He must always keep things with him, putting in an ice pick and a shovel.
Also, always go with a tarpaulin without saying it’s too heavy.
Also, if one is lost and the weather turns on them, it will be better if he doesn’t go any further when he doesn’t know where he is anymore, but stop and stay where he is.
Not staying still, but trying to stay warm in the cold.
Do not stay still and sit, but try to keep warm without going any further.
If he keeps going, he will go far until he eventually runs out of gas.
And those looking for him will not find him right away if he continued traveling like that.