How these women love these children
Because they especially take care of them when they’re children starting from when they’re born.
As much as Lucy knows about some of those, how to love these children
She will speak to us about what she knows and what she personally thinks.
What you know about these children, how to love these children
Women take care of them starting from birth when they take care of them from birth.
Please talk about what you know concerning their love for children.
[Taking care of] children a long time ago
Our caretakers cared for us by talking about everything.
They would always talk to us starting when we married letting us know everything [that they could].
They also talked about how to take care of children if we were to bear children.
You see, our caretakers were not how we are these days.
We didn’t see a lot of Caucasians, nor did we see things like money.
I didn’t see money for a long time.
Because I grew up poor, I didn’t have those kinds of things.
Neither do I forget how my mother took care of me.
I remember it clearly.
My mother took care of me like this:
She didn’t allow me to be frivolous with food, food or water.
What she gave was the only [stuff I ingested].
You see, my stomach is used to it now.
I’m going to tell youpl what I’m like.
My stomach inside is used to how I’ve always eaten.
I will not fill it before noon even to this very day now.
Neither will I fill it before it’s time for dinner.
It’s used to me not eating randomly.
The first people back then were not like this.
They did not eat randomly in between meals
Because there were these three [set] meals: drinking something in the morning,
And then at lunch at noon, they would finally eat real food.
We ate then and turned out to be full.
And what our mothers gave us were not [entirely] filling; they would leave us wanting more.
And we would eat dinner in the evening.
And then after that, we wouldn’t ingest anything else until morning.
And our stomachs would be used to it, so we wouldn’t be thirsty at night.
Only in the morning would we [ingest] a little when we woke up.
And when my mother gave me a piece of pancake when I had nothing else, she would give me a little nibble because we didn’t have a lot.
And I wouldn’t add to or try to add to what little she gave.
You see, a person can do this.
And if our descendants learn, they can do it.
I am continuing that only with my stomach to this day through my eating habits.
However, some of those things are changing from what I’ve taken care of.
But, they wouldn’t let us nibble as we walked around or were standing.
They wouldn’t not let us eat standing.
And I see this today too; and when I came in this morning, I watched youpl
People drinking coffee take the cup and then walk around.
Listen, does it really settle well inside?
This is how it has changed
How the instruction of those first people back then changed.
I watched youpl when I came in this morning.
After this person filled [a cup] without asking permission from above
After he fills a cup, he goes, drinks as he walks, and goes into rooms.
You see, this is how it’s changed.
Youpl say that the life of the people back then has changed.
This is one of the changes.
When we bore children, you see, they didn’t let their urine make a mess.
We didn’t take care of our first children with repeated diaper changing.
Children started using diapers when Caucasians became numerous.
We took care of children by waking up with every little move they made.
We with children could not be lazy.
Because we loved children, we took care of them with a lot of love.
We didn’t leave them a lot and didn’t babysit.
And now, I’ve had 14 children.
Those ten, I gave birth to these ten in my home without going to the hospital.
And then these four after the [first] ten
Because my body was a little amiss, I finally went here [to the hospital] to give birth to these four.
But these three were not born in the maternity wing
But this last youngest one was born in the maternity wing.
You see, I did not suffer for long, nor was I in labor for long
Because I had already suffered to give birth.
I'm talking about what I know.
When I was first pregnant, my mother instructed me,
“If you want to give birth without problems, and if you want to have a good laboring period that’s not too long
“Every time you think of it, go outside at night and in the morning.”
You see, we adhered to what instructions we had without doubting them.
We adhered to them.
And then when the child was born, we took care of him.
We took care of him with our mothers to instruct us.
Every time the newborn child rustled from sleep, we had them urniate [in a waste container].
We always did that, never wetting the bad, always keeping it dry, and we never made a mess.
And when I started with that, when I learned [the ways of] clocks when clocks first came
I learned when they defecated and urinated by the hours.
I truly took care [of children].
You see, our caretakers, our mothers would tell us
“When [s]he grows up, do not shout at him.
“Admonish him without raising your voice.
“If you do that, [s]he will not obey you.
“However, if you raise your voice and shout at him loudly
“That child will not live right.
“He will be stubborn and disobedient.”
You see, I am talking about what instruction I had that I know.
They would say back then, I hear people say this:
“The life of Yupiit is changing now.”
That’s how they’ve changed.
You see, everything had traditional wisdom connected to it for us; it had instructions.
When we disobeyed them sometimes, there is also regret when we disobey that traditional wisdom.
That’s what I know about taking care of children, loving children.
If a person loves a child, [s]he must take care of him with love like that.
They must also have them know about what brings misfortune.
Let them know what will cause them shame, what will get them incarcerated, what will put them into jail.
You see, our children are the most important for us parents.
And if by chance one of our relatives is incarcerated
His parents cannot socialize well with their families because of that
Because they2 raised them, because they2 took care of them.
You see, this is how [our lives] have changed.
We say that the traditions of those people back then have changed.
We know that it has changed now.
I just started off with what you know of one of the changes.
They didn’t let us ingest anything as we wandered about.
And even if we were very thirsty after we ate, they wouldn’t give us water right away.
And then our mouths would be dry because we were so thirsty.
That saliva turned white.
Only when that happened, they would give us a little water and then we drank that.
And even when we really wanted more, we wouldn’t add to it because they wouldn’t let us.
We waited for meals. We were used to it.
My stomach only knows and is used to how my mother took care of me.
It got used to not drinking anything outside of meals.
I would like to translate what you just said into English for those who do not speak [Yup’ik].
I also just said that children didn’t have diapers.
We didn’t put them in those as we took care of them.
We watched over them, keeping their urine from going on the floor.
She said that…
Say that my mother helped me when I first [gave birth]
But after I gave birth, my mother helped me once with the eldest.
And afterwards, when I was going to give birth to the next one
Across there in the original Bethel where the landing strip was
I gave birth to the second of my eldest.
I knew that [s]he was going to be born.
Because I knew, I prepared a mat for when I gave birth.
After I prepared a mat because it was in the summer, in July, I gave birth a second time on July 6.
And then when I was [in labor] after I prepared, I took out scissors
Because I watched how my mother took care of it when I first gave birth.
I set out scissors and thread to tie be tied.
And then when that child was born, I took care of it myself.
[Here was] the belly button, umbilical cord here, and the end over there.
When [s]he was born, I tied it, and tied it here.
And then I cut it with scissors in the middle.
I took care of them myself
But these four after the ten, qulem cipneri, because I [gave birth] 14 times
I’m telling you this story.
What [?]. Did you understand? [?]
…because some women are weak.
Back then, when there was no other woman in the village.
When they2 [delivered a child] by themselves2, they2 helped each other.
Her husband would tie their umbilical cords and cut them.
When there was a women close to them
Her husband invites here, telling her that his wife [is in labor] and for her to be with [his wife].
Another woman would help her from what I know of back then.
However, because her husband has no help when they have none, when she can’t do it herself
Her husband helps her deliver the baby.
This is what that’s like.
And then part of loving children is like this:
When a child can’t get up, his teachings are unintelligible
And even though [s]he is told, [s]he doesn’t understand, isn’t yet able to understand.
And when he finally wakes up and his body is strengthened, wakes up, starting to sit
These things dangerous to him, how things on the table when they eat
Because that child doesn’t know that [s]he will get burned
Have that child briefly touch that hot thing.
And then after that, try to have him touch that [hot thing]
That child will have already learned. [S]he will know that it’s hot.
They say that should they somehow get accidently burned
[S]he will know that it’s hot [and avoid it].
Because it's like they are gradually learning when they start sitting.
And when they start feeding them when they start eating
[A parent] teaches their child about those.
Also admonish him against grabbing these various things.
Don’t let him grab things, and don’t give him things to grab.
They say that when a child grows up being allowed to grab things
Allowing him to grab these [various] things as he grows up
When he grows up and he is able, he has no reservations about taking things.
[S]he can also take another person's possession when [s]he wants.
Because [s]he was not admonished, being allowed to take whatever [s]he wanted whenever [s]he wanted.
However, when [s]he is admonished against those from the beginning
[S]he will also learn like that.
Also, when [s]he starts understanding [words], when the child starts understanding
When [s]he starts understanding what we say as [s]he grows a little
We have traditional wisdom from those who raised us for when we have children like this:
A child is aware when [s]he first wakes up.
[S]he isn’t unruly when waking up, not shouting, not laughing
But quite, because they say they are aware.
They say that when he is aware, we should then tell him some traditional wisdom.
They say that when they are aware and focus on traditional wisdom.
They sometimes tell us, “Look, [s]he’s suddenly aware.”
When these children are suddenly quiet like this,
“[S]he suddenly aware,” watching one thing.
They day that's what it's like.
If that child is spoken to like someone older
[S]he will not forget it and remember it more clearly.
But [s]he is more still later after being told traditional wisdom.
We also start moving about and [doing things] when we wake up.
And then after that child is still
[S]he starts moving about and is like [s]he’s unaware now.
And then when [s]he grows a little more, say to him,
“Now, treat your peers with love.”
[A parent] tells him this because they love him, telling him to treat his peers with love,
“Now, treat your peers with love today.”
They say that because his mother or father loves him, [s]he also wants him to go well [in life] with those [peers]
Tell them to treat their peers with love because it’s the most important instruction.
And then, they say that someone, even if that child is not her own, someone else’s child
When she sees him, she will tell him traditional wisdom as if he were her own, loving him as much as her own children.