She passed away when our priest was [?Greens]. A long time.
And my wife passed away in the spring around Easter.
What was her name?
Elena. Elena Andrew.
Hunter?
Andrew. (Andrew?) Yes.
Yes.
First, did you stay in the community house when you were young?
Please tell a story about that.
When I was young, I grew up in a community house.
Then, you know, I would always sleep next to my father in the community house.
Among many people, you know, you about the community house.
There was one in [?Cuukvagtuli]. Our competitors had a community house.
[I slept] next to my father.
Then the sleeping areas above had two feet beds like this in the community house, two feet of wood.
Then when it was time, I would go down to the nateq, floor, to the floor planks, you know, the floor.
We would sleep without thinking anything of it.
We would sleep using these small mittens of ours like this, or those real Yup’ik gloves as headrests.
It wasn’t unusual to us a long time ago, you know?
That’s how we lived.
My grandfather raised me.
He raised me like this: he wouldn’t let me sleep in the morning.
It turned out that he had wanted me to live well.
Then when I slept like this, he would come wake my up by doing this here.
Then when he [?] me from the floor her, he would say, "Quickly go outside."
He said that I would get better outside. When I went outside, I would feel better, being awake with no more trace of sleep left.
And to this day, I never sleep in the morning [?].
I should occassionally speak English.
Yes.
Where was that community house?
In Kayalivik. In Kayalivik.
Did you have a lot of young companions there in that community house?
There were a lot. Young boys would only stay in the community house.
In the community house, the youth would stay in the back wall.
They would stay in the houses. They wanted the youth to only stay in the community house, you know?
These adults and the old men would be here toward the door, across from each other like this.
Those would speak to people like this.
They would speak to their grandchildren like this.
Then after speaking to them, after one addressed and spoke to his grandchild, they would speak sternly. They would be scary when they spoke sternly.
Yet they would always speak about good things.
They would instruct the ones inside on the back wall.
Yes, that’s how I lived.
They were probably all men in the community house.
Yes, yes, only men do that.
And then...
Little girls, little girls who had grown would also stay by their fathers in the community house listening to them speak about good things.
When some of those did that, they would once in a while.
This little girl would keep wanting to be in the community house.
Apparently, she wanted to hear what the men of the community house spoke about.
Yes, what the old men spoke about. Yes, that’s what people would do.
What were the adults like in that time?
The adults lived only trying to improve boys. They instructed them, telling them to live well.
That’s the only job for adults.
They only wanted their relatives, these young boys, to live well.
They did want what they said to be lost. The only wanted to be heard.
Those old men I watched would only speak of good things.
Yes. Yes, write them down.
What...
You see, because you’re making me hurry.
No.
Write them down, and start from the beggining if you are to know them if you are smart.
From the beginning, then you’ll understand.
Then those... are we ready?
Were those adults like how they are now, or what?
No, they weren’t like how they are now.
It’s because they don’t go out, and they have no place, because they are not gathered anymore, but scattered in their houses like this.
Now, only I speak to the boys, my relatives, or even if they’re not my relatives, who do well [to come] a little about what they need to hear.
They listen to them.
And these days, some of the ones who were mischievous whom I spoke to get better right away, are better.
They get clothes, get things, have everything they need, no longer in misfortune.
What would those adults teach the youth?
They would teach how they would travel, and how they would travel in the ocean.
They would always speak to them to teach them everything about traveling.
That’s what they’d do.
They would speak to those we were going to travel like. They even told them what they would do if they came to misfortune in the wilderness. That’s how they [taught] us.
Like going to school?
Yes, like going to school.
And then because we’re Yup’ik
And if we have no other food, if we have something with no other food, if they eat it raw, we must eat it raw.
Then they would instruct us like this:
If we’re going to travel, they told us to travel with a little food, a little scrap.
And we should always bring a shovel with us.
Also some cloth to work with.
Since I grew up with an increase of cloth, I always took cloth to work with with me.
And always bring fishing tools with us.
Then if the weather turns on us, they told us not to travel right away either.
They told us not to travel right away as we think to.
Instead, they told us to stop where we’re not shielded [from the wind] liek this, you know, the land like this, the land here.
If it hadn’t snowed here, and it was visible like this.
They told us to stop like that, and even to set up our tent.
Then if we have absolutely no tent, we should hollow out the snow like this.
Make a space hollowing it out like this, then go in.
But we shouldn’t go into the leeward side in the land here, but hollow out the snow there and go in.
And poke a hole above us like this as a breathing hole.
You see, I absolutely know that snow is suffocating.
Have you ever experienced it?
Yes, I’ve experienced it. It’s suffocating. It’s very hot.
A person will suffocate and die if he’s not told about that.
It’s suffocating, then he dies.
That snow is dangerous.
Also, if you sink, I also experienced sinking to here like this.
The weather was calm, and it was cold and chilly like this.
I left my wife and children to go hunt, hunting, for minks.
Then this small mink that was acting strangely was dragging
It had its forepaws here, and its hindpaws were down there.
When I was curious about that, I sank. I followed its tracks.
The tundra here was here.
This part was ice.
There, I did have a staff, I used my staff.
As I was curious about that, when I was going to reach the tundra here, I fell and it reached here.
And it was cold out there.
And my matches were here, covered in plastic.
And I also had long fur boots like this, the ones used for traveling.
I sunk.
When I sunk, it didn’t reach past my boods, and I poked where I would go.
I would reach the land before [the water] would go here.
Then I went on the land.
I went up wading. Though I had sunk, I went up on land.
When I went up, I quickly took off my clothes in great hurry because the weather was calm though it was cold.
I quickly wrung them all. I poured the water out of my fur boots and would do this.
Then because there was a lot of grass, right when I put on my clothes, I stuffed grass in here.
I bunched grass and put them here, put them here.
Then when I was done with them, I looked around and noticed pale dry dead wood.
Those dry dead wood, you know, the ones we use for woodwork.
Then since I had a small kettle before there were a lot of portable stoves, before there were portable stoves
I lit the fire with the matches from here that were no longer wet, real mathes.
[?] real matches like this.
I started a fire and made a kettle of hot water.
When it got hot, I sipped some tea.
When I did, I warmed up. I warmed up from this cold.
Then when I was done, I pondered.
Then after I had tea, my legs started getting warmer, the ones that I filled with grass
Reaching here and past it.
I always used to walk because I didn’t like mushing dogs when I was hunting.
Then I tried traveling.
Should I’ve gotten cold, I’d have to go home.
I walked all day and [my legs] got very warm. I got very hot. I didn’t go quickly.
I went to every one of my far away tools, you know, those steel traps, and went home.
And I went home in the cold...
You see, the instructions of those people back then are old, their first ancestors.
I am living according to the ancestors.
Now, we who are trying to be mindful must live according to our ancestors’ wisdom of long ago.
We will live well if we live according to our ancestors like that.
Well, that’s how it is.
Okay, ask me something whenever you want.
Some who are elders now, some who are elders now say that a long time ago, elders, people would not get sick. Is that true?
Yes, it’s true.
People didn’t get sick back then.
Once in a great while, you see, one person would get sick.
And sometimes one year would pass.
Then sometimes if one is to die, he would be the first to die in a long time.
Yet after that had passed, sometimes five years would pass [with no deaths] like that.
And there were few who had TB.
They admonish people against getting close to those with TB.
Caucasians have started admonishing against this. Though we do this to those with TB, they don’t give it to us.
A pesron will not spread his ailment, you know?
One who is and thinks like that without being wary will live well, and nothing will touch him.
Yes.
Nothing will touch him if he’s not wary though they tell him.
Now, I am living like that through the instruction passed down to me by my father and grandfather.
Then, a longt ime ago, did the elders have beliefs, and what were their beliefs?
Shamans. Only a shaman.
And, you know, they didn’t know God, that priest.
Back when I was growing up, missions would arrive to Kayalivik where they would compete with Cuukvagtuli.
Right away, we would dance back and for like this, back and forth like this, back and forth like this every year, every year too.
They would do that.
But what was their belief?
What?
What was their beleif?
The Yup’ik people? (Yes.)
Without any belief, they would say this about what they call magic in English:
They called it the Spirit of the Universe.
Turned out to be God.
They said they would do that, respecting the Spirit of the Universe.
Tuned out to be God.
They referred to God as the Spirit of the Universe.
Would the people of old speak about the devil?
Yes.
The people of old didn’t speak about the devil like that.
Yet they would be shamans who called on their spirit helpers, and I would watch.
You see, they would do things for some reason, and I wouldn’t know what they did.
Did you watch them?
I would watch them.
What would they do?
They would do [whatever] they did.
When they stopped, they would speak.
They said that they fixed and predicted the weather.
They also said they’d instantly go to the moon.
You see, people were strange. People were like legendary little people.
Yes.
Then they would feel a person like this, feeling for his extreme pain.
Then when they let go of him, he got better.
How did those people [do it]? Those people of old are amazing.
Would they ask to be paid to do that?
No, they didn’t ask to be paid.
But those people who called on spirit helpers
When they wanted that person, their relative, to be saved, [they brought] various things, because they didn’t have Western clothes because they only had Yup’ik things
Something, including a bearded seal skin, and a young bearded seal skin
Various things, wolverine skin, wolf skin
[Giving] something, that’s what those people were like.
That was their payment, [?skin] of something.
That was their payment. They knew nothing about money.
Back when you were young, when you traveled to go hunting, or when you traveled somewhere
Did you [experience] anything amazing?