In the fall like this when it first freezes before it gets thick, the ice is dangerous.
Also, part of it also freezes late like this.
When it repeatedly warms up, it freezes late, and even when it’s cold, part of it freezes late.
Also, when it freezes, it’s dangerously thin.
A person has no means to understand thin and dangerous parts [of ice].
But if he has a walking staff, if he examines that ice with his staff, he will know.
Ayagina’ar said that the staff was part of an admonishment.
They told people not to be without them to gauge the ice.
My father used to tell me this, including other people:
If a one suddenly sinks like this and floats, they said not to go up to land right away.
They said to try to keep the ice from closing up.
If it closes up and he tries to get out right away, he will become weakened.
Ayagina’ar said this:
"If a person has gloves as he falls [through the ice], he should wet his gloves and have them stick to the edge of the ice.
"If he does that, he can get out of the water, but he should take his legs out first.
"Then when he gets out..."
If he gets out in the cold like this before there is snow, he should take off his clothes right away
If the land here is close, and if grass if visible.
Wring them out even if it’s cold, undress and take off the wet clothes.
Then put them on again, putting a layer of grass against his skin.
Then he should make a considered decision if he is getting colder
If he tries to urinate and drinks his own urine
His own urine if he’s alone, or if there are two of him, his companion’s urine, if he drinks the urine from one who can urinate
They say a person will not freeze to death if he does that.
Please join us tomorrow.
Ayagina’ar will instruct us on what a person should do when lost when the [season of] the year is like this.
These elders speak about things they’ve experienced.
They also speak about things they’ve heard, things they’ve heard their elders back then say, to young people so that they will be heeded correctly, and that they will go through life well.
If a person knows these traditional instructions, if these young people adhere to them
Young people, especially today, do not know what they should do.
That’s why their parents should let them know [of those things].
Always instruct them, especially in these current dangerous times.
As Ayagina’ar said
After some river [ice] is thick, they get thin after the weather warms up, making them very dangerous.
Let’s also listen to what a person should do when suddenly lost.
If one gets lost and the weather gets back, it would be better if he doesn’t continue, but stops right away and stays put.
Not staying still, but trying to stay warm in the cold.
Not sitting still, trying to stay warm, and not continuing on but stopping [where he is].
If he continues on, he will go far and eventually run out of gas.
And those who look for him will not find him right away if he continues on like that.
When they start traveling on [frozen] rivers, one who’s going should not forget to take his ice pick, walking staff, tarpaulin, and his shovel.
Also, when he’s going to travel, he can tell his family that he’s going to that place, that he’s going somewhere there.
If his expected return has passed, the people from his hometown will first go to where he wanted to go.
Some angrily reply to whomever did [wrong] to them that they shouldn’t do that
That I shouldn’t live my life doing that.
Then if it’s a woman, I should not reply harshly to her if she [?wrongs me]
They told me not to reply harshly to her and turn away from her.
Then they said that if my age-mate, if my age-mate continually does that to me
If one puts my down, and if one says I’m a bad hunter, if he puts me down
Or even if he says I have nothing, one may say I’m a bad hunter with nothing, not one single thing
They said to only reply if we can’t take him anymore.
My father would instruct me like that, to answer however I want.
The people I was born in time to see back then didn’t know about Thanksgiving.
In my earliest memories, I found that there was no Thanksgiving.
ONly when there were you know, priests here in Kwigillingok, did they show how to celebrate Thanksgiving.
When one of the priests talked about how it first started, I think it was Didmer
He said that those captives from across the ocean, somewhere far away, they crossed the ocean in their captivity.
You know, captives don’t live very comfortable lives.
They had many hard times, then they crossed that ocean.
Only when they had landed safely did they start planting crops.
They [harvested] the crops they started planting.
Then they started this Thanksgiving tradition here, you know, [in thanks] for God’s care, though they had also been suffereing greatly when they were captives back then.
They started this Thanksgiving tradition especially in thanks for those crops that they grew, that God let grow for food.
During Thanksgiving, when they [spoke of] those things, when they brought that up, when they told about it to us
To those who now of this Thanksgiving, we must be thankful to God as they were.
You know, we must be thankful for everything.
I realized afterwards when I thought about it
We must be thankful to God for all of the ways that God takes care of us.
I have one thing that I’m most thankful for as we’ve reached this Thanksgiving season.
Recently in the month of August this past summer, I would be sick before then.
I had back problems.
But right when August became, I was more sick than ever before.
And my body would gush out sweat, and my hair would be soaked with sweat.
It turned out it was because I had developed stones in my internal organs inside.
I would have undoubtedly incapacitated had they not found those in me at the hospital.
That is what I’m most thankful for to God during this Thanksgiving season
Because even though I was like that, he has allowed me to live to this time, this day.
We are now experiencing the traditional wisdom of those elders.
In the summer during fishing season like this, they tell us to try to catch fish.
Our elders tell us not to sleep too much, but to try to catch fish.
They said that the ocean is not dependable.
Now, the ocean is showing you how undependable it is.
But if it wants to close it off to us, it will close off hunting for us. The ocean will close itself off to us.
Also, when I ponder, fish are sometimes scarce in some spring seasons, some summers.
Also  those seals are scarce some spring seasons.
Also, those birds would come in small numbers in some spring seasons.
They would say that there were none. They wouldn’t tell anyone that there were none.
But sometimes, you sees, and some years
Those would not be scarce, with lots of fish, and even lots of seals, and even lots of birds.
That’s what they were like long ago. They wouldn’t say that there were none left like that.
They say that a boy especially moves out when it is time for him.
They also said that many, some, many have started doing this now.
You know, in villages, boys marry people who are not from the same village.
They move to another village as our elders back then called it.
Then there’s that important traditional wisdom I used to hear.
If a boy moves to another village, we boys, this is what they especially warned us about back then:
They said that if we move to another village that is not our own
If we move to that village that is not our own where we grew up, we should live carefully.
You know, we should try not to sow discord in this village.
You know, this is what they especially admonished against:
Do not try to sow discord among those around you, your fellow people who go through life with you, there where it’s not your home village.
Watch, they said, if you do not heed that, if you sow discord where it’s not your home village
That village will wonder about your parents.
"How, has he not been instructed by his parents when he was a boy?"
They said they will especially say that without my knowledge if I sow discord where it’s not my home village.
And though I want to tell them about that traditional wisdom here, I cannot tell them
Because they won’t understand Yup’ik like this since they only speak English now.
But it’s better to give them examples or metaphors through these things
Not excessively naming them or whatever.
Their minds are negatively affected when done excessively.
Those elders who share wisdom about the future, if these two are not known anymore, they can be replaced
Those who provide wisdom for the future to these boys.
But these girls who help out in their houses, their grandmothers work with them instead.
Their wisdom is one and the same with those two [old men] when I look closely.
And though this wasn’t my grandmother, when my maternal aunt instructed my older sisters
Being almost exactly the same, in conjuction, her traditional wisdom was the same.
Their admonishments are one and the same. Their instructions are also one and the same.
You wouldn’t hear any surprising [different] traditional wisdom.
We didn’t have children like this a long time ago where things were readily available.
We didn’t do things like how they do it now.
Instead, we took care of children as our instructors told us to.
We forsook sleep; we didn’t indulge in sleep.
Then as we were told, we would only breastfeed them ourselves, only breastfeed them
As we were admonished against nursing them with Western bottles.
Then as we were instructed to forsake sleep to take care of them by our grandmothers, or our maternal aunts
When we slept at night, you know that children’s diapers need to be changed now.
But we didn’t do that in our time.
As they told us to forsake sleep
Right after we slept for a short time and turned to them, when they hadn’t urinated, we would let them urinate or defecate into their little waste containers.
We didn’t have an easy time with diapers.
Then, you see, those who are taken care of like that know how they are taken care of though they are very small
Because they’re conscious form the start though they’re small children.
They said not to raise your hand against them or shout at them when you raise them.
They especially said not to shout at boys, saying this:
"Should they reach the time when they start hunting, if they start to subsist by themselves in the wilderness
"If they see an animal to hunt that their minds wil be afraid of
"They might thoughtlessly flee the wong way
"Or they may thoughtlessly try to chase that animal the wrong way."
For that reason, we were admonished against raising children by shouting at them, shouting at our children, or physically grabbing and hitting them.
There are also separate pieces of traditional wisdom for raising little girls.
It’s like what I just said, not to shout or raise your hand against them.
But they said that because they will be helpers, since they will help those of us who are mothers
We must raise them without shouting at them.
And they said that from the start, have them watch how things are done, what women do, have them be conscious of them.
But it’s detrimental in these days [that they’re] going to these schools.
In my observation, my close observation, when they go to school, their behavior changes.
And they start becoming less and less obedient.
Eventually, some become unmanageable.
Though some suddenly lose their mothers or become orphans
They uphold what their mother did, and make it shown.
They even strive do to things well, and they do not let their food become dirty.
That was what we were told, what we were always told.
They always ended it with the important fact that we would have no food someday if we don’t take good care of food.
They also said not to always be without food, for subsisting fathers to take care of those who are mothers.
They told them to always take good care of them, and always make them into edible food.