Hello, testing. Testing. Are you getting any reading at all?
But we are grateful to them.
We should not be jealous of or envy those around us, wanting to be good hunters who catch a lot.
We must ponder and listen to the [?].
Am I doing the right thing to him?
If we don’t ask questions why he or another or the best of your friends...
...avoided from a good friend or parent or wife or son.
So, we have to ask questions if we are...
...in their mind, to their trial and errors in time of life.
To where a person that scrutinizes the other people and their elders that have...
...can gain that knowledge to where, just lot of these elders just...
You will never know what you’re [?], the trials and errors that you are doing
But you do not understand thinking you’re doing the right thing up until you ask questions.
What led her to [?], then left her on that island to be drowned still remains to be seen.
So, based on that story, you have to...
...want to do to seek the answers.
Only through quesionts through your elders can you get knowledge and wisdom on how you’re going to lead your own life.
To take an example, you young people like to hunt.
You just can’t go out there and...
[?] how you have to butcher it, you have to seek knowledge from your elders.
And if oyu don’t ask any questions, seeing none of it, you just...
...it’s, you know, I remember this traditional wisdom as a legend.
Remembering it now...
In my opinion, God helped with that legend.
He said this: "Didn’t my father, didn’t my grandfather..."
...wanted it to grow.
And then the spruce tree with the big [?] grew, its branches raised...
...it [?].
God helped that.
These days, well, we have always...
As his grandfather was struggling in his mind, that spruce tree grew as God commanded.
That’s all, and I’ve not said the ending in case you may not know it.
There’s another side to it.
At the very last request.
A thought came to this woman, but her grandfather...
And that’s where Christianity comes in.
If you truly ask from the bottom of your heart, you’ll get the answer of what you requested.
Who are you and where are you from?
I’m from Tununak, and my name is Carl, Carl Flynn.
I’m a part of the IRA Council in Tununak.
Now...
Really? IRA Council? (Yes.)
Okay, so with telling stories as you’ve said, how did it start?
Also, please tell us the very first thing you said again.
I’m going to repeat what I said.
The true beginning of this legend
There was never a compeltely accurate telling back then.
The beginning of a legend is very far from this day.
The land was thin a long time ago.
And the little people existed back then when the land was thin a long time ago.
And their companions that they call egacuayiit that look human were always common
Before the time of that legend.
Now, I’ve been saying this:
If you are smart, if you know the entirety of what you’re like, and if you know how a good person should be
I’m telling you because you’re my [?great-great-great-grandchild].
You can make a legend that will help a person live well as a good person.
If you hear a legend, do not accept it as you hear it.
Instead, pretend that everything he is talking about is relevent to yourself, and try to understand it as it applies to you.
If you’re wise, you will think like this: "He is telling it to me."
If you strive to be like that legend he is talking about if it is good
If you want to be like what he is talking about, treat that legend as if it applies to yourself.
Also, some legends apply to what people are like.
They are fun and amazing.
But if the fun and amazing ones are not related to what people are like
Discard those and only accept the good things into your flesh and heart
So that you will become like that when you are able in the near future.
When you are able and you start trying to live your own life, choose to be like that.
Some legends especially apply to people.
One person, one of my relatives, my own paternal aunt told us three brothers legends because she was to tell us legends.
We had fun listening to her. I had fun listening to her.
And when she was done, when that legend was over
They only told legends in the evening when they had no more chores to do, before going to sleep when they had gone to bed.
And they fell asleep to that legend all night.
They would tell legends only as they applied to people, what people should be like.
My late paternal aunt told us that legend
When she was done and finished that story, she said that we should never tell those legends to our peers.
She admonished us against telling that legend to our peers.
Instead, she said that it should be ours.
You see?
A legend like this is not a cause for irritation.
It is also something that has always been. It is also important.
A legend like this is also important.
You watch TV. You watch TV every evening.
When TVs started to come around, I enjoy watching TV.
And aside from that, aside from having fun, I apply them to myself.
I do not want to be like what people should not be like and discard it.
And I take upon what a person should be like.
I apply what a person should be like to myself.
If you hear a story or legend, listen to it completely, and compare yourself to it.
You know what you were like in the past.
Apply it to your past, apply it to yourself as you listen to it.
Since we are alone and I must talk to you and give you lessons, I am giving you lessons.
And I have no such restraints to do so.
I see.
Is that...
Yes, you’ve told enough.
Look, let me add a missing part of the legend that you haven’t heard.
The legend is about a married couple.
The wife is a woman that did not consider herself objectionable.
And they bore a small child.
That woman didn’t consider herself objectionable, and had no qualms with her husband.
THe man however, had many qualms with his wife.
And the man didn’t let his wife know of his qualms, and she didn’t know that she was objectionable.
At the dawning of one day, he invited her to travel with a kayak.
And then he left her on an island in the sea that would be covered with water, and she dug for clams, qapilaat.
As the wife was having fun and enjoying herself, she realized that her husband was traveling away going back home.
"Hey you," she was surprised, "hey, are you leaving me?"
"With all of the qualms I’ve had with you since we married some time ago
"Pay for all of your objectionable ways there.
"You are tormenting my mind. I do not want to be married to you anymore."
He left here where the water would cover it.
Would you envy and choose to be like her?
Ifyou think you’re objectionable, go to the elders and ask them questions.
Ask them questions. Before you run out of questions, you’ll become an old woman.
Let me stop there.
Thank you.
Thank you so much. (Is that enough?)
Yes.
Okay, thank you.