...in their travels
We always hear about people drowning now.
Please talk about what and how.
(Okay.) Compare (Yes.) drowning when going fast and going slow, which one has more drownings and why?
Please speak about that.
Back at that time, they had kayaks for traveling.
Then when the wind suddenly picked up on them, they had thin pullovers made of bearded seal intestines.
Seal gut pullovers that they put on.
With those, the rim of the kayak here, you know how they’re round?
Would you see kayaks? (Yes.)
You know how they’re round?
[S]he would put the hem around the rim of the kayak.
Then finally, bind it, not with twine, but with binding material that they made by cutting sealskin in a spiral. They call that ket’garluku.
Though a wave does this to him, it can’t go inside his kayak.
They used to do that.
Water can’t go inside his kayak because it’s under his hem.
Then these boats, they’ve don’t really sink.
But this thing they tend to abuse, try to abuse, leads them to misfortune.
What’s called alcohol leads them to misfortune.
When there was none of that, there were no accidents.
We didn’t hear of anyone in an accident, drowning, in the summer.
Now, people in every village don’t want the youth to abuse it.
They do it even if they’re not young.
Dying in great numbers like this, like they’re being scattered.
That’s how I compare it, like being scattered.
You know when we scatter things, they scatter. And what we call a salt shaker scatters [salt].
It truly seems, when I ponder upon it, that what they tend to abuse makes them die in great numbers like that.
They didn’t know of any [accidents] when there was none of that [alcohol].
When there was none of that, they wouldn’t get into many accidents.
Like that. Their means of travel back then also weren’t big. Kayaks were their only means of travel.
So now, we also hear now that we don’t hear traditional wisdom anymore.
In your observation, why don’t they talk about traditional wisdom anymore?
It’s because our elders are all gone.
It’s because there’s none of our elders to speak of that traditional wisdom. There’s no one to talk about them anymore.
And some probably know them.
[Some] probably hear about the old traditional wisdom.
It’s because there’s no one to speak about them anymore.
You see, the people I was born in time to see wouldn’t change what they were instructed.
They’d speak of one thing in one way.
When one instructed, [s]he’d speak of it.
Before long, when another instructed, [s]he’d speak of it.
Because there are none of those who’ve become elders to talk about them anymore
They don’t talk about this traditional wisdom anymore, because those that talk about them are gone.
Also, our elders here say this
They always say, it seems, it seems that they put [the blame] on young people for the disconinuation of traditional wisdom, saying that we don’t heed advice anymore.
Why is it like that now?
Now, you see, we’ve started experiencing what they’d talk about.
We’re starting to experience what they’d talk about.
Though one is given advice, [s]he cannot follow it.
After listening, then [s]he goes away, leaving [the instructor].
With that, some would think of the far future.
This is what they spoke of.
I’d also hear that they won’t adhere to traditional wisdom anymore.
They said that when they have no more instructors, they won’t adhere to traditional wisdom anymore.
I’d hear that a long time ago back then.
Now, to you, is it true what they said about how they’d stop adhering to traditional wisdom?
Yes, yes, it’s come true now.
You see, it was like people back then knew what was a long time to come, like they knew.
Whatever [wisdom] that you want to leave with us
Leave us young people, or those listening, with some traditional instruction.
Okay.
What would you leave with us?
I leave behind, this is what I want to leave behind:
Treat each other with love, young people, treat each other with love.
I tell you not to affront those around you.
Treat each other as family.
Now, you see, these people easily go astray.
Starting from traditional wisdom, or, being offended.
[Man and woman] the same, the same, even a woman has become like that.
She goes astray because of being offended. She goes astray from that.
But like this, do not affront your fellow young people.
If you treat them the same, even if they’ve become a man or woman
So it will be like you’re sheltered, like you’re sheltered.
Remember this even when I’m gone.
Okay, thank you. Thank you for speaking with us.