Now, your name, and how old you are.
My name? My English name?
In English and Yup’ik.
In Yup’ik, they call me Angukarnaq.
And when they don’t call me Angukarnaq, [it’s] Taluar.
And when they don’t call me Taluar, [it’s] Allirkar.
But I won’t say some of them.
What about in English?
In English, I have the name Anissum Andrew Jacob.
Please spell Anissum.
A-N-I-S-S-U-M.
Do you want paper? Paper’s across there. I have a cabinet across there.
It’s okay. We can do it with this.
How old are you now?
Now, 77.
Where were you born?
In Iquk, Russian Mission, Yukon [River].
When and why did you move here?
We moved inland to Akula in the spring, in the winter inland to Akula upriver.
Then my dad had a brother, [the] oldest brother.
The oldest brother had three children like this, two boys and this girl.
When he was gone, that one married a man from here.
When we came inland to Akula a long time ago for spring camp, that other boy shot himself.
The 12 gauge misfired on him. It took this off, taking off the skin, when he [?] like this.
We went with him. When we were going home, we came across him.
We returned through Kuicaraq to go up north.
Then when our father saw him, that boy asked to be brought along, to be brought somewhere.
He said that Akiak, there’s a hospital in Akiak.
We brought him there.
We’ve been here since then, at least upriver in Ayimqeryaraq, Kalskag. You know it?
There.
But I’m not sure when. Maybe 1920-something, ’28 or ’29.
We ended up there around then.
In the spring.
How many children, grandchildren, and great-grandchildren if you have any do you have?
I don’t have any of my own.
But my sister’s children’s children are my great-grandnephews and great-grandnieces.
My daughter Maggie over there has two, [I mean] three adopted kids, two boys.
I’m not sure how many great-grandchildren I have.
And I have many grandchildren.
And across there are my own grandchildren, over there is Barbara.
Barbara and who?
Barbara, Mary, Alexandra, Matthew.
One of the older brothers, look at their older brother up there, drowned last year.
Yes, last year, last year [?].
How did you get the idea to make a star?
They didn’t have one here.
I made them one like how they celebrate Russian Christmas in Russian Mission to the north.
The star, a flag, and this has a ball that is this long.
It was very pleasant to spin that.
They would call that the star, or what, the light. Up north in Russian mission, they call it a qaltayak.
It has a wooden handle, and it round like this.
I made one for them here out of plastic.
I put a cross above it up there.
Now, you see a cross above a flag, right?
Yes, I made one for it like that.
Please tell me about that metal star, how you made that star.
Who?
The metal star you made, metal.
Please tell me about how you made what you made in 1952.
I worked on it for a long time.
Maybe two, three, two, three weeks I worked on it, maybe two weeks.
I was a janitor at the school over there. I’d work on it in the evening when I was done.
I wouldn’t do it all day, except in the evening.
And I didn’t have tools, well, before [Western] things came. And we didn’t have electric lights, only traditional lamps.
I’d keep drilling it like this.
Did you see it over there? It has poles of something.
And those poles, what they’d thrown away when fixing the hospital, I took from the shore upriver and used them for the poles.
They’re copper, you know. They’re good.
And the star, and the star [was made with a] five gallon can.
They had five gallon cans long ago.
You probably don’t know of those.
Five gallon can [of] gas, Blazo, kerosene, those things.
They had five gallon containers.
I took an empty one of those because it wasn’t rusty and was soft, and cut it into pieces with scissors.
After cutting them, I secured them with a wire.
A small one.
I wouldn’t solder them, but tie them.
Metal?
Yes.
I’d tie them with wires.
I worked on it for a long time. I think I did it for two weeks, you know, because I’d only work on it in the evening when I used to not get tired.
Here, downriver, I am from downriver.
Downriver now, there are these: they only have old singers during Russian Christmas.
Here, however, there seems to be more youth like this.
Yes.
Do you elders somehow encourage and teach them? Please tell me about that too.
Look, these new singers now
They can’t sing or follow these old [songs] because they’ve started using songbooks, Western songs.
Long ago, however, they never saw those songbooks.
Instead, they sang, they sang with their own [memory].
Now, however, as you know, you just spoke about the old ones downriver.
They sing with what they learned back then, and eventually, they’ve reached this time.
Then now, since they use those books, they cannot go along with the old way because that’s new.
And they’ve started singing in English. They sang in Yup’ik long ago.
During your time back then, when they sang Russian Christmas songs like this
How much did you learn when you didn’t use books?
We used to sing without books upriver back when I was a little boy going to school in Kalskag.
Upriver, one of my former peers, there's one left in Kalskag upriver.
And he's old.
Some, however.... all of them have passed away.
When you go to Kalskag and ask around, you’ll hear about [?Zakhar] Levi.
He’s become a very old man.
He was a singer.
He was a singer, and was the lead during church.
Then now, he’s stopped doing that. Others have instead started, you know, these new boys.
He doesn’t read, but he sings. He doesn’t know how to read.
Back when you were learning, did you seem more focused than the youth today who are learning songs?
Oh my, I can’t say anything. I don’t know that.
We [practiced to] learn.
We [practiced to] learn how to sing.
And we couldn’t read books, but followed the one who was singing.
We followed the one singing the song.
Only like that.
Now, however, they write. They write, they write.
They sing with those books.
But long ago when they started using those books with songs
You know there’s a song that goes somehow like this. Do you know them?
They’ve started singing with those now.
I ask one last thing, my last question.
What’s Russian Christmas to you?
To me? I don’t know about Russian Christmas.
What’s Russian Christmas to you? What does Russian Christmas to you?
Because I went away as a little boy back then, but we used to have Russian Christmas long ago on the Yukon River, up north in Russian Mission.
We woud all be boys. We would have Russian Christmas with all boys.
Grown people, you know, we had grown ups watching us.
How many, two or one.
We’d have Russian Christmas.
It’s the same as Alussistuaq, Christmas.
We’d have Russian Christmas like Christmas.
But we wouldn’t say "Merry Christmas."
And we didn’t say this when we were done: "Merry Christmas."
We wouldn’t because we didn’t know it.
[?Prázdniku, prázdniku] only that.
And we never heard anyone say, "Merry Christmas."
Only when they had Christmas at school did they say, "Merry Christmas."
In my earliest memories, I realized that people would go to church at the Russian Orthodox church held only in Russian.
Now, they wouldn’t do it in English, and wouldn’t do it in Yup’ik, but only in Russian.
And they would read only in Russian.
No English, just Russian.
Just those.
And they had a high priest.
His reader was the former priest Nicky [?].
That high priest would speak in Russian, but Nicky [?] would translate it into Yup’ik.
That Nicky [?] was very fluent in Yup’ik.
What was he? Was he Yup’ik or what?
He was Yup’ik from over there.
I think they refer to Unalaska as Tayarumiut it Yup’ik.
He’d apparently been a priest. He came from there.
When he was no longer a priest, he became a reader.
And hewas the high priest’s speaker.
Look, if sometime you go to Iquk in the north, Russian Mission, Yukon, Russian Mission
Look, up north, there’s one person, Qakngacanrituq.
And he’s my senior. He’s maybe two years or three years my senior, that Qakngacanrituq.
I know him. I went to school with him when I lived up north in Russian Mission before I left.
He will tell you things right, and probably what I don’t know.
Okay, thank you.
You’re welcome.
Watch, he will tell you if you go there.
Watch, if you go sometime...