Let’s speak.
Well, a long time ago, when I became observant
When we were growing up, we realized that we would hear about what my spouse talked about when we were growing up.
But for us young people, those first Caucasians were scary.
We would see several Caucasians.
We didn’t always see them. Only once in a blue moon, we would see Caucasians who arrived.
There you have it. Then one day, we were here in Anuuraaq when they built a school here.
They built a school in the middle of us, then they started going to school.
Then we tried to go to school, oh my, our parents were very reluctant to let us go.
They told us not to go to school under any circumstances.
They said that those were starting some kind of unacceptable behavior. They said those schools [?made them soft].
They were very scary when we did it then.
Though they admonished us, and after I had gone to school, after I had checked them once...
Wait, that fell.
Are you a couple?
Was it because we were too loud?
No.
Then after we had gone to school, we went home since they told us to stay.
These people kept saying that these schools are faulty.
Over there, they have a bad mischievous result.
They said that they would become foolish far in the future, not thinking about what they should be doing when they start bringing things that cause mischief.
We didn’t go to school, but our poor young people and our children are starting to go to school.
They’re finding out about things and they write about us.
The Caucasians have done that, and they didn’t seem to physically abuse any Caucasians.
The work of those shamans were also like that.
People have started having fun about those people they have malicious intent.
And this, among their many pieces of traditional wisdom, among those who wanted to speak to us, they say that jealousy is part of traditional wisdom.
They say that a jealous shaman would be jealous of a person who is living a good life
They place curses on them to make them bad hunters, or they destroy the riches of one who had been going to live well.
Those have great malicious intent.
Then, these pieces of traditional wisdom
They said that though they despise us among our peers, and they say that we poor young people, girls here, are lazy
And because I wouldn’t go out at night, and I would stop going out at night when it got dark
They would intimidate me, saying that if I am lazy that I will be a beggar liek this
And they said that it would bring me to misfortune after I was lazy, [?] my family because of my desire to [have things].
But those who taught us well would tell us that.
And they told us not to misbehave among our peers, not to [?], not to be inattentive, not to act foolish among our peers.
When they got up, they would always tell us, "When you young people have children too
"Even though your child seems like a child, or if you admonish them when you put on their skin boots, ’Now, if your peers do anything to you, run away [?].’"
They say that they pay attention.
They say that what these elders of ours heard when they were growing up are theirs.
When I remember that now, what I didn’t want, that they would become mischievous in the future
And since I don’t speak English and don’t hear them speaking English, I remember them.
And when we had children and got married, they told us to love our spouses.
We should pay attention to our husbands, and never be unfaithful.
And if we women go to [other men] without our husbands’ knowledge
They said that eventually, we would become pregnant with a child that is not our husbands’.
Back when we were growing up, we realized that when they spoke to us, they would tell us of unacceptable things [?] them.
And when they did that watching us, we who were listening would think this:
"Oh my, that person apparently knows us. (S)he saw us." It seemed that they knew us very well, like they had truly seen us.
It turned out that those who really wanted to speak to us emptied their hearts of what they had experiences, telling us so that a person would do well.
And our poor children, when we have children, they said never to bring them [to others’ houses]
And do not hold their hands to have them visit other houses.
They said they’d become mischievous.
They said that their unacceptable behavior would exacerbate our poverty.
A mother who looks after the house, and the father who travels for what we need
They said that we women should be thankful for whatever he catches when he arrives.
Or if he earns a little money, we women should not be angry wanting beautiful dresses, or something like beautiful shoes
Because, they said, that we stand here with good clothes that they’ve gotten us.
They say that those destroy our spouses, what they have earned, what our poor husbands have earned.
They said that we should work dextrously with them as our spouse worked dextrously distributing seal.
They said not to treat those lightly.
We should not take his heard earned money and go.
And as we go, if we come across things that bring mischief, or we drink, or other things
They admonished us against all of those dangerous things, and that we shouldn’t do that in front of our children. They said that we would teach them.
it turned out that when they start going into military service, since we have a lot of male children, we start living destroying our mental health because they abuse alcohol.
However, may a person live life without exacerbating things like that in these days.
And their warning of danger, that if we start being mischievous when our parents who teach us, when our elders teach us
If we start being mischievous without thought for anything
Stop paying attention to those who teach and instruct us, telling us to live well without hindering those among us
Instead, they said that we should be good, pleasant to be seen sitting in our homes.
So, they said, that our house would be peaceful.
And if some guest who feels helpless comes in, try to make them feel at east, if we, you know, do not live mischievously.
When they said that, though we wanted to, yet we would sometimes come across things
We missed our desire to be good.
And these days, since these young people, our descendants, are now in great need of teachers these days because there’s not a lot of people
Since they want to hear instructions, I find that daunting.
We grew up, needing to listen to their traditional wisdom well like this
Because they’ve already strated speaking through KYUK here, and those women instruct.
And those women, it seems that through their disregard for their husbands, they’re like knee guards through that
And we didn’t have different children [from different men], with our very own husband here.
They said that we only had children from our spouse, without adding any from others.
They said they were beautiful.
Oh my, I would want that, oh my goodness.
Here, we would be scared that we would be impregnated without our knowledge.
And it was very scary to become pregnant at a young age, to bring forth a child.
They said illegitimate are embarrassing. It was an admonishment.
Apprently, this was the mischief that our elders back then would talk about.
That import Western instruction these days is very good. Oh my, they’re so nice to hear. Caucasians make us feel nice.
When we watch things on TV, when they inject people who are rowdy, including women, they would become very abnormal.
They become limp [sedated], and it seems they have no more [?] to me.
If some rowdy person comes upon them, it seems they wouldn’t be able to hold up with their strength.
You young people shouldn’t do bad things that are admonished against.
Do not follow what the West tells you to do too much
Also because they say these things, including marijuana, have substances and that they do not end well.
You shouldn’t use them.
Our life here is short.
Our youth and our time growing up seems close, yet we become weak like this and can’t do strenuous things.
That’s why you should be careful like that, not following only bad things.
If you live life doing housework, making money with enthusiasm, it will make us grateful.
But, use your money for yourselves, your houses, to help you with what you need.
And now, since I don’t know how to speak English, I don’t hold it in high regard because I don’t use it.
Only when they really want me to, my spouse across there goes with me, he goes with me and I take something, because I have no idea how to give it.
I am thankful that I don’t know because I stay in peace.
Because the ones we watch say little, but we have probably said a lot by now.
If this is all for us, have what we said not become a lot?
Is that all?
This is all I want [to say].