Yes.
Okay.
Ready? Okay.
Imguuq, Martha H. Jackson, Kwethluk.
Even though I’m not originally from there.
Where are you originally from?
I was born in Tuluksak.
I see.
So, were you born in time to see the people of old who lived in community houses?
I was born in time to see them but just barely.
I see.
I just barely born in time.
I was born in time to see their practices.
And people had their own separate bowls made of hollowed out wood like this.
We all had our own separate bowls.
I would think afterwards, "Even though they didn’t know about doctors, they didn’t share bowls."
After my stroke, the left side of my tongue is paralyzed.
I see. It’s okay. I can understand you.
Probably. I may be understandable.
Yes, it’s good. It’s good.
So, some of the traditional wisdom our people had
Now, we want to hear about them in case they help these young people.
Would you like to say any piece of traditional wisdom?
I would like to say something, but I wasn’t observant when I was young.
I would wake up to someone speaking because I would not move but stay still and listen.
I would listen to them as they were speaking.
These various things:
Stealing, and a woman who does not listen to teaching, also because women were separate, different from the men
A woman instead does what she traditionally does.
And they would say this to us: "We always hear about traditional wisdome every day, and during the evening."
They would also tell us about instructions on how to be.
Because these poor descendats of ours probably are not taught by their mothers
They do unacceptable things, and they also have children out of wedlock.
And two of my grandchildren have illegitimate children.
I think that it’s because I hold down my tongue and do not speak to them
Because they speak English, not Yup’ik like us.
The wisdom surrounding women, they would also tell us women this:
"Look, dear one, you’ve grown this much. When you see a boy, your lips rise."
They said that she would give the boy a big smile.
I would fear that. They would do this when they passed each other: "That one doesn’t smile."
They would say this to me because it was scary.
There is actually a multitude of traditional wisdom.
But because we’ve forgotten them doing that, we don’t bring them up with these young people, also thinking they won’t believe them.
Since they are educated in English, we don’t think they will believe the traditional Yup’ik wisdom that I remember.
To them, my goodness, it’s embarrassing when they have children out of wedlock
What kind of face we should put on.
And when we’re going to pass these boys and the wind is blowing from their side, we would think this:
"I which way I should pass him?"
I would pass him on the downwind side, remembering the traditional wisdom passed down to me.
They had traditional wisdom for everything including stealing, and taking something from another person and eating it.
That said that we were stealing.
It is dangerous.
May he hear of it somehow.
Some of the young people here and the boys who drink become different.
They tend to steal.
That is the first reason that they tell us.
They would tell us, but we would forget it then remember it.
It would come up in our minds.
That’s all, right?
Yes.
Is our Yup’ik language, the way we are speaking in Yup’ik now
Should we not lose it today, and why?
I don’t know. Some of them are also amazed as if hearing it for the first time.
They watch us.
The instructors would like it when we did that.
And watch him without looking away from his mouth. They said to try to [set it] into our hearts.
Oh pity me, I am not a good person, and my children do not listen to instruction.
It’s unfortunate that the admonishments we speak of seem to be for naught.
The admonishments that we feared seem to be of no importance to them.
But this, among the traditional wisdom passed down to them
If one keeps the traditional wisdom with him and goes forth with it, he will do well.
Because I have a paralyzed side of my tongue, it keeps me from speaking well.
It seems to affect me more like this, but I am understandable.
Then back when the churches first came here
And when people started hearing about the church’s Bible
They heard it and found that it was not too different from Yup’ik wisdom. (Yes.)
Is that true?
It’s true. It is true, but it’s unfortunate that we do not adhere to them
Because we don’t adhere to them, and we do not teach them to our children.
Some of them... I am grateful. I am grateful for Lagilek over there.
For Carrie.
She would adhere to the traditional wisdom passed down to her long ago.
I would think, "Wasn’t she inattentive when being taught?"
It’s because some people keep them in their hearts.
They would tell us that it is true.
Are there few great hunters these days?
It’s unfortunate that these people don’t know anything about being great hunters.
And when we’re going to encounter those who pass by, they would look down and pass by us.
This is part of what I just said.
Did people have ancient social interactions since ancient times?
They seemed to have social interactions. And when a guest came, they would always invite him to eat when I had moved here to Kwethluk.
I remember what my late older sister Qaltayak used to do
They would probably also talk about how hard it is for guests to go to villages where they don’t know anyone.
They would also probably tell them to be sociable with guests.
That’s what they would tell us.
They say that an unsociable person has no close friends. He has no relatives.
However, a person who is spoken to or given a small admonishment seems to respond affectionately, as if he were treated with affection.
Even a little admonishment such as "Don’t do that" is enough.
To you, have the young people these days become mischievous?
It seems they now lack common sense.
They only seem to think about what kind of fun they can have.
In contrast, they would be respectful to people before.
When a person was traveling with a sled and found something, he would put it in.
When he returned and was finished eating, he would take that thing and go out.
It turned out that he would show it to people without stealing it.
When he had found the owner, he would give back what was lost.
Now, I would hear that people have things that were lost.
The traditional wisdom passed down to us comes up in my mind. It turns out that we who have become old women like this remember them.
When one’s mischievous phase has passed.
The poor peolpe back then probably lived difficult lives.
They lived extremely hard lives, and we felt the need to respect them.
And out of embarrassment, we would obey right away, adhere to their admonishments, and obey right away.
We wouldn’t want to be bad like that.
What about now, wouldn’t girls have admonishments surrounding boys?
Yes, they had admonishments.
And they would make that man do things only husbands do if a woman makes love to him.
It was so scary it made our hearts skip a beat.
And some of them say this: back then, they would only very rarely hear about people taking their only lives, young people killing themselves.
They said that they would only very rarely hear about them.
Is that something unfortunate to you concerning our young people?
It’s not an accident, but something admonished against.
Someday in the last day, they will appear.
That’s what they did.
They tell them not to do that. And our life as we breath, try not to destroy our life.
They would tell us to keep moving forward.
After struggling, they pass. It turned out to be true.
I’ve started experiencing it now since I’m not young anymore.
Try not to destroy your life.
Instead, try to move forward with what is right.
I have a lot of spittle.
Oh, I thought I saw... do you have any questions that you want to think of?
One other.
Is this Yup’ik language, you know... maybe I asked already.
The Yup'ik language, you know how we're speaking in Yup'ik now?
Do you want to keep the young people from forgetting it? And why don't you want our Yup'ik language to be forgotten?
Well, they tell us to be still and observe. And they would also say that when they talk to us about this langauge.
We must only pray for God to help us.
Becoming like this, people apparently become unable like this. My arm also deters me.
I feel helpless.
When my daughter over there travels anywhere, I feel extremely helpless.
Yet I scold her and shout at her for not listening to me.
My grandmother would also speak to me like this as if she were shouting at me.
Is there a meaning behind an elder speaking to a young person as if shouting?
They would tell them not to look away from the person’s mouth who’s speaking of good things.
They said it was so that it could be stored in the heart.
If he’s going to do something, he will remember that admonishment.
He would end up not doing it.
Do you want to say anything that you want the young people of the Yukon and the Kuskokwim here to hear?
Oh my, I am not disinclined. I can’t see papers either. My eyes have gone bad.
They can’t see anymore. And with writing, the paper looks white.
It is good that these people are speaking about traditional wisdom.
It brings great sadness to mind when listening to them out of the desire to be like them.
It’s distressing wanting to be like that.