Okay, I’m going to say what I want about these
These things when I was a boy, when we were boys
Our food that we hunt on land, sea animals, and these birds.
There are no more these days.
These sea animals are becoming scarce, and these birds are also becoming scarce.
Back when we were boys, at least when I was a boy, there used to be a great many birds in the spring.
The wilderness was quiet. It wasn’t like this.
We wouldn’t hear anything rumbling like this at dawn, rumbling outside.
When they went to spring camps in the spring like this inland in the Akula region, it was wonderful with various birds calling.
And these hunters in the evening when evening was setting, they would spend the evenings hunting muskrats in the spring camps inland.
They would make loud pops, the air filled with gunshots like this everywhere.
And these birds, because they would camp in the spring on the shores of lakes inland
It was fun with the swimming birds calling.
It would be wonderful in the spring.
For what reason, when I think about it, are they gone since they don’t hunt them anymore?
We boys also had these lesson: we hunt these little birds.
There were a great many of them too.
We would hunt those little birds with arrows.
And, you know, we wouldn’t discard what we caught.
Also, these girls would pluck their feathers and cook them.
However, our mother would also cook what we caught without discarding them.
The people back then would respect and revere the food we got from the land like this.
Yet what are they doing these days?
And our children do not hunt these little birds that we used to shoot arrows at.
What we used to hunt on the land here are no more to be seen.
And then when those in the trees hatched in the summer, there would be very many entering smoke houses.
We would also hunt with arrows.
We skinned the little things, opened them here on their chests, removed their flesh, and propped them on their wings here.
Then we tied them and hung them in the trees.
They called that nakaculiluki. That’s what they did.
There were a great many little birds without any change in population.
Also, our caretakers
Starting from the spring until the birds went downriver like this, they would eat them as their food source including their eggs.
We wouldn’t hear anything about there being no more, or anything depleting.
But this is what happened: every year, something would have low numbers.
And sometimes, there would be a lot, occasionally decreasing.
But they wouldn’t be gone, wouldn’t be affected.
There were always a lot of birds and sea animals.
And then, they would eat those birds like this in the spring until there were fish.
They only stopped when they went downriver, stopped going out to hunt.
There was no one left like this in Akula, but [they were] down on the Kuskokwim.
They turned to the fish. There also a great many fish.
Through there reverence, because they are God’s gifts and they revered them, he always kept them at high numbers.
When I think on that these days, they would watch and be careful about whatever food they had.
There used to be a lot of fish across there when we were boys like this.
They would also bump each other to the riverbank here.
And sometimes when we were swimming, the fish would bump into us somewhere here.
Then these days, since we don’t revere them, there are no more of some things.
People back then revered them.
And then, our food sources are evidently connected to us humans.
And then during beluga hunting season, they would admonish us against wading in water when they were hunting beluga.
On this side when we were across there, they would admonish us against wading in water.
They would admonish us like that, saying that they were hunting beluga.
And so, there are no more these days because we don’t hunt them anymore.
And there are no more of these little birds because we’re not hunting them with arrows anymore.
However, our Caucasian counterparts who regulate them are trying to raise bird populations by restricting us from hunting them.
Those who raised us back then didn’t stop hunting these birds.
After having them as a food source in the spring inland
And then, after they fished, when those birds couldn’t fly anymore as they molt, and the chicks
When their young were the same size, they would start hunting them, returning with full kayaks.
And they wouldn’t be affected, wouldn’t deplete.
Yet these days, there are no more of some things including little birds.
Or is it because we don’t hunt them anymore?
Well, that is all I have to say.
Then, you know, when traveling, you know back when they traveled
You know, should they get lots or something happens, what would they eat in the wilderness when they got hungry?
You mean when they got hungry without food?
Yes, you know, if they are lost in the wilderness with no food, what can they eat?
How would they do it, you know, in the winter or summer or sping or fall?
Okay.
People back then would instruct us like this if we had no food, or were in an unfortunate situation:
If we have no food, one can have food like this:
These voles are food sources if he has nothing in the wilderness, but only if he has a fire.
Those can actually be food.
However, I also used to hear that ptarmigan feces can also be eaten as food. Those things.
You just asked me how they could eat if they had no food.
We see these voles in the winter.
Those can actually be food.
But also, if he has not eaten in a while, he should never eat raw meat.
Or as he’s traveling, if he hasn’t eaten in a long time
If he comes upon a fish trap like this, you know the blackfish fries they call alungyaraat, he should never eat those.
They said that they would kill him through his stomach.
Being without food, but it’s worse to be thirsty.
If one gets into misfortune in his travels and is hungry and thirsty
We are admonished that if we are tired, not to eat snow even if we’re thirsty.
They told us not to eat snow. They said we would kill ourselves. They said our heart would weaken if we ate snow like that.
However, if he does not have water, he should put a plastic bag inside here.
They would melt it in warmth. That’s how they would instruct them.
That’s also how it is down in the ocean if he gets into misfortune without water.
His catch’s stomach, you know, its intestines...
(Anything?) What? (Anything he caught?)
Yes, the intestines of whatever he catches, a seal, a sea animal.
He should cut it to whatever length he wants and drain it. One should not drink at the first thought down in the ocean before water seeps out.
If he gets into misfortune, if there’s one of those around him
Cut its stomach or its long intestines into whatever length he wants, drain it, then put snow inside it.
Please start again.
Okay, about what I was just talking about
After draining the sea animals intestines, put snow inside it.
And then, they said to put it into the warm spot here, but not touching his skin.
It will melt here, tying its ends like this.
They say that’s how they get water down in the ocean if they get into misfortune.
However, if he gets to misfortun here on land or sinks into water
If it’s cold, even if it’s cold, he should take off his clothes right away if he can before they freeze.
He should quickly wring his clothes to make them better, and put them on.
And when he puts them on, if there’s grass, he should fill and line them.
Including the area down here.
This is an instruction when it’s cold. But, they are told to continually fold these here, including these like this.
However, they said that if he stays still and freezes, when these can’t move anymore, he will not be able to walk.
And if these also freeze, he won’t be able to move.
They would instruct us to do that if we didn’t have anything around us to save us.
We should keep doing this with these [arms] in the cold, and these [legs], if we’re not moving.
There are many ways to get into misfortune here on land.
He should do whatever he can.
And then, they would also instruct us like this:
If we are traveling in the extreme cold and suddenly fall
If we do not immediately go under the ice, depending on if we do not sink in
You know, after we do that, if we are unable [to do anything else]
Do this with our glove to make it stick [to the ice].
Keep that stuck, occassionally doing this.
If it would not come off, he will be able to get out of the water by pulling that like this if he is able to come out.
There is a lot of traditional wisdom about getting into misfortune.
They said that if we get into misfortune, you know, not to panic and try to hastily save ourselves.
They said that if we try [too hastily], we will kill ourselves.
And in the water here, when we travel, we should observe the water for what can save us.
They also told us to observe how to use these waves. That’s how they instructed us.
He must only physically travel through his being observant.
And, you just asked me about being without food.
But I do not know what to do if one does not have anything.
But if he has skin clothes that can be eaten
If he has a fire, he should char it, not eat it raw.
If he hasn’t eaten in a long time, that will save him.
They would instruct us that it’s safe to put ptarmigan feces into the snow and eat it.
We used to try those when we were boys.
We would eat ptarmigan feces like that.
After putting them in snow, we would try eating them.
Because that’s traditional wisdom. What?
Were they okay?
They were good, they were okay, because of these trees, because they eat these trees
Because they eat plants, and lowbush cranberries, and Labrador tea, and the top parts of trees.
They were okay. Those are not admonished against. There’s nothing dangerous in ptarmigan feces.
That’s all.
Do you have any other thoughts?
What?
Can you stop recording for a while?
Is it time to start? (Yes.)
Okay, so to you who are listening these days
I’m going to speak about what’s been on my mind and what I’ve experienced.
These things: the sun, and what becomes visible, appears, before the sun in the morning
When they become visible these days, we say they appear, and they appear when they come into view.
The sun rises across there
If we’re here toward the water on the Kuskokwim.
The Kuskokwim down there is on the side, with the west cutting into it inland.
If he gets into misfortune somewhere here, or if he’s lost, if it gets cloudy, if a blizzard sets, or gets foggy
If it’s night, or he has absolutely no idea where he is, and he doesn’t know where the Kuskokwim is
Being completely lost.
Three of us experienced that when we were going to Newtok.
But before this, I used to observe the sun and moon.
It doesn’t rise anywhere else. It rises across there, a ways upriver across the Kuskokwim.
And then, before it gets too high, it goes above the Kuskokwim.
It goes downriver toward the ocean.
And then when it goes above the ocean, our ocean odown there, toward our ocean, it finally goes up there.
It goes without going any higher.
And then when it goes across toward the land, it goes down to disappear on the land here.
The moon and the sun.
And then, you know, the Big Dipper (Qaluurin), you know it. You talk about the Big Dipper.
Do you know it?
We used to refer to the Big Dipper as Tunturyuk. Tunturyuk.
It’s like Erenret Iquat [?constellation?] points them to a certain direction, like it faces a direction for them.
When the sun sets, you will observe that it faces Erenret Iquat.
And then it goes over there, goes through the area across there on the other side.
And then when it gets close to the ocean there, it bends down.
As soon as it bends down, Erenret [Iquat] appear, and the area toward the sun brightens.
I also used that to find my bearings.
And at that time, you know, as we were coming from Newtok, our compass was bad and broken.
We had apparently gone upriver.
We thought we were going down to the ocean as it was getting dark.
When we thought we were going to the ocean, we backtracked and went to the land. We had no idea where we were.
We set up a tent and went to bed as it started getting wet.
And then as we were sleeping, I opened my eyes, and the tent was a little bright, also because it was warm.
I faced it and found that it was cold, and it seemed bright up there.
Because the tent had a little hold, after doing this with my forefinger, I saw that the moon was over there.
I finally understood where we were.
The Kuskokwim was down there.
We woke up.
And then, even though we didn’t know where we were, I told my companions that we were going to go toward the Kuskokwim.
So, we went toward the Kuskokwim.
Also, that river among the hills that we called Qurrlurnat, we thought that we would recognize it.
And as we went, we recognized things.
That’s why they would instruct us to observing everything on the land as we went.
We should always make them landmarks.
Also, we should always find our bearings with these [willows with red bark].
And the things toward land, when it’s good, when it goes to our home villages, use those to find our bearings.
Also, we should know where ponds or elevated areas are here.
That’s how we were instructed.
They said that if we happen to recognize it, even when the weather’s bad, we will know which direction and where our home villages are.
That’s why those who raised us back then would tell to always be observant as we traveled like this. We should always observe everything.
And when it gets clear at night, mark where the stars above are.
Or if a star is in the direction of a village, that village will be [marked as being] there.
But, they also wouldn’t stay in their houses all the time.
They would gauge it when traveling in a certain dirionction, using those stars to get their bearings like that.
We experienced it like that.
We eventually reached placed we recognized.
And it was even foggy when we traveled.
But with that moon, I knew which way the Kuskokwim was.
And I told my companions this: if we run out of fuel, we will walk down to the Kuskokwim.
And yet the Kuskowkim was gone because it was foggy.
I said a plane would see us down...