[?] was saying [?]. You think it could be leukemia?
Or, she was [?] and her skin was really dark.
Was her blood bad?
Their ailment was in her blood, and it was bad.
It could be some other kind of sickness too.
We’re not enough of the story [?].
What about these, [?] is that, they call them chickweed that we have growing?
It’s what I was just trying to get, but we’d have to see that.
I have bag of them out in my office, but they’re from a Western store.
But they really like those, those kind of flowers.
Yeah, but my friend got that tea for me, and looks really like that.
Those things, Lucy, since these can’t see those false chamomiles, though they hear the name, they don’t know exactly what it is.
Yes.
I think they were wondering...
Those false chamomiles grow in old settlements.
Yes, he over there knows them.
I’m not a good translator.
No, it’s not that. Did she get sick after taking medicine?
No, she...
She was already sick from something in her blood. There was some disease in her blood.
[?] six months to a year.
Her hair was coming out. Her skin was turning dark.
Does that ring a bell?
And that’s when she started that medicine.
How long ago was this?
How many years did that last?
Her sickness?
Yes, [since] when?
This past winter, and last year
She’s good now. She’s gotten better now. She’s back to normal.
Just now?
Yes.
And what year [?].
The years now, she started here, you see.
She started this year, and now, she’s been good these two years.
Okay, must be ’81. (Three years.)
Probably. I don’t know those [years].
[?] daughter is healthy now?
Three years as compared ot six months that she was [?].
Who was that, and where did the doctor examine her?
Here. Yes, she has caretakers here, and she always used to go to Anchorage.
It’s because we want to find out what her sickness was.
Yes.
The doctors here...
She also has a doctor here inland. Her caretaker is inland at the hospital.
Half of it.
She said half of a berry [?].
Let’s take a break.
Let’s stop for a bit.
I have a headache.
...when they do that, they stop bleeding.
She said if they got a deep cut, they usually put Tobasco on it.
People have slightly different saliva...
...they would do that to it.
I don’t know that.
She doesn’t know it.
Has anybody ever heard of that?
...if they’ve used anything other than [?] oil or something.
Other than oil?
I mean, what was used traditionally.
When they have earaches.
A long time ago, what remedy would they use for earaches?
I do that too now. When my children have earaches, I pour some oil and fill them inside.
Would they use anything else?
Oil, would they use anything else?
But I used to watch some of them
How many times have I watched it? It was dangerous.
They would roll up a piece of paper like this so that it had a sharp point.
After they rolled it to a sharp point, they’d put it here in the ear of the one with the earache.
Then they’d light a fire there. It would burn down and spark, then they’d get better.
So are these false chamomiles?
Those are absolutely false chamomiles.
See, those are false chamomiles.
What are they called?
Chamomiles. Chamomile.
What are they?
C-H-O-M-I-L-O-T?
They’re talking about how we would pour oil (Yes.), yes.
That one with an earache.
The top parts of false chamomile.
(S)he saw them.
And these, these too, the bark of the branches of these little trees.
Some of those children have sores on their mouths, the sores going from their throats inside going out to their mouths.
Then their bark, not doing anything with them after removing their leaves, these kinds of trees here.
They wouldn’t use just any trees for medicine.
But it would be clear which ones, these ones that are [?].
You see, after ripping off the barks from these, when they put them on sores, huge sores with pus
They get wrinkly.
Do you know how this flesh gets wrinkly?
You know how when you wash clothes or deal with water for a while, the skin of the hands becomes abnormal?
That [happens] when these are in contact with sores.
For those with sore throats, and bad sores in their mouths, keep these in their mouth.
Because they taste so bad, the inside of the mouth becomes different.
Their bark is also medicinal.
Though they grow out there, rip them off, and overlap the inner parts of their bark.
Open sores heal right away, not grow for long, sores.
You know how some of children tend to get sores in their mouths?
Those are also medicinal.
Have them keep it in their mouths, but though they swallow their saliva, let them be, keeping their throats in mind.
That’s how we used these.
She was talking about these kinds of bushes.
They could use these like I said, take out the bark, and take off the black part from the outside, and use it.
How can you translate ”peqlirtellria [wrinkled skin]" into English?
I don’t know.You know how the flesh becomes different?
And something, you see, when you keep these in your mouth, your mouth becomes different, wrinkled.
Well, that’s when it’s sore inside, and it turns like that, I think. It gets wrinkled. Your mouth is sore on the inside, and it gets to the point where it’s wrinkled like that.
When we use those, [?].
Peqlirnarqelluteng [Making it wrinkly], I don’t know how you can describe that.
But they’re kind of strong.
When you put them in your mouth, they’re bitter, and they’re kind of...
...kinds for sores in the mouth.
And you can use them anytime, even in the summertime.
When we’re playing outside when I was young, we used to eat the shoots from these kinds of trees.
You know the leaves that are just coming out?
We eat those.
And then those, there’s all kind of plants that you can eat.
And some of the plants that are dangerous
If you don’t know them, you don’t have to eat them.
But anyway, she didn’t mention those. But we used to eat...
[?Yuuquq]. A yuuquq is here on this paper.
Oil, we Yupiit would clean out our guts with real [seal] oil, the oil of the marine animals, seals.
You know how we render oil from those?
During the year, you see, they would have us take a remedy once to clean out our guts.
I also practiced cleaning out my guys for a long time like that.
And as I had a lot of children recently, I would use it when I had a lot of children when I became a woman, because we practiced it.
Though I wasn’t sick, though nothing was wrong, I would take that remedy some winters.
A cup, filling a cup halfway with seal oil
We would start the morning when we woke up [like that] before there was anything in our stomachs, before food, with nothing in it.
We would fill that cup haflway with seal oil, and drink it in the morning right when we woke up.
We struggled. We’d finally finish it, oh my, because it’s strong.
Since we tried to make ourselves healthier, we would have it like that.
Then we’d sit still, sit still right then.
Our stomachs would make sounds, get bad and make sounds.
Then when we needed to defecate and went to the bathroom, a hard piece of feces from inside would come out.
Why would they have them clean out?
Then when it came out, only when the hard feces came out
Then warm fish broth
We would take occassional drinks from that fish broth, putting salt in it.
When we occassionally drank that, we would defecate a lot.
It would clean out our guts inside.
But we wouldn’t eat, or drink anything hot until that broth came out from our guts.
We would eat, or drink anything hot since tea makes us stop defecating.
We would only drink what we call broth, fish broth, until we stopped defecating.
Then one day, I examined what had come out of my guts inside.
I had no more feces to defecate, and the ones that came out last were hard, and were varying sizes. Some were big.
They were very hard.
A lot came out, and some were big.
Then out of curiosity for that big one, I took a stick from there and split it open.
After it couldn’t, it split open and I found that what was inside looked like a Western fruit [apple].
You eat Western fruits [apples]. Their inside are like that.
Though it was very hard, it split open and the inside was white.
The inside looked like an apple, like those Western plants we eat.
The insides of those hard ones are apparently like that.
Though I tell you about what I used, I don’t know some of those remedies that I heard of but didn’t use.
But I told you something true. I’ve been telling you about what I used.
And just now, how I cleaned out my guts by taking that remedy
The hard ones that came out last were green, very green
And their surfaces were hard.
I just talked about how I split that kind open and examined it.
During the year, they’d always have us clean out our guts.
And though we weren’t sick, when we didn’t want to eat and our stomachs wouldn’t get hungry, they’d have us clean them out.
It makes you hungry, you see, it makes you want to eat after cleaning out your guts.
That’s how we used that seal oil, but we wouldn’t always do it.
But we would do that in one year as a remedy.
Joanna wants to take a break [?] for a while.
She was saying that she used to use seal oil once a year to clean their insides, the inside of their stomachs.
And they clean once a year.
She says she still does it now.
And sometimes in some winters, not every year now, but then she does it in some winters now.
She said they used to use it even when they weren’t sick.