After having me paid, (s)he was daunted by landing.
Then when (s)he asked us to go down, two of us went down.
And later, I stayed for a few minutes here, and the one I was going to go with called me.
He said the [?] were going to go inland.
He told me to go down quickly, and I went down.
Starting off
When they had an election about alcohol, it didn’t pass, and it’s how it has been.
What do you think about that?
It didn’t pass?
That alcohol regulation didn’t pass, the one where they tried to sell alcohol here again.
Yes.
What do you think about how it didn’t pass?
I absolutely do not support selling those at restaurants
Because I’ve always known that this [alcohol] is not used correctly.
I know that many of our young people are caught in that, drowning
And married couples get divorced.
Also, when this married couple get out of hand, they take their children and have better people take care of them.
I absolutely do not like that because I’ve watched them from way back when I was young.
Because I used to see them before I was drafted here by the army
When I would come here to Bethel by snowmachine
Since I watch and know those who misbehave, I do not want them to sell that in restaurants here.
I’m very thankful since yesterday
Because I listened to the news anchors reporting that nay was the majority.
I’m very thankful for that.
However, without having established it
My mind will leave with you the next thing, because it says this:
They may not seel them in restaurants anymore, but it won’t stop coming here by plane.
I also just heard that this morning on the news.
Also, the one asking for signatures holds a petition.
They said that it will be put there
So that they will stop coming here by plane.
I will also keep a very close eye on that.
Without your knowledge, I have knowledgeable people help me to understand it.
Having reached this age this day, since it’s like I lose everything
I forget things and can’t understand some words.
I’ve also started forgetting what I’ve put down in here.
Though they’re right there, I forget where I put them.
I’m very happy for what was [passed].
So, it’s still like this now: they can bring in alcohol.
In your observation of that, how do you compare selling alcohol back then, and being able to bring it in now?
It’s not good.
I don’t want sellers to sell
And I don’t want a liquor store here in our town.
Our young people who’ve just stood up, who came after us
The young people know nothing about our traditional instructions
Our traditional Yupiaq instructions.
When spoken to, their mouths hang open.
When I speak to my grandchildren in Yup’ik, their mouths hang open.
Yet when I speak to them in English, they go.
All of them have become like that.
And when I go to little villages, these Yupiat would only speak English, these little boys.
I am by no means happy about that.
When it’s in plenty now, and I was part of the tribal council back then
Way back before these people grew up.
As a part of the council, we fought for it.
When it was time to vote when we noticed it was time to vote, we voted to stop that.
It was a lot [accomplished].
We had all of the [liquor] stores close up.
We Yupiat, when there weren’t a lot of Caucasians, overcame that right away then.
If several people like this, even five, speak with one mind, they are very strong.
But do not disregard God.
As he said, if three people are gathered in his name, he is among them.
And it’s true.
When I was in the army, I walked in a dangrous place when the Japanese went down there
When they came through the points down there.
When I was going to leave here, our pastor Makneq, he’s already died.
Makneq’s instruction:
"Do not give up praying."
Like that, that was the extent of his instruction to me.
It’s very true.
When I stopped among my peers, I would always remember it.
Also, though my peers misbehaved, I was with them and watched them.
And every evening, we would have parties when we were in school
There was alcohol among them, nothing but beer among them.
Because I knew about it, I tried not to take it up
Because it goes wrong, and ends with misfortune.
My Caucasian friends here would encourage me to drink one can.
He eventually got mad.
But he didn’t lay one fist on my body here. Not once did a fist land on me.
When he started yelling at me, when they started yelling at me
I would answer them, would answer them in English as in their language
I said that only when he buys me a pop, any kind [of] pop, that I would drink with him.
After he was angry and pounding the table
He’d get better later and buy me a pop.
He’d have a beer, and I’d have a pop.
It was good.
Though I keep admonishing my fellow Yupiit
And James Active inland from the same village as me, though I keep admonishing them
If I weren’t with him, James Active inland would always be in jail
Because he likes to [party] with these Caucasians.
I treated him like my baby.
I would wake him up in the morning so that he wouldn’t be late.
Also, though these Caucasians drink, because they don’t break their rules in the army
The First Sergeant always woke up very early.
He would whistle outside of them, going around to wake them up.
Then they would always have alerts at night, [in the middle] of the night...
Without any excuses, when the fire alarm blared
We’d get ready, go out, and wake up everyone who was asleep.
Then we’d go inland, inland from the houses to the area between the spruce trees.
We’d hide in what they called foxholes.
Then the sergeant would arrive and circle us when it was almost time to go back.
When there’s almost a fire in Anchorage, a siren sounds at night.
I heard that you were one of the first mailmen here on the Kuskokwim. Please tell us about that too.
I wasn’t a mail man.
One time, I went with the mail delivery.
Downriver in Kuiggaq where it’s called Oscarville
That mail man lived there and had a trading post.
He’d taken over a trading post.
They would speak of that Caucasian
That he would row upriver here on the Kuskokwim to deliver mail.
And when going upriver downriver from Kalskaq, we would enter the little creek on the left.
We went upriver through there.
You see, three of us traveled from here to deliver mail.
The boat, we loaded a huge wooden boat with mail here.
You know, I know that they weren’t all mail at that time.
They were mostly beavers, you know, beaver skins.
They would put the mail in those huge mail carrying bags and lock them.
We stacked and pressed them down.
We loaded the boat, then covered it with canvas.
Then we covered the canvas with plastic.
We nailed down the outer edges so it wouldn’t open.
But where we would sit, the front, and the back would be empty.
We would put our gas reserve in the rear.
And there were no huge new boat motors back when I went.
That storekeeper placed a new seven horse Evinrude motor on the boat
And put a gas reserve in there.
And those things that have sails that they call Columbia.
The Columbia boats they use to travel the ocean down there.
We used one of those those that wasn't very big with a motor in it.
We pulled a vessel with that boat as we went upriver.
When we reached Kalskag, we anchored it in the water near them.
We went inland with that other vessel we pulled behind us.
He looked for one who wasn't lazy.
They called him Matvi, Matvi Brasken.
He used to be from Lomavik.
When we did that before Lomavik was deserted
My companion’s wife was that limping man’s sister.
Then one of the men looked strained wanting to go with us.
There were three of us men, with one woman as our fourth.
We went downriver, then went upriver through the creek over there.
It was narrow. Here on the banks of Cingik, things would be flattened.
It would be [?up on the bank].
Apparently, those were black bears’ fishing areas.
Then we arrived as we went upriver.
The standing radio pole had another spruce tree placed on its side like this.
It had wires up there.
On the side of the that pole was a winch.
Stuck on the side of that was where you operated it.
We brought our boat to that.
We [?secured it] underneath at either end.
We raised it with the winch and set it askew.
We placed it into a square sled.
And then we would go, pushing the sled.
The spruce trees were placed on their sides measuring steps like this.
Then on the trees placed on their sides was the path for the metal wheels.
That had those wheels.
We went inland through Qass’uqitak.
In watery paths, we would slightly bend our knees.
And when we went up on the tundra, we crossed through the tundra.
We arrived and there was a pole like that on the riverbank.
Apparently, it was at the end of the river Kuicaraq inland
The mail delivery path went downriver from its headwaters to Tumkuvigpak.
The metal sled stopped on that path there.
Then we put in our boat.
There were houses there on the banks of Kuicaraq.
That plywood house inland form that pole had various fish traps in it, even had wooden fish traps in it
Because the people from Kalskag fished there.
Then we went downriver on through Kuicaraq.
We went downriver following its current.
Then the fork, the right fork when going downriver
We slipped into the little creek.
As soon as we slipped in...