What? (It looked bright.)
You haven’t started it yet? (Yes, wait.)
Okay, when you start it, ask me about how they prepare what they need to use in the fall.
Will you be sitting like that?
Yes, I’ll be sitting like this. (Okay.)
So, how did they prepare in the winter like this?
You mean how people back then would start preparing in the fall?
Yes.
Our ancestors?
So, I am not very old right now.
But now, I am 68 years old.
I’m from Tuntutuliak.
And they would call me Ackiar in Yup’ik.
Then after Westernization, they’ve started calling me Nick Lupie.
And so, you just asked how they started preparing in the fall
Or how they started preparing what they’d need to use in the winter.
Now, I’m going to speak, yes, about what I know and what I’ve seen.
In the fall upriver in Kialiq when we were boys
Upriver at the mouth of Kialiq, they called that stream Qukaqlircaraq.
We used to stay there.
Our caretakers, however, were not sedentary in the fall like this.
Or, they also didn’t travel without physical labor.
These things they used for the fall, when they came from the fish camps across there like this
They would gather wood in the fall.
And they didn’t have boats, only kayaks.
Because there is a very high tide in the morning during the fall like this
They would start traveling early in the morning in the dark.
Sometimes, however, a kayak would appear coming through Cingik downriver towing wood.
In the fall like this, when they were going to travel here to the headwaters of the rivers to go to winter camps
They would gather those.
Our elders, those who raised us, were not like how we are now.
They would travel, rowing with their own arms, rowing through the water.
Then when it was time for them, they started going upriver.
They brought those pieces of wood with them.
Then they would put their possessions as cargo on top of them.
Those without boats would move with wood.
Then when they arrived at the headwaters of the rivers where they would camp for the winter, they would bring the wood inland.
Then they would prepare that wood, preparing their fish traps to catch fish with.
Those who raised us back then lived hard lives.
They would make that wood into fish traps, large fish traps.
The openings of those large fish traps were like this, wide and long.
And they were like this, the inner components they called ilulirpiit.
Then they would make the middle of the fish traps by expanding them.
Then they would place the third over there.
They referred to those real fish traps as qamut.
These big fish traps were not like, you know, traps for blackfish.
And they had gaps of this size, made them with gaps of this size.
Yes, they didn’t make those large fish traps without a process.
They used these as measurements.
And then they would put the split spruce there.
Then after doing this, they would make those large fish traps with about this size gaps to the side.
When they started working on them like this, their hands would get raw from doing this.
They wouldn’t use twine, but they split wood like this until they were thin in diameter, thin.
They would make them about this wide, but thin.
They wouldn’t work on those without a process either.
They had measurements of how thick to make them.
When they started doing that, these got raw from doing this.
When they started bleeding, they would cover these three with skin
When these got raw.
These too, these would get raw from holding it.
Our ancestors back then were not like how we are now.
They had wooden possessions.
They used wood to make their possessions.
They used it for their tools, their things, their houses, what they had in their houses, and sleds.
They used this wood for survival.
However, when they started setting them, they would check on them every day like this.
And they would wake up in the morning when the tide had gone out after coming in
They would get up at night, go down to the stakes of the fishing tools, and stick them further in after chiseling the ice like this.
This is how our caretakers were back then, not like now.
Then when fall came like that, they would also prepare things for their women to use.
They made what they called waterproof fish skin boots out of fish skin, including king salmon.
They referred to fish skins as amiriit.
Hold on for a moment.
Please start again.
It’s time to start? Okay.
Just now, I talked about men’s work, how men worked to prepare their things.
However, women would work separately before it froze to prepare things for their men.
Clothes they would need, skin boots, and these fish skins, king salmon
They called it "removing fish" when they made fish skin boots for them.
Also, with those, they wouldn’t just stop at removing their flesh
When they finished removing their flesh, they wouldn’t work on them right away.
They would also soak the fish skins in urine like this to remove the fishy smell.
They say  that when they aged urine
Into some containers, the men would urinate into the designated containers to age urine, as they called it.
Those would smell very strong.
They would soak the fish skins in those.
Then after soaking them, they would scrape them, scrape them after putting them on boards.
Then they would hang them outside to dry.
And then when they dried, they would make them into skin boots for their men.
They called it making them fish skin boots to travel with like this.
Their men would also prepare.
When they stopped using those traps for black fish, what they called large fish traps
When they were going to change them from the blackfish [traps]
They would also then make those fish traps.
Then when they started setting them
These days, we temporarily store blackfish in various things, old boxes and burlap bags.
However, the ones I observed that raised us didn’t have those.
Their women would also prepare containers for them out of grass.
When they’re no longer green like this but become pale, they would gather a lot like this.
And in the summer like this, I forgot something.
Their women would prepare those that they would use, the coarse grass that they would use for stitches and other things.
Those who raised us back then always had the future in mind like this.
They would always prepare what they needed in the future even if it was far because they didn’t have anything.
What they had was only made from what was on the land.
To them, they couldn’t afford not to do that.
They would prepare what they would need way ahead of time.
In the summer, they would use tall cottongrass for stitching.
When the women started gathering tall cottongrass, they would spread them out to dry them, as they called it.
Then when they had, as they called it, dried out, they wouldn’t gather them but weave them.
Then when they were done, they rolled them up.
That’s what they did with the grass they’d use for stitching.
When I remember those during our time, I also find it difficult to do it.
And then their men
They would make these tools, fish trap-like traps to catch minks.
They would make fish traps small, about this long, and a certain size after measuring the streams.
Those were also not made without a process, but had measurements.
Their inner components would not be like this like a blackfish trap.
They would be like this, and this over there would be like a den.
When I watched my older sister’s husband like this back then
He would do this with his hands, and measure the entrance, what they call the igyaraq.
That’s what they were like, not made without a process.
Then when he made fish trap-like traps for land otters, he would make the entrances like that.
Then he would measure with his hand like this, doing this with his thumb to measure their width.
Those would also not be made without a process.
These days, when I remember how they used to live back then
You know, when I remember them, I would feel like they had difficult lives.
But since I [grew up] when after Westernization, our caretakers lived with some Western things.
But they didn’t get a lot of [Western] things.
They had these things, tea, floud, sugar, and once in a while, pilot bread.
However, when they brought in whatever they got, they would smell very strong.
These days, those don’t smell like anything.
When they took out pilot bread, they would smell strong from afar, they smelled nice and good.
These days, I don’t notice them anymore.
But once in a while, I smell them when they’re close.
That’s what those were like.
What about the admonishments they had for men, you know, when they traveled in the fall like this?
So, yes, when they traveled like this
They would admonish them when it was dangerous like this.
They also told them not to make too much noise in the wilderness. They told them not to make too much noise like this.
Only those who’ve gotten into accidents, they will make a lot of noise if they fall into water.
They also admonished us in the fall like this not to scream or make too much noise in the wilderness.
They said that only those who were helpless would make noise like that.
Then if they hear someone making noise or screaming, they would understand that he got into an accident or sunk into water.
These days, however, since they are no longer admonished, since we no longer admonish you
They don’t know how to act anymore.
They also make a lot of noise and scream between villages.
They admonished against that.
So, I experienced that one time when I heard someone who had gotten into an accident.
Not long after Tuntutuliak was established as a village
When we were in Kelliq down there, and there were people upriver too.
You see this lake toward the water from this house.
In the day like this toward the evening, someone was screaming inland from us, and I thought it was our inland neighbors.
It turned out he had fallen into the water down there.
One of the people going down saw him just as he was about to freeze when there was no village like this.
The people back then had a lot of admonishments.
They would tell them not to make noise like this.
Then, when they were also going to travel like this
They would always say where they were going to go.
When they wouldn’t return like this, they would know that they had gotten into an accident.
When they travel with boats these days, however, they don’t say anything.
Then when they don’t return, they don’t know what happened because they didn’t say anything.
It’s because they don’t consider before traveling these days.
Or they say they’re going somewhere, then go to other villages.
That is what causes us confusion these days.
We don’t know what the next generation is doing.
Or we think they’re somewhere [else].
These days, even if they die in the wilderness, we have no idea about them.
You see, it’s because there are not a lot of things that bring us struggle these days.
Now, the people back then were not like this.
They always observed everything.
And in the fall, they would always speak to us boys about our future, what we would experience, things they had experienced.
They would explain dangerous things, in the wilderness too.
And everyhing on this land, elevated hills, had names, and all of the creeks had names, and some lakes had names.
They knew they layout of the land.
These days, however, since we are not pointing things out in the wilderness to our children anymore
They don’t know anything, including these river, and lakes, and these elevated spots.
And when they get something and are asked what area they got it from
Or if they lose where a person is, or a person gets lost as they do these days.
When they ask the person who saw him about the area he saw him, he doesn’t know its name.
They only say, "Over there," because we don’t point those out to them anymore.
We used to talk about everything, but we wouldn’t always use them.
But when we came upon them, we would recognize them.
Yes, a person must only live according to the traditional wisdom.
If he does not abide by traditional wisdom, he will not live right, and he will have need of the things his peers work for.
They would talk to us like this back then: if we live using and abiding by this traditional wisdom, we will live well
Not being lazy, not sleeping too much.
They would promise us that.
However, we didn’t come upon the time they pointed out.
But when we come upon them these days, we recognize it.
That’s why they would talk to us like this back then:
We should pay attention to someone who is talking to us and watch his mouth.
They said that if we look away from him, we’ll have no idea what he’s talking about anymore.
And indeed...