Well now, Qunuin, come here.
Now, I don’t have any other memories, yes.
However, I have memories of the people I was born in time to see.
I want to tell them about the old ones before. (Yes, okay, yes.)
If it is opportune.
You see, I grew up over in Chefornak.
I grew up in Chefornak. It turned out...
And their descendants, they said that the descendants of our descendants would begin what people would be like on this earth.
They will start it.
And then they said that their future descendants, it seems that the people have started going through this these days.
It seemed they spoke as if seeing it.
I reached this age and remember them.
They talked about it as if they were looking at the people that would live in these lands.
They said, "Pity."
They said that when they have reached the point that they would become like that, even the young people would become like puppies.
Look at it now.
I completely understand that those people would talk about this time as if they were truly seeing it.
Oh my goodness, and now, these people have reached it, every person from the villages.
And none of them was left out as all villages reached it.
They said that people would become like when the young people start disregarding traditional wisdom, when they don’t adhere to traditional wisdom anymore.
Oh my goodness, also, my grandfather over in Chefornak who was known as Elegtaq
My grandfather Elegtaq would tell stories. Apaprently, he grew up across there around Eek, upriver from there.
They called that place Allauguulleq. My grandfather Elegtaq was from there.
I also used to see the old woman they called Aluskaq’s Mother out there on Nelson Island.
He said that they were not separated when it was called Allgauguulleq.
He said that their lives were not apart from each other.
Well, I have just told that story. Consider it like this.
And, pity me, even though I didn’t use all of the traditional wisdom, I believed.
I believed what little wisdom was passed down to me. I have not obeyed every piece of wisdom passed down to me though.
But when I heard people instructing, I would believe.
Also, my instructors would tell me this:
"Now see here, even if any of your peers do anything to you, never retaliate with bad intent.
"Live by treating people well, and never be like them.
"Instead, speak of and treat that person who wronged you well until he goes forth as a better person."
Oh my, when a person indeed had done bad, I would be extremely thankful when they would stop looking back. I would be extremely thankful.
When we came to an agreement, I would be very thankful for him.
Oh my goodness, I just told that story now.
I told very little of the story of one of the people I was born in time to see, very little.
And now, I’m going to speak about current times, cousin.
These days, you see, I had this many children, thirteen.
And now, I cannot succumb to my mind’s dejection, because I will not be doing it to myself when I am dejected, but to those who’ve gone.
Also, I fear that they may no longer by worthy to be taken by God.
But I thank God because he lets me see those who’ve gone from me.
They didn’t show themselves, but God lets me see them.
You see, I woke up and night and relaxes, and without deviating, I took my tobacco and chewed.
And when I had chewed for long enough, I took them out, put them in, and put up the container. I lay facing the back of the bed, and shot up and stayed still.
Oh my, as I was staying still, there was a bright light around me.
Oh my, when the light came upon me, I opened my eyes and looked up to what looked like a circle of light above me.
There were three people inside.
I looked up to find that the light up there enveloped my children.
Here was their older sister Pangall’aq, Nanugaq, and the third was Uyanguaq with whom they shared a mother downriver.
They were wearing Heavenly clothes that they never wore before.
Oh my, there were happy up there and pitied me.
I faced the front of the bed toward them, looked up, and watched them.
As I saw them, I thanked God.
I thanked him because no other allowed me to see them, only he allowed me to see them.
You seem as I stopped and stayed still, up from where they were, because I didn’t look away from them, a man spoke from where they were. Wow, he definitely knows.
"Mary, you will also be like this as these are."
Oh my, I thought I was going to be pulled away right then, but my dear grandchildren from out there appeared here in front of me.
My goodness, when they appeared and watched only me, they, you know...
They don’t stay apart from me. They always gather around me.
When they had gathered in front of me, I told them, I told him
Only at that moment, when my dear grandchildren here were missing me, I asked them to leave me just for that moment.
I told them to be with me as much as they wanted later when it was time for me.
Oh my, I was disconcerted.
When I was finished, when that was finished, the light up there was starting to go out. And they had me watch them as they were in some place.
They had me see them as they were there before the light started to go out.
When I stopped watching them, it started to go out, and winked out.
Also, I didn’t not sleep but given new awareness like this, cousin, I was giving new awareness.
My goodness, young people, what a paradise. The paradise where everyone wants to live in.
It was very bright. There is no light like it.
It seemed that as I looked around from here, like this, I wasn’t sleeping
It seemed that the world was like this as the land meets the horizon.
The grass on the land was extremely green, seeming like the green [ulvaiyaaq].
The land there was too beautiful to behold.
And when I briefly watch TV once in a while and see something green, I wonder why I don’t remember that extremely green place.
It seemed that the land in the entire world all the way to the horizon was like that.
And there was no tundra like the tundra that we have here.
It was so smooth, and I didn’t see a lake or a creek in there.
My goodness, as I turned my neck like this going this way
When I turned this way, I saw three people standing wearing long white robes.
When I watched them over there, I realized that two of them over there were accompanied by Jesus.
I gave greater thanks for seeing Jesus.
Also, I started expecting to see him first and foremost during the fall at the time.
I kept expecting to see him.
And the things outside at night when sleep left me
When the things outside started clamoring in the night, I would get up after trying to lay still and look around outside, and look at the stars above.
When nothing else would happen, I would sit and lie down.
You young people, you see, that world, oh my goodness, it is such a wonderful world.
That paradise had nothing bad. There was nothing bad to be seen. That world looks very good.
It was very bright, extremely bright. And yet there was no sun in that world.
And yet it was bright, very bright, [without a source of light].
Oh my goodness.
As I was looking around liek that, I would watch those people too. As I did that, they would disappear and I wouldn’t know where they went.
When they disappeared, I would pull back my neck and look in front of me to see two of them still in front of me.
And since they were a little far, I wouldn’t recognize Jesus’ companions though I tried.
Oh my, I looked in front of me to see two people, the taller one on this side, and the one next to him was shorter.
I looked at those two and it seemed that the taller one on this side was Qayuq’s father.
I felt that I recognized him by what his mannerisms.
It was certainly Qayuq’s father that started to live here, the one who started to live here.
That’s all for that.
You see, when I stopped seeing them, after I watched those two, I lost sight of them with no idea where they went even though I was watching them.
Oh my, it seemed that after that, our pitiful world that we live in without thinking anything of it
When my mind came upon where I was together with them, it seemed it was a little red when I was alongside them
Because we live in this world without thinking anything of it.
Oh my goodness.
After that, I pulled my neck back and I was slow as if my body were closing up.
When it closed up, I realized that I was sitting on my bed where I sleep. I was sitting on my bed.
I was in distress through I was like this imagining being in that paradise.
And I thought this as I was standing there, when I thought I was standing there:
Oh my goodness, where are all those young people. Oh my goodness, I wish that they would live in that paradise in great joy forever with no worry about what may happen in the future.
"And they would have no worries about what may happen to them. And they would live there with no worries about what we call death if they live by the instructions given to them."
You see?
Now, I imagine these things because I do this repeatedly.
Something causes me to do that. I don’t do it by myself. Whatever it is sees me and causes me to do that.
It also gives me light like this seeing how I am. It probably takes pity on me.
You see, we also used to learn about the Bible over in Kwigillingok back then.
You see, when I went out and would be on my way to cross over, I would think first about my request.
When I crossed, because I would only leave your dear cousin in the house
Light came upon me in a circle around me like this.
It turned out that it started.
Starting from there, it comes upon me when it wants to.
However, my mind does not grieve over my many children because they’re not anywhere else, and they are not lost.
Since the first ones appear to me, I think that they are not lost
Also becaues the younger ones go before they come upon anything bad.
But the ones that grew a little who were going to go, I would understand because they were clear, I would understand.
And the little ones, you know, would raise their hands and be happy.
But my mind does not want to [disregard] how they were like that.
But now, I think about going after them, going after them.
I do not want to think of my fellow people in any way except through love.
I only want to think of every one of you, my family, my fellow people, with love.
I have the mind to see with my entire body what I’ve seen.
The people that I was born to see back then lived hard lives.
Because they obeyed the wisdom passed down to them, they lived long lives.
And we didn’t hear of any misfortune in the village I grew up in.
Only after a very long time, one of the people who had gotten old would pass away.
And they were nothing like how it is these days.
They wouldn’t know of any misfortune for a long time. And they would hear of misfortune from areas around them.
They would finally hear of something happening to someone after a long time.
But only after a long time.
Now, I started living downriver in Qinarmiut when it was populated. My husband had be live there.
And now, I cannot forget these descendants. I cannot forget these descendants.
I want them to be good.
Let me tell you a story, cousin.
Recently, when was it? Maybe last fall. Ceńavaralria tried to bring me upriver with what he called a huge plane.
He said this to me...