This... youpl¬ [?].
And [s]he also brought up a little about it.
But the topic of our meeting here
is traditional wisdom about walking staffs.
Everyone needs this [naturally] grown tool.
They also told me back when I was a boy
That I should not travel to the wilderness without a staff.
And the next, my paternal uncle, was supposed to be here
But Elataaq probably didn’t come in.
They’re good. They’re talking about good things.
And they almost talk about what we work on here
We who are called search and rescue.
Concerning us [our organization], that’s not what we are.
Many people who want to can join even if they don’t have the title.
They can help us.
So, first of all, I am thankful for this.
It was like it was our ears all winter.
Before they told us anything, we wouldn’t know anything.
Despite that, I also hear about them through CB radios
But before I hear about it from these two, I leave that alone.
I am like a helper for them2.
When they2 say something, we2 make calls to our surrounding [villages]
[S]he, my child, and I helping each other.
It’s good that [s]he’s taken care of us all winter.
It truly seems that [s]he goes ahead of our struggles
Telling the villages outside of here
When we lose someone from here.
But [s]he lets our surrounding villages know
Bringing what the willing will need
So that we who will go do not have to.
It truly seems [s]he’s like a helper.
In the past, [s]he would always go with us
But [s]he didn’t do that all winter.
But in my observation, [s]he worked harder than we did.
[S]he lets us who are called search and rescue know everything [she can].
I am very thankful for all of this person’s help…
…saying to pull him in, that he will be heavy.
If I have a companion and [s]he falls into the water
If [s]he cannot be taken and is in danger
They said that I can throw that at him and take him.
Also, when I take him, I should also bring him to a grassy area
Take off his clothes, wring them, [put] grass [inside] and put them on him,
insulating them with grass.
They say that grass is warm.
[S]he used to say that they’re warm.
That’s why last fall, upriver from the airport
They used to bring Arthur’s child out of the water who had fallen in.
But he would sink again, unable to come out of the water.
They would have been able to take him had they had some rope
from what the ones2 who told me the story said.
I remembered that traditional wisdom that was told to me.
We have a lot of lessons, lessons that we heard.
We young people who have grandfathers,
our grandfather’s traditional wisdom.
Also, if we come to the outskirts of a village in the fall, he would say to me:
If I come to the outskirts of a village and see an elevated place
I should go to it, climb, and look around me
I should look around the village to notify them [of my presence].
I should thoroughly observe this elevated area,
and these [other] elevated areas, and the lakes around them.
They said that they will save me
if the weather turns bad and I do not forget them.
But I’ve never done that.
It’s because I forgot them back then.
Sometimes, though, I knew them.
And then [s]he would say to me:
A self-confident person only comes upon misfortune
Someone they call cacetulria.
However, [s]he said that someone who isn’t self-confident
does not come upon too much misfortune.
Indeed, I have experienced that.
Because I’m scared by nature, I’ve become this old
before coming upon any misfortune.
Only a single time in the winter around this time
When Alba downriver and I went returned together after coming here
[S]he wanted me to camp close to Kwigillingok downriver.
I told him that I would go down, that the village was close.
Because I became confused just as we reached the village
My companion and I stopped and I said to him,
“We should stop without continuing further”
Because there was a blizzard blowing outside.
Apparently, we had stopped right inland from the village.
In the morning, I looked out when it was getting bright
to find a school in front of me.
I’m thankful for what the person before me talked about.
I can’t add a lot to them.
I’m also thankful because I had thought that
I wouldn’t be standing here before youpl.
I’m surprised and thankful that I’m now standing before you¬pl.
I have nothing else to say
Except that I’m thankful as he said.
I had moved from here last year, going downriver to Napakiak
But when I hear about anything, I can’t stay still.
I always have to call with the CB radios.
I also listen for him to request help.
And downriver, two of us encourage others
Encouraging our2 fellows downriver.
I’m thankful that he inspires us to follow.
But when he calls…
Fred is a good leader to us, along with this…
…about mushing dogs.
But these men and the older ones know more than we2 do.
But because they’ve asked us2 to
We’re2 going to talk about dogs, dog mushing,
as we2 were asked to do.
You see, the people I was born in time to see back then
didn’t have a lot of dogs.
Also, it seemed that someone who had a lot of dogs seemed to have five
from what I’ve seen.
They also took care of and loved those dogs like real people.
And some of them didn’t seem to be leashed at all in the porch.
They would huddle in the porch all together.
Didn’t they ever even fight?
And then when it was time like this,
the people back then would tell stories
They say that a long time ago, they had dogs that when they pushed sleds
They would leash them2 to the side here.
They got help from their dogs as they utilized them.
Back a long time ago, they tried to have them help.
And our elders would say this, also when I started mushing dogs:
Only its stomach makes a dog a mushing dog.
That is probably true.
Only its stomach makes a dog a mushing dog
Because it strengthens the flesh for all of us.
We Yupiit also know that
When our stomachs are empty, we’re not happy, and smile so little.
I also used hear about dogs a long time ago
That that one over there has a great leader and is obedient.
And when I hear about some dogs like that, they would say
That that person’s lead dog is very smart.
No matter what, even in a blizzard, it brings its owner where he wants.
Is that true?
Yes, that’s what it is.
I also thought that dogs had minds like me.
Because I’m doubtful, when the dog helped,
I was very thankful for that dog.
Look, since a long time ago…
…as a boy, I traveled to go hunt
because there were people in the hunting ground there
And it was the only house.
I was overconfident because I would have companions when I went
and I was scared by nature.
I arrived at the house to find that they had gone just ahead of me.
Back when we only survived by eating food from the land
We would also hunt for minks back then
when the weather outside became like this.
We weren’t sedentary because of them.
We also lost sleep to try to catch those in the spring like this.
When I got there, I thought,
“Let anything that wants to harm me do it.”
I forsook myself.
Let anything that wants to harm me do it.
Oh my, because I was so scared, I brought my lead dog inside
to accompany me.
It was my companion to keep me from being scared.
It was the only thing to boost my morale.
As I was laying down when I was full,
my dog was laying face down down in front of me.
At some point of this night
We used to have oil lamps back then that had wicks
Some with three, and some with four.
It would seem very bright.
That was an oil lamp.
It would seem very bright to me.
My goodness, my heart was filled with fear.
With the dog as my source of confidence, I said,
“Like us, but these dogs are probably smarter than we are.”
As I was there, I noticed that my dog
Had already started rocking the door back and forth.
My goodness, it truly seemed that it was interacting with something.
I thought, “As expected, something is going to happen to me now.”
My goodness, I stayed still.
As I was there, you see, something that look like a white cold draft
was slowly coming inside.
And when it had come in a certain distance, it contracted and went out.
I suddenly thought, “The next time, it’ll go further.”
And my dog started becoming walking about here.
It was obviously scared like me. It was scared.
The next time, I saw that it was getting worse
Even waving its nose, almost barking.
Eventually, you see, the draft was coming inside.
It came in quite a bit reaching the middle.
When it extracted, my dog dog went up behind me.
It put its snout into my spine behind me and stayed.
When that draft went toward the door, when it went out
My dog behind me pushed my back with its snout.
I thought, “This [dog] is probably asking me to go out.”
My goodness, after I had tried to stay
My sleeping mat, and after I put on my parka
I rolled up and bound my sleeping mat,
put on my hood, and went out.
[Qakugcaq] toward the door, there was a cloth hanging out by the entrance.
The exit going outside, however, was a real door.
When I was going to go out, when I put on my hood
I blew out those2 lamps2 in a circle.
I turned them off.
My goodness, I estimated [the size of] the door going out.
When I reached that cloth,
I was afraid that I would run into the [qakugcaq].
My goodness, before I did, I went out.
When I went out, this way, and I probably did it the wrong way
I think people told them to go around clockwise.
And I didn’t look around, only beneath me in case I tripped.
When I went around it, I never saw the area around me.
I spread out my dogs because I only had three.
When I spread them out, my lead dog came
and went where the lead dog would go.
When I put the harnesses2 on its head
It put these2 on by itself
without being told to and crouched.
And then after they2 were harnessed, I didn’t look around
Only watching what was in front of me.
My goodness, I mushed them when I finished [preparing] them.
I started going like a snowgo because [it was so fast].
My goodness, I was so scared that the [qakugcaq]
would take me from behind.
I was amazed at my dog.
It was of great help to me then.
It pushed me, obviously wanting me to go out.
You men know what dog mushing is like.
I’ve always heard
That its stomach is what makes a dog a mushing dog.
Also, these dogs that have litters raise and love them.
And then when it’s time we utilize them,
teaching them how to be sled dogs.
Eventually, they learn like we do.
They know how to do things, know where to go,
And they know where to stop to take us to our hunting grounds.
This is all I’m going to say.
It apparently hurt or killed someone.
Back when I was a boy, I never heard about those.
But we have started hearing about that now.
And because I have my earliest memories inland in the Akula region
These dogs didn’t wander anywhere either.
Their owners kept them leashed.
Also, they always told us not to go near dogs
because they will bite us.
We who have become grandfathers
We pass that wisdom on to our grandchildren.
These dogs are apparently all different.
Some are friendly, and some are easily angered like me.
We must also remember that,
And we must teach it to our grandchildren here.
My grandchildren go to see my dogs down there
But I admonish them against treating them excessively.
I also tell them not to bother them.
I watch over them because they have this traditional wisdom:
Even when this dog doesn’t seem like the type, when the others do
It attacks people along with the others.
I cannot add a lot to that.
But now, I have youpl tentatively written down to stop at 2:30.
But we will wait for three o’clock for them.
At three o’clock, they will speak about subsistence.
Youpl will take a break now.