First, please say your Yup’ik name and your age.
I am from Kwigillingok.
My Yup’ik name is Miisaq. They call me Miisaq
And in English, Milton M. Lewis.
When and where were you born?
I was born in Kwigillingok. I was born in Kwigillingok.
How old are you now?
Going by my [birth] certificate that came from Juneau, I am 74 years old.
First, please talk about how they celebrated Thanksgiving when you were growing up.
You see, when I was growing up as a boy, the people that I was born in time to see didn’t know about Thanksgiving.
I grew up without Thanksgiving.
Only when we started having, you know, priests in Kwigillingok
That’s when they first shared Thanksgiving.
How did they celebrate Thanksgiving in the beginning?
When they first started, when they about how it first started
One of the priests, I think it was Didmer
They said that those who were captives from across the ocean, somewhere far away
In their captivity, they crossed the ocean.
You know, those who are captives do not live very comfortably.
They kept getting into unfortunate circumstanes.
Then they crossed the ocean.
When they landed safely, they then planted crops.
They [harvesteed] those crops they started.
That is when they started this Thanksgiving celebration.
You know, how God took care of them even though they greatly sufferen in captivity.
Escpecially those crops that they grew, that God allowed to grow
Out of gratitude for their food, they started this Thanksgiving celebration.
During Thanksgiving, what kinds of traditional wisdom or admonishments would you hear?
Now you may start.
About traditional wisdom.
During Thanksgiving, when they would bring that up, when they spoke about it
To those who know about Thanksgiving, we must give thank to God as they did.
You know, we must be thankful for everything.
I realized afterwards when I pondered upon it
We must thank God for all of the ways he cares for us.
Until this year, what kind admonishments and traditional wisdom did you hear when you were growing up?
When I was growing up, I used to hear things aside from Thanksgiving
But especially for us, you know, Yupiit, what our ancestors were like.
Here is one piece of traditional wisdom I used to hear
When I listen to people telling stories like this here on KYUK
What our ancestors were like back then, you know, their traditional wisdom
It seems that I haven’t heard one thing I used to hear. They probably talk about when I wasn’t listening, when I sometimes don’t listen.
They’ve started doing it now.
I am thankful especially for that important thing that I used to hear
It’s important for us boys
I want to speak about that traditional wisdom I used to hear when we were boys, and I’m thankful that you asked.
A boy a long time ago, we had this piece of traditional wisdom:
They say that a boy especially scatters [out of the home] when it’s time.
They also said that a lot of people have now started doing this
You know, boys marry people who are not from the same village.
Our ancestors back then say they move to another village.
That that piece of wisdom I used to hear is important
If a boy moves to another village, they would especially warn us boys about this:
They said that if we move to another village aside from our own where we didn’t grow up, we should live carefully if we move to another village.
We should try not to give, you know, sow discord in this village.
You know, this was the thing they especially admonished against:
Try not to sow discord among your peers, your fellow people, those who go through life with you there where it is not your [home] village.
They said that if you do not heed that, if you give reason for commotion where it’s not your [home] village
That village will look for your parents. "Did his parents not teach him when he was a boy?“
They said that they would especially talk about that without my knowledge if I give that village that is now my own reason for commotion.
These days, I think that people don’t hear that traditional wisdom since then
The important traditional wisdom that if a person moves to another village aside from his own that he should be careful.
He should try not to sow discord in this village.
Or more importantly, that he should take something of from the people that he’s joined and lives with that is not his own without their knowledge.
They emphasized that.
These days, I repeatedly hear about those who move to other villages that are not their own and sow discord in the village they moved into.
Then when I think about these place here, Bethel
I don’t hear too much about those who need admonishing, except for these who come from some other villages.
They sow discord.
Because back then, though some people heeded that piece of traditional wisdom, however, there have always been some who did not heed it, you know?
Even though a person, a boy, was given instruction, when he has the idea as he goes, he sows discord in that village even though he didn’t grow up there.
This was the important warning that I used to hear our elders say because boys especially, you know, move [when getting married].
Then this other one that causes commotion is important:
A boy, when we boys get married, you know, they told us to love our spouses
Because women, you know, are weaker than men, we men.
Now, when some are not careful with their spouses, and when they follow their idea to physically abuse them
In my observation, it’s like they start a sickness in their spouses.
They say this is the reason we must be careful with our spouses.
Should they, you know, go before us, they tell them to be careful with their spouses so that they would not be filled with regret.
These days, I hear that even though they take spouses that are not from their villages
Though they take spouses from other villages
They do not heed that and beat their spouses whom they are supposed to love, whom they are supposed to love as themselves.
You know, let me move to this subject.
When we get marrid, we are supposed to love and agree with our spouses as ourselves.
They said that if we love our spouses, we will love ourselves, we men, their spouses.
They’ve started doing it, especially these days.
When they are not careful with their spouses, they start sicknesses in them.
And this sickness cannot, you know, it has no medicine when it spreads.
Before it spread, doctos now [treat] them.
But for us these days, as I ponder upon it
We must be careful with our spouses in our relationship
Because unintentionally, you know, if we treat them harshly and physically abuse them, we will start a sickness in them.
Especially for this reason now, since I’ve never heard it on KYUK when elders tell stories and give instructions on what they used to hear back then
Wanting to put my thought somewhere, I wanted to talk about it
Just in case that the ones who will stand after us might remember it if they hear it.
Lastly, please say something you are thankful for this year.
Now, I have something I’m thankful for as we come to this Thanksgiving season.
Recently last summer in the month of August, I would be sick in the past.
My back would suffer.
But at the beginning of August, I was more sick then ever before, sweat gushing out of my body, and my hair would be [soaked] with sweat.
It turned out that I had gotten stones in my internal organs inside.
I would certainly have been incapacitated had they not found those in the hospital.
That is what I’m most thankful to God for during this Thanksgiving season
Because even though I was like that, he has allowed me to live to see this day, this day.
Because it truly seems that these doctors are [the work of] God’s arms
And because our prayers are answered through that.
We pray for those around us, and they are helped with these doctors and nurses.
I had gone through that when they were going to perform surgery because I had been suffering so much when I was sick.
It would have been good for me had I not awoken [alive] because they were going to anesthetize me for surgery because I was suffering so much.
Then I immediately changed my mind.
Let me pray to God, and let me give these doctors and nurses to God.
If it was not my time, I asked him to help me through them.
Then I immediately said prayed about several things to God when they were preparing to perform surgery on me here.
"These people," I said this, praying a short prayer: "Jesus come and be with us.
"And bless these doctors and nurses."
That was all I prayed for.
Then God heard my request.
And my ailments that they removed from inside
The doctor told me wife in there when they were finished with me that they had removed 80 or 90 stones from my intenal organs.
Afterwards, I gave great praise to God in my mind.
This is what I’m most thankful for in this Thanksgiving season.
Thank you.
You’re welcome.
There were so many stones.
[?Don’t tell me I smiled.]