...as soon as we got here. So are you ready?
Okay, okay. Here’s my last question.
Is our Yup’ik language
Well, our Yup’ik language. We’ve been speaking Yup’ik now.
To you, should the young people not forget it, and why?
It should not be forgotten.
If that person by chance comes across an old woman or an elder, he might need someone to speak for him.
If a person knows our language, and the English language, it is of great help to speak them.
You see, my grandchildren have a Caucasian father.
They  mostly speak English, but they know Yup’ik.
Elizabeth Howard’s children downriver.
They also help with communication to someone who comes to misfortune somewhere.
But since they are so hindered by k/q and r/g distinctions, they don’t speak much Yup’ik.
Um, we should not lose our language.
One will do well if he equally understand English and our langauge.
When he goes among Caucasians, he can speak like them, then when he goes to his own people, he can speak like them.
It will be well to have them equally like that.
Some... I swear, last question. This is the very last one.
Some Caucasians say this: those people gathered there who are indigenous, there is no one else in the world like them.
They are the only people like them, and their culture is unique to them. And no other has a culture like them.
And then they say that when they lost their langauge, they disappeared. It was like they were scattered.
To you, if we lose our Yup’ik language, will we go extinct as if we were scattered? (Yes.) Will there be no more Yupiit?
Yes, we will do that, becoming unable to understand each other.
A Yup’ik here and our ancestors didn’t speak much of anything else, only mostly Yup’ik.
And then if a little Yup’ik forgets these Yup’ik things, I just told you about it.
Somtimes, when I admonish these little Yupiit speaking in our language, they answer me like this: "I don’t understand you."
And yet they are little Yupiit, and I speak admonishments to them in our language.
And some would say, "That’s not written in our textbooks," when we explain our culture to them.
They’ve started leaning to these high school textbooks.
That’s all. (Okay.) Thank you very much. (Yes, you’re welcome.) Yes, thank you very much. (There you go.)
(He’s over there.) [?] is coming. Come if you want to.
Come through here.
Ready? (Yes.) Okay.
Okay.
And so, the ancient Yup’ik wisdom, and the various ancient traditional wisdom from back then
When Yupiit first started understanding the Qaneryarat [Bible], and when they first read and understood the Bible
They said that some found that they were similar. Is that true?
Yes, what they said is true.
Also, when they speak out it through these TV’s, I hear it.
They say that this wisdom is from long ago.
The wisdom is also present through what is in the Bible.
From the ancient ancestors here, that wisdom is theirs.
And because it was theirs, when these Bible appeared, we recognized what the old ones would say back then.
They said that they would speak as if they knew about the Bible, even their admonishments.
The admonishments have truly existed since ancient times.
(Are they no different?) They’re no different.
When I was small, I found growing up that we would listen to traditional wisdom.
When we were small and slept in the community house, the old men would speak to us.
And the girls would be separate in the house. (He might take your bike.)
That’s how it was. (Get your bike. Get your bike.)
Also, they wouldn’t let us boys sleep too comfortably.
Because I’m an orphan and didn’t watch my parents
I would do with what little I had.
And I would go to bed in the community house after gathering grass for a pillow, but would take off my skin boots.
Now, when I tell the next generation about what I was like, they probably doubt me.
But the old men would say this to me: "As you go, if you make your own living, you will not be like that.
"If you do not forget where you came from."
This is indeed true.
And when I helped the old women like this, they would promise me. Apparently, it was for what was my future now.
And then, they would also tell me this:
"As you go, if you live to see another day, your descendants," it was apparently the next generations here
I would come to speak to them.
They said I would also speak to them if I didn’t forget their traditional wisdom.
Even though I have reached this age, the elders’ traditional wisdom continues to appear.
A person speaking like this does not speak of anything else in my observation, when I started being observant.
A person speaks of things that are no different from another, without any other traditional wisdom.
Also, in the spring liek this, this traditional wisdom still exists, and even women talk about it.
They told us never to be without a staff in spring even if we’re traveling by snow machines, sleds, or walking.
And if one walks on the ground in the summer, they also said not to be without a staff.
You know of those black things that are on the tundra. Those are dangerous.
If a person steps there and is pulled down without holding anything, he will disappear.
However, if he is holding something, that piece of wood he’s holding will save his life.
This is the wisdom passed down to me.
They also told them not to be too excessive with their descendants, including their children.
That’s what they would speak of.
But these days, I start remembering them.
And when I speak like this, I start remembering some of what they said.
You probably have something else to say, or ask.
I intended to ask Lucy.
Would the elder women also pass down traditional wisdom to girls?
Yes.
Well, do you know my little older brother, Evan [Keggup’aq]?
Yes, his late mother would always speak to us about that traditional wisdom and instructions when she was alive.
And then about how to bear children, and how to have a husband.
And then they also had wooden circular calanders that they would stick wood into.
When the days, when the day reached that, they moved it and stuck it in there.
She would also teach us.
Our mother wouldn’t teach us because she was a little abnormal.
However, our father would talk to us about these admonishments or traditional wisdom.
Or, he would speak to us about what we shouldn’t do.
I would mostly be around our father because I wasn’t reserved around him.
My relatives, however, could not speak to him, only us.
Charlie and I would mostly speak to him.
And sometimes, when he was alone, I would be with him even though our mother was visiting someone else.
And sometimes after going with her, I would go home to be with him,
To you, Lucy, should we not forget the old Yup’ik wisdom today?
Yes, we should not forget the what the old ones said even when reaching this age, becoming an old woman.
Also, I speak to and admonish some of the children.
Henry, I also ask you that question.
To you, why shouldn’t we forget the traditional Yup’ik way of life and wisdom?
One should not forget traditional Yup’ik wisdom, trying to live differently.
It turns out we must remember the elders’ traditional wisdom.
I never used to remember them back before I took a wife.
These days, it seems that when I do things like this, and when I do little things
And when I walk around dangerous areas, I start to remember that.
You should not forget ancient Yup’ik wisdom at this age.
Also, some say this: elders do not teach anymore these days.
However, they would tell me this: as I go, I will start teaching.
And because I remember that these days, I speak to and admonish these next generations.
I also speak about how the effects of traveling.
And now, some fo the ones I used to teach help me out, and they thank me for speaking about those.
And recently, one of the boys over there who’s become an adult asked me what alcohol was like.
And since I had experienced it and know it, I told him what I was like.
I told him this: "When I was an alocholic, I didn’t have much.
"However, since I have stayed away from alcohol these days
"It seems that these things I have are available.
"And when I think of something, I take some money and get it."
I told him that if he does that, try to quit drinking alcohol before it brings misfortune upon him.
I told him I’d be thankful if he quit that.
We shouldn’t keep from answering a question from the next generation.
But it’s better to keep teaching him about his future.
Also, when I speak over in the high school
I speak to them, including the girls, about what’s in their futures
Going up to when a girl takes a husband, and a boy takes a wife.
That is the wisdom passed down to me.
They said that if I do not take care of what little I have, I will have nothing.
You know about those who are frugal.
It better to save these little things.
He isn’t without anything, able to take and use them.
Anything else?
Yes, I will ask you this other question.
Lucy, to you, concerning the young people these days, including boys and girls
Are they becoming more mischievous and disobedient?
Some of them seem to do that.
Even if their fathers or mother speak to them, and when another speaks to them, and when I speak to them, they do not believe.
Those who are not taught from the beginning probably do that.
They are like that. They seem to doubt and not believe them.
We tell them that they will experience them someday.
And the traditional wisdom and saying, they say that we elders do not speak about them anymore.
These admonishments or what’s in the Bible, they say we don’t speak about them anymore.
Henry, concerning the reason for becoming disobedient, the young people’s disobedience
Because they are losing Yup’ik wisdom and their langauge?
You know, they don’t understand Yup’ik speech anymore. Does that seem to be the reason to you?
Yes, at least the recent generation starting after 1950.
We know that they’ve recently started speaking only in English.
And these days, some of them don’t have instructions, Yup’ik instructions, anymore, with no idea what they are.
But their parents, in my opinion, if the parents speak to the ones who only speak English about the Yup’ik way of life [in English], it would be better.
However, those who speak Yup’ik understand.
And since I’ve been speaking upriver in the high school starting two years ago, I know that.
Some of them say this:
With the Yup’ik way of life, what the West say is more true.
Western wisdom is more true.
However, they say that Yup’ik wisdom is not.
They’ve started turning to the West because they’ve started speaking only in English.
That is how they answer.
That’s all. (Okay.) That’s probably enough. (Yes.) Okay.
Thank you for having me speak. I always think that I won’t have a chance to speak like this.
That’s okay. We’ll come again sometime.
Okay. (Okay.)
These, it’s done.
That was one side of a whole tape or what, one tape?
That was the rest of the tape that we put in there.