Now, I am thankful to these people who came from somewhere far away to have me speak about what I wouldn’t have spoken about
When I’ve wanted to speak about.
And when I sometimes come across KYUK over there, I want to speak.
I want to say this, in case some one of the boys may come to a realization.
So, hear what I have to say, all of you who are listening, includin in the areas around them, and even here in Hooper Bay.
Now, I hope that some people, eve just one, will say that in his mind.
Especially with this thing that ends lives that you tend to abuse
It it were a traditional instruction, if alcohol were an instruction, no one would use it no matter who they were.
One tends to abuse it because it’s not an instruction, but admonished against.
However, they don’t practice these traditional instructions.
However, they break themselves over what are not part of traditional instructions.
But I am thankful for speaking though it wasn’t much.
Thank you very much, goodbye, but have a good day.
I used these back when the people of Hooper Bay were afflicted with big sores, including little children.
I used this
Because I heard there was no remedy when it’s all over.
The sores also grew large, and on my buttocks down there, they started pulsing along with my heartbeat.
Then I started thinking, remember what the people up north said.
The urine, I went to get my great-grandparent’s urine.
I went to get it with a container, and washed myself with that.
Whoo, very strong.
The sores on my body burned.
It was sore here, and I washed the slimy discharge off of my buttocks.
I was having slimy discharge.
It’s like fish slime, from the sores.
Then when I was done, I dumped that out, and replaced it with another that I boiled, rinsing these sores.
I rinsed with their broth.
When I finished rinsing, my body was then in great suffering, like all of it was pulsing
Too many sores in my body, mostly in my sit[ting area].
They grew large, pulsing from my heart, along with [my heartbeat].
And next day, when I finally got better.
I kept breathing it, it’s like I smell it for long time.
It’s like it coulsn’t get out of my mouth, my breath.
Then the next day, I woke up and they had become clean, had dried up.
Then when they dried up, following that time, they improved until eventually they got better.
And after that, I never went through that again.
These days, in the winter
These pieces of rain gear, rain pants
Those are things that should not be missing when one travels in the winter like this.
In order for this body to stay well
Through that, when we traveled on the land here in the wilderness, these pieces of rain gear, yes, should not be missing
So that this body will stay well [and safe].
Then, should one also be withouta rain gear when they come to misfortune in the wilderness
If the weather turns on them, they would instruct us
They said that if we get lost, we shouldn’t keep going but stop
Or if a blizzard starts on us.
They said that if we are standing as we are now
If we have nothing as we travel, and don’t have a tarpaulin
They used to instruct us like this:
They said that if we get into misfortune and a blizzard sets on us, we should dig into the snow like this.
They told us to go in, but to have something in hand.
They said that this walking staff will also save this body.
Or if he has not staff in the winter, he should hold a little tree as he travels.
Then if a blizzard sets and he’s lost, he should dive and have the snow build.
But those things, you know how we call those deep hollows [?kanarvikneret]?
If there’s a blizzard, the [the snowbank] up there is tall, and this is deeply hollowed
They said we shouldn’t let the snow cover us there.
Instead, they said to dig a snowbank that isn’t tall.
When we go in as soon as we fit in there, we should cover the entrace here with snow.
But they said not to have it encase us.
Do this to the know, and set this [staff] upright up there, piercing the ceiling.
If the snow covers us, we should do this with [the hole] up there.
They said that if it’s airtight under the snow, the person will suffocate.
These traditional instructions when I became aware when we were boys, one should not ignore the like this.
Sometimes their stomachs, when they didn’t have these stores, when they only had what they gathered from here
Sometimes, they would discouraged from their stomachs.
We would also be discouraged from having nothing, no clothes, and did not ignore [traditional wisdom].
Those people I was born in time to see back then only gathered [?through hard work] from here, not from stores.
Those were their food sources.
I also know that their bodies were strong.
Though these people looked old, they would be strong like this.
Also, those people I saw in my earliest memories were good.
They were compassionate, and [followed] traditional wisdom.
They were also good like that.
They also followed their traditional wisdom.
The people who were my instructs always told me not to act mindlessly like this.
I also joind those who were being mischievous.
They said that those who are being mischievous together, acting mischievous, do not let us gain anything.
But they said that one who is always sensible, who constantly does what they should do
Would go [through life] correctly, and well.
This is what they call our medicine, rosewort.
It’s Yup’ik name is caqlaq.
It’s our medicine for sore throats.
I’m going to cut it now.
Oh my.
I’m going to cut part of it and chew it.
This was their medicing long ago when they didn’t have [Western] medicine.
With these, when I had a bad sore throat recently, doctors did things to me, gave me all kinds of shots in the clinic.
They gave me many shots. I took this and ate some.
Then I ate and woke up the next day to find my sore throat was gone.
But this was their medicine long ago.
There’s some over there, and inland.
When they grow, there are a lot of them.
And altogether now, I got one whole full jar.
And though my daughter rejects and fears these
"You’re so foolish. Wouldn’t your grandma tell you to eat these when you have a sore throat? And she’d chew them and feed them to you when you had sores."
We used to do that long ago.
She said that if I look for vole caches with mare’s-tail tubers
If I find a vole cache with sticklebacks, needlefish
She said I should eat one, but just one.
Then as I was looking for vole caches, I found one with so many moving.
Then I thought, "Oh my, didn’t my Aana tell me that if I found a cache with sticklacks that I should eat one?"
I ate one.
When I would go to the wilderness, that’s how she would instruct me.
Then one day, my companion found a vole cache, since Ignatius Black and I were friends when we were small.
When he found a cache, he called to me, "Oh my, what are these?"
Oh my, I went to him and found those bugs.
Those things that go into ears, [?meriit].
Oh my, they were moving. How could we eat them?
After I [?], I heard my companion, "They’re not sticklebacks. I won’t eat those."
And we traveled on.
When we arrived home, my Aana [Mother], my great-grandma ended up asking me what I did with those.
"So did you eat?" "I ate." And he was thankful for me.
Oh my, what were they?
Maybe they were my Aana’s work. I think she bewitched me.
My baby son, my last baby, was bitten, bitten by his older brother.
He bit him here, bit him here twice.
I found him and found that he took this and stuffed the two bite punctures with these.
He stuffed and bound them.
He showed them the next morning, and oh my, they were healed. What was swollen and red was gone.
At that time, the health aides were also amazed at that, the [?].
He was supposed to get shots.
Since he didn’t want to travel there, as he was supposed to go in the evening the next day
He stuffed them with these without our knowledge.
They healed. And he never said there was any problem with this part.
He stuffed them with these.
And so, I lived by trying to obey my parents when I was small.
And my father’s traditional wisdom back then never leaves my mind.
He told me that if I do not live well and go to other villages that are not my own
He said that when they hear my name, they will know me by my misbehavior.
He told me so that I’d be ashamed [of being like that. And now, I always remember his instruction.
My mother also told me to always be compassionate to those around me.
You young people must obey your parents.
And never forget the traditional wisdom you were told when you were small.
It’s especially important for you to respect your parent in the home.
Do not speak harshly or do things harshly
Try not to [negatively] affect your parents’ mental state.
Your parents, those who are parents are heartbroken without your knowledge when you misbehave.
Then, my parents used to tell me this:
If I deal with something, even smoke or something that I get tired of smelling
Starting from when we were smell, they’d apply seal oil inside our noses
Because we might get headaches, and we might be negatively affected by that odor.
The same way with gas, we get tired of smelling gas even though they’re not smoke.
We must apply [seal oil] inside our noses, and also apply it to children’s noses.
Also, if you go to the wilderness and get sick
You have no medicine if you’re in the wilderness and get into misfortune.
If you have seal oil when you have a bad cold, if your throat inside is bad and has prickling pain
You must [?take] seal oil. My mother used to say that to us.
Also, they would have us drink [seal oil] if we had a persistent cough
When we had no aspirin, they would have us do that when we were small since we didn’t have clinics.
It’s very bad for you to abuse alcohol.
Instead, alcohol only leads to trouble.
Also, when a person abuses alcohol too much, they come upon things they’re not supposed to and bring misfortune upon themselves.
Also, this other one, smoking...
Close it.
The other one, smoking only goes to the mind, and along with this body.
I don’t experience what it’s like.
But I hear about what that smoking is like, that it destroys the mind.
Also, that one who smokes too much starts sleeping all the time.
That’s what I hear [happens] when they smoke.
I think that truly happens.
One who smokes too much sleeps all the time.
They also [become] forgetful, you know?
They forgot what to do. And when they put things down, they immediately forget them.
Once, we almost suffocated inland.
There were three of us, my younger sibling, that one who moved to Kwethluk, and me.
When we set up a tent in a deep hollow, a blizzard started at night.
When we [set up] when it was windy, the weather turned.
I opened my eyes and felt suffocated. I shot right up and hit this.
Apparently, the snow was weighing down on it.
We went out after much effeort, and our things were wet, yet the weather outside was very cold.
Apparently, [being] under the snow if very hot and suffocating.
As the snow was melting like this, our things got wet, our bedding.
That’s why they would admonish us like this: if the weather turns on us, not to seek shelter in deep hollows, not to have snow fall and cover us.
Instead, [seek shelter] in short banks, or if there’s snow, where it will be thin.
Also, pierce the ceiling up there, and move [the staff] back and forth.
Then if we know that we will not arrive back home
They said we should stick something in the ground toward our destination and go in.
They said that if dawn comes with good [weather]
We will know where we are, and will go toward our destination.
You see, because they don’t instruct on how to discern [one’s whereabouts]
And because we don’t instruct it, we don’t know it anymore.
We have no idea what to do these days.
I also remember that those who raised us back then had us know our relatives.
Though they lived in other villages, you know, they said they were our male cross-cousins, maternal uncles, maternal aunts, female cross-cousins.
They would be pointed out.
These days, we don’t know how we’re related anymore.
When we were boys like this back then, those who raised us would point out [how we were related].
And when these families arrived from other villages, they would point out [how we’re related] when they arrived.
They said that we and that one are related.
We’re cross-cousins, or neices/nephews and maternal uncles. Like that.
Through that, we would know them when we were demonstrated [how we were related].
These days, however, we don’t know how we’re related anymore.
And by now knowing how we’re related, how we’re not shown [how we’re related]
People are starting to fight these days.
And yet, though they’re related, they don’t know each other.
They’ve started opposing each other these days.
People back then were peaceful.
There was no one fighting.
We’ve gotten better, not suffering anymore.
The West provides us with akauterments through our clothes, transportation, different things, food, and these houses.
We’re not suffering anymore. They aren’t cold at night anymore. We’ve started being in hot [home] environments.
It’s gotten better.
But they’ve become bad, we’ve become bad these days
They’ve started fighting, started killing each other.
They’re exactly what the traditioanl wisdom pointed out [would happen].
Now, you boys and girls who are listening, remember what you just heard.
Those who raised us back then were not like this.
There not a lot of possessions in the house because their houses were not like this.
And when they slept at night in the cold, the little bukets filled with water would be frozen, would freeze.
And though they were on top of stoves, though those kettles had  been warm, some would be frozen.
Back in the 1930s, there used to be a lot of snow when I was a boy.
Sometimes, when there’s persistent southern winds and heavy snow, they say the marsh freezes, cirmiggluni.
Though there’s snow now, the tundra here is not frozen.
Though there’s a lot of snow, sometimes there’s not a great flood of water, though there’s a lot of water, but the melted ice ebbs out late.
They said it would probably freeze repeatedly and deplete its water.
But when it’s ice and can’t do that, there’s a great flood of water.
Also, when rivers have a lot of snow, the ice isn’t thick.
Since it’s not as thick as it usually is, I don’t think that it’ll flood though there’s a lot of water for that reason.
Back when it would get very cold, it’s not like now as you know.
Would you hear of anyone freezing to death?
We didn’t hear of anyone freezing because we had warm fur clothes.
Though it also gets cold now, it doesn’t get as cold as it used to.
Since we don’t have good [warm] clothes anymore,  when it gest a little cold, we like to say it’s cold.
These things when I was a boy like this, when we were boys
These things on land were our food sources, animals to catch, marine animals, and these birds.
These days, they are depleting.
These marine animals are getting scarce now.
These birds are also getting scarce.
Back when we were boys, at least when I was a boy, there used to be very many birds.
The wilderness was quiet. It wasn’t like this [now].
We wouldn’t hear anything rumbling at dawn, things rumbling outside.
When they went to spring camp at spring inland in the Akula region, it was wonderful.
Different kinds of birds called.
And these hunters in the evening, in the early evening, the muskrat hunters would spend the evening [doing that] in the spring camps inland.
They would start popping. The air would be filled with gunshots everywhere like this.
And these birds inland, since they would set up spring camps on lake shores
It was fun with the birds swimming and calling.
It would be wonderful in the spring.
When they traveled to their settlements, they would go upriver and [?] what they would use for their houses
Because those winter camp settlements would be on the riverbank.
Then when they arrived
Those things that they brought with them, if they arrived without having brought wood upriver
Those related men who work together would gather.
They would travel with a Yup’ik boat.
They would load it with [?] and even wood for houses and bring it upriver.
Then when they arrived like this, those relatevies who work together would help each other to build a house.
Those relatives who work together would work on that house they would stay in for the winter.
Then when the house is done and it’s time to go in, when they go in
There wouldn’t be a sing person, but familes with several members.
If there are four familes in one house, these will be here, and on the other side here, and here.
There are four of what they call families in English.
There would be a lot of people in that one house, those relatives.
Also, when they were there in that house, these food sources
That one family alone wouldn’t have them, but everyone in that house would eat from what food they had.
Some would have [their own] houses, where those who provide for their [nuclear] families would live in one house.
But there would always be a lot of people in them.
These several [nuclear] families would live in the house, those relatives.
That’s what they were like.
Also, their food stores that they got from the wilderness, blackfish, saffron cod, or various fish that they catch in winter, fall to eat frozen
Inside the house, and not only for the ones who caught them, but that food would be for everyone in that house, including their men over in the community house.
That’s what those we watched back then were like.
We small boy also had this learning experience:
We would hunt these little birds.
There were also a lot of them.
We would hunt those little birds by shooting arrows at them.
And, you know, they wouldn’t throw away what we caught.
These little girls would also pluck their feathers and cook them.
However, our mother would also cook what we caught, not throw them away.
They respected them like this, those poeple back then revered the food that we caught from the land.
These days, however, what are they doing?
And our children no longer hunt these little birds that we used to shoot arrows at.
They things that we used to hunt in the spring are no longer seen here on the land.
Then when the birds in the trees hatched in the summer
There would be very many going into smoke houses.
We would also shoot them with arrows.
We would skin the little things, open them up from their chests and remove their flesh
And prop the here on their wings
Then thread them through and hang them on trees.
They called that nakaculiluki, "making them into bladders." That’s what they did.
There were many little birds, and they wouldn’t deplete.
Our caretakers here, starting from the spring until the birds went downriver like this
They would eat them as a food source, including their eggs.
We wouldn’t hear anything about them depleting or population drops.
But they would do this: every year, something would be low in numbers
And sometimes there would be a lot, with fluctuating populations.
But they wouldn’t deplete, wouldn’t go exctinct.
There were always a lot of birds and marine animals.
Then they would eat birds in the spring like this until there were fish.
They only stopped when they went downriver, wouldn’t go [hunt them] again.
There would be no one left in the Akula region, only down on the Kuskokwim.
They also turned to fish. There were also a lot of fish.
Through their reverence, since they’re God’s gifts and they were revered, he always kept them in large numbers.
When I think about these these days, those people kept a close eye on and were careful with whatever food they had.
There used to be a lot of fish across there when we were boys like this.
And they would ram into the bank here.
And when we swam, sometimes the fish would ram into us somewhere here.
Then since we don’t revere them these days, things are depleting.
Then when they hunted beluga, they would admonish us against ever wading, when they hunted beluga.
When we were across there on this side, they would admonish us against ever wading.
Saying that those people were hunting beluga, they admonished us like that.
Then there are no more these days because we don’t hunt them anymore.
And there are no more of these little birds because we don’t hunt them with arrows anymore.
However, our counterparts who regulate them have put restrictions to try to raise their numbers
Having us stop hunting birds.
Those who raised us back then didn’t stop [hunting] these birds.
After it was their food source inland in the spring, then when they went downriver
After they fished, when they molted and couldn’t fly, along with their chicks
When their offspring grew to the same size, they hunted those too. They would return with full kayaks.
And they wouldn’t be affected, wouldn’t decrease.
These days, however, thigns are disappearing, including little birds.
Or is it because we don’t hunt them anymore?
As I sat there, I found my dog was already rocking back and forth in the door, oh my, as if sensing something.
I thought, "As expected, it’s going to get me now."
Oh my, I stayed still. As I stayed still, you see, something that looked like white steam slowly came in.
Then at some point, it retracted and went out.
A thought came to mind, "It’ll come closer next time."
And my dog started pacing here. It was clear it was afraid like me. It was afraid.
Then next time, it got worse, even waving its nose around, and almost barking.
Eventually, you see, this steam starting coming in.
When it finally retracted after reaching the middle, my dog went behind me.
Behind me, it put its snout on my spine and stayed.
When that steam went toward the door, when it went out
My dog behind me started pushing my back with its snout.
A thought came to mind, "This [dog] probably wants me to go out."
Oh my, after I tried to stay, I [rolled up] my bedding, and put on my parka
I rolled up and bound my bedding, put on my hat, and went out.
There was a piece of cloth hanging here on the outer entrance.
But the exit to outside was a real door.
When I was going to go out, when I put on my hand, I blew on those lamps in an arc. I turned them off.
Oh my, when I went out measuring the door, when I reached that cloth, I bumped into that [?qakugcaq] that I was afraid of.
Oh my, before I [hit] it, I went outside.
When I went out, I went this way, and I think I went the wrong way
Because I think they said to go around it following the way the sun goes.
And I didn’t look around, only for what I would trip over below me.
When I went around it, I didn’t look around me.
I spread out my dogs because I only had three dogs.
When I spread them out, my lead dog came to the lead dog’s spot.
When I put the harness on it, it put them on by itself without being told to, and crouched.
Then after I harnessed it, it didn’t look around except what it was watching [in front of it].
Oh my, when I finished them, I went hait.
It seemed like a snowgo when I went.
Oh my, I was so scared that [?] would take me from behind.
You see, I was amazed by my dog.
It helped me a lot at that time. It pushed me, clearly wanting me to go out.
There are many instructions, instructions for us young people, the traditional wisdom of our grandfathers for those of us who have grandfathers.
Also, when we reached the areas right outside of villages
He would tell me this in the fall: if I reach the area right outside of a village and see an elevated hill
I should go to it, climb it, and look around me, look around the village
Making mental maps of these villages.
I should pay very close attention to this elevated hill, these elevated hills, and the lakes around these elevated hills.
He said those will save me when the weather turns bad if I’m not forgetful
But I didn’t practice those.
I used to forget them all the time back then, but I would sometimes know them.
Then he would tell me, "An overconfident person only comes to misfortune"
As they say, an overconfident person.
They said, however, that a timid person doesn’t come to misfortune too much.
Indeed, I experienced that.
Because I’m easily scared, I’ve reached this age before coming to misfortune.
But only one time in the winter like this recently, when Alba downriver and I went home after coming here
At Qavartarvik downriver, he wanted to camp with me near Kwigillingok.
I told him that I’d go down, that the village was close.
When I got lost as we reached the lands, my companion and I stopped, and I said to him
"Let’s not continue, but stop, because there’s a blizzard out there."
It turned out that we stopped a short ways inland from the village.
When I looked out in the mornign as it was getting bright, I found that the school was in front of us.
I am thankful for what the one before me just said. I can’t add too much to them.
But there’s also an instruction that these didn’t speak about.
There’s another instruction: you can try to save yourself, and you boys can save yourselves.
No matter where you are in the wilderness, even if it’s during the cold season
You must keep yourself warm by your urine, your own urine.
I’ve also done that.
All day, since I hadn’t eaten for the whole day, and since my body was wet
As I went, I would urinate into a cup since I had a cup, and would drink it right away.
I kept warm and eventually reached my village, since I knew where my home was.
During the time when the days were long but cold, I made it alive.
Then another instruction if you reach someone who’s come to misfortune in the wilderness, without food and cold
This is also the first thing: you can help that cold person with his urine or your urine to warm him up.
And most importantly, don’t put him in heat.
If you put him in heat, you know, and you women know, and we men see it
When he’s by a heat source, the cold goes inward.
Though his outside looks warm, the cold inside goes in. It gets stronger inward.
There are those cases.
These things just now, I was hoping some would talk about them so that we could help someone
Should happen across someone that the cold is killing, but [still] alive.
That’s the first thing before giving him food, the first way we can help.
Our urine that they point out, what we have always done, and we can help ourselves if we are [freezing] like that.
Thank you.