I used to see Qakianaq back when I was a boy.
Luqinquq, the old Caucasian man they called Luqinquq had a store down there.
So now, since you became observant, starting when you became observant
Urucaraq here, from what you have observed after you were born in Urucaraq
Talk about how Bethel here has grown and changed to this day.
I just started off by telling you about what I observed.
Yes,[but] the [device] down there wasn’t going.
Just now, it’s just started again now.
You asked me about that community house.
I observed that community house when it was standing.
And back when they took fire baths
When they covered the smoke hole after they took fire baths like this, we would go in and see them.
Because when they were finished, the old men would talk inside the community house.
It was also hot.
And when they had just taken fire baths in the winter like this, it was nice and hot.
When these old men that we liked to go see started talking, they started talking.
We would go listen to them because they were pleasant.
But because I’m inarticulate, I forget what they said [?].
How would they cover the smoke hole?
You mean how they covered the smoke hole?
When they finished taking fire baths, when the fire down there was going out, one of them would cover the smoke hole.
They would cover the smoke hole of the community house.
And after they closed it, those men would be naked like this when we entered.
They hadn’t put on clothes.
It was probably after they had dried off.
These settlements, Aagurmiut and Urucararmiut, had one community house.
Sometimes in the winter, probably when Aagurmiut wanted to take fire baths
They would drag sleds with wood inside and go to the community house together.
Down there through Kepenkuk
They would go over there to the community house through Kepenkuk
Because Urucararmiut and what they called Aagurmiut upriver from them had one community house.
The [settlement] down there is actually Aagurmiut.
Those people would gather
Because it seemed that they lived like this without animosity toward each other or discrimination.
And because those people of old would help when one of them came to some misfortune.
They wouldn’t ask for money or a reward.
They helped each other from what I’ve seen.
Murilkellemni tua-i ava-i qanrutamken.
The community house inland, down around Joe Lomack’s building downriver
Its back wall was toward the water from there.
The one they used to call Urucaraq wasn’t a lake, it was dry but had a river.
And its river, the bridge down there
That first schoool uprver, upriver over from the Moravian church
Yes, the old church
There were steps made of boards reaching down to Aagurmiut.
That is, to this Luqinquq.
Luqinquq had a store there.
He had a Caucasian partner who had a house toward the water from him.
Those were partners in those days.
They called him Kassaussaaq [Trying to be Caucasian].
Those people of old were good at giving various names suited for them.
In my earliest memories back then
There were Caucasians in between here
In between Aagurmiut and Urucaraq, but not a lot.
They also talked about Kenirkauyar back then.
Kenirkauyar there was a [Western] dancing hall here.
But they didn’t do it at random [times] like this, only on Saturday.
It also went until 12 o’clock.
That was when they stopped.
And they wouldn’t let us frolick all the time.
At midnight, they would tell us to return to our villages.
They also admonished us against wandering about.
You see, these first Caucasians back then
They also apparently helped each other back then like Yupiit.
Even though we were Yup’ik, sometimes even Caucasians would admonish us.
Also, even though I was to be mischievous
My late mother talked to me some morning, even if it wasn’t all the time.
I would become unable to move when she talked to me even though she didn’t do it all the time.
These days, I don’t hear people speaking [to the young people].
It’s because we who have become elders have gone out.
It’s like our traditional wisdom is sleeping.
Our traditional wisdom, they would tell us to especially revere our land and the water.
Revere it.
This is what our teachings were like:
We should [treat it with as much respect] as our bowls.
These days, it’s not like that.
It’s become different.
What does it mean, as much as our own bowls?
This is how I understand it:
Our bowls, when we eat
It’s probably because a person back then had one bowl that [s]he watched
over.
[S]he loved and revered it.
I think that that was a metaphor
To revere our land and the water as much as our bowls.
That’s one piece of traditional wisdom from the people of old.
They also used to say
That a boy should not have relations with a girl before taking a woman [as a wife].
We these days are destroying ourselves.
We are apparently destoring our lives, and destroying our bodies.
And through this alcohol that I heavily abused.
That is evidently something that destroys our bodies.
Also, when a person misbehaves, it is visible in all the land.
Especially back then.
Because they were especially well-behaved back then
One who occasionally [misbehaved] was clearly noticable.
These days, though it happens every day, we have become [worse].
It’s also because we elders do not say anything anymore.
Back then, they used to talk to [the young people], even if they didn’t say a lot.
They didn’t do it excessively.
They would also sometimes gather us in the community house and speak to us.
And over there, the first Caucasian Moravians would sometimes gather us and speak to us.
These days, they probably do that sometimes.
But my inability to understand English is getting worse
Even though I understand a little now.
My deteriorating hearing is probably making it worse for me.
They’ve started speaking mostly in English now.
But youpl young people know that well.
Because we back then did not have a thorough education
I don’t understand people who speak completely in English
Even though I touch on some of them.
Ask me questions.
I am the most ignorant.
Okay, something that you can think of
One piece of traditional wisdom that you can think of
Or please tell us several that you can think of.
Back then, this was the most important one they said:
They would tell us to help these people that were struggling or that were unable.
Also, they said not to make fun of anyone even if they were struggling under any circumstances.
That is probably bad.
They told them to instead help these older people who were unable.
They said that a person’s mind is powerful.
Also, even if we entered another house
Under any circumstances, even a match, a nail, or a single thing
He used to tell me not to take anything from that house.
How much is it [now]?
They also said that in the wilderness, a person does not forget what [s]he put in the wilderness
Even if it’s the wilderness.
That is probably true.
They said that a person does not forget what [s]he put even in the wilderness.
You just asked me about something important.
My instructor always used to tell me
To never under any circumstances make fun of anyone struggling.
He said to help someone that was unable instead
Without talking about money for payment.
But why did they warn so much against boys having sexual relations with women?
What was the meaning behind it?
This is the meaning behind it:
They said that a woman is death.
When I strived sometimes, and would suffer back then
And being in the wilderness though I didn’t catch much because I liked being in the wilderness better
I would sometimes think when I couldn’t catch anything:
“Well now, was it for my hunting
“That I was told like this that a woman is death?”
Because I was mischievous, I did various [mischievous] things.
I used to think, “Well now, was this why they admonished me
“Because I would be unable to catch these things I was hunting in the wilderness?”
I told you the truth. I was mischievous.
In my observation, an obedient person lives well.
It’s clear who obeys what their parents say and lives well.
[S]he also doesn’t seem to be in need of anything.
It’s because [s]he listens to the traditional wisdom [s]he heard.
Someone like me who does not obey traditional is wisdom is like me
Always in need of things.
In my opinion, this Yup’ik wisdom
Is no different from what the Bible says.
It’s because the dear ancestors of old would talk about the Spirit of the Universe.
It corresponded with the origin of the Bible, our unseen Heavenly Father.
It corresponded with that.
Though the poor people didn’t know, they called it the Spirit of the Universe.
They also said that the Spirit of the Universe would tell us to repent.
My poor teacher would especially say
That I should never under any circumstances make fun of anyone struggling.
I should instead help whomever is unable.
He said that a person’s mind is powerful.
This is what he would say.
It is true.
It seems that in all the land, though we don’t have the same language, our traditional wisdom is one.
But many people also don’t adhere to them anymore.
It’s because we who have become elders do not speak anymore.
It’s like it’s dead because no one talks about it.
But youpl have started doing this
And I am thankful when I see people speaking [traditional wisdom] on what they call the TV.
I am not doing well right now.
Because we of Urucararmiut around here grew up watching Caucasians
Because we started observing them, we are not like those around us.
But because those around us watched well
And because they would always sleep in the community house
From what I heard back when I was a boy
The boys wouldn’t sleep in houses, only in the community house.
Also, from what I heard about the community house back then
Before dawn, because one of the elders would always speak
In the darkness when they woke up.
It seems that our ancestors back then lived well though they weren’t frivolous.
These days, we have become frivolous like this.
We weren’t like this
Nothing was taken lightly.
And food, Western food was not in excess.
It seems that it was always scarce.
These days, those planes bring us cargo every day.
Back then, they would only bring them cargo twice, in the spring and fall.
It would bring stuff all the way to the mouth of the Kuskokwim, and what they call Canineq down there.
Only two barges in the spring, fall.
That's why those Yupiit of old, no matter who they were, even Caucasians.
They carefully watched and didn’t take things lightly.
Our ancestors back then wouldn’t talk about Western things, only mines.
They would call the Western thing a mine, and they would talk about old mines.
They didn’t speak too much about Western things here in my observation.
This is what I think they did:
Those Caucasians were looking to make money back then.
There were not many jobs at that time.
Though they always fished, this fish was their currency, and wasn’t it expensive?
Once in my observation, two chums like this cost two quarters.
But things were not expensive at that time.
But Western things were scarce.
There weren’t many Western things, not like now.
They also had lights with what they called kerosene
Only when it got dark.
The poor people I saw back then did not take anything lightly.
But they lived seemingly in fear that this Yup’ik food would become scarce.
My instructor also used to tell me not to sleep during food gathering season.
He said that I had a lot of time to sleep all winter.
But I didn’t obey him because I was mischievous.
Though I fish, we are not like that these days, at least most of us.
Well, my time is nigh.
It’s almost time for me to go on air.
In the church, when I started trying to go to church after I quit drinking alcohol
After I quit drinking alcohol, I tried to go to church though I felt very constrained.
I tried not to miss any Sundays.
Are you still a bell-ringer today?
One day, one of them invited me to work in the church.
Though he asked me, I refused him at first
Because I felt constrained since I abused alcohol so heavily.
But when I first started trying to go to church back then, I would sometimes be invited
He would ask me, not all the time, for me to help in the church over there.
One day, I answered him
Thinking that I didn’t want to do it for long, I said to him
…I didn’t [?] him [?] the church.
They also used to pay me $50 per month.
And then eventually, they gave me a raise to $100 per month.
In my opinion
When I thought about my past because I remember it