I’m struggling, also because my eye is bad. The light is bright for me.
I wish I had black sunglasses.
(I’m sorry.)
Alright.
Talking with Paul G. and Lucy Nicholai for the record
just in case we don’t know who they are sometimes.
(In Yup’ik too.)
And in Yup’ik, Cialuq and… what’s your Yup’ik name again?
My real name is Qakvaralria, but when my late older brother passed away
I wonder why they changed it?
Now, they call me Neviar.
(I see, yes, okay.)
You probably know her English name.
(Yes, yes.)
Yes, there’s no way you wouldn’t know.
Yes. And then Cialuq first, the season around us
is spring now.
Were there admonishments in the time of people back then
that they should follow in the spring?
Various things. This was the only…
So they’re talking with this camera.
Okay.
Okay, proceed.
Yes, right around here then they’re talking with [us].
(Okay.)
They [said] this, and you know them too
Our caretakers back then when spring set, when spring set like this
They would tell us to always have an ice spud because it’s our eyes.
Indeed, you know it too.
There’s nothing else.
The old people, the old people only made completely sure
to admonish us against being reckless.
Who were you in Yup’ik again?
Nev’aq.
(Nev’aq, okay.)
Neviaq.
(Neviaq.)
Neviar.
(Okay, Neviar.)
Back when you were a girl, you probably went with
your family when they went to spring camp.
Do you want to say anything concerning that?
When we went to spring camp like this, youpl don’t know
Arnangiaraller, the mother of the late Iqalluk and famiuly
She would say this to us when we would travel about in the wilderness:
“Take a walking staff. You see, if you should even trip,
you can get out [of water] by putting the staff on its side.”
She used to tell us that.
It seems he knows about Yup’ik ways.
Sometimes, I’ve also heard them say to be quiet in the evning.
Yes.
(Why?)
They told us to be quiet.
They said, you see, that the nepengyaq would be attracted by our noise.
What?
(A ghost.)
Also, when the people from Kwethluk would go
to their spring camps or when they went hunting
Would there be no one left a long time ago?
They went up. They said not many stayed behind.
I didn’t know about those old things back then.
They said that there weren’t a lot of people in Kwethluk
Because [our] ancestors would hunt for ground squirrels.
That’s what their subsistence.
We can’t live those old ways that were lost.
You probably know them.
As we always babysit, I don’t go to [Qula] anymore.
Were there a lot of animals they hunted around Kwethluk back then?
My goodness, they were not scarce when our late caretakers
[set] fish traps and animal traps.
I didn’t set animal traps because I only had a few
[from] my late father.
Like Westerners, these Westerners are making these [people]
unlike Yupiit [back then]
[Using] animal traps and fish traps, material for fish traps [back then].
I am still doing that now with a fish trap
Only for black fish.
A long time ago, did people have a tradition of
giving water to animals they had caught?
Animals from the coast. Animals from the cause.
(They dipped them, they dipped them, yes.)
I used to see, and you probably don’t know valerians,
you know, the roots of flowes that smell nice placed on their noses
And they give them a little food or water.
They probably did that to all [animals].
I don’t know the very old ways. But…
Why did that do that to them?
They said they treated them as guests.
They pretended to receive them as guests.
You see, they also did that a long time ago to fish,
and putting [food or tobacco] in their mouths.
Animals from the coast.
Have you ever seen that? We used to do that a long time ago.
We were small, I wasn’t tall, I was small because
we were orphaned when we were small.
Yes, me too… he didn’t ask me.
And then Neviar, these girls in the year of their first menstruations
a long time ago
Did they do it here in Kwethluk too or what?
They don’t anymore.
(Did they separate them from society?)
Personally, you see, a long time ago, they would say
that they didn’t have me abstain
because they didn’t want me to be destitute.
And yet they had me abstain and kept me from traveling a lot.
And then when we were going to move from spring camps,
they had me throw ash on into the water.
Like that.
What is that?
(He might not understand.)
The water… do you know what araq is? You know, from stoves…
Where the fire had gone out. Where the fire had gone out.
(Where the fire had gone out.)
What was the reason?
That’s probably the custom of [our] ancestors back them.
(I don’t know, it’s their custom.)
She probably doesn’t know.
It was our ancestors’ custom when they abstained.
(Yes, as expected, our ancestors’ custom.)
They say they don’t abstain anymore now.
They don’t abstain anymore.
I haven’t seen anyone abstaining.
They also told us not to look up [at the sky]
during the year of our first menstruations.
Why?
They said we might lose our eyesight early.
That’s how it was.
These…
They also talked about those, and I hear about this sometimes now.
Paseqaq down there tells me
That people jigging now catch fish
And then he said that when one of the girls did something
When she fished, they said that the fish “broke.”
What’s that?
They tell girls within the year of their first menstruations
and those who miscarried not to.
(The people back then talked about those.)
Even the fish know [that] they [had gone].
Is that the only admonishment for fish?
They talk about it like this.
And spoiled food, they told them not to eat spoiled food raw.
She’s talking about spoiled food.
(Yes.)
They also told girls within the year of the first menstruations
not to pick berries.
They told them not to dig for mouse caches or pick berries.
They also abstained by eating only grebes and ptarmigans.
I personally did that.
I only ate grebes, ptarmigans, and dried fish from the previous year.
Fresh [dried fish]…
(We wouldn’t eat fresh [dried fish].)
But they don’t abstain from [fish] from the coast
because they said that ones from the ocean don’t have slime.
Surfaced seals at least.
They don’t abstain from spotted or year-old bearded seals.
What do they call these months, these months here in Kwethluk
on the Kuskokwim starting from Iralull’er [January]?
I don’t know them in Yup’ik except for the first ones.
Some call them by Yup’ik names, at least the fluent ones.
I mean, you probably know some of them in Yup’ik too.
They’re written, but they say some aren’t the same.
Yes, because our dialects are different.
You see, they have different dialects even when they’re close.
You know that.
And then, a long time ago before churches became prevalent here
When they buried people, they would put
their possessions on their graves.
Why did they do that?
They did that a long time ago, our ancestors back then.
Now, when a person passes away
You know, you also know that they burn their possessions.
They burned and destroyed them. They’ve started doing that now.
(And throwing them away.)
They don’t follow the old customs anymore.
They say that those, you know, various things,
pots, kettles, storytelling knives, necklaces
Those were grave markers.
That’s what they used to say.
Because there were no Caucasians a long time ago, those people
would put their few possessions where they were to be set.
I also used to examine them over there, even old guns.
They say they would put them when they passed away.
These days, they give them to people.
It’s better, unlike before.
You know them too.
Would you like to say anything about traditional instructions
that girls should adhere to these days.
They used to admonish girls against ever smiling at a boy.
They say a woman leads to death.
They said this: “A woman leads to death.”
They also told me never to stay out late in the evening.
They said, you know, that some creature would take me.
What about you? Do you want to say any traditional wisdom
that boys these days should hear?
You know, I only told you about what instructions I had?
When [the season] became like this, the staff with a point
that we call an ice spud
They told us to always have those.
They say they show the way. Indeed, it’s completely true.
You will know thin spots.
That’s what those elders back then used to say.
Before, the first thing I told you about was those people’s instructions.
And for a long time, because we were orphaned when we were young,
we did things ourselves.
Evidently, a person will only live by his traditional wisdom.
He will live [that way].
And if he’s sedentary, he won’t have anything.
You also observe these people who have nothing.
They call that being too lazy to do their work.
However, if one works hard despite not wanting do, even if he doesn’t
have anything, they say it’s like he’s rich.
He has things, even these pieces of wood.
Indeed, that’s completely true.
Because that dear youngest one watched me
He gathers wood like this even though he is not ordered to
because he watched me.
I don’t have much else to say.
These days, to you, are young people mischievous?
Yes.
(I don’t know what they’re doing.)
Personally, that one, you see…
(They’re different from what I’ve seen.)
They’ve become different now because of alcohol.
They’re nothing like a long time ago. You know them.
And a person wanders around for no reason,
and he’s immediately dead at the hands of alcohol.
They also speak without thinking.
(They’re not like before).
These elders know that every person does this.
Alcohol is killing them off very quickly.
And some go together and die at once.
Or they drown, they mostly drown.
And some who have become different recently kill [themselves].
Suicide is admonished against.
They kill [themselves] over a woman.
(Someday when the world ends,
those who’ve committed suicide will not be saved.)
Even if a person is suffering, may [s]he stay.
And even if [s]he wants what others have despite not being like them,
his peers wake up when they wake up.
Now, you see me here.
I am alive like this.
But I take care of these two here.
But now, I can’t do what I used to before.
Pity, I don’t go drift netting much anymore too.
Now, during fishing season, I go once and sometimes a second time.
But I use a tethered net that I used to use for fishing,
at least small fish.
Does this, from you…
Huh?
(Okay, keep going.)
For this, whichever of you2 can answer this.
Should we Yupiit not lose our past subsistence
that we also use today?
It truly should not be lost.
My goodness, what hunting implements a person has,
I didn’t tell you about them, you see.
When my late father removed his little fish nets, he would put them up.
That was his custom.
And now, I can’t do those.
I watched him.
Is our [Caucasian] counterparts’ instructions [or laws]
making it like our subsistence is being lost?
I’m not sure what going on with them.
Some people now, my goodness, they don’t remove their fish traps too.
Speak loudly to him.
You see, I don’t completely understand when people speak quietly.
Back then, did they respect elders?
Their tools?
No.
(Okay.)
Elders, did they respect elders?
Those people back then who are not like us,
those a long time ago, were intimidating.
You also know their customs.
We couldn’t treat them in any [bad] way.
They were intimidating. And when going into a house,
they couldn’t go further inside.
I couldn’t go inside even though I was mischievous.
I was hestitant to go inside out by the door.
I would only go inside when they told me to.
Now, they try to go out at the end of the house inside.
These days, should our young people keep from losing
our Yup’ik language and why?
(Yes.)
Why shouldn’t we lose it?
You see, these people who speak English, the ones they speak
[only] in English to, seem like they’re not completely wise.
My grandchildren here, Vera’s children, I tell their mother
“Look, speak to them in Yup’ik so that they’ll completely understand you.”
Shoud, they teach this Yup’ik language in schools?
Yes, please.
Is that all?
Two minutes left on this tape.
(Okay.)
Are we2 done?
We’re done.
(Okay, thank you.)
Okay, let’s see.
(Well now…)
Has Kwethluk always been here?
My goodness, Kwethluk was here in my earliest memories.
We were far downriver, and there were only several houses.
It wasn’t populous like this.
It was at the time of the store down over there.
The called us the Upriver People.
This here is the original Kwethluk.
My earliest memories are in Eek.
And in my earliest memories, we were going down to
what they called Aparuka’armiut, as in…