W-I-N-I-(F-R-E-D)
W-I-N-I?
What about your last name?
Beans.
Beans? There are Beans [families], and also Bean [families].
Beans, yes, yes. (Beans.)
So, with those things
How will those who struggle with alcohol in our home villages
You know many say this: "He does not heed advice. He will stop getting advice."
About that, please tell us how we can help those.
We know those who do wrong things like that, and not only with alcohol.
There are many, various ways to live wrong.
We should not think like this about those around us, you know, that [s]he is doing wrong.
"This one is difficult. He is unmanageable. Let him be."
We must not do that.
Now, my child, using myself as an example.
Now, my child lives without heeding any advice compared to their peers.
And people know it.
Though they are told, they’re very disobedient.
Then since they are mine, I keep trying to tell them.
You know, since I love them, I will not say this, cannot say this:
"This one is unmanageable. Let them get out of my house here."
I will not say that.
They’re mine. They’re no one else’s.
I raised them as my child.
They will also be mine for however long I am alive, and how long they are alive.
Though they don’t listen, always instruct them, try to instruct them.
Starting from when they’re small, they tell us to try to instruct them.
They tried to instruct me when I was small.
Turns out, they tried to instruct me though I was infuriated with them.
Sometimes in my mind, I’d be very infuriated with those who tried to instruct me.
But I didn’t talk back to them.
They already told me that one who talks back will be like this.
They also told me that one who is angered when being told will be like this.
You know, though I wasn’t big, and though I wasn’t active yet, I would be scared to be like that.
They already told me when I was small.
I also didn’t live obediently
But I would remember the traditional wisdom passed down to me.
If a person is like that, without forgetting their past
Though that one is disobedient, if one doesn’t give up, they are better than me.
Because [the child] is theirs.
We also hear about our food supplies, and even for us women, what we sew into our clothes
They said no one will do it for us. They said we’ll do it ourselves.
If our child is bad like that, and is disobedient, does wrong
It seems no one out there will do it for us.
Instead, we will try to [correct] them on our own.
They said that the Yupiit back then had traditional wisdom about a boy.
They said a boy can change.
They said he shall be repulsed by his lifestyle.
They also said it would be especially so for the traditional wisdom [whose outcome] I feared when I became observant.
However, they said that if a woman is like that, it’s harder for her to change her life, her ways
You know, if we don’t try to change her from back when she was [small].
They said she would change like this.
You know, back when we didn’t choose our own husbands, when they didn’t choose their own husbands.
They said that this would change her, and when she marries into another village.
They said that before long, she would take back her bad behavior.
[?Because of] that, they would try to advise and instruct us women from the beginning.
Now, also, this alcohol
Since this wrong way especially is getting stronger
To everyone, women, and men, girls, and boys
Since doing wrong is strengthened along with alcohol, it’s become more difficult.
For us like that, though they’re disobedient like that, and they don’t listen about alcohol, speak to them.
And just because they had alcohol, when they sober up, don’t be infuriated with them where they can see.
Instead, show our love.
Try to let them know our love, you know, our motherly love.
Also, do not be infuriated with them while they’re drunk.
Also, if they do that in our home there while we’re with them, do not run away from them.
They may try to act scary. They won’t do [anything] if they have no challengers.
Also, after they’ve been drinking
And, you know, though they do something bad in the house there, at least this is what I’m like:
Try not to run away from them, try not to leave them.
You know, I’m more scared of what might happen after I leave.
And if either is exasperated and we leave them to stay alone there, which will be exasperated?
Or else, they may take a weapon and try to hurt themself.
But I’ve always tried to stay there in my life, and in my spouse’s.
Also, the next day if my child had been drunk
Comfort them the next day, and don’t scold them right away.
Comfort them as I used to by trying to make them happy, and ask what they’re going to do.
Don’t first bring up only his drinking the previous day, or his angry if he had gotten angry.
And if I had been scared, don’t bring those up, but comfor them.
And they also say, and I see them, when they’re hungover, yuussugluki.
And one of them seems to be irritable while hungover.
Only when they’re not like that anymore, when they have fun, and start to speak well
And they don’t seem to speak well when hungover.
Only when they start speaking well, and don’t expect it anymore
Then we should tell him what had happened the day before or whenever.
And don’t scold them, but speak to them kindly.
Explain, thoroughly explain, how you were scared, and how you were scared to leave them.
Don’t scold them.
One of them will be very regretful then.
They will be regretful.
Say you love them, and show your love.
"Because I love you, I stayed here since I didn’t want you to do this."
I spoke about my thoughts.
"You also say you love me. If you truly love me," you know, tell them not to do that again.
Also, always pray for them.
Ask for them not to do that, that they shall not do that.
I do not have my children to wish them to do that in my mind.
But always pray for them, to ask on their behalf.
Probably since our children do not always want to listen to those
And they stop going to church and don’t want to travel.
In spite of that, I tell them to believe.
Also, when I instruct random people, and even when I instruct my children
I tell them to believe.
Anyone who works hard for something, especially works for alcohol, and even one who works for smoking
It seems they must have faith in something to help them to me.
Though a person goes with absolutely no faith, they will have no strength.
Believe one or the other.
The church, believe in the ways of the church.
And if you can’t believe in the ways of the church
Yupiit speak of things that are no different from the commandments of the church.
Believe in Yup’ik wisdom if you don’t want to believe in the church’s ways.
Try to believe in, practice, and obey Yup’ik wisdom.
A Yup’ik, you know, who has gotten older will not be perturbed if a person asks them
If one asks them about traditional instructions, and advice for the future, to me, they will be very, very thankful.
If one asks them that, they will be happy to me.
Now, though I’ve stopped worked, when people ask me, I am completely thankful from inside in my heart.
A little piece of Yup’ik wisdom
Especially not that I’ve become an old woman, it truly seems that that Yup’ik wisdom has come to be stronger.
It’s because they’re no different from the church’s Bible.
They are very strong and good pieces of wisdom to me, those pieces of Yup’ik wisdom, instructions.
That’s why I said that.
Also, as I’ve lived up to now, my children are now grown.
And they’re not with me, making their own living.
I tell them not to worry, but they also do not ignore me.
And now that we have phones, they always call me on the phone.
And it’s clear that they try to keep me from [not] having a phone.
When they call me on the phone like this, and when they tell me not to worry about them
I tell them this:
"What will I worry about you other than alcohol?"
To me, there is nothing to worry about other than alcohol
You know, if they’re not sick.
Then I also tell them again that I don’t want them to be alcoholic.
I also don’t want their mothers, my children with children, to be alcoholic.
I try to [?show] them many bad things, I am not good.
I tried to raise them [?by showing them].
I tried not to drink alcohol, and tried to take them to church.
Then when they tell me on the phone, I tell them
Or when they had been drinking the previous day, these men must especially be told.
When I tell them, I say
"Because I love you, I’ve never drank alcohol since I didn’t want you to feel helpless."
Also because they see their peers with alcoholic parents.
Also because they bring [children] out of compassion and want to eat with them, saying their mom and daddy are drunk.
I would be very thankful for their compassion.
That’s what I would tell them.
"Because I love you, I did not try to make you feel helpless as I raised you.
"Repay me out of great love
"Think of me, and try not to abuse that alcohol that I don’t want you to get into."
That’s what I tell them, to repay me like that.
To those who love a child
And we also scold our children.
You know, I did that when they were with me.
Yet we love them, yet we shouldn’t keep from scolding them.
After scolding them, comfort them again, showing my love.
And I tell them about what I scolded about, "Because I don’t want you to do that."
Especially these days, they’ve become more difficult like this.
It truly seems that these poor people are in between our Yup’ik and Western ways.
It seems my grandchildren here are in between them.
In spite of that, and in places here, our grandchildren are starting to speak only in English, at least my grandchidlren are.
I do instruct them in some places here as fluently as I can.
And it truly seems that it shows they don’t want to listen.
Or, they even show that they don’t think things are true.
But though they do that, we must try with them.
Also, we must especially not do that just because they don’t want to listen.
Though they don’t listen, they will someday have regrets about one that encouraged them.
Someday, they will think that they were treated with love.
When I was growing up, I used to think that those who instructed me like that didn’t love me.
It turned out, they instructed me out of love.
Considering that, I always try to instruct them.
And even when they’re random people here
You know, because they knew I was a counselor, they come to me back home.
And when they’re sad, or even when they’re not children, or even when they’re adults.
With those that ask me, I am very embarrassed inside, you know, because I don’t feel capable when someone comes to me for advice.
I am completely embarrassed as I do my best with them.
I am not ashamed of my life, and I am not ashamed of how improper my children were.
I also use that as an example.
It’s because, poor thing, if that person has no one to tell them
If they think they’re the only ones like that, they will not try to be good.
I also talk about my children
Always doing well, a mother always doing well and having fun
She will not have these children that she’s thankful for, or raise them [always doing well].
She will likely live sometimes being sad, sometimes struggling.
This is not to instill fear.
But since I’ve experienced it, I talked about how it’s like that.
How was that?
Okay.
Oh, it’s going to run out.