Yes, he first wants to thank you for coming.
Also, I will say his name.
This is Fred Ollie. He’s the principal of the school here.
Especially for the adults and the young people who speak Yup’ik
It was given to them.
And so, he said that he would want to do that with this...
... he wants to do it specifically for you.
Twelve years ago, I came to Alaska and went to the village of St. Mary’s to begin teaching.
And needless to say, I didn’t know much about Alaska.
I didn’t know much about Western Alaska.
And I met, one of the first people I met was a nun, was a Catholic nun by the name of Sister Scholastica.
And some of you in this room know Sister Scholastica.
She’s still doing the laundry at St. Mary’s.
And she gave me the best advice that anyone ever gave me.
She said, "You’re new to Alaska. You don’t know anything about these people.
"So what I want you to do is to say very little and to listen, because there’s a lot you need to learn."
And it was very, very good advice, because even now, twelve years later, I still find that I do too much talking and not enough listening
Because there’s still a lot that the elders of this area can teach us.
What do they call nuns again?
He said that he came to know a nun by the name of Sister Scholastica.
When I was at St. Mary’s, I met students from all over, all over the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta in the coast.
And in 1974, I had a class of students who I was particulary fond of.
And those are these students here.
And I promised them when I left St. Mary’s
That no matter where I went, I would alwyas keep a picture of that class in my office, and I always have.
I lived in Juneau for a while, and I kept a picture of these students on my wall in Juneau. And now here in Bethel, I keep them on my wall.
And one of the reasons I do that, is because I look at these various individuals and I still keep in contact with them.
And it makes me realize how much things have changed in this area
Because I can see the change in these students as they grow up.
And when he came here, he said that he kept it in his office.
He uses this because he watches things changing.
He can see that they are not like before...
Pass this around. Some people want to see it.
When I look at the pictures of those students, and I think about what they’re doing now
One thought comes to mind...
...being happy, living at home, or living somewhere else, but happy with themselves.
Students who feel good about who they are are the students who did exactly what I think this conference is all about.
They’re the students who took time...
...people in their villages, and I really mean that.
When I look back, and I see the students again who are happy and successful...
...to learn from people who have lived a long time and have had many rich and wonderful experiences.
And then...
I want to conclude by again welcoming you to this week.
I want to thank you for taking the time to be with us.
I’m very excited about it because this week, I get to be a student too.
I’m going to try to sit in on as many of the talks as possible so I can learn just along with everyone else.
So once again, I want to thank you for coming to Bethel, for sharing your experiences with us.
And if there’s anything I can do to make your stay happier and more enjoyable, please let me know.
Thank you very much.
Recently, when Nastashia called me to talk about this
When she asked me to talk to you about how to continue our way of life or our culture
I was daunted.
Though I was anxious, I was daunted.
I was thinking like this:
Since I am younger, I thought it would be better of our elders took care of it.
I will work on this as best as I can
But I will not go for long.
Some of you probably know that there was a meeting up in Kasigluk
Our elders from here on the Kuskokwim and the Yukon.
I wasn’t there. I was not deliberately absent.
I wanted to be there, but since we are not always free from work, I wasn’t there.
But I was told that when you held the meeting there
That you worked on what our way of life is like.
For the benefit of those of you who have some limited understanding of the English language, let me paraphrase the main points.
Very recently, when Nastashia Martin called me to speak on the issue of how you could continue with the Yup’ik language
I’m sorry, Yup’ik values
Although I was enthusiastic about it, I also had some reservations
Primarily because of the fact that I feel that it’s an issue that can best be addressed by our elders.
I am young, and because I am young, I feel that I have a lot to learn.
But I’m going to try my best under the circumstances.
Very recently, there was a conference at Kasigluk where the elders of the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta were the prime people who attended the conference.
Although I did not have the privilege of attending this conference
I understand that the main focus of the conference dealt with the issue of preserving our way of life.
I would like to have been there, however, circumstances sometimes relating with jobs prevents that.
And so, I just mentioned what I would talk about
I had thought that our adults would be better suited to cover it.
Our elders here instruct us
And they show us what’s in store for us.
It’s because they know what’s in store for us since they’ve lived.
Look, let us examine it.
Before we started having school in English, our elders saw it.
It’s clear that we will start speaking only in English.
Some of you probably know Pavila who was from Qinaq.
My grandfather.
He would tell me this:
He said that when he traveled with a sled when he was young, he would come by two Caucasians by chance.
And the one day, he said to me
Yet sometimes now, there would be two Caucasians in one village.
Now, the date of that is around the late 1950’s.
He mentioned this: "Their tongues are increasing.
"And it would probably be better if you learned their languages."
That’s his wisdom, though he never spoke English.
The wisdom of our ancestors appeared like that through my grandfather.
At that time, I didn’t understand what he was saying, nor what he meant.
Yet now, as I’ve started working and observing, it turns out that what he said was absolutely true.
I somehow feel that the main speaker this morning on this subject, how you could continue with Yup’ik values, should be one of the elders
Because in my opinion, they are the real people who should be giving us this guidance on the issue.
It is them who have given us guidance so that what is left of our values can be preserved.
It is them who had the wisdom to push for a Western type of education
So that we could be able to at least see and hopefully understand what is happening today.
For example, my grandfather Pavila who is from Qinaq was telling me that in his youth, when he was traveling throughout the region with a sled
That sometimes, he saw more than one white man in the whole region.
He said, however, in the late 1950’s, he said there are more and more of them in the region.
And sometimes, there are even more than one white person in a village.
He said at the time that you should learn their tongue, you should learn their language
So that you could at least understand what is it that you want.
It was through him that the wisdom of our elders was brought forth.
He saw much in advance, what was going to happen today.
I’m very thankful that through his wisdom that they pushed us for education.
Going forward.
Let’s go over my work.
How Yup’ik culture will continue.
You know that I work with land at Calista Corporation
And I work with how to take care of the land.
It is not difficult to merely take care of the land
But it gets difficult when we try to combine our ways and Western ways to take care of it.
Our ancestors, we, and our descendants originate from the land.
Our ancestors utilized this land.
You see, when we go outside, or we breathe what our counterparts call air.
And if we don’t have that, we will suffocate.
Our people utilize this land for survival, for absolute survival.
We hunt animals from the land, then put our catch on the table and eat them.
And then sometimes when we hunt, we would use sometimes use the hide to make clothes, make skin boots, or those old skin boots.
I’m talking about those with this in mind: this land keeps us alive.
And then, the things from the ocean keep us alive.
When this land gives us anything through our creator, let us be thankful
And be humble.
And I think it would be good if we help those around us through what we get.
As most of you may know, one of my major responsibilities with Calista Corporation is to run and manage Land and Natural Resources Department.
Land management in and of itself is not difficult.
But if one were to look at land management strictly from the standpoint of Western land management
However, it gets difficult when one begins to look at land from the standpoint of Yup’ik values and trying to put Western values into it.
The very basis of our society is land, the Yup’ik society.
Our ancestors looked at land much the same way that we look at the air we breathe today.
We need air to breathe so that we may survive.
In the beginning, and even today, the Yup’ik people have always been land users.
We survived with the land and what the land provided us.
Land provided us with clothing.
We needed to dress ourselves so that we can protect, we can be protected from any kind of weather.
The sea also provided us with clothing and food.
My point here being: land is something our society has needed and will probably need for a long time to come to survive.
What it has provided us, we must receive thankfully, humbly, and we must share that wealth with others.
Continuing on.
But how will our way of life and our culture continue?
We are told, "Please focus when you’re in school."
And then when we are requested or told that, "Focus when you’re in school," what does it mean?
And then who will teach us?
Now, let us ask ourselves, "Who will teach us?"
Now look behind you, and look at those next to you, or look around here.
Those who will teach us are sitting here.
Since they have lived, if they, our elders here, talk to us about our way of life
If we obey them, we may one day live with little hardship.
Let’s do it.
When our elders speak to us about something
And we are thankful when they instruct us
Let us listen.
And if we don’t stop at listening, but obey some of what they say, we probably will not have much difficult times.
Just who is to be our teacher?