Ready.
Okay, please answer that how you want.
Please say it again.
Okay. Is the anceint Yup’ik wisdom, the ones that have been since ancient times, no different from wisdom of the church?
You know, the ones written in the Bible?
Yes. They are no different. We found that in the Bible, they were our traditional wisdom.
And when I was in the church, when I finally went to church, I would recognize the traditional wisdom passed down to me when they spoke.
I would recognize the traditional wisdom passed down to me.
How would the women be instructed before taking husbands?
Oh my, the men were scary to us.
The men were scary.
And we wouldn’t play with each other informally, and we wouldn’t see anyone holding hands.
Long ago, men were very scary.
I was scared of them.
And I would hear about how I would get pregnant from my mother.
And we would take husbands whom we never expected, those we did not expect at all.
What wouold they say about becoming a woman with first mensturations?
And for first menstruations, they would have us abstain.
When we became women, the men feared us a lot.
They say that a woman leads to death.
I would be scared. And they would tell us that we would make men crazed for women.
Now, they don’t get woman-crazed.
They said that they would have girls with their first menstruations abstain for ten days.
They called it aqumgaluteng.
Did you not go through that?
I went through it.
I abstained, and they had me put on certain clothes.
And they wouldn’t have me look around the area. I wouldn’t look around the area.
I may have looked around sometimes.
(Were there admonishments?) Were were admonished.
And when we stood up, they would have us replace what we were sitting on. They would have us raise our hands.
They would warn us about water.
During this time, I had my first menstruations.
(Why did they admonish against water?) They say can see you better at this time.
And raw meat.
And you couldn’t look around?
Yes, they told us not to look around the area. (Why?)
I don’t know. They probably told us our eyesight would go early.
And when you were going to cross paths with these boys?
Yes, they would do that.
What would they tell them to do?
You know, downwind from them. They tell them to pass in some direction.
Why?
I don’t know, something about them.
And then, back when people who weren’t from the same village saw others, would they recognize where they were from by what they wore?
They said they had decorations like that, including their parkas.
People from a certain area had unique decorations.
What kind of decorations did you have?
I don’t know.
Did these...
There are stories somewhere about these orphans.
We hear that as the Caucasians were coming, as they were coming somewhere, that they found a, um, sandbar...
A qau͡gyaq?
And orphan that people abandoned on an island...
That’s not how it... (Yes, on a sandbar.) On a small island, I guess so, but it was on a sandbar.
Would people discriminate against those orphans?
They had strong adminishments about orphans. They had admonishments about them.
They would admonish us that even if others picked on orphans, never to join them.
Why so?
Well, they had admonishments about orphans.
And they would admonish us that even if they, you know, made fun of people that looked funny, never to join them.
Who would take care of the orphans?
Back when they wouldn’t get checks, a woman would take care of the dear orphan, but I think their relatives would take them in.
I think they took them in when they lost their fathers.
And then, you probably had a small doll.
I was never without a small doll. Caikaq and I would always play with small dolls.
And so, did your small dolls
Did you have different toys for the winter or the summer?
Yes, there were storyknives in the winter.
We would always tell storyknife stories. Now, we don’t see anyone telling storyknife stories, and don’t see anyone playing with small dolls.
What are inuguat (small dolls), and irniaruat (dolls)?
When different things, birds, came, they would take out small dolls and dolls.
Why?
They didn’t take them out in the winter, but kept them stored.
And then when the birds came, probably the jaegers, they would take out the small dolls and the dolls.
Why so?
I don’t know. Because they revered nature.
I also hear about people jiggin down in Bethel.
They say they would catch fish, then the fish would disappear.
Some say, "They probably disappeared because a girl within the first year of her menstruations or one who miscarried is jigging." Is that true?
That’s probably true.
Were there others like that...
When I observed them, I found that they would say that as an admonishment.
And then, back before there were a lot of Caucasians, I don’t think young children had names.
I used to hear this: when they would ask him what his name was, he would answer, "I am this person’s child," or "I am this person’s adopted child."
Did you hear about that?
I used to hear that. They probably didn’t have English names, only Yup’ik ones.
So how would they get names?
They probably named them. We name them now.
No, you know how they bring them to the church, and baptize them with names?
How did they name them before there were churches, when Yupiit lived traditional lives?
They would give them Yup’ik names.
Downriver in Qinaq, we only had a mission church.
It was our only church when it was built.
When I grew up, I found that there was no church, but a mission house.
They would hold services there, and hold services in the community house.
And then they built the old one.
It was their only church.
And long ago, these people probably always shared their food with each other.
They shared their food with each other as if they were a single family.
These days, these young people are started to forget how to speak their Yup’ik langauge.
Also, they don’t hear about traditional Yup’ik wisdom anymore.
As they call it, Westernization will spread among Yupiit who don’t speak Yup’ik or who forget who they are.
Will we Yupiit be as if we were scattered someday if we don’t speak Yup’ik anymore, or if we don’t hear about those ancient Yup’ik things?
We probably will.
We shouldn’t lose this language.
Why so?
It’s an ancient language.
I’d kin dof like to get Nicholai to say something in...
Please ask Nicholai a question.
Ask him if he want’s to say any ancient traditional wisdom that young people should follow.
What was it again?
Okay, as him like this: does he want to say anything that young people should follow in these days?
He asked you to speak about ancient traditional wisdom concerning young people.
Back when I was a boy
Down in that house, there was an old man, not young, in that house.
He would gather the boys there like this in the evening.
We would go in.
I still remember to this day one of the things that old man said, and it doesn’t get old.
Back then, it turned out that that man would tell us to be careful in our lives.
Also, to treat those around us with love.
It turned out that the saying to treat everyone with love was to be followed by every person.
And even if he sees him for the first time, he wants to be spoken to and socialized with.
That man would speak about this.
But what he said one day
That old man also told us people who eat food to try not to run out, that we should subsist as we live if we are well.
It turned out that being without food is bad for those who eat.
The poor people couldn’t afford to waste food because they didn’t have these Western nets.
However, he said that some would have nets made by knot-like tying.
That’s how that man, old man, would speak of them.
Those, they couldn’t afford to waste those tools.
That’s why they would sometimes, as they say, starve with a shortage of food.
They said the ice broke up. They told me to tell Wifey that the ice broke up. (It broke up.)
Well, we have no more tape. Thank you very much.
You spoke more.
Thank you.
You’re welcome.
And her mother...