Annabelle Olik, Kwethluk, Iiguaq in Yup’ik.
So first, are you originally from Kwethluk?
I’m not originally from Kwethluk. I’m from Nanvarnarrlak; I’m from the Akula region.
I see.
Now, please tell me old stories of when you wen to spring camp when you were a girl.
Were they fun?
The wilderness was fun.
When I was a little girls, when I was small but before I was orphaned, I used to live in the Akula region.
Then those [times], I don’t know what it was like when I was small
Because I was orphaned when I was small.
You see, I have early memories of them taking to Taklirrlak over there in the spring.
You know Taklirrlak?
To Taklirrlak over there, in the small river there.
And there were people in our hometown, this Beaver family.
Anguksuar and family’s parents were always with us.
Before I started hunting back then
These men would travel to hunt muskrats.
They would bring home various things, land otters, or beavers, or birds.
And when I observed my late parent
When I went walking with him, walking behind him, he would go periodically waiting for me.
And when we reached a creek, he would take out the fish trap.
He would take them out and they’d be filled with blackfish.
Then he’d put them in his reed bag for fish.
After setting it once again, he’d go home.
When he went home, I’d also go behind him, occassionally tripping.
Because I was weak, I would trip.
Then when he arrived, if he didn’t cook them, he’d thread them through to make [?nuutekat].
There were so many of the fish he cut, loche, blackfish.
Because they also hung their excess birds.
And they’d set drift nets down there in the water next to them.
Also, there are only loche over there, you see. It doesn’t have salmon.
The only fish are loch and blackfish over there, over from Tegyaraq.
Then I would also go with him when he traveled.
He would go the the banks of Taklirrlak to a shallow place.
He would do this with wood.
Many little snares would be like this.
They call them negarat.
I would watch him inland from him.
Those three of what he called negarat [snares], those wooden sticks.
Those kinds of little snares like this, snares.
Then he’d skin the bird.
He’d skin it, and leave the wings in place.
He stuck a piece of wood, then after filling it with moss, he’d put it between those.
Then when he would check on them somewhere, I’d always go with him.
Then we would come to them from inland
There were so many flapping their wings in three [snares] like this.
These parts were stuck [in the ground] like this.
Here were the snares.
There’d be so many long-tailed ducks, black scoters caught in them.
They were drawn to that bird decoy down there.
He would wade to them, take them out, and [snap] their necks.
After he removed them, he’d [snap] their necks.
He would stick them into his belt here.
Then when they’d amassed, he’d go inland, then take others off.
Then when there were no more, he’d reset the snares.
He’d reset them, then leave them.
His reed bag [filled] with birds
He would come home with it filled full with long-tailed ducks, black scoters, and probably greater scaups.
Women would also subsist back when I first became observant.
They weren’t sedentary.
When they arrived, they’d work on their chores, plucking feathers, or butchering them, or threading and hanging those little blackfish.
In the spring, though it was spring, people back then would work on so many fish.
They’d even hunt muskrats to earn money, since it was their only source of income in the spring.
When they became pregnant
When muskrats were in early pregnancy, they’d return to their villages.
They’d go home again, ending their spring camping.
Then when their spring camps were over and they arrived in their villages
After staying for a while, after putting away those fish they worked on, they’d go down to the Kuskokwim.
They’d stay downriver in Bethel.
At your mother’s grandma’s, since their late grandma was her sister, we’d stay there all summer.
How was that?
So, as you just spoke, you said that you were from Nanvarnarrlak.
Where there a lot of old settlements around there?
Were there a lot of people? No?
There weren’t a lot of settlements. There weren’t a lot of houses.
They were numbered.
To me, when I ponder and imagine them
There’d probably be a little over ten houses.
They weren’t, you know, heavily populated. No village was heavily populated.
Only Nunacuarmiut inland from us had a large population.
And Nunapitchuk had few people.
Paingarmiut also had few people.
They were just upriver from around Atmauthluak inland.
Their settlements were like this: Nunacuarmiut, Nanvarnarrlagmiut, Nunapicuarmiut
And Atmauthuak was in their river.
There were four villages like this, but they weren’t heavily populated.
They weren’t heavily populated.
Their houses were all traditional. Their houses were made of sod.
I would see log houses like this either.
My parents were the only ones with a log house in my earliest memories, and they had a sod entry porch.
That’s what they were like.
What about these? Rivers and creeks inland have names.
And now, some of us young people forgot their names.
Do you know their names? Can you say them?
You know, some speak of Kakeggluk [Mucus] and others.
You see, since I left the Akula region before I learned it, I don’t know the [names of land and water] of the Akula region.
I don’t know them. (I see.)
You know, though I lived there
When I was a little girl like this before I grew up, when both of my parents passed away at the same time
I went down downriver.
But those two downriver who passed away, the mother and daughter took care of me.
Where did you first see a Caucasian, a Russian?
Where did you first see a Caucasian, and were you scared then?
I wasn’t afraid. They said the first one we saw was Angliluaqalleq.
Angliluaqall[eq], who was (s)he?
He would roam anwhere inland.
Maybe Angliluaqalleq. I don’t know. Who was (s)he again?
I’ve forgotten their name.
(S)he spoke Yup’ik, but (s)he was Caucasian like this.
(S)he would travel to various villages like this.
After spending the night, (s)he’d leave.
And though it was dangerous, (s)he always traveled.
(S)he had a kayak like this with two cockpits.
Those were their only storage places.
I wasn’t afraid of them. I wasn’t afraid when I first saw a Caucasian.
That was the first one I saw inland in the spring, the one who always traveled in the spring.
But downriver after that, I also used to see
Those first, the firs missionaries:
Kil’pak, Kil’piit, Qakineq, and that one they called Hincia.
Those and Puciinaaq were the first ones I saw.
There weren’t a lot of Caucasians downriver in Bethel.
And since Yupiit are good at giving names, every Caucasians, all of what Caucasians there were had Yup’ik names.
What names did they have?
Some were called [?Rare Cooked].
What else again?
Even Wrinkled from Soaking, and other things.
Some were even Small Bugs.
People back then who’ve passed on had silly names.
They would call them random things, even some were Seal Oil Containers.
Then the traditional wisdom people passed down to these young people.
You know, you sometimes watch on TV elders giving instruction.
They make videos like this about various Yup’ik wisdom.
Should we young people not forget those?
Indeed, we remember the traditional wisdom, our traditional wisdom.
We don’t always forget them.
It’s like our young people these days can’t do it anymore.
You see, when we were girls back then, they would give us admonishments.
And they told us not to fight each other, and treat each other with love.
And though those around us look unpleasing
You know, they told us not to treat them badly, or reject them.
Instead, they told us to treat them with compassion and love.
This too: they said that if someone says something bad to us while we’re outside like this, we shouldn’t reply.
They told us not to reply.
The traditional wisdom passed down to us now
And if we become women, if we become women like this
You hear about those becoming women when these little girls become women like this.
They told us to be careful.
They also told us not to gravitate to boys.
Watch, they said, if a boy notices us, he will become abnormal.
We lived in fear of that.
We would only play by ourselves and with our fellow girls.
These boys
At least when we grow up
Though we play with each other when we’re small like this, nothing happens to them.
But when they’d [?grown], they’d admonish against that.
They would admonish us women against interacting with a boy.
Watch, they said, he would become abnoramal, until eventually he becomes abominable.
They said it’s because a woman is death.
This is what they’d tell us.
These days, these young people, children, are going to school, and many have started speaking English.
And when spoken to, some youth do not understand, don’t know what they’re being told.
Is it unbeneficial to lose the Yup’ik language?
Indeed, it’s unbeneficial for our grandchildren [to lose] that Yup’ik language.
My grandchildren, since I don’t speak English, since I don’t always speak English
I always speak to them in Yup’ik.
They do understand, but they can’t understand some of it.
All of them understand when spoken to [in Yup’ik].
But sometimes, when asked to do something, they don’t know what to take.
And when asked for something that is specifically said, they don’t know what they’re asked for.
But many of my granchildren here, since I always speak to them, they know much of the language.
But I don’t like it when these Yupiat, Yupiat like this
A married Yup’ik couple, and this is not half, and their spouse or wife or mother or grandmother is not half
Always speaking to them in English, speaking English from when they’re small, I don’t like that.
Then when they’re spoken to like this, they stay still unable to do anything.
They can’t understand anything.
Without speaking English to them like this, Yup’ik at home, if they speak to them in Yup’ik at their home
They will always speak Yup’ik.
Then when they go to school, they will learn in English.
Look at how they raised you
All of you know it, and you know your fellow boys here.
They have no problems speaking Yup’ik, speaking English. They have no problems.
These days, however, our children’s children have a problem.
They’re [situation] is bad to me.
Well, we’ve run out of time.
Okay, well then, thank you.
Yes, thank you very much.
Though I’m inarticulate. (No, it’s good.)
Henry Young also says, you see, that one Caucasian was named Milt Sac.
And Milt Sac, oh my, I forgot about Milt Sac.
Milt Sac, that dear Caucasian, was very pale.
He had no [color], no blush.
Like this, (s)he was as pale as that church over there.
Here, I’ll take that. (Okay.) Thank you.
You’re welcome.