I don’t know. We should explain the meaning behind that.
I don’t know the meaning behind that because I’ve never done that.
We from the upper Nushagak River also do that.
When we catch these dangerous animals upriver
When we first catch bears, black bears, those things
The blood of that dangerous animal we caught, we open its mouth
We reach in and take its saliva.
And then after putting it on our hands, we apply it to our faces.
They say that when that bear sees us
When they see us living as themselves through that [saliva]
They will will not come to us and attack us like this.
They respect [and acknowledge] their saliva that we applied on our faces.
That’s what it’s like.
They do that and should not be afraid of it.
Okay, we asked the original question about the ritual of getting the first seal.
It’s been a long time since they’ve stopped doing that since they’ve turned to these priests.
It’s been a long time since they’ve stopped.
Explaining the meaning behind it,
I am going to explain, talk about the reason that they have started doing that.
They say that a long time ago, people didn’t do that.
But that child whose father sent him away in those bladders
When they sent him, he stayed there for a year.
When he was there with the living creatures, the seals
When he returned only after [the year] of his stay had passed
That child had them start doing that.
He had them start giving water to those seals [they had caught].
During his time, they had started doing that [to seals].
When he was a child, he had gone where those living creatures go over there, staying with them
And he only returned after a year, when a year had passed.
He only came [back] when his trip had passed. That [child].
He had them start [giving water] to [seals].
When people catch those seals, they don’t discard their bladders but inflate them.
They inflated every bladder from those seals and kept them all summer.
And when fall came, they deflated them
Sending them with the current under the ice.
And so, they would do that to the bladder of the seals they had caught.
I think its spirit is there.
It seems they think it’s inside its bladder.
They say that [the seal] returns the next year.
That’s what those people used to say.
They say that the ones who had caught those bladders, they return to the ones who caught them.
They apparently thought that that's what they did.
They would ask them to come again when they sent off the bladders during the Bladder Festival.
They say that that…
Later. Let me translate this first.
Kurt Bell…
…the shaman [send] the child of that couple.
In the past, that couple’s children wouldn’t stay alive. They kept dying.
And then, one of their children.
That shaman wanted to do that to their2 child, include him with the bladders being sent.
That shaman had hit to do that.
Send him to the land of those living creatures.
He, however, saw the land of those living creatures as a house.
When he arrived at the land of these seals in the winter.
They said that some of them picked on him, the one who was sent with the bladders.
Those seals and spotted seals were different there.
Yet, they said that some of them treated him with love.
They said that when he started hunting after he returned
He would recognize those spotted or ringed seals.
He recognized them like us people.
They said that when he started hunting then, because he recognized them
He would strongly shoot them with arrows.
He shot them with arrows and harpooned them hard because he recognized them.
That's what that's like.
He expanded on that thing about boy going out to the seals.
There was a man and a wife whose children would not live.
They kept dying and dying [?]
And so, this one child [?]
[?] that child with a bladder out to the sea.
And so, that’s what he did.
And, and then that boy…
…he traveled there like that to them to do that to them.
Okay, he…
…they didn’t do it very excessively.
But you probably don’t know those that do that.
I understand it. (I see).
Whats he's saying is that those people that were,
Or, those seals that he recognized that were good to him,
He made sure that he made a good clean kill.
You know, really made sure that he did that.
It seems like this was a really important ceremony to go through.
Why did they stop doing that after Caucasians arrived?
When the priests appeared, they stopped doing that. (Yes).
Only when these priests appeared
Because these priests appeared
They forsook that and stopped doing it.
I see. Like this? Which of these2?
Were they ashamed of it or did they tell youpl to stop?
Though they weren’t told to stop, they stopped doing that.
Their practice with a seal
They stopped adhering to their practice.
I’ll do one, and I hear something different over there.
But Kurt Bell says that after the missionaries came, they stopped on their own.
May I say something?
Yes. (Okay).
In what they said, yes, to the bear’s faces, black bears or brown bears
It’s mouth, they take [saliva] from its mouth and apply it to its face.
When I was a boy…
Who are you? (Edward Weiss).
My grandfather used to tell me this:
After shooting and killing a black bear
And then like that, I should get saliva from inside [its mouth] and appy it to my face and my hands.
And then said this to me: when I grow up and start hunting
Should an injured black bear or those brown bears take me
It will see my face with its saliva on it.
He said that that’s why it won’t breathe on me.
Their breath, black bear saliva is extremely potent on people.
That’s why they evidently kill people by breathing on them like this and making their faces swell.
He said that it won’t do that to me.
And then after that when I had reached a certain age, 25
I missed a killing shot on a brown bear and it took me, took my gun like this.
However, it didn’t breathe on my face, but turned like this and breathed.
That’s what they instructed, even now.
Just now [?]
Okay, that’s [?] why from up the Kuskokwim. He said when his grandfather…
As [s]he imagines you older men
You apparently respect, qigcikluki, animals that we hunt.
[S]he said that now, in your opinions
Do yourpl descendants do that as youpl are?
Or are they not doing that?
If they’re not, [s]he’s asking if youpl think that the animals we hunt will decline.
Now, I…
…I am going to briefly [leave] her question.
I am not worried about the depletion of these seals, the animals down from the ocean that we hunt
But these chicks, eggs, of these birds.
I admonish my children, my offspring when their chicks hatch:
Do not hunt when they are chicks, when they are young.
But even when they hatch, their mothers, when their chicks are small and young like this
I admonish them against hunting them.
Those young and my children are probably like those chicks.
That’s why I admonish them
Even though the [chicks] when the birds’ eggs hatch are not my children.
And when they’re getting larger, if someone takes them away to tame them, is apparently going to take them away
I will admonish him against killing them all, including the mother [and father].
I tell them not to kill the mother [and father] saying that their chicks will have no one to take care of them anymore.
I tell them that these seagulls cannot be taken care of by anything else.
I tell them that they are young and pitiful should they lose their mothers, their caretakers.
I admonish them about that.
Well, he says that for him, he doesn’t think that there’s not much danger to the seals right now.
But he tells his children about the birds that, when birds have this, you know, when the eggs start hatching
And the mothers [?]
And then it’s no different.
We used to hunt, and then our mothers would rever our catch.
They were very thankful for it.
And now, we who have become fathers, and she who is a mother knows them because she has sons
When her son catches ptarmigans, she is very thankful for them and welcomes them.
She doesn’t think it’s too little.
She is thankful for and reveres all of his catches.
She doesn’t leave them scattered or doesn’t let them go to the [?] as we were always admonished. That’s all.
Now, these days…
…I don’t know that.
We mothers, you see, [who are] young[er than you] have no one to instruct us.
Would it be well if you had them instruct here on the KYUK news?
Or, give them time to instruct us.
We have many children who are trying to make a living. We don’t know.
I am also leaving my children in the dark.
It’s because I’ve never heard them since I lost my mother so long ago.
I like when these old people speak. They are true.
It’s still [practiced] now, but it’s disappearing.
The Western teachings that have appeared are eclipsing them.
It would be well if our Caucasian partners gave us time.
If an elder speaks on KYUK radio or on the news, teaching our children, [s]he will help us.
We would be thankful if they gave them time, and they would learn a lot.
Thank you, Larissa.
When we’re going to hunt, they instruct us concerning black bears…
They tell us to make a walking staff out of wood.
…a walking stick is useful in the fall for thin ice or dangerous things.
That was an instruction back then for the people up north.
When we’re going to hunt in the mountains, in the grass, or when we travel
They told us to keep holding that walking staff.
And as we travel, a black bear will eventually attack us.
They say that these black bears are like people.
They take things with their forepaws like this.
They say that before it takes our gun, we should immediate give it a staff.
They said that that will save us.
We give it, it will take it, and we will shoot it.
That was a long time ago.
…we had shamans, we apparently had shamans
We call those superstitions.
Yes, we say they are superstitious, originating from shamans.
Wait, I don’t understand that. Piciruiq?
You know, that’s not real and originates from shamans.
We say that shamans are of the devil.
When we acquired faith in God
Many of those and traditional medicines are forsaken.
They’re forsaken.
And now in our village down among the coastal people
We haven’t forsaken the practice [surrounding] catching seals.
When this person, even if he’s not young, catches the first seal in the spring, having also caught one the previous year
When the first one who goes seal hunting catches the first [seal]
They always distrubute that seal, uqiqurluni as we call it.
Every part of the first seal that he catches is distributed to everyone including what meat it has.
The first [catch], even if he's not young.
Every single year, we still haven’t forsaken that to this day.
When they bring that seal on land and [butcher] it into pieces, they distribute all of it, including what meat it has.
That’s what they call uqiqurluteng.
That [?first] catch, we also [?]
That's what happens. We haven't forsaken it.
You see, [we do] that in our village.
When this person catches the first seal, the women of the village wait eagerly.
And not only its meat.
They include other things to its blubber.
[?]
And pieces of cloth.
They don’t give it by itself, but add Western things to it [?].
Okay, he’s also responding to your earlier question if those rituals are still…
For him, this, Phillip Moses from Toksook Bay said
They still do the first seal, not only the first young man seal, but the first beaded seal of the season.
What they still do is, they still, the women look forward to this.
They cut the bearded seal up into blubber and meat
And then they call the whole village to come for the share of the whole thing.
So, they don’t keep it for themselves.
What they do is they give it away to everybody else in the village.
And not just the pieces of the seal,
But they also today include, like, things they buy from the store:
Pieces of cloth, or crackers, or whatever, you know, whatever…
She asked the reason behind giving that bearded seal to the others.
This is their tradition:
When the first one catches a seal in the spring like this, he wants to eat those bearded seals.
Because they want to eat
Back then, since they did it for them, they don’t [eat] bearded seals in the winter like this.
The meaning behind what she asked is showing love for each other.
Its meaning is love for each other. Yes.
Yes, that. That’s what it is. It’s love.
Okay, you asked for the reason for this sharing, you know?
He said, Phillip Moses said…
…we were going to work on showing reverence from 10-12.
I’m going to talk a little since it’s nearing 12 o’clock.