...Neresgaaq would probably laugh about it like that.
Can you talk to me about what you heard about the first Western contact? They probably mean the barge.
Huh?
The large sea vessel, you know, the funny things you used to hear about what Yupiit were amazed by.
Should I tell you stories about that first?
Yes.
I won’t say too much about a long story. (That’s okay.)
And after I say what I need to say, I won’t speak for too long.
Okay.
I grew up hearing hearsay about a shaman who lived across in Apruka’armiut whom they called Ississaayuk.
They said that he would start speaking as he was drumming.
They said to see that unrelated different people would burst out through the warmth.
He learned to speak with those.
They said that one day, they asked him to do it because they wanted to see it.
He complied and spoke like a Westerner.
I’m probably telling this story forgetting about some parts.
They said that when summer set and the ice on the Kuskokwim broke, a huge ship went upriver through the Kuskokwim.
And they say it stopped across there toward the water from Cinik, toward the water from Qemiterak.
They say that when the curious unsuitable ones went to go see it paddling kayaks, the ones who recently lost family members or whose daughters were in their first years of menstruations
When they couldn’t reach it, they would go home, unable to get close to it.
They say that only a select few would reach it
That huge floating ship had a lot of Caucasians.
They said that on the side toward the end, their eyes tended to shut.
They said that when they were going to speak, speak amongst themselves
They would only speak English to their peers after going "aa-a."
They said that it had two masts.
They said that on the ropes between the masts up there, a little moose was repeatedly untying.
They also said that one Caucasian up there was always pointing to the east.
Doesn’t his arm ever get tired?
He was their compass.
I also used to hear about Illugngali, an old story.
The infamous Illugngali who was not short tempered.
They said that his name, it may have happened after. It may not have happened before.
They said that he... I will place my [?] Illugngali later, okay?
They said the Caucasians called him Kallugngali.
They said that the ones who arrived looked for the leader of the Kuskokwim, calling him Illugngali.
And yet they say they didn’t know him.
They said that the next year, another ship came. It was different, unlike that one.
They said that it started giving out good things that people wanted.
They said that when Ississaayuk’s daughter started giving things out that ship, probably the first one
She would admonish them, saying that they were illusions and would disappear when they left.
He told her to buy as much as she wanted only when the next one came.
They abandoneed this first ship.
He said that it was only a fable.
The next year when the next one came down, arrived and anchored there, the kayaks went down like that along with Illugngali.
They said that they were sending something to Illugngali.
And they say that they gave Illugngali a big beautiful metal necklace that looked like a side labret.
They say they delivered it to him. They say that they loved him.
The many Caucasians looked out smiling at him as he docked his kayak on that ship.
[?And they said that when he drank alcohol as he was going out, he was going] "eru-eru-eru."
"The devil is going to defecate," he said as he pulled down that Caucasian’s pants.
I wonder what would come from the devil’s bowels?
When he dropped a large cylindrical piece of feces, he went, "Ee."
And he defecated normally.
They said that one of the ones grinning looking out up there [?].
But they said that he was holding herring eggs in the hood of his skin parka.
Illugngali was angered because he was short tempered.
Eventually, one up there took him.
He took his woman’s figted necklace and threw it into the water.
He had the Caucasians up there watch him.
They said that Illugngali talked all day starting in the morning.
They said that eventually, something grew out of the corners of his mouth and was seeping something white.
And then the tide rose, and what was full flowed out.
It lowered as Illugngali was talking.
Death came firs to the one who [?] him.
They said that even though they went home, the cargo they left didn’t disappear.
They said that one who understood the very first ship that came at the time said:
They said that the devil is writing papers from here in Alaska.
The devil was staying in a hotel.
They say that its accompanying devil, the first ship, shows it
Eyes that close on its side.
I’m telling this story from what little I heard told to me, possibly forgetting some parts.
The electrician across there that was curious about the one who defecated
I just told it how I heard it, and I probably changed it.
What kind of stories do you want me to tell? What our ancestors were like or what?
What about the thigns the West brought back then?
What?
You know, the things the West brought?
What about them?
You know, the new things that they brought like flour or sugar or other things.
You mean [?food]?
Yes, or any other things.
The things...
And the machines, like boat motors or snowmachines.
Those machines were probably not the first.
Yes, but you know, the funny ways that people were amazed by them when they first appeared. You know, what you heard about their thoughts or what you did.
I didn’t come upon those.
But these people from Kwethluk over there were left alone without going to fish camps.
After that, a huge barge, not a ship, a barge, drifted ashore to Curirneq down there.
They said that it carried food, flour.
But they said that they did not carry tea.
They said that it only had cigarettes made from real tobacco leaves.
And they said that they had clothes made from caribou and good small caribou skin sleds.
But they said that even though its seld had a rope as thick as straight spruce saplings, it snapped.
They said that they spilled various things from [the sacks], spilled flour and took out their containers and dropped them.
They used their containers for sewing fabric.
They said that the barge’s leeward side had a huge mound of the flour they spilled.
And it surpassed the roof of that barge.
They said that when the tide came in high in Cuirneq down there, the flour would settle down all day before the current took it out as the tide went out.
The floating flour would also be pulled by pulled by the sunken flour on Cuirneq.
They said that before it returned, the current would flow again.
They spilled out the flour to the ground from the [sacks] that were filled with food.
They spilled them out because they didn’t know what they were, saying that they were going to use them for water containers and pots.
They only tell those stories about how they didn’t know Western things.
They said that they only looked for tobacco inside that boat
Because they said they first learned how to use tobacco.
They said that they first learned how to use Russian tobacco.
They said that that barge was carrying tobacco.
And they said that it didn’t carry tea, but carried what was apparently unground coffee.
They said that those who had learned by repeatedly going to Caucasians, right when they were about to be depleted
And the [containers] that they took out and disposed of, when butter was getting low
They said that Kanaqlak arrived on a boat, the father of Tarruy’ak and family.
When he recognized them and he put them into his boat, some suddenly went to him but were late and some didn’t have any
These Western foods like [shortening], things with berries, and syrup
The things they didn’t eat and spilled out our of fear.
That’s all for that story. There’s a lot to tell about it.
They said that those who didn’t go to fish camp [stopped fishing for flounders] and ate pancakes or frybread all summer
Those pancakes or frybread.
Oh my goodness.
They didn’t prepare for tomorrow. They said that they focused on the flour sacks to use as sewing fabric.
They did that when sewing fabric was scarce.
If they brought in flour every year, the wise ones would keep what was inside.
Yes.
They did that, wanting to bring in sewing fabric.
From what I’ve seen, these boat motors, machines, snowgos, and these boat motors came first.
So, you know, did you hear funny stories about the things they were amazed by?
Kakianeq, Mistussiikaq, who traded here in Anuuraaq, he first traded before he came here to Kwigillingok.
He would get things because he had a huge double boat made of old skin.
He would disappear out into the ocean with a sail to Quinhagak. Apparently, he would cross to Quinhagak.
They said his parent was a Caucasian named Mistussiikaq.
He would arrive having filled his boat with flour, sugar, tea, and tobacco.
Yet in the fall, he would distribute them to people in the Canineq region going up north to this side of Nelson Island.
They said he was racking credit.
In the winter, however, right when it froze, he collected their debt, using a sled to visit those who were indebted.
One summer, he brought an instrument, what turned out to be an instrument with pipes.
Their instruments looked like little [canisters], unlike the [?malik’itaat].
When he was going to play the instrument, everyone from Keggukarmiut, even the old men and women, would go upriver to listen to him.
And people would come from Nunapigmiut downriver to listen.
Eventually, he brought boat motors that would just be set on their boats.
My goodness. When he loaded his big boat and was going to travel back and forth on Keggukar with a boat motor
Every person from those villages would go to the coast to watch him.
I heard that my maternal uncle Angassaaqun was a reindeer herder upriver along with other people.
One day, you see, Angassaaqun arrived.
And when he arrived, he took those instruments and those boat motors, then took them away.
Apparently, he traded them for live female reindeer.
And he went across to Paru upriver from Keggukar, the Caucasian named Paru
He would arrive with skiffs with sails.
However, some of the ones who wanted to trade for them traded live female reindeer
The thigns the skiffs first brought.
Paru did.
Once in a while, he would come on a skiff bringing many things.
I didn’t see a lot of Caucasians on the Kuskowkim.
Each year, there were more Caucasians. And there were more ships coming in.
Some of the ships brought those good things.
Then one day, I heard that a Caucasian by the name of Neqliyaq arrived over in Apruka’ar with a multitude of ships.
When that person from Canineq fished in the summer, Isqaq down there would be covered with tents for the people of Chefornak who were drift netting.
And across there along Apruka’ar, there would be many tents going all the way to Kuiguyugmiut.
There were also people from Cingigpak upriver in Anllermiut.
They said they were his fishers.
He beautified the people.
They started wearing Western made clothes, cloth pants for the men, and cloth dresses for the women.
They also got dishpans for bowls.
There was also an increase in kettles.
They were seen everywhere...