And I knew about worry, 16, as a girl I would be the one to go to each house.
I would think that. Then one day, I agreed.
Oh my, I married him and found that I was reserved towards him out of respect.
I would lay next to him like this with all of my clothes.
You know, they take off their clothes and put on gowns or something to go to bed now.
I would go to bed by my spouse with all of my clothes.
You see, I would go to my family out there and my husband was inside
In there [?] you know the ones that split up there.
When I would go downriver to my family, I would not want to go back, you know, not want to return.
My mother would say to me, "Go back already."
I would go out when I was tired. My mind would be smashed as they say in English.
Poor me, I would go upriver to my husband’s house.
I would go in and it would be completely silent.  I would go in and he had already gone to bed. I was so disrespectful. I was so disrespectful.
And since I knew that my husband was laying there, I would lay next to him with all of my clothes.
Ooh my, when I married and they got me, I would go in
These days, a man takes a wife without giving anything to his wife.
I went in, I think they used to do it a long time ago.
There were two huge cardboard boxes.
And then that girl, my husband’s older brother’s child, would take something out, their mother’s mattress.
They were beautiful accessories for beds, all new blankets.
That was the start of my beginning.
They would give things like that.
That girl started giving me things from those boxes.
She took out and gave me an atkuk, a fur parka.
You know that fur parkas are expensive these days.
And they were overwhelming.
She gave me a parka, put it next to me, and I wasn’t thankful.
You know, I didn’t want a husband.
After that, she also took out piluguuk (2), fur mukluks.
She took them and put them next to me.
She did that with many things.
There you go.
And then, my husband didn’t do that with his family like that.
They took me in the fall. The next spring, I wanted to be with my family. I used to do that.
And when I wanted to go home, my husband wanted to move me to Up’nerkilleq, but I refused.
He left without me.
And then I became happy with my family.
He came in the spring, and they told me that my husband was going to come and move in with my family.
When he did that, I was, you know, thankful.
That’s right, my mother would tell me, "He will provide for us."
He was going to come and move to take care of us.
Because I knew that, you know, I started treated him well, also because I would keep my back to him before.
And I started looking at him sometimes. He was very intimidating.
They must have respected each other. I, at least, did that.
And then he moved in with us.
Oh my, I didn’t get pregnant right away.
Because I wouldn’t let him touch me as I went to bed and closed off my mind.
And some mornings, my mother would say this to me: "Do not suddenly raise your hand."
You know, men probably know that women raise their hands in certain ways.
Sometimes when he brought his arm like this, I would do this out of dislike for him.
My mother would say, "They don’t do that." I didn’t know.
Everything has ayuqucirtuutet, rules.
She said they don’t do that.
She said a man takes a wife for fun.
I would be hit with fear.
And then I was pregnant with Robert Nick, Yuukaq, who’s inland.
I got pregnant. When I was pregnant, I could finally face my husband for long periods of time.
Nick turned out to be very good.
And then when I was pregnant like that, I finally started observing him reading the Bible.
My husband was always working hard.
The one my parents chose turned out to be a hard worker.
He started reading the Bible. He would read the Bible every evening.
Then we had two childrenb, Robert and Margaret I think.
He became a pastor at a young age.
It’s very nice. I can say how nice it is.
He wouldn’t frolick. We used to frolick.
Now, there are places to play like the Teen Center, and others.
When I would play in them, I would never see the one who’d become my husband.
Since he was like that from the beginning, my parents wanted me to be with him.
He started reading the Bible.
And before long, they made him a pastor. He became a pastor in Nunapitchuk at a young age.
And he just died as he was still a pastor.
And we had nine children.
Wow, he was so dedicated to that.
And as he was a pastor, he built that little store inland.
Before he made it, he said that he first went to the pastors, the Moravian pastors, and went to the pastor in Kwethluk.
He was extremely knowledgable with absolutely no Western education.
He asked if he could work at the store alongside being a pastor.
And they gave him the okay.
That building inland, Nick O. Nick Trading Post, was built only after being reviewed by the knowledgable priests here.
And then we raised our children like that.
And we never did this even once with alcohol.
We used to travel over to the city several times after he had built the store.
Some are very smart, are destined to be smart, even if they have absolutely no Western education.
I am not praising him, but speaking of him as an example.
When we used to go to the city, it turned out that Caucasians use a little alcohol in their friendly social interactions.
And then when someone comes in, "You want a drink?"
We would go around over there in his colleagues’ businesses.
And when we came in after he made himself comfortable, "Nick you want a drink?" they would ask him. "No."
When he said "No," the smart ones would say, "Sorry."
"I’m sorry, Nick."
After that, they would say afterwards, "Nick, you’re lucky." They would say that to him.
I will not keep from speaking about what I said because they’re good.
When we were boys in the fall like this upriver in Kialiq
They said that the creek upriver at the mouth of Kialiq was named Qukaqlircaraq.
We used to live there.
But our caretakers would not live in the same area in the fall like this.
Or, they would also stay in one area like this without traveling.
Towards fall, when they came from the fish camps across there in the fall
They would gather wood.
And they didn’t have boats, but traveled by kayak.
Since the tide would come in high in the morning during fall, they would start traveling in the morning in the dark.
Sometimes, however, a kayak would appear through Cingik downriver towing wood behind.
During the fall like this, when they were going to go the headwaters of rivers to their winter camps, they would gather those.
Our ancestors, those who raised us, were not like how we are here.
They would travel by straining their own arms, rowing through the water.
And when it was time for them, they started going upriver.
They would bring the wood with them, then put their possessions on top as cargo.
Those without boats would move with wood.
And then when they reached the headwaters of the rivers where they would camp for the winter, they would bring the wood inland.
Then they would prepare. They would prepare the wood to make their fishing implements, their fish traps.
They would make the wood into big fish traps.
Big fish traps were like this. Their openings were wide and long.
And they were like this, what they called the inner funnel.
And then they would also make the middle of the fish traps by enlarging them like this.
And then they would set the third one over there.
They called those original fish traps qamut.
These big fish traps were not like, you know, blackfish traps.
And, you know, their gaps were this wide.
They made wide gaps, yes, they had a procedures to make those big fish traps.
After measuring these, they would put the split spruce, put it there.
And then after doing this, they would make certain gaps like this on the side for those big fish traps.
When they started working on them like this, their hands would get raw.
They would use twine for the things they worked on like this.
Instead, they would thinly split these pieces of wood
There were about this wide, but thin.
They also had procedures for making those. They measured the thickness.
When they started doing that, they become raw here from doing this.
When they started bleeding, they would wrap these three with skin
When these became raw.
These too, these would get raw from gripping.
Our ancestors back then were not like us.
They had wooden possessions.
That wood was used for their possessions and tools.
They used for their things, houses, things around their houses, and sleds.
They survived by using this wood.
Let me talk about the traditional wisdom I grew up with.
I grew up where we alone had a settlement inland in the wilderness or downriver at the mouth of Tagyaraq.
But when I was a girl, we would be in the fish camps in the summer, then in the wilderness inland in the fall with no one around us.
And downriver at Tagyaraq in the winter, there was no one around us.
But we would start seeing people when we went to fish camp.
And I stayed with my grandmother because my grandmother raised me, because my grandparents raised me.
However, I lived with two other women. We were a family.
And then my grandmother would tell us and admonish us in the morning when we got up not to fight each other. She told us not to fight each other.
We little family who were in that house did not fight as a small family.
She would tell us to instead do our chores and help each other without fighting.
And then when we went there to a populated place, she would also say this to me when I was going to go out in the morning:
If the people outside picked on me, and if they picked on me as we were playing, I should run awy. She told me not to retaliate.
Then she would also say this to me:
Even if a person wrongs me, do not retaliate, but I should treat all my peers with love, always with love. We should treat each other with love. She said we should treat all of our peers with love.
When I was a girl, when we were girls, she would speak to us about how we should behave for the day.
That why we feared her because it seemed that she was scolding us.
When we didn’t adhere to her wisdom, my grandmother would shout at us as if scolding us.
That’s why we were scared of disregarding her wisdom.
She would instruct us to treat each other with love like that, always treat each other with love and never fight our peers.
And no matter what anyone does to us, never to retaliate.
She said that we should be hard working. She also said not to visit all the time.
She said that if we visit people too much, we will get hurt someday.
She said that if we visit too often, we will get hurt someday.
And then she said that if we visit other people too much, our things will deplete.
She said that our things will deplete when we should have been working.
And then she talked about little things since we are all women. Back when I was growing up, people would take these grass and weave them.
They would make containers for the fish they caught in the summer.
And they would pair king salmon and cover them with tall cottongrass.
She said that if we do not prepare, it would be certain what we’ll do: we will ask for things from our neighbors.
If we don’t gather tall cottongrass to hang fish in pairs, we will ask for things.
She said that if we do not save things, we will be beggers. That’s what she would tell us.
We were poor. There was nothing pre-made when we grew up.
And then she would tell us... it was like how it is now when we were growing up. I haven’t become an extremely old woman yet.
But when I was growing up, since I grew up with those old people, they seemed to be very old-fashioned.
That’s what she would tell us. If we don’t save things, we will be beggers.
And she said that if we’re going to see, see how it’s not scarce these days, if we’re going to sew and we do not save things, we will beg from our neighbors.
Or she said that we might borrow even a needle, or we would beg if we didn’t save things. That’s how poor we were.
That’s why we respected the traditional wisdom passed down to us.
If we see a little fish, this little bit of fish is the first.
If we see a little fish, she said that we should accept it without thinking it’s too little. We should hang and dry it.
She said that it would become food if we hang and dry it.
In the summer like this, she said that we should cut even a single little fish and hang it to dry.
And then she said that when it dries, we can eat it dried and boiled.
However, she said that if we think it’s too little and ignore it, the worms will eat it, the worms will destroy it, flies lay eggs on it, and it will get worms so it’s no longer edible.
It will no longer be edible.
That’s why she said that we should store even a little bit of fish. She said it would be food even if it’s not much.
That’s what they used to tell us.
And then she said that should we get a hunter, since we’re all women, even if there’s a lot of food to process, a woman should not be overwhelmed by them.
She said that she shouldn’t be overwhelmed and do a sloppy job. She said she should thoroughly dry it.
She also said not to dump food scraps to places where people trod, but to where people do not trod.
She said that food scraps are eyesores when they’re a mess on the ground here.
She said we suffer without food, when the stomach has nothing. These are the wisdom passed down to us.
She said that it’s worse having an empty stomach than any sickness.
That’s why even a little fish, this is our traditional wisdom.
That’s why she said not to despise a little fish even if it’s bad, but to save it.
She said we won’t dislike anything if our stomachs are empty.
This is the traditional wisdom passed down to us when we were young.
And she said not to litter with that little fish, but to throw it where people have not trod.
And she told us to throw the slop from cutting fish to where people have not trod.
She said that since a little fish is the backbone of a person, it should not be disregarded.
She also told us to eat without disliking anything.
She said that if food is scarce, we will not dislike or reject anything, since a person truly will not reject anything if he is hungry.
Well, back when we were growing up, when a person was suffering in sickness and was on the verge of death
We people would stop going into that house from outside.
And then after that person was sick for a long time, since our ancestors’ bodies were strong back then
When he died, his caretakers would prepare him, taking him down from somewhere here.
They would clothe them, put on their parkas, some of them boots, some of them sealskin boots, put some seal gut rain parkas on some of the men, some of them fish skin gloves, and some of them fur gloves.
They would sit them down down there with two wooden supports. They would sit down like this with their faces showing so that they were airtight.
However, they would light a little oil lamp in front of them because those were the only light they had.
The people who wanted to from the houses outside would bring him food by putting a bowl down there in front of him.
They said they would do that to feed their dead.
And then when his casket inland was done, they would tie him with five ties and lay him down, attach ropes, and take him out through the smokehole up there.
And they wouldn’t do it through the door, but through the smokehole.
And when they took him out, they would place him by revolving him around the corners.
That’s what they did with them.
And then they said that should we marry and take care of a child
They also said not to push them to our husbands. They said that that man travels, he is a traveler.
That’s why we should not push that child unto that man.
They said that when we cannot get out of the situation, he will have to entertain the child since a married couple are supposed to help each other.
But they said that he’s a traveler. We should not let him take care of the child.
They said that he would be sad when he leaves.
It will be bad when he’s sad over his father traveling.
They said that he will eventually start worrying about the child he left behind and have bad trips if he keeps being sad over his father leaving.
They would admonish us against pushing our children to the husband when we have children.
And then when we raise our children, they also said that since we are the ones who stay in the house to take care of them unlike the traveling men
They said that we should always watch our children in the house.
And they said not to excessively react to them when they’re mischievous.
They said that they worsen when we get too exasperated with them.
They also said that in reprimanding, we don’t need to add to our voices. Do not hit our child. Do not hit him.
They said that if we hit him, he will become overconfident.
They also said that if we shout at them too much, he’ll be overconfident. They said we’ll make our child overconfident.
That’s included in women’s traditional wisdom.
They said that we will make our child overconfident if we shout at them too much.
He will behave badly, being disobedient though we admonish him.
And if he’s mischievous, if we react too excessively, his mischievous behavior will get worse.
That’s why they say it’s better to encourage a child.
And then they said that when we reprimand them, they said that all people can be irritating.
They said that they don’t always treat a child with love. They reprimand him when he becomes tiresome.
They said that we will reprimand them.
THey said that after reprimanding him, do not laugh but leave him be.
Leave him alone without saying anything if we reprimand him.
Only when he gets better, speak well to him after reprimanding him.
If he cries, do laugh at him like that after reprimanding him.
They said that he will become bad if we laugh at him.
They also say that children who are laughed at become bad.
THey would include that in the things we should do when we raise that child in the house
Because it’s not easy to raise a child.
It’s hard work. We worked hard back then when we raised our children.
And they were not like how it is now when we raised our children.
We didn’t keep throwing diapers away.
That’s why we had a lot of traditional wisdom.
And if we sleep too much, they would urinate on us.
That child will urinate on his mat and urinate on us, and it will smell like urine.
Now you try to be spick and span.
They said that if we sleep too much, our house will smell like our child’s urine
Because we don’t let them relieve themselves at night.
Waking from our sleep, we would have our children urinate in the urine buckets at night.
And when we got up, we would take his urine bucket, go out, and dump it.
And we would always wash their reusable diapers because they didn’t have a lot
Because they would run out of diapers, we who didn’t have a lot would wash them later.
That is our traditional wisdom.
And then love is also an important part of traditional wisdom.
No matter what our peers do to us, never retaliate.
Then if a visitor comes, be sociable with him even if you don’t know where he’s from.
I was very shy.
I would be very daunted when they said this to me: "Even if you see him for the first time, socialie with him. And even if you see a guest for the first time, welcome him with your mouth and talk to him if you don’t have anything else, or feed him if there’s enough for him."
They said that through socializing by talking or feeding him, a person becomes a close friend.
They become friends with those they socialized with.
They say that some people are daunted when going to villages, and it’s true.
Those things that we talked about are true, that it’s difficult to go to places where one has not gone before.
That is why we must give a warm welcome to someone we don’t know whom we’ve never seen anywhere before.
They said that he is daunted since he doesn’t know where he’s going.
He’s daunted by that village because he doesn’t know the place he’s going to.
That’s what it’s like. When we travel where we haven’t before, we’re daunted.
That’s why you young people should remember this.
Also, even if what family you have does anything to you, never retaliate with their wrong against you as your motive.
We were also told to respect our parents.
That’s why to you who still have parents, these are the wisdom passed down to me.
We must defer to our parents, respect them, and try to adhere to their traditional wisdom.
That’s what we were told.
That’s why we respected those who raised us.
This is the traditional passed down to me when I was growing up.
Our traditional wisdom, there is a lot of wisdom for a person.
There is traditional wisdom for everything.
If we spoke about them, we would speak a lot. There is traditional wisdom for everything.
Those are the important wisdom that was passed down to me, how to take care of fish
And loving our peers no matter what they do to us
And not retaliating no matter what anyone does to us.
I would pass down what will never cease to you, my grandchildren, if you would remember it, I would pass down traditional wisdom to you.
I just said that you must love your peers.
Treat even those who do wrong to you with love. And do not do the same to those who wrong you, but treat them with love.
This love is what you must pass down.
Then, love your peers, and depend on your god.
Now, I am passing it on to you, my grandchildren.
And then my grandchildren down there, your relatives down there
I tell every one of them, teaching them so that they would pass down the traditional wisdom.
Even if I go and you do not see my, I want you to remember it.
I tell them at the dawn of every day to treat their families, their siblings, with love, or even if they’re not siblings
Or to never retaliate no matter what their peers do to them.
Also, I tell them not to speak harshly.
You know, not to speak without thinking.
If you speak without thinking, you will regret it someday.
You must remember that which I passed down to you.
Even if I go from here, you must remember them. That is how I pass them down.
Women would separately prepare their men before it froze like this.
Clothes and skin boots for them.
And these fish skins like this, the king salmon skins
They called it preparing fish skins.
That’s what they did when they made them fish skin boots.
Also, they wouldn’t just remove the flesh
When they finished removing the flesh, they wouldn’t work on them right away
They would submerge the fish skins into urine like this.
They removed the fish smell.
When they were aging urine, as they called it
Their men would urinate into those containers, their original containers.
They called that aging urine.
Those would smell very strong.
They would submerge the fish skins into those.
And then after soaking them, they would scrape them.
After working on them with boards, hang them outside and dry them.
Then when they’re dry, them make those into skin boots for their men.
They said they made them fish skin boots for their travels.
Their men would also prepare.
When they no longer needed those big fish traps that are used to catch blackfish
When they were going to change from the blackfish
They would also make those fish traps.
And then when they started setting them
These days, we store blackfish in various things like boxes and burlap bags.
However, our caretakers that I observed back then didn’t have those.
Their women also used to prepare containers for them with that grass
When they weren’t green like this anymore, when they were getting pale.
They gathered a lot like this.
And in the summer like this...
I forgot to say something.
Those women would prepare that grass to use for stitching, what they would use for stitching.
Those who raised us back then always did things for the future that they were heading towards.
They always prepared what they would need even if the time they would need it was far ahead in the future.
It was because they didn’t have anything else. What they had was only from the land here.
They did that because they couldn’t afford not to.
They would prepare what they would need way ahead of time.
They would gather tall cottongrass in the summer for stitching.
When the women started gathering those tall cottongrass
And then they would spread them out like this to dry them, as they called it.
And then when they were dried, nalaluteng as they called it, they wouldn’t gather them, but weave them.
Then when they were finished, they rolled them up.
That’s what they did with that grass they used for stitching.
These days, when I remember those things that we did back then
Even I find it difficult to imagine doing that.
And then their men
They would also make these mink traps that are shaped like fish traps.
They would make them small, about this long, and then about this size. They would measure the creeks to make traps.
They also didn’t do th ose haphazardly, but had measurements.
And their inner funnels here were not like blackfish traps.
They would be like this, then it woud be like a den on the side.
When I would watch my older sister’s husband like this
He would do this with his hands to measure the entrance, what they call the igyaraq.
That’s what they were like, not made haphazardly.
And then when he made fish trap shaped land otter traps, he would make the entrance like before
And then he would do this with his hands and measure the width with his thumb.
Those were also not made haphazardly like that.
They would also tell them not to make too much noise in the wilderness when it’s dangerous like this.
They told them not to make too much noise like this.
They would only make noise over those who’ve gotten into accidents, such as if someone drowned.
They would also admonish us against shouting or making noise in the wilderness in the fall like this.
They said that only those in dire situations would make noise like that.
And then if they hear someone making noise, shouting, they would understand that he has gotten into an accident or has sunk into water.
These days, however, since they are no longer admonished, since we no longer admonish you, they do not act appropriately.
And they now make noise and shout like this between villages.
They used to admonish against that.
Also, when they were going to travel like this
They would always say the area they were going to.
And when they didn’t return like this, they would know that they had gotten into an accident.
These days, however, they do not say anything when they’re going to travel by boat.
And then when they don’t return, they don’t know what happened because they didn’t say anything.
It’s because they go to random places these days.
Or, they pretend to go somewhere and end up traveling to other villages.
That’s what’s making us so addled these days.
We don’t know what’s going with the latest generation.
Or, we think they’re someplace.
Even when they die in the wilderness these days, we have no idea about them.
The young people these days have completely left behind what we were like before we were young, these young descendants of ours.
They’re worse because they don’t lack anything.
Because we lacked everything when we were young.
We lacked clothes, all food, and everything.
However, these boys, our descandants, these days are like they don’t know anything at all.
They don’t know how our ancestors survived.
It’s because they’ve started taking anything they want and need.
In the past, we only traveled by rowing kayaks.
I never saw motors even once back then.
And we had mud houses.
And I never saw a Caucasian even once. The Caucasians completely missed us.
These days, however, since there are a lot of Caucasians now, these young boys have become strange.
This alcohol especially affects them. Alcohol makes them foolish.
He sometimes destroys his mind when he does that too much, when they do too much wrong in this day that God gave.
My mindset is destroyed when I don’t speak on that.
Also, when they heavily scold in the name of our lord.
For those, my mind sometimes wants to speak thinking like this:
"We were not made for ourselves. God made us. It’ll be okay if I don’t do that."
Now, all you boys who hear and are listening now, remember this:
"You were not born of yourself. God, instead, made you, and had you born to be his child.
"However, you stray by yourself. You also bring yourself to misfortune.
"No person will shelter you as you live aside from him. Only God will shelter you if you boys ask for it."
Let me tell all of you who are listening now. Hear me.
Back before we had these Western things, every single person was extremely good.
They wouldn’t hear about saddening news or, you know, people going missing.
Now, however, to you boys who are listening now, everything has become commonplace.
Every single thing has become commonplace, even misplacing something in a random place.
When it’s put, it’s already as good as gone.
If you remember that God made it, you would live by ignoring those.
Now, try to live righteously from this very moment.