I haven’t figured out what they are. (Yes, I have no idea about them.)
Okay.
I think we’ve started rolling.
William, please tell us where you were born, and how old you are now.
Okay.
I was born in 1915 long ago when the Kuskokwim here was peaceful
And people rowed like this.
And they rowed to fish, with no boat motors.
How old are you now from what you think, what you know?
I think I’m 75.
(Say your name in Yup’ik too.) Callerkuaq.
(Callerkuaq?) Yes.
I see.
Please tell us about your first work when you were young too.
I was one of the elders in church. I would preach in church.
And for the youth, I was the young people leader.
And after that, I was in the council, IRA Council, back around ’43.
And since then, I never stopped working with [tribal] council laws.
I also especially know about the traditional instructions of our way of life among Yupiit.
And these, I was not a student.
And the federal government, the Territory of Alaska, I also observed their laws.
I would also learn by watching these people who were knowledgeable about laws.
These days, this alcohol that is a problem among us Yupiit
What it was like in the past, it’s still closed here in Bethel or in villages.
Please talk about what it was like, and how it compares to today.
In 1930, I heard about [someone drowning in] water in Akacakarralria.
And I saw that alcohol got him.
Then afterwards, I heard about someone shooting themself under the influence of alcohol.
They were far apart. I think it was the year after.
And quite some time after that, I also heard about a person who’d gone missing in the spring when the ice broke.
And when they found him in the summer, we went downriver to see him.
Those are the first ones that alcohol got.
Then starting recently from here, it’s become common.
These boys are short-lived.
And when it was open, they dropped in great numbers.
And in our current days, it’s worse than ever.
Sometimes, I sleep in fear because these young people are distressing.
What instructions can you give us about that, and how we can help those who have that addiction?
With those with that problem and addiction, they say the first is love.
Also, though they do it a lot, do not find fault in them.
Instead, do not treat them any different according to the love of our ancient way of life, our ancestors’ practice.
We evidently cannot love by completely eradicating that.
Some think that no one will socialize with them.
We must also talk to them about wisdom concerning their lives.
Now, when a person with an addiction says this:
"I want to quit. I don’t want to drink anymore."
Sometimes we answer them like this: "I do admonish you. You don’t listen."
How would you instruct us to answer that person who has that desire?
That one who has that desire must believe in what I said.
Sometimes, I see them truly quit that.
But now, some of them can’t quit.
I work in the tribal court for alcohol. Sometimes, there are nine boys.
But we work on them with our court.
I like it.
But those little children that are this big
I can bring them in altogether without any threat and speak to them as our ancestors used to.
Yet these big ones who are 20 years old
To me, that one cannot be worked with like those children in that Yup’ik teaching space.
But we do not ignore the one that needs it, bring them downriver if we are wary.
Now, I can speak about what I know and have experienced.
You just said that you tell children or young people about the traditional wisdom that you used to hear.
Please bring forth that traditional wisdom you used to hear.
This is what it’s like: "My son, obey your father and mother. Obey them so that you will live."
That’s traditional wisdom for [children] who aren’t big.
Also tell them this: if they hear something when it’s time to go to bed, to go home right away.
They say that after midnight, in our way of life.
They say that when it’s after midnight, a person splits.
Something will happen to his mind inside.
He will go inside the home and act like he has no chores do to after midnight.
That is what our ancestors spoke about.
Whatever else that is important that you want to say
It may be a traditional instruction, it may be an admonishment, or our traditional ways, the ways of Yupiit long ago
Now, say something you want to say.
Back in our ancestors’ time, there was nothing but the community house.
They would instruct us there in that community house.
But when I went into a house, I would stand out there by the door.
There would be someone instructing here.
These two dear people would speak to me of dear things.
And from the [?barriers] out there, we couldn’t step anywhere or go anwere either.
Now, I don’t come across people giving instruction anymore.
In our current days, I don’t come across those anymore.
Why is it like that?
It’s an ancient practice since a long time ago.
Our Yup’ik instructions do not change after over a hundred years, and it does not create unrest.
But one can talk about peace. A person can admonish them for peace.
Also, small villages would have leaders, one elder who was an instructor.
That person was like a great authority.
Every village, I used to see them a long time ago, and downriver in Napaskiak, even this little village that they call Ayalpiit.
You also just said that young people don’t hear traditional wisdom anymore.
That these don’t [hear them] anymore. Why is this so?
It’s like that because this state is going to overshadow us.
Covering us like this.
We started what is called the Yup’ik Nation.
I call it the Ancient Way of Life.
I can also say that, "Obey your father and mother. And stop following your every inclination as you live."
Now, he’s getting strong, getting better to me, downriver in Akiachak.
He was almost lost.
Then that boy Willie, how close are you in age? You might be the same age as him.
Also, our traditional advice and instructions.
And those the same age as him, I have a council with his age-mates.
My mind doesn’t worry about them now.
But I still haven’t taught them about the stars and the winds, how to survive.
Much of how to survive has still not been brought up.
You made me curious about survival with the stars and winds. Please [talk about it].
I thoroughly know about these four winds.
They [concern] fish.
I know when fish are coming in the summer through these [winds] because I always went fishing.
And I knew whether they’d be abundant.
One wind [heralds] no fish.
They say that the west wind, though you may fish, they won’t bite
Those things...
You must also observe the stars above.
Up on the middle of the sky, there are seven spinning stars, a clock.
If the seven spin like this, when it faces the day over there, when it stops and faces it
The star will rise, being the only biggest and brightest. It pulls the Days [?constellation?].
And when it arrives, the Days appear.
That was when our ancestors started working.
They said it’s time. Also because they had no clocks, because they didn’t see clocks.
Also, when they [?twinkle] like this, it will be windy. They’re connected to the wind.
And though the wind blows from there, if a shooting star goes in the opposite direction, the wind will blow from there.
These are what they call scientists who are knowledgeable about fish.
Though we didn’t have those, we were knowledgeable about them. I know them because I always used to fish.
And I know the ones that stayed downriver with flowing currents. They’re discernible.
Those are things I learned, what I learned.
Also, when it would be windy in the spring, they said that it heralded fish.
How was that?
That’s what they observed.
It’s good to observe this world, our world.
I see.
If you want to say anything else, or if you have nothing else to say.
I’m extremely thankful now.
I want to join you to speak about this ancient way like this.
And that person, you know, who was he again? Twitchell.
I’ve wanted to speak, but since I didn’t go downriver, I haven’t.
Willie...
Willie, what’s your view on the unification issue?
The unification issue has been a topic of discussion on AVCP’s convention, I would guess for the last four to five years.
I think it has made a slow progress, but nevertheless, it takes time to work on issues of relevence that affect the whole region.
Just recently, prior to the convention we had in what we call a Unification Forum Meeting in Emmonak, where the regional nonprofits were invited
And at that time, we discussed with Nunam Kellutestii, Ceńaliulriit, YKHC, AVCP, and Yupiit Nation
About the unification process that AVCP has undertaken based upon the directions that they received from Kipnuk’s convention resolution.
At that time, we also understand that not many of the people in the villages really understood what the unification meant.
The unification that we’re talking about is the development of the regional tribal government.
So, at the recommendations at the Imangaq forum meeting was that the nonprofits eats a supporting resolution in concept.
And we did receive commitment from the organizations that were represented there.
I believe that one of the things that this conventions will talk about how to select people to sit on what it’s called a constitutional committee.
The constitutional committees task would be to review how the other indigenous people in the United States, for that matter the whole world, organize under their own types of government.
As stated, as I stated earlier, not everybody understands the tribal government issues.
So, one of the tasks of this committee would be to educate the people.
By that, I mean they will be traveling to regional senators to conduct series of public meetings to get people to understand and up to speed of what we would like to achieve under the unification plan.
I think one important thing about the unification plan is that the organization and their boards are not the individuals and the authority to develop this government.
Ultimately, the people in the villages, those that have the voting rights, would be the ones to vote on the issue, and then proceed with the development of a government.
You think you’re gonna see a lot of support after this unification forum?
I believe so
Based on some of the comments that I heard that there’s still a lot of questions that needs to be brought out and answered, and we had a little bit of taste of that yesterday when I gave the Yupiit Nation report.
I think, especially the elders, have already understood the concept.
Bit it’s, according to the comments the comments from the elders that I’ve heard is that these young people that are bilingual aren’t too sure whether to go with the old ways or the new ways.
I think in developing a regional government under the unification process, both the old ways and the new ways needs to be incorporated.
So that whatever comes about would best represent the people, and work for the people.
One other question.
Though you didn’t say? (Yes.) Is it ready?
I don’t think AVCP is boycotting, not to rejoin AFN, and it’s on the agenda.
What I think what I think AVCP wants is true representation of our desires if we are to go back to AFN.
And I think using the example of the 1991 process, AVCP had some specific issues that we wanted AFN to address.
But, on the eleventh hour, our concerns weren’t heard.
And for that reason, we did not go back to AFN, among others.
But that was the primary reason. I think if AVCP is to rejoin AFN, the AVCP leadership needs to sit down with AVCP leadership
And discuss how representation would have to occur, and AVCP needs to be involved in such a statewide organization.
Do you have any additional comments you want to [?].
I guess, as far as the convention here, the 2005th annual convention of AVCP
This, I view as a turning point where our people are beginning to understand that we need to work together as a united group of villages.
Whatever forum the unification comes out of, we need to support it indivdually and orginazaniolly in order for it to succeed for our desires.
(Thank you.) Thank you.
You should’ve spoken in Yup’ik.
The [?] that it covered.