Please speak.
What’s our conversation going to be like?
Does it seem like it’ll be good in that machine?
Even if it’s not too long, you can say what you have to say without lingering on anything.
It’s good, it’s fine.
Okay.
I only speak of my earliest memories and what I’ve realized.
Also, we elders have realized now
We realized that it’s like we don’t own our land here, our very own land, anymore.
We don’t do what we want on our land anymore.
And then, we can't do what we want in our waters either.
But I do have some ideas when I think about the people who will live in the future.
We who have become like this will not be standing for many years because we people are [like] flowers.
Our offspring grow too. Those first ones who grow pass away.
That’s true.
I always think about this:
Downriver in Napakiak, probably around 1971, a Caucasian who came for the first time said this:
If we don’t determine our hunting grounds, we won’t have any land.
And at the time, I admonished them against following those allotments. Turns out [I was right].
Shortly after, that representative arrived again and said this:
Caucasians are going to come and cover this land.
[S]he said that if we don’t do that, we will have no lands or hunting grounds.
Pity, we believed and established allotments.
And then we realized after that
That our children and grandchildren have nothing from here from us, the ones we’ve always loved.
Did we give them to our [Caucasian] counterparts? Did we give it to them?
And then I think like this:
When we elders, we elders or those who can vote, are gone, what’s going to happen to this?
Who’s going to uphold it to our way of life?
By my estimate, no one will uphold them.
And even though our children are Yupiit, they won’t uphold it when they go forward with it.
And then, a lot of people don’t like my advice.
I may not speak correctly about many people.
We heard, I personally heard recently some time ago:
If we become the Yup’ik Nation, we will proceed to our way of life.
I examined it and realized
That if we’re the Yup’ik Nation, we will not go anywhere with our way of life, but only if we are traditional.
If we are traditional with no Caucasian governers, but govern ourselves as we did in the past.
And this allotment has become a cause for unrest for Yupiit today who claim they own that land.
Wr all understand this: land ownership leads to unrest.
However, I want youpl to outline a huge area of land like this and speak of it to [non-Yup’ik people] out there.
I say in my mind that I want youpl to do that.
Last year, I wrote to them out of state.
And I am speaking of it because my grandchild sent it and wanted me to end it with that.
I’ve said this, I’ve said a lot, that since our earliest memories, our children and grandchildren are lost.
And I say that we are lost in out own lans as if we've become outsiders.
We’ve already become unable to do what we want on this land. It’s like we’re outsiders.
Now, if we disapprove of that, if we truly disapprove of that, let us look at the traditional [way of life].
Many will call me crazy now.
If we go forth as the Yup’ik Nation, we will be governed by Caucasians from out there.
Let’s gauge the situation. AVCP already governs us.
Official documents have been established to go as Yupiit and we are told to go forth with those.
That is the way to go as Westernized [people].
But the traditional [way of life] is for us to be ourselves, so we can go forth as we want.
In my opinion, I prefer that because it has been part of my earliest memories from long ago.
Villages didn’t have governers. All of them were only governed by one of their own elders.
Even though it’s not a lot, I’m speaking about it because I don’t want to disregard my grandchild’s opinion.
How does this seem to you?
[?] It’s good. I like it.
About how one should traditionally live.
Because my grandchild also brought this up, even if I don’t know a lot, [I’m speaking] only about what little I understand and know.
I only saw a little of it.
We saw what [s]he asked about through how we didn’t see a lot of these [Western] things
All of us who have grown up without anything [Western].
And then [s]he asked me this: if we [govern] ourselves, how will our lives go?
I can answer with this: the ancestors were the only ones to grow up with, going though what the ancestors instructed.
[They] also hunted with the ancestors’ instruction…
Now, start by bringing up what they asked.
Leave out what’s not recorded in there and finish it?
Yes, please start by bringing up what you [said] about his question.
Okay, yes, I have no idea where I stopped. (It’s okay. Just start.)
When my grandchild asked me, [s]he asked about what will happen if Yupiit governed themselves.
When [s]he asked, even though I [don’t] know everything since I only know a little
I’m not the only one who knows. My peers who did not grow up with a lot of [Western] things like this know it.
We tried to obey and adhere to our traditional wisdom back when we didn’t have a lot of things including money.
You see? A person must only go forth [with the wisdom of] the ancestors.
The elder did not come as a new thing, [but] as an ancient thing, ancient traditional wisdom.
And those who worked on fish for us were dexterous, those who instructed us on fish.
We were instructed like this: do not make a mess of food and food scras when we didn’t have freezers.
And it depends on the fish cutter. We stopped depending on her.
We wouldn’t [gather] what would spoil, as they say [in English].
And then we also walked on land as the ancestors instructed. Only though the ancestors’ instruction.
We especially tried to obey instruction in the fall and spring.
It was because the land and the water were dangerous in those2 times.
Because it was dangerous in those2 times, our ancestors especially instructed us on those.
And then about how we should live, how we should live treated our fellow people
They told admonished us against [treating them badly] just because we’re people.
We didn’t understand this at the time, but we realized what it was later.
Living life [treating others badly] just because we’re people is like this:
A person [who treats others badly] just because he’s a person does not watch what he says to other people, and gives no consideration about offending them.
He also does not have love or good thoughts.
They say that one who is like that does not live another day, as they say.
Those are our sources of support
Before we started going with these books, before these books started dictating us.
We had mercy on someone pitiful.
Also, the state apprently has this without our compassion:
A person should abondon his child when he’s 18, stop teaching him, and have him live separately.
That is not how we Yupiit are instructed.
They say that even when a person becomes an old man, though his daughter gets old, though his son gets old, he does not steer them wrong.
It’s said that we should not stop [caring for them].
However, the way our counterparts go is very unsuitable to us.
Now, all of these students disregard us elders.
They only trust in the wisdom of the books that they know, truly.
A child of the next generation talks back straight away when instructed.
Or he is offended by instrucion when they are corrected.
I am so thankful, my grandchild, that I’m telling you this.
It’s not mine. It’s ancient from long ago.
What we know here is from ancient legends.
Eventually we’re alive, they are born. Eventually, they’ve come to those who remember them.
Thank you very much.
I should dearly thank you, also because I’m surprised to have come in here.