One Caucasian was watching them.
When they were struggling, he told them to get off.
After placing a rope across like this, he twisted a piece of wood, twisting like this.
He strung them around through the many people’s [?struggles] but came short.
That Caucasian clamped them with hide.
That was back when Yupiit didn’t have clamps or nails.
What is it?
Well, my age... (How old are you now?)
I am not very old.
I asked Johnny Samuelson, Cakayak, his age, saying that I don’t know about counting years.
Then when he said his age, I said to him, "Then let me be that age too."
I can’t tell you how old I am.
So, where were you born?
They said I was born over in Kwethluk, in Ceńaqliit [Shore/Riverbank].
And I grew up in Kipnuk.
And when I had fallen in love with a young lade across there, I went to her in Anuuraaq and married her, my wife across there.
As you are a young lady, she had a pretty face like you
Also because she hand handmade Yup’ik earrings.
Should we move on to Yup’ik things? (Yaa.)
Okay, let me tell a story about what my instructor taught me about Yup’ik instructions.
I’ve become disinclined to speak for too long.
When I was growing up, they would tell me to try to live life with an alert and wise mind.
Then when I had grown and started traveling and going with them on sleds, they would tell me this:
They said that when I am able, and I start catching animals from the wilderness and down from the ocean
If I hold on to this one hide, there will be more, until eventually I have a kayak.
Then they said that if I catch a mink or muskrat in the wilderness inland
They said that if I hold on to the other side without immediately giving it away
They said that if I have a little bit and there is more later, it will be good if I give it them.
You see, I desired these shoes
These Western shoes, and these pants that are pre-made out of fabric.
When the fathers of my fellow boys returned after going to the city, they would have shoes, and fabric pants [?].
I would be barefoot, and would not wear pants in the summer at fish camp because I didn’t have any.
Though I would go to bed, I would not be sleepy because I desired what they had.
Now, [my wife] across there used to make me skin boots.
I’ve started rejecting them because their soles are too slippery on snow.
They get holes too.
I respond to her like this:
"Because I coveted these shoes too much, wanting them too, I try to use these shoes."
And after one of the women who instructed me watched me, she would [?say] to me:
"If you are mindless, if you are mindless, you will go forward coveting your peers
"Though your peers take what they need."
Since I was mindless, I coveted my peers though they took [what they needed].
But, you see, I feel especially displeased with one of my children.
Apparently, he’s not saving what money he gets through checks.
If he saves what money he gets through even small checks
When they accumulate, he’d be bale to pay for a snow machine.
And he’d be able to pay for a boat motor.
It’s no wonder they tell us
They said that passing money by, immediately passing money by to whatever is in the stores
If we follow our minds whims on whatever we want and pass money by on those, we will not have [important] things.
They said we wouldn’t get an expensive boat, or an expensive motor.
They also said that if we abuse alcohol, we will not have expensive clothes.
They said it’s because we use those for mischief, what we would trade for what we need.
Now that I’m an old man, I’m seeing that traditional wisdom that was passed down to us.
The people back then evidently did not give baseless instruction.
Instead, they instruct us on things they’ve experiences, what they’ve experienced before us.
And some didn’t keep their mistakes to themselves, but admonished us against committing their mistakes.
When I listen to Min’garalris here in the steam houses, he says
He said that he watched a man when he was a boy, Min’garalria is from Qinaq, someone they called Aassitugaq.
His wife was Marayill’er, and their sons were Nasquna’ar, Panigassa’ar, and Ayimquutaq.
He said that that man he watched was not lucky in hunts, and he wouldn’t catch a lot down in the ocean.
Instead, he said that he would be in landlacked places. He lived on the land.
He said that every year for a long time, he would keep muskrats, minks, and other fur-bearing animals.
However, he said that he always had a boat, and always had a kayak made of seal skin, and those seal skin boats.
He said he always had a boat.
He said that because he kept whatever he caught, he would sell them for boats and sell them for kayaks when he had enough.
They would tell us, ’Back when a married couple made their own living when there were no Caucasians, if he finished their fathers small sled
"And if he finishes a wooden shoever, and holds on to a small axe, and an ice chisel
"They will be able to have things, even if that family’s poor father is poor."
He also said that if he keeps that fishing dipnet that catches sticklebacks
And he said that if he makes fish traps out of straight-grained pieces of wood that catch fish
And if he sets fishtrap-like traps to catch minks
He said that even if he’s poor, if he acts as a rich father of a family
If he gives his children an abundance of things, even if they have ragged clothes, he will take care of them until they are strong enough [to do so by themseles] in the future.
This is the traditional wisdom passed down to us before Western contact.
I also used to see people who were as poor as we were.
People who have male children and have little mistakenly believe that they are poor.
When their sons started hunting and trapping fur bearing animals, their fathers would suddenly become rich when fur was expensive.
Also, when they start bringing in animals down from the ocean, we forget that they are poor, and instead want to be like them.
When they have fathers who take care of them well, and they do not pass by what they had caught, but instead sell them.
And then they would say, "There may be five brothers in this family who are great hunters
"And this married couple may only have one son
"If the couple’s son wishes to be like those five brothers who are great hunters and is not lazy
"If he competes without their knowledge by subsisting, he will become as great as those five great hunters."
They say that it’s easy to compete against great hunters without their knowledge. They say that brothers argue.
"Tell him to fish with a drift net." "I don’t want to fish with a gill net." "Tell him to gather wood." "I don’t want to gather wood."
This is what they mean about how it’s easy.
They say that even one person can compete with them on their level.
These are what we were told in our early childhoods when there were no Caucasians.
And these young ladies who were not married, as they got older, they gave them a lot of instructions and admonishments.
And they would admonish them against ever meeting great hunters at night while people aren’t watching.
They also told us not to meet young ladies at night.
They said that if we become confident and take a girl because people aren’t watching, we will bring death upon ourselves.
We "pretend to have wives."
They talked about that to have us fear it.
And when girls had their first menstruations at home, they would tell them, "Now, from here, you menstruate.
"Never pass an unmarried young man, a boy, upwind from him, but over there downwind like this.
"If he smells your emanations, he will get addicted to it. Eventually, it will ruin him."
Would they tell you that? (They would tell us.)
Don’t you recognize that?
No, I recognize it completely.
They say he smells her emanations.
Then now, when they tell me to speak about old traditional instructions, I reply in my mind
"Our traditional instruction back before Western contact is late. It’s late."
You see, the young children of the next generation that I see are now getting into the Western way of life.
They also make fun of the Yupik language that Yupiit, their mothers and fathers, grew up with, what they call a language in English.
Instead, they choose to speak only in English.
That’s why when I should be instructing on our traditional instructions, and speaking on them
I started thinking that it’s too late. Neither am I excited to teach what I was instructed.
Because after some people listen to me, if he looks away, he will drop it without respecting my stories.
But when he sees a Caucasian, he will change, smile, and go to him speaking English.
And he forgets what I instructed, does not remember them.
But what we were told was that if we come into possession of fur that is worth some money, not to let it pass by.
They said that we should keep it until there’s more.
They said that if there’s more and we sell a lot of even little things, we will get helpful things from them.
Or, one time, one of my grandfathers said to me
"Now, when you start hunting seals, do not keep letting them pass you by.
"If you keep even one hide, there will come more, until eventually you have enough to make a kayak."
Since mink skins are worth less these days
It’s become easy to trade mink skins in stores, trading in fur.
They suddenly get enough for kayaks.
Since they’ve stopped using kayaks, I am no longer excited to talk about our ancestors’ ways.
Watching these, including my children whom I instruct
When I teach those traditional instructions, even though my children, my sons, do not [physically] do it, it seems they come and close my mouth.
It’s because my children whom I teach do not follow those traditional teachings.
That’s why I feel inarticulate.
Though I want teach our ancestors ways, it is late, as they say in English.
And sometimes, after I teach my grandchildren when they’re gathered, I ask them, "Do you understand my instruction?"
"Ung’alu," they say they didn’t understand what I had been taught when I speak to them in Yup’ik.
Well, I’m tired of speaking. This is all I’ll say.
I want more when they tell a few stories upriver in KYUK in Yup’ik.