Traditional wisdom, you know, for the young people today.
You know, ask him about whatever he wants to talk about.
You know, admonishing them or something.
Please start now.
Is it time now?
Now, these young people, before, when we were young
Our descendants now have completely left what we were like when we were young in the past.
What makes it worse is that they do not lack anything.
Because when we were young, everything was scarce for us.
Clothes, and all food, everything was scarce for us.
However, it’s like the boys of the next generations these days do not know anything.
They don’t know how these ancestors worked hard to survive
Because they can easily take anything they want or need.
In the past, we only used kayaks and rowed all the time.
I never saw a boat motor once back then.
And we had a [traditional] mud house.
And I never saw a Caucasian even once. Caucasians didn’t come anywhere near us.
Now, however, since there are now a lot of Caucasians, these young boys have become different.
Alcohol especially affects them. Alcohol makes them act crazy.
Sometimes, they make me very despondent when they do that too much, using the wonderful days that are God’s gifts the wrong way.
Without saying anything, that makes me very despondent.
Also, when they blaspheme against our lord
For them, sometimes, my mind wants to say something thinking like this:
"We didn’t create ourselves. God made us. It’s okay if I don’t say anything to him."
You see, God made people for himself.
But they are divided now.
So, I hope that today, after this, one of these boys will come to a realization
May he come to a realization in case he is doing that the wrong way too much.
Now, we will not live for too much longer.
I have also taken upon many years. I had thought that I would have been gone already.
But I am thankful to God that he has allowed me to live this long.
If these boys always turn to him for help and go with him throughout all of their life
With everything he does, he may sometimes be given what he asks for.
You boys here, all of you boys here who are listening, remember this:
You were not born of yourself. However, God worked on you and made you to be born.
So that you would be his child.
However, you are not going by yourself. Also, you bring yourself to misfortune.
No person will help you as you try to live here aside from him.
Only God will help you if you boys ask of it.
All of you who are listening now, let me tell you. Hear me.
A long time ago, before we had this these, every single person was extremely good.
We didn’t hear about anything that made us [?sad], well, and people going missing.
Now, however, for you boys who are listening, everything has become commonplace.
Every single things has become commonplace, including hearing bad news about something at random.
When something is put, it’s already gone [stolen].
If you remember that God made them, you would live life without paying them any mind.
Now, try to live life well from this day forward.
This too...
Is that all?
What was I going to say again?
Now, I am going to speak about what I’ve been thinking about lately.
Now, we have absolutely no respect to our creator, God our creator.
His nativity, Christmas, and Quyavik, Thanksgiving
You prepare for them the wrong way. You boys who are listening, listen now.
You prepare for them the wrong way, the wrong way.
Yet what you are supposed to prepare, your heart inside, you do not prepare for God.
So after this, remember [not to] prepare the wrong way.
You see, we have no other help.
Since I also want to help you now, and I want to make you repent from the wrong ways of your mind. But since I’m not God, I can’t make you repent.
But you must kick yourselves off. You must kick your lives off, but only by yourselves. No one will help you.
Only he will help you.
Now, I am very thankful to these people who came from somewhere far away and had me speak about what I wouldn’t have spoken about, what I’ve been wanting to speak about.
And sometimes, when I come across KYUK over there, I want to speak.
I have been wanting to say this in case one of the boys might come to a realization.
Now, hear what I said, all of you who are listening.
And the people aroung you, and even here in Hooper Bay, I hope that some people, even just one, will say that in their mind.
Especially this thing that makes life end badly that you keep using
If this alcohol that you keep using were a traditional instruction, no one would use it.
You keep using it because it’s not traditional instruction, but an admonishment.
Yet you do not follow the traditional instructions.
Yet they are broken [from doing] what are not traditional instructions.
But I am thankful that I have spoken even though it wasn’t a lot. Thank you very much.
Goodbye and have a good day.
Thank you.
Who are you in Yup’ik?
Cimiciaq
(Who?) Cimiciaq.
"Jimmy-and-Jack," Cimiciaq.
Cimiciaq.
It’s like English names, "Jimmy-and-Jack."
How old are you?
Seventy-six years old. I’m almost 78. Seventy-six years old.
Without gray hair.
Do you have a husband?
No. (Did he pass away?) They passed away.
Long ago, long ago.
How many children do you have?
There are four of them.
What about altogether?
Altogether, including the ones who passed away...
...and Nathan have a [?fisher’s]...
These are the medicine that we’ve always had starting from our ancestors, rosewort roots.
The roots like this, these rosewort roots
Our ancestors of old would peel them, peel them
A long time ago, when their children had sore throats, they would chew then then do this.
They [?] for them.
Then when thye had other ailments, they would also put them on their sores.
It helped them, but after they peeled, removing their outer layers.
And sometimes, they would peel them, put them into a pot, and boil them
They would also apply it here when they had sores or rashes, and here too.
You know, it was like an ointment.
They used to use these a long time ago, including the other ones, wormwood. People even drank them.
Do they also drink these?
What are they?
They’re, you know, (Rosewort roots?) rosewort roots.
These things (Yes.) I chew them when there are sores or rashes.
When we have sores, they get better, and we use them when we have sore throats.
We only swallow their liquid, but don’t swallow these parts.
You know you told me earlier that you had a lot of sores before?
Ii-i.
Did you use those?
I used these when there was a sore outbreak in Hooper Bay including among the small children.
I used this because I heard that there is no kind of medicine [for sores] all over.
The sores grew large. And on my bottocks, they started pulsing along with my heartbeat.
Then I started thinking, remembering what the people up north said.
That urine, I went to get Amaurrlugaq’s urine [?].
I went to get it with a container, washed myself with that, whoo, very strong.
And my body was burning, sore.
It was sore here. And I washed the slime of my buttocks.
I had been discharging slime. It’s like fish slime from the sores.
When I was done, I dumped that and replaced it with these [rosewort roots] that I’d boiled, and rinsed these [sores].
I rined with their liquid. I rinsed when I was done.
Them my body was in suffering, and it seemed that all of it was pulsing
Too many sores in my body, mostly in my sit[ting area].
They grew large, and they pulsed from my heart, along with [my heartbeat].
And next day, when I finally got better, I kept breathing it in. It’s like I smell it for long time.
It seemed it couldn’t get out of my mouth, my breath.
Then the next morning, you know, I woke up and they had become clean, had dried up.
And when they dried up, following that, they were getting better, until eventually they were gone.
And after that, I never went through that again.
What are those in English again?
Root, root...
What are these roots in English again?
Roseworts. Yes, these are roseworts.
Would they also use these rosewort roots for drift nets?
They probably also used them for drift nets.
(No.) Are they different?
(Those different ones.) These are different.
Those are yarrows.
No.
Yarrows... (These are rosewort roots.)
They’re rosewort roots.
The yarrow roots below...
THey use them on drift nets.
When they use them on drift nets, this drift net starts catching a lot.
From there...
They’re like Vicks. Others, other kidns are also like Vicks.
Yarrows are not those. Those...
Ready?
I know when I was a boy.
I was born, and I know when I was born, 1902.
I am 88 years old.
I am also now the elder of this village.
Now, I have no more elders too.
I work at the alochol [?mission].
I speak to these boys and those with mental health problems.
Also, I always speak to them about the traditional wisdom I learned back then, and nothing else.
They get better.
And even thought they had mental health problems, and they had thought of committing suicide
They come to a realization when I have those as my speaking tools.
In my first memories, I had instructors, and they instructed about everything.
Those were my grandfathers, great-uncles, and maternal uncles.
When I was very little child, my father also instructed me
But I lost my father without being able to fully observe him.
However, my mother raised me.
I also used to pity that mother of mine like that, looking at her [situation].
Without my knowledge, she looked at me, I wonder what she was thinking. I looked at her and she had tears streaming down here.
It’s clear that she felt pity.
But the instructions when I had become aware as a boy should not be ignored.
And sometimes, their stomachs, when they didn’t have stores
When they only [ate] what they got from this [land]
Sometimes, they become downtrodden from their [empty] stomachs.
We would also be downtrodden because we had nothing, had no clothes, and did not ignore things.
Those people I was born in time to see, only had what they had obtained [?worked hard] for, not from stores
That was the food that they had.
Their bodies were also strong. I know them.
They these people looked old, they were strong like this.
Those people I saw in my first memories were also good.
They were compassionate.
And their traditional wisdom, they were good like [what the wisdom instructed].
They were in accrodance with their traditional wisdom.
Those whose responsibility I was always used to tell me not to act foolish.
I also used to join those who were mischievous.
They said that those who are mischievous do not obtain anything.
However, the one who is mindful, the one who always does what he needs to do
He would go through life right and well.
That was what we were like.
What we were like was nothing to boast about.
It would make us despondent.
And these Western things back then, the lumber and these [?]
They would use that oil for fuel.
(When you’re almost done, I will wave to you like this.) Okay.
Has it started? You start?
Yeah, go ahead.
This is our medicine, rosewort.
In Yup’ik, it’s called caqlaq.
It’s our medicine when we have sore throats.
I’m going to cut it.
My goodness.
I’m going to cut off a part of it and chew it.
This was their medicine a long time ago when they didn’t have [any other] medicine.
When I had a very sore throat recently, the did things, the doctors gave me shots all over and I went to the clinic. They gave me shots.
I took these and ate.
ThenI ate and I found the next morning that my sore throat was gone.
But a long time ago, this was their medicine.
There’s some over there, and inland.
[?They say that when ?] there are a lot of them.
And altogether now, I got one whole full jar.
Though my daughter refuses and is scared of these
"You’re so foolish. Wouldn’t your grandmother tell you to eat these when you had a sore throat, and would chew them and feed them to you when you had sores?"
We used to do that a long time ago.
And those things, wormwood, their juices too.
And last year, not this summer
My last baby over there, I call my last baby my baby, because Peter is my last baby, because I love him so much.
He was very swollen. He went to the clinic, and the clinic didn’t do anything to him.