Now? Okay.
A long time ago in the qasgiq, young men like us stayed in the qasgiq
We stayed with all the adults who lived in the qasgiq
These were what those elders talked about most
Of people striving to survive, and of going hungry with no food to eat.
They talked to us about those many times.
Also if we are struggling, out there while hunting and gathering, to help others.
These 3 especially are rules to follow
This is what I heard:
If I come across someone in trouble while traveling
I am to help them out as much as I can  with what I have.
We were advised that way. If they don’t have ammunition or food to eat, to share what I have with them.
They also told us like this: some day when we have nothing
They told us that an empty stomach is no fun.
Of all things that a person suffers,
Nothing compares to the pain of an empty stomach.
A person who is hungry cannot be strong.
Also if a person has wasted some food in the past or thrown away some food
The thought of that will haunt a person and he will regret “Arenqiapaa (unhappy exclamation like oh no or too bad.)
“I should’ve ate that food and not thrown it away!”
They said that is how it is.
In his mind everything starts looking good enough to eat because he is so hungry.
These things especially were taught to us.
Also in the winter, during the cold weather when we are hunting, that is when we struggle.
They told us not to travel empty handed.
They told us to never travel without a shovel and an ice pick.
Also to have names for rivers and creeks.
They said that a person, during a time of want, will stand by a river or creek that has a lot of fish and not know it if they don’t know the name of the place.
That is why our ancestors named all their hunting places
Places with different kinds of food or fish.
If a person doesn’t know that name of a river, he will not know if that place has fish.
That is why we are told to learn all place names of rivers and lakes.
Places where we hunt for food, these are what was taught to us.
Also to know which lakes and rivers always have food.
That place upriver “Ecuilnguq” always has fish.
Also I hear “Qagatmiut” area above us i always has fish.
They taught us that streams with a strong current that flow from the mountains always have fish.
A person will survive if they stay with streams or rivers with strong “boiling” currents
If we know of places like that we can fish with hook and line or use a net to try to survive,  that is what they told us.
They told us that when the water in the  Yukon river becomes dark, fish move to clearer waters, fish  enter clearer rivers.
Even these Yukon river fish die till there is no more fish.
And then when there is no more fish, they told us not to stay but to go to places that have black fish, places where black fish traps are set.
They told us also to go and try to survive at those places.
We not only hunted for our dog teams, we also hunted for ourselves.
They told us that these foxes and ravens are smart.
A fox and a raven will show you where there is food or fish, because there is nothing they don’t know.
They also told us to be watchful of foxes and ravens.
These things are what was taught to us.
It is true that foxes show where there are fish. Ravens also show where there is food.
If we go to places where  foxes and ravens are, there is so much blackfish, then that is where we set our blackfish trap.
They also told us if to catch enough
And to think of our communities.
Those people when  they were alive, they had love for each other. Love was their way. They loved each other.
They gave to each other without asking for payment, without asking for anything in return.
Sometimes troubles are many among us
Sometimes when we have a problem and ask for help, they tell us
“You helped me during a time when I needed help so now I am helping you as much as I can.”
They were not against each other, they loved each other.
This is what they told me.
Is that all?
Yes. It will be enough.