Saying she became an old woman.
They say that they don’t call those who walk by themselves old men and women.
Instead, they call them older men and women.
We who know about our ancestors’ traditional wisdom will not hold them back
Because they live long lives on this earth.
Do wish early deaths upon our people whom we love?
If we love them, we must especially tell them about our ancestors traditional instructions.
And then, we Yupiit have instructions to wholeheartedly welcome our fellow peoples without discriminating against them, but in accordance with them.
Everyone in Alaska is asked to stand with one mind with each other.
Some people say this about part of our beliefs: "Our traditionals beliefs are good and powerful."
That’s not the case. That’s now how it is.
We should not destroy our ancestors’ sense of community and should not get rid of it.
Our ancestors say that our ancient sense of community is a form of love.
If we do not practice love in our lives here, how will we be saved? We have no other salvation.
Our ancestors practiced live, and they were saved as they continued
Because they practiced that with all of their fellow people without discrimination.
Even if various other religions try to divide us, discrimination is bad, and leads to unrest.
But if we use our ancestors sense of community, we will live in peace, and our faith will be complete
And we will be saved through that love.
We must make our descendants especially be knowledgable about these, including how to take care of our land.
We who know the traditional wisdom should not hide them.
You see, they said that our ancestors were like this:
They said that a young boy would wake up in the community house in the dark to an old man already speaking about how a person should live life right.
In the same way out in the houses, they said that an old woman would be speaking in the dark so that those she loved would wake up to traditional wisdom and teachings.
Do we do that? We haven’t done that.
We should bring up what our ancestors were like to our descendants.
We have no other salvation. We only have salvation through community.
Jesus came down only to complete community to everywhere on earth.
Let us know this: that sense of community will teach us how to live well, be strong, and live long lives.
It is a great thing how our ancestors stood as a community.
Even if they say that other religions are superior, do not believe them.
The one God has no superior, no one greater, and cannot be despised. He is as he always was.
We believe in one god and to Jesus to whom there is no one greater, no one higher, and no one stronger.
He is as he is.
For that reason, let us Yupiit instate community, especially among our descendants.
A young person is like this these days:
When he learns to speak English, he is proud thinking of himself as knowledgable, yet he does not know how to live, and he does not know what is in store for him.
Now, we must provide these for our young people so that they will know about our ancestors’ lives, especially about their sense of community.
This is all I’m saying even though it’s not a lot. Thank you.