Okay, ready.
Okay, what you just asked, what would I believe?
Our ancestors, this is what our ancestors believed.
They said that we should especially believe this:
They said that the Spirit of the Universe is watching us below.
They said we shouldn’t forget that. They said that the Spirit of the Universe is watching us.
Then they said that if we know that, we should take heed to advice.
We should follow the wisdom passed down to us.
They said that we would do well to take heed to advice, living without going against them.
Then they said that our elders would say this to us: "A person who is called righteous..."
...what you said.
They said that if we do not forget that the Spirit of the Universe is watching us, that [Spirit] will give us wisdom.
And [the Spirit] will not have us disregard our elders’ instructions.
And they said that if we do that, we will become wise.
And we will be called articulate [teachers].
And like this: what he says must be accurate.
They said that everything he says must be true.
And they said that things would go as they say.
They said that if the Spirit of the Universe is grateful to us, he will make us like that if we respect him through everything we do.
Then they said that if we respect him, only if we respect all of our elders, we will respect the Spirit of the Universe.
That’s their traditional wisdom.
Through they never heard about the dead rising again, they used to think that if a person dies, he is dead and will never live again.
So if you know your ways, will you also be able to know what is good or bad in others’ ways as well?
Yes, yes.
About other people’s ways
Other people’s ways here, the people who are called Caucasian work toward commotion
And especially the ways through these TV’s
Acting senselessly as our ancestors admonished against, focusing especially on being mischievous
And having some of our people focusing on it as well
This mischievous ways of our counterparts, the other people.
So, what’s a good way of the West?
You mean a good Western custom?
Well, other people.
Our good Yup’ik ways are also like this:
Heed the advice of our elders in every village, even if they want them to live without commotion.
But they talk about one day.
In that day, though a person is mischievous all day starting from when he wakes up
They said [the opportunity] was open, and in the community house where they couldn’t have commotion, having commotion was open for one [day].
They said that’s what they were like.
You see, they wouldn’t have them stay [queit] all the time, but have them do that.
However, they said that when that day passed, they told them not to do that, told them to stay quietly.
Since they wanted to be happy like this through that, our ancestors would give them one [day] like that.
So, how will I know other people’s good ways?
If we see our peers, other people’s, good ways like this.
This is what our ancestors were like back then:
I lived over there were they herded reindeer. And they had separate rendeer here in Bethel that were their very own.
And they had their own reindeer in Akiak, and in Akiachak, and up in the mountains.
Those would herd separately like this without working together.
Then they would occassionally say this:
You see, the people from there or Akiak or Bethel would do that. They would take care of their own reindeer.
And that custom they’d established was good.
Never would we go through there.
It was good that we started doing that, and their way was easy to follow.
They would follow that good way without rivaling each other.
These days, we should be like that as a Yup’ik Nation.
All of these villages have different customs.
They also want to accomplish different things.
As an example, the people here from Atmauthluak have accomplished something better, and we had never accomplished that before.
We examined it and realized that if we did what they accomplished, we would do well through something better.
What?
How to take care of our land.
Also to own our land, that it should be set to us [in our care].
If we also do that with one mind, we will become stronger.
What is it?
We will proceed without commotion.
Here’s what it is:
We take this land of our very own and govern it, without letting others, Caucasians, who do not own it govern it.
We would govern our land as our ancestors governed it back then
Without letting others who’ve come from far away govern it.
We would do that in accordance to the right and good way they were.
However, if we follow the way of our counterparts, we will come to discord.
They will fight, and even claim ownership.
They will also grumble, saying that a person is walking through their land there.
We Yup’ik people’s ancestors did not have that.
Instead, they lived well without commotion.
Many times today, all of their parents work to earn money.
Among those, if they have children, who is going to teach their children about our culture?
These days, they’re like this: they try to earn money as our counterparts.
Them even though some are instructed to work to earn money
When they get money, they only give it to alcohol to become crazy, hurt others, and get into misfortune.
They they tell their parents not to do that, to frugally take care of their money
They don’t take care of them, but use it to act insensibly.
That’s why after making the work a lot, they fire them.
When both of their parents are working, who is going to teach these children after they’re gone all day?
These parents will teach them, talking to them about how to work.
This is also how that person should work, a man or a woman:
They will only work hard if they’re obedient.
No, you didn’t understand my question.
Those with children today...
These parents who work today, and some have babysitters
Some of their babysitters are like this:
They tend to curse.
And the little ones would speak like their babysitters, swearing.
They don’t know what that is, don’t understand it.
Yet some babysitters, instruct them after their parents [leave].
And one who does that is rare who babysits well.
He instructs them on how to do well, and to be obedient though they’re very small.
He doesn’t instruct them on bad things.
I know and see some very small children curse though they don’t know what they’re doing.
Their babysitter teachings them wrong on how to lead bad lives.
So today, how will we emotionally move our young people today?
How will we let them know about our traditions or good mindsets?
Particularly when they wake up in the morning, instruct them well.
No, these [youth] are now starting to follow their own minds.
How will we be able to fix them?
We can fix them how our ancestors back then used to fix them.
Continually instruct them, speak to them, do not be harsh with them but make them feel affectionate.
Let them want to obey us.
Though they’re like that, and even if they do bad things, do not despise the bad things they do too much, but admonish and love them.
And explain to him the bad consequence of what he’s doing, saying that he needs to be [better] like that.
They say that one who always scolds him, or speaks harshly to him
Or like this: "Since you did it by yourself though you were told and disobedient, you are like that,"
They said that that is as forceful as a club to that one who does not heed advice.
However, they said that if one says this: "How different do you think I am from you? I am like you."
Every person has one mind, is of one mind.
But, they said that historically, the traditional wisdom, though a person was called that, and though a person was called bad
They said that a person’s mouth has always fixed him, and makes him change his ways
Without getting tired of his [bad ways].
Then, do not be impatient, "When is he going to become obedient?" They said not to say that to him.
They said that one must not despair, but try to fix one who like that by speaking to him.
When they had community houses a long time ago, they would speak to the young men and teach them what to do in those community houses.
But these days, in schools from way out there, they’re getting teachers who have separate cultures.
And their beliefs are very different.
And especially TV’s like that in schools.
Yes, through our youth learning about others’ cultures these days
It’s causing them to be like that, not heeding advice, following their own mind, starting commotion as they are watching TV.
They watch it.
And this Bible instructs us like this:
"Their eyes are only watching desire, stealing, killing each other, and committing adultery."
We are looking right at those with our eyes.
That Western culture is especially leading our people astray.
Then to what we believe.
A person without faith cannot be healthy, and he will not fix his sickness well without faith.
That is the truth.
Those people who live without faith like that are already told about.
The Bible tells us, "A person who does not heed advice does not believe." That’s what the Bible says.
And back then among us Yupiat, a person who does not heed advice is called a non-believer.
One who does not heed advice is called one without faith.
Since a long time ago, that’s what our ancestors called that person.
And they said that since the one who does not heed advice does not believe, he is living a bad life.
They said that he may be agile and strong
However, they said that these elders, our ancestors back then, instead say this about that person who does not know what he’s doing and does not heed advice:
He is inhibiting.
They say he is like one, these days we say those on the verge of death are inhibiting.
They said that one who does not heed advice and follows his own mind is like that, inhibiting.
They said he is fated to do this: as he does not know what he’s doing, he will suddenly disappear, stumbling like this:
Sinking, or is killed, or he hurts himself.
He suddenly dies.
They say that he "stumbles" while he doesn’t know what hes doing, even though he was called a fast or strong person.
They said that for that reason, our ancestors called those who do not heed advice inhibiting.
Yupiit have traditional wisdom that are like their commandments, instructions. Those who follow them do well.
One of our instructions is like this: those of us...
And speaking like that is like this for our ancestors:
They say a person who is not very mindful does not instruct others’ children.
He only instructs his very own children on how they should do well.
They said, however, that he does not instruct another’s child.
They said that those who are like that are called unmindful and stingy [with knowledge].
They said that though they want their children to do well
They disregard another’s child and cannot instruct him.
They said that one with that mindset, though their father wants his own children to be good
They said that his chidlren instead will be [bad] like that.
However, those children that he has not spoken to or instructed, they said that they will do what [he wants his children to] in his mind.
Then, they said that if we wish bad things upon a person, it will instead come upon our body.
Since they’ve repeatedly experienced and seen that
When a person changed his ways and his unmindfulness, they would talk about that so that the person in the next genertion would not be like that.
They told him not to live unmindfully, but showed him how to live well.
Without being embarrassed, he wants a person to do well.
They say a person who changes his ways becomes like that, instructing on everything he’s seen.
Then when I was growing up, I watched two women.
In Akiak, though [another] was a guest and she saw him for the first time, she instructing him on how to do well.
She spoke to and enjoyed [the time] with him.
And the other was especially like that in Quinhagak.
Even though the Caucasian didn’t understand Yup’ik, she spoke to her as if he did, making her laugh, really enjoying [the time] with her.
They enjoyed [their time] with them without discrimination.
Then one day, one of the Caucasian women said in church
She said that it was very certin in her mind that when she died, she went to Paradise because she was like that.
She spoke to and isntructed every person.
They say that one who wants every person to do well is righteous.
They say that we should help others without thinking of being immediately paid by that person.
That is a traditional instruction like this, and I read this in the Bible in Peter’s writings:
"To one who is a leader, he should speak to and lead these people to do well.
"And do not think about being paid, but to lead them to righteousness."