About Christmas from before, when you first learned about it when you were [?growing], what instructions did they give about generosity?
Back then, our ancestors were peaceful. They were peaceful.
They had their elders like this to instruct them, admonish them, and advise them.
Also, they weren’t wealthy a long time ago. And these Western things weren’t on hand.
They would help those around them who didn’t have anything, as was traditionally instructed. That’s what they were like.
Also, they helped those who didn’t have anything by looking at what they didn’t have, and also lent them things. That’s what the people I was born in time to see were like.
Then one who didn’t have a provider liket his, you know, these orphans, widows, they helped them with whatever they needed.
They helped them without expecting payment.
They also admonished against expecting payment.
They told them not to do this: "This person may reward me. Let me do this." They said not to do that.
Instead, without thinking of payment like this, help those who are in misfortune around them.
Seeve those who have no helpers. That’s what people were like.
What did they say was the meaning of being okay without payment, but to go ahead and help? What meaning did they prescribe to it?
They prescribed this meaning to it: that has good aftereffects [later in life].
You know, we didn’t hear promises back then. And we didn’t hear threats.
That’s what people were like.
So, how old were you, how old were you when you first heard about Christmas? And what did you do [?] Christmas?
We started hearing about Christmas. We started hearing the Bible.
And they also didn’t know of preachers, but they would hear of them, started hearing of them.
And one day, eventually, a preacher started arriving.
So, when Christmas first start, how did you...
We only started hearing of the first Christmas and when it began.
Then they started having Christmas, you know, when they were given a pastor downriver in the old village of Qinarmiut where I grew up.
When they were given a pastor, he started the Christmas tradition in my life.
What would [s]he have you do?
They’d celebrate Christmas as they do now, celebrating as told in this Bible.
And they would give each other things, you know, including little things.
People weren’t like this a long time ago.
And when this Bible appeared, they were absolutely nothing like this.
Instead, they’d give each other things. They’d even give each other smoked dried fish.
When they didn’t have Western things, what else would they give aside from food?
Well, food, [they’d give] food.
Also, for those without anything, those who had [something to spare] would give them some little things.
(Would they not sing because they didn’t know?) They wouldn’t sing.
But, you know, they’d [sing] Yup’ik dancing songs from legends, oh my, that’s what I knew from the beginning.
They’d sing songs from legends, Yup’ik dancing, and drumming at the cusp of fall before winter.
It was the people’s tradition.
Then in the winter, they’d finally invite [other villages] and have a dance festival.
They’d [bring] as much food as they could.
Then when the Caucasians came, they also started [giving and eating] Western things.
That’s what the ones I was born in time to see used to do, the ones who first started celebrating.
This person’s tradition of giving to one who doesn’t have anything as much as they can
When you started becoming observant, does it seem the same as our counterparts’ tradition of giving, or what is that like?
And on account of one’s namesake, you know, these next generations
Those who are named after their late relative, they’d also give them a gift for that reason.
They would do that.
Even if it wasn’t Christmas time?
Yes, even if it wasn’t [Christmas] time.
And so, how old were you when these lay pastors or priests
How old were you when these traveling priests starting arriving here?
Where I grew up downriver, when I started getting wood, getting trees, they were given a lay pastor.
[S]he would preach like this in the community house.
When [s]he spoke of this Bible in the community house, we’d listen.
Then after that, we started doing [various non-Yup’ik] things.
That old preacher started arriving, an old person.
It seemed that Caucasian was sent all over.
[S]he was from far away yet spoke Yup’ik.
Now in some villages, in some villages, they take names [at random] and give presents.
Back then, [would they have Christmas like that]?
They never did that at all.
They’ve started doing this sometime ago.
It was only until recently. It was recent.
When those lay pastors came to the churches, I mean, would they gather people in the community house, and how did they celebrate Christmas?
Those people didn’t celebrate Christmas.
But the guests that came, this lay pastor among them had us start celebrating Christmas in my short life [at the time].
How did [s]he have you celebrate?
[S]he had us start celebrating like this with Christmas [songs], you know, they started singing Christmas songs.
However, they would give each other little things. They’d give each other little things.
They only started in my lifetime.
So, what do you want for Christmas this year?
Have those who are listening hear.
The birth of Jesus, that I didn’t hear about a lot back then, for our sake
This is what it is: this, our unseen life, this Holy Spirit is our life.
That’s what it is. They say this is like this: you know, because God is powerful
You know, he made this Word flesh, made seen what was unseen, only heard of.
He made him seen, made flesh, and had him be born.
They say Jesus was born like that.
His father had him be born. He gave him as a gift to this world. He was a gift.
This is true.
Like this, you know, in one of the songs, there are lyrics like this: "Look at me, believe and accept my gift."
To those who do not accept him like this, youo know, to those who don’t accept Jesus, there is a verse in the Bible like this:
"He makes only those who believe in him worthy to become God’s people, the ones who believe in his [Jesus’] name." There’s a verse like this.
Then for those who accept him, he goes into their life
Only if [s]he accepts him, only if [s]he accepts him in earnest.
Then he becomes a savior to that person. He becomes a savior.
However, to one who hasn’t accepted him, he doesn’t become a savior to that person.
Then it’s like this, there’s also a verse like this:
"I admonish those whom I love and chastise them. For that reason, enthusiastically repent.
"And look, I stand at the door and knock.
"If a person hears my voice and opens the door, I will go in and eat with them, and them with me." There’s a verse like that.
Then if a person doesn't welcome him, he will leave them on on wayside without having become their savior.
That's what it's like.
Then I want to talk about God’s advice like this. I want my voice to spread.
If a person passes away in sin, and now, we heard yesterday that someone passed away upriver in Kwethluk.
Then that person from here also said this:
"There is none among us who lives by themself or dies by themself. But as we live, we live for the Lord."
The believers’ creed says this: "We live for the Lord. And when we die, we will die for the Lord."
That’s why whether we live or die, we are the Lord’s. That’s what believers have said, and it’s true. It must be true.
However, those who aren’t true won’t experience that.
If a person isn’t true, they will die, then their life will pass in misfortune.
Instead, [s]he will be in fire.
I spread my voice about that to the people, and [I spread] my voice to our counterparts here.
I’ve been thinking of one of you lately wanting to speak of this, but I was uncomfortable and intimidated by you.
Then I thought that one of you would translate what I said.
If a person passes away in sin, lives this life unacceptably
Instead, [s]he will go into the lake forever, to be in fire forever in the utmost suffering.
There are many ways to resolve our lives.
But when a person is no longer here, we’ve heard [of one] upriver.
Then at that time, [the life] stops.
You know, with whatever resolution [that life] had.
So now...
So then this...
You see, this is my thought: that either you or Aqum’aq would translate what I said into English.
I want them to understand how they could [live] well.
Let’s see.
Our workplace here has a policy like this...
Now, wish us good tidings, tell us of your thoughts, you know, wishing us a Merry Christmas.
Okay, so let me talk about it now if I have some of those people to listen to me.
Jesus’ birth, you see, God... is it going now? Is it going now?
Yes.
You see, God’s love fo the people of the land, how there is nothing greater than his love for the people of the world
This is what Jesus is like, it is told like this in the Bible saying this:
"The Word was always there, and the Word was in God, and the Word was God."
Look, it’s like this: it just said when when the Word has always been, not talking about its beginning.
Look, how there is nothing greater than God’s love, it’s like this, now understand it:
It says that there, you see, it’s light has a greater light than the light here.
Also, inside those is a shape that is happy and joyful but without anything added.
Furthermore, there’s also a song like this, there are lyrics in a song:
It said that had Jesus not been hung, every person’s life would be lost.
Then when Jesus came down, it was like this: look how there is nothing greater than his love.
Look at the light, the wonderful light, and the darkness below, miserable death, repulsive.
Furthermore, with the extent of God’s love, it truly seemed that he sent Jesus down right away.
It truly seems that he put [Jesus] over from the people of the land, put the people of the land closer to him with the greatest love.
With so much for this, I like that one too. I don’t mind it.
Then should there be time for me to talk about what I wanted to, and should you want me to, I would.
Please wish a Merry Christmas to us who are watching now.
All of you who are listening now, I say hello and wish you a Merry Christmas.
Thank you.
You’re welcome.