You came in then sat down. Let’s begin.
Ready?
Shall I begin?
This is medicinal, our medicine from a long time ago rosewort.
And in Yup’ik... what is it again?
I’ve forgotten it.
This was our medicine a long time ago. I’m going to cut and taste it.
It’s terrible eating this little things.
Then when I had a sore throat, I eat the entire then, then my stomach felt better inside.
They’re good for stomach pains too.
This was our medicine a long time ago.
These are called caqlat in Yup’ik, caqlat.
They don’t eat these, except for their roots.
We didn’t know about them. My mom always used to tell me, Ceng’ulria, my great-grandma, about those.
And they’ve somehow changed these days.
They’ve started living Western lives, not using what they did long ago.
They’ve changed now.
They also used to try to scare us a long time ago.
They said that something would happen when we pretened to be a man’s wife. That’s what my mother used to tell me.
It turned out as I’ve turned old now, I would remember what my mother said.
My mother would say, when I reached the bottom, when I reach the bottom I would remember my grandma.
I thought my grandma was my real mom.
And after I played, when I came in after I played outside, I would embrace her and suckle on her breasts. How old, I was older than 13.
It was because I was their baby, my mother’s [baby].
I was the baby, the only girl.
Our big family, only three of us are now living.
These two are men, and I’m alone.
I am the only one who’s alive.
TB claimed my older sisters.
Since my mother wanted me, she did whatever she could to make me live, whatever she could.
She also had me eat these when I was small. Though I thought they tasted made, I would eat and swallow them.
Those are things from long ago.
Then one day, my mother told me
What did she call me? "Grandchild." "What?"
She said that if I go search for vole caches, she said that if I search gor mare’s-tail plant tubers in vole caches
She said that if I uncover quarruuget [sticklebacks], needlefish, in a vole cache
She said I should take only one, just one.
Then as I searched for vole cahces, I came upon one, so many were moving.
Then I thought, "Oh my, didn’t my mother tell me that if I find sticklebacks that I should eat one?"
Then I ate one.
When I was going to go to the wilderness, she would instruct me like that.
Then one day, my companion found a filled vole cache
Because Ignatius Black and I were friends when we were small.
When he found a filled vole cache, he called to me, "Oh my, what are these?"
Oh my, I went to him and found those bugs.
Those things that go into ears, meriit.
Oh my, they were moving. I wonder how they could be eaten?
After he had [?], I heard my companion say, "They’re not sticklebacks. I won’t eat those."
And we traveled on.
It turned out that when we arrived, my mother, my great-grandma, asked me what we did with those.
"So, did you eat?" "I ate." And she was thankful that I did.
Oh my, what were they? Maybe it was my mother’s doing. She seemed to do something to me.
Is it done?
Oh my goodness.
That’s what we did a long time ago.
And my baby son, my last baby was bitten, his older brother bit him.
He bit him here, he bit him here in two spots.
I found him and found that he took this kind of thing
He stuffed the places where the teeth were with this.
He stuffed and bound them.
The next day, he showed them, and oh my, it healed. And what was red and swollen was gone.
At that time, the clinic workers [?] him, [?].
He was supposed to get shots.
Because he didn’t want to go, he was supposed to go the evening of the next day, he had stuffed them with these without our knowledge.
And they healed. And they never said that anything was wrong with this part.
He stuffed it with these.
You see, my baby is always scared. These one is always scared too, you see.
My father... his father is my husband’s cross cousin.
They are cousins, they’ve been cousins for a long time.
He passed away several years ago.
After he passed away, I’ve been trying to raise my sons over there by myself.
I always tell them about his precautions.
And I never forget what my mother said, her precaution.
Is that all?
(Yes.) Thank you.
Okay.
Okay, thank you for this wonderful day [?] today.
So, I tried to obey my parents when I was small in my life.
And my father’s wisdom never leaves my mind, when he used to tell me
If I do not live well, and I go to other villages that are not my own
If they hear my name, they will know that I am mischievous through what I’ve done.
He told me to try to make me feel ashamed [to be like that]. And now, I never forget his instruction.
My mother also told me to treat those around me with compassion.
You young people must obey your parents.
And never forget the traditional wisdom passed down to you when you were small.
You must especially respect your parents inside the home.
Do not speak harshly or do not do things harshly.
Try not to upset your parents.
Your parents, those who are parents, are heartbroken without your knowledge when you cause trouble.
That is my piece of traditional wisdom, because I want you to be well.
Then, my parents used to tell me this:
If I do something, smoking, or some other thing that smells bad, in my house
Starting from when we were small, they would apply seal oil inside our noses because we might get headaches [from odors]
And because that odor might adversely affect us.
It’s the same with gas. Even though they’re not smoke, we get tired of smelling gas.
We must apply [seal oil] inside our noses, and apply it to children’s noses.
Also, if you go to the wilderness and suffer, you have no medicine if you have an accident in the wilderness.
If you have seal oil when you have a bad cough, if your throat inside is bad [?with prickling pain], you must [?take] seal oil. My mom used to do that to us.
Also, if we had a persistant cough, she would have us drink it.
When we didn’t have aspirin, she would do that to us when we were small because we had no clinic.
It is also clear how we can live well.
Though as for help from anyone, no one can help us. We alone can [have ourselves] live well.
Thank you very much.
Thank you. What you said is very nice.
Henrietty, John, Carlton, Eddie.
Seven?
Seven.
Wow, fourteen altogether? Then two adopted?
Seven are living, right?
So, how many grandchildren do you have?
I don’t know. I have many grandchildren.
Ready to start now?
It is not good for you to use this alcohol.
But this alcohol only leads to trouble.
Also, when a person abuses alcohol too much, he comes upon something wrong that he’s not supposed to do and brings misfortune upon himself.
And the other one, smoking...
Close it.
The other one, smoking, goes into this mind along with this body.
I don’t do it, [so I don’t know] what it’s like.
But I hear about what that smoking is like, that it destroys the mind.
Also, that person who smokes too much starts sleeping a lot.
I hear about that when they smoke.
That is probably true, that one who smoke too much starts sleeping a lot.
Also, you know? They forgot what to do.
And after they put things down, they immediately forget them.
One of my sons, though I admonish them, since they sometimes do that
I do scold them with what I can, like us, like us... this is my spouse.
Close it. Come here.
That’s my husband right here.
Stop [?].
Ready?
Can I quit?