…he didn’t refer to it as one.
It seemed like a hypocrite.
And some say this:
They will only believe a person speaking in English.
They will not believe him even if he speaks Yup’ik.
They say that their minds are no longer true.
Because our language is a gift from God, it is our strength.
We can do anything though it seems impossible through our
ability to speak Yup’ik.
It’s in the way.
Ready? Is the tape rolling this time?
Okay. Our ancestors used to say that was the most important.
And some said this:
“If you forget how to speak Yup’ik,
you will also forget the words of wisdom and the teachings.
“Who will you be if you become like that?”
Now, let’s get into this now.
The ancient instruction, one of the most important of Yup’ik instructions
Is revering the land, revering everything no matter what it is.
Please talk about what that instruction is.
Please also talk about what you have seen
as you have lived up to this day.
Yes, is it time to start? Okay.
Do I say my name first?
My name is Joshua Phillip.
I was born… I am Maqista in Yup’ik; Maqista is my nickname.
I was born on January 1, 1912.
I am now 79 years old.
What I have seen, watched, and understood
I am going to tell youpl about what I personally understand,
not anyone else.
Our ancestors apparently had this piece of wisdom:
Even if you see your fellow human for the first time, welcome him well
And love him as much as yourself.
And yet they had never received or seen this Bible.
And they had never seen even one Caucasian.
And they wore clothes that were all fur.
Yet here is their traditional wisdom:
You must love your peer as much as yourself.
Now, I finally understand
In our belief, they say that Jese brought two [commandments] down
saying this:
The commandments were given through Moses
But compassion and truthfulness [came] from Jesus Christ.
And then, our ancestors’ unknowing traditional wisdom:
You must love your peer as much as yourself.
Our ancestors instructed that most importantly, saying this:
“Eventually, they will start saying that person cannot be fixed,
“That he is bad, mischievous.”
Here is their traditional wisdom:
“Do not, under any circumstances, go along with what they’re saying.
“And do not criticize the one they criticize.
“And if you see him, chat with him so he’ll be happy,
and feed him if he’s hungry.
“And if his clothes are tattered, if you have any to spare,
look at him and give him one of your clothes.”
That is treating others well, showing love
The most important instruction from our ancient ancestors.
And then, I read this in the Bible:
It’s said that the Old Testament and New Testament are unified
into one word saying this:
“You must love your peer as much as yourself.”
That’s what it is. We have no other salvation.
They say that we have no other salvation under this entire world
Except for compassion and truthfulness.
This compassion and truthfulness were the most important
instructions of our ancestors.
This is what truthfulness is like:
That we should not speak lies, nor give false accounts,
But only speak the truth.
It is the companion of compassion, related to it.
There were two that Jesus brought down, compassion and truthfulness
Long before our ancestors heard it, they scattered that compassion
among their descendants.
Love is the greatest.
They also say that the Bible says something else:
We have no other salvation except through compassion
and truthfulness.
Those2 are the greatest pieces2 of traditional wisdom for us.
Has this been according [to what was planned]?
It is.
I am now going to talk about how we traveled this spring.
In the spring nearing summer, I had this idea:
Well now, to one of my past hunting grounds inland
When summer sets, I should go see one of the places I used to
walk about with a canoe that has a small motor.
And then when summer set and there was no more ice
We portaged through the route upriver from Tuluksak
to the headwaters of Elaayuk.
That’s the first time we went downriver through there.
When we came upon tussocks of grass as we went downriver, I would stop and look around from a vantage point.
When I was climbing to vantage points,
I would come across empty pop containers.
And as I traveled with my motor on the river
I would see plastic stuffed in tree branches.
It would be stuck there.
I saw a lot of those.
I didn’t think anything when I first found out.
Eventually, we went far downriver over there
Pity, because everything had old pop containers
I had a though because there were old pop containers
My goodness, look at our children.
It’s way too polluted, not like our ancestors.
These are the most prevalent:
Old pop containers, plastic, and where the pick berries, diapers too.
And in their camp sites, there’s nothing but debris
where those aren’t put away.
Back in our ancestors’ time, they made the land pristine.
There was no pollution, none of those.
There were no old pop containers, metal, plastic, or diapers.
And as they were there, old drift nets too.
What [nets] that were set all winter is here to the mouth
of the Kuskokwim and even the Akula region inland.
It’s polluted. It’s polluting the fish, and the land here is polluted.
And yesterday, when Matthew Beans was telling a story,
he said this:
When he goes to villages on planes
He sees a lot of those plastic and paper products
when he gets close to villages
The things that the wind carried like a storm.
When I saw those so much there, I had this thought last spring:
I will tell them in the church.
Or even outside of the church, I will point those out to them.
Our ancestors were pristine.
They revered their land here and alwauys kept it cleaned up.
And in their time, their water, the Kuskokwim
Even outside of the Kuskokwim, they revered the creeks too,
kept them from being polluted.
Neither did they pollute the land where they subsisted.
Our ancestors always kept it cleaned up saying this:
The Spirit of the Universe is watching us.
They said that the Spirit of the Universe is watching us
without leaving anyone out.
The intelligent read in the Bible, and I read too
It says this in Psalms 24:
God owns the land and everything on it.
He also owns all that live there.
Pity, we who are polluting our land these days
who are called [Christian] believers.
Will we [truly] be believers polluting our air and land?
I pondered and realized
That we believers will evidently not have air like that.
Our village where we stay in the winter,
and our subsisting grounds in the wilderness
We must keep them like a cleaned up house
Our air, hunting grounds, fishing grounds, and our Kuskokwim.
And these days as I travel on the Kuskokwim,
I would see a pop container drifting along here.
And yet it’s where we subsist and commercial fish.
Gross, what will happen when it rusts?
You see, our ancestors back then said this:
These fish are easily repulsed.
They said that if these river has anything bad in it
The fish will not go in it because water keeps them alive.
Because they know that if they go in it,
they will die before they reach its headwaters.
Since a long time ago, they say that they can’t go in polluted water.
Since our ancestors’ time back then, taking care of the land
and taking care of the water
They have admonishments on those from what true things
they have learned over millions of millions [of] years.
Their admonishments only concern what is true
What they understand, what they have seen with their very own eyes.
Because it’s like that now, we must take care these days.
Things are depleting, and fish are depleting this days
Because we are not respecting our water and land, polluting them.
Can’t we incinerate these [our garbage]?
Or, we must leave them buried in the land
to keep our land cleaned up.
Nallunrituci enengqellriani assilrianek
caranglliisqumanritarci enesi.
Your land, air, and hunting grounds are more important.
You must watch over it more than your own homes where you sleep.
Keep it cleaned up.
Because our land is polluted these days, God cannot bless it.
He’s reducing things, reducing the fish
And it seems he’s reducing these cloudberries.
He cannot bless a polluted land.
Let us not put it to another person or Caucasian
Except to us who live in the land.
Those things that must be cleaned and watched over
We should only put them on ourselves, not pass them to another person.
As we are not careful of ourselves
And as we do not instruct our young people to
respectfully use that [land]
We’re making it become like that because we hide
[the knowledge] from our young people.
Now, let us instruct them from here on out
To share the land and keep it pristine.
It’s very clear that when our land becomes pristine
God will bless it like [the time of] our ancestors
Making things abundant, making nothing scarce,
making everything we use on this land available.
They can do that for birds, small animals, caribou, and minks.
When they tell stories of our ancestors’ time back then
They said that their traps would be full, and couldn’t catch any more
minks when they couldn’t swallow.
Things were abundant back then.
Because the land was cleaned up and pristine like this
God blessed it like that.
There were instructions for every kind of meat
To bury the leftovers we won’t use in pits and leave them.
And if we see a caribou bone or the bone of another small animal
in the wilderness
If there is no lake near it, to bury it in land and leave it.
If there is a lake nearbly, go throw its bone in there.
That’s what our ancestors instructed.
They asked to the keep the land that they saw here pristine.
When I returned from my travels last spring,
that’s what I wanted to say.
Our caretaker, the creator and owner of the land cannot bless it
when it’s polluted like this.
There you have it.
And then, you see, it’s apprently very expensive to clean this land up.
These days, you see, I saw people getting paid to clean up the land
over there.
And yet, they’re called cleaners.
Now, they only have their eyes on money.
Back then, however, our ancestors didn’t watch for [money].
Our ancestors back then only looked out for living long lives.
They were like this:
In their lands, there was no grass growing,
[because] they cleaned up their land after the grass grew.
And then in the winter, they would shovel the trails.
Our ancestors also shoveled trails to get water.
Because they were like that, their land was blessed.
And those who cleaned up would say this:
“Enjoy [cleaning] dust, enjoy cleaning up in your life
without thinking of money.
“Cleaning up is expensive.
“So you may have food in your future, on everything you look back on.
“And then as your future always has food like that,
you will live long on the earth.”
That is the promise of cleaning up.
It’s no wonder in my earliest memories back then
I would see old women and old men supporting themselves
with their knees as they walked.
They couldn’t stretch [their legs] because they were
such old men and old women.
It turned out that our ancestors, including the women,
would live long because they always cleaned up their land.
And they started walking supporting themselves with their knees.
That is the reward for those who clean up.
And then they would tell these stories:
This great hunter was lacking unlike his peers.
And his name was Picuilnguq [Bad Hunter].
And even when he tried, he wouldn’t catch anything.
They say that those people who envy these good hunters
They become cleaners in villages though no one orders them to.
They apparently become cleaners in villages
because they’re ashamed that they can’t catch anything.
When that happens and they [clean up] like that
The ones who are called great hunters, good hunters
A person who cleans up like that becomes a better hunter than them.
This is what it is: God [sees] that person cleaning up his land
And repays him with what he wants out of gratitude.
That’s their reward. As long as he lives, he will be like that,
living without lacking anything.
Cleaning up the land has these great rewards.
We should not ignore it.
They also used to tell us this:
You will come across a log on its side on traveling paths
completely blocking traveling paths.
Do not pass that log laying on the traveling path.
Take it and throw it over where travelers do not go.
It has this result: as you travel on this land
You may travel without severe misfortune on this land.
That’s its promise.
And these days, they will be like this:
Even our fish camps, clean up even our fish camps
And wash the fish off of fish cutting areas or other places.
Do not pollute the fish, our fish cutting areas, or fishing grounds
with metals or paper products.
We must make incinerators and burn paper products.
We should also bury our metal [trash] into pits,
not throw them into the water of our Kuskokwim River
Because we will have no more fish on the Kuskokwim when that rusts.
That is the most important thing we must watch over.
We are called [Christian] believers these days.
If we are believers, we would always clean up land that is not ours.
We should properly use what God has lent to us.
But we do not understand this days.
It’s probably because the young people speak English.
It’s like that depriving us of everything.
And the pollution is depriving food of our hunting and gathering grounds.
That ability to speak English will not save us, only our belief
And cleaning up our land out of respect through faith.
You see, this is how our ancestors back then treated this land
that they used:
They would respect even the wilderness as their own houses.
And then, they also respecting the Kuskokwim, their water where they
subsist, and the places where they trap blackfish.
And they would never let them freeze or spoil [what they had caught] saying that the fish traps would not get fish anymore.
Because there is a lot of that now, and drift nets spoiling [catch],
the fish are depleting.
We must understand that God has cursed us through that.
We have worsening shortages of things, shortages of fish,
the food that we are given.
My goodness, let all of us elders be in accordance
Let us instruct our descendants to take care of this land
to keep it pristine.
When it is pristine again, God will certainly bless it our of gratitude.
When he blesses it, the things we eat, sell, and gather
will increase all in the same way.
I am thankful when I hear people sometimes talking
[about traditional wisdom] on the radio.
This important thought that I had last spring
I am speaking to all of you who are listening about
what I wanted to say about the things I saw with my own eyes.
We must raise up our young people to be like that.
Now, I have been like that with my children for a long time,
telling them to clean up regularly.
And I have them watch me as I clean up in front of them,
and have them watch me clean up our fish camp.
I also tell them not to throw these empty motor oil cans into the water.
I wrap them in plastic and throw them into holes that I dug in the ground.
I don’t only tell them, but instruct my children on what I do
by having them watch me.
We fathers and mothers must do that
To respect our land like our ancestors since the beginning
And to watch over, use it well, and keep it pristine.
My, we will do well if we do that.
Will God not thank us in the last day?
Will he not tell us that we cleaned up his land?
Because he owns it, he certainly made those who cleaned up
into great hunters a long time ago.
Begin with that.
There is a lot to this.
I’ve said what I wanted to say when I arrived.
I also talk about how to clean up both the land and water in churches.
Respect them.
There is so much to this.
Let us all not fail to raise up our young people
and tell them to keep this [earth] pristine.
I say this to my children:
Even if you had slept there for the night, always leave it cleaned up.
We must tell them that.
These days, I also see used diapers
The used diapers of their loved ones are [scattered], a lot.
Are those not a cause for ingratitude in God’s eyes?
It’s time for us to take care of our land in accordance like our ancestors,
keep it cleaned up.
Thank you. I thank you if you’re listening.
I will also try to do that as I’ve said as much as I can.
Thank you, I have told you what I think is important.
Cleaning up apparently also makes for a long life.
That [subject] is over now.
Let’s2 move to another [topic] if you can move to another.
Okay.
Should I go this way?
Ready?
Now, I’m going to ask you something else.
[S]he said you’re doing this too much.
Please try to stay still without moving too much.
Sometime recently, one of your daughters
When we interviewed one of your daughters, [s]he asked her now she was raised.
And then she said that this is what she thought:
When one of their peers misbehaved, your late wife
would gather them all and admonish them.
How is admonishing like that now
You know, we’ve started hear know that people only discriminate
against someone who misbehaves.
And some who are families do not love him too much
Separating him because he’s mischievous, disobedient,
an alcoholic, or something else.
How did you and your late wife raise your children?
What is raising a child like?
Child rearing is also part of the traditional wisdom
from our ancestors back then.
My father raised me back then, and probably when I needed it,
he would instruct me without regard [for my feelings].
Or, he would also gather my family and my older sisters
to instruct us on how we should live.
And then they would say this to us:
“Do not despise your peers in life. Instead, humble yourselves
before them in life.”
Adhering to that ancient piece of wisdom, our pride should be
as much as what they tread upon in our live.
Let us be as humble as the grass they tread upon.
And then they asked me when I took a wife and had children
When I had children my father said to me, “You are now a father.
“You are now an instructor for your child who is born.
“I will not teach or instruct you.
“I have already instructed you on what you should
pass on to your child whom you love.
“I have also talked to you about what has not originated from me.
“I’ve passed on my father’s traditional wisdom onto you.
“You are doing that, but I will watch you.
I will admonish you when you warrant it.”
And then this: “Children are different.”
Now I have nine children.
Five are male, and three are female.
These people are different. One of them tends to be mischievous
and disregards [instruction or wisdom].
They’re evidently different as our ancestors back then have said.
They say that descendants are different even when they shared a womb.
That’s what they say.
But even though they are different, compassion is the most important
piece of traditional wisdom.
They also used to tell us this:
“If one of your family members is mischievous and disobedient
“Because youpl, his siblings, try not to be like that in life
“Youpl, his siblings, must gather and admonish him.
“Do not scold or criticize him, but treat him well with love.
“And do not speak harshly, but with tenderhearted love.
“Because yourpl sibling is like that, youpl must admonish him with love.”
And then if you take in a son-in-law, it’s an ancient custom
If you take in a son-in-law, love him more than your own children.
No matter what he does, do not react violently to him, but speak to him
and instruct him with tenderhearted love.
My son-in-law is [mischievous] like that,
and he abuses this alcohol
But I have never spoken harshly to him to this day
according to what I was instructed.
Concerning what little instruction I gave [him], I talked about that wisdom
with tenderhearted love for my own son-in-law.
That’s why my son-in-law cannot leave me alone today.
And if he seens that I need something, he will help me.
That’s what trying to treat everyone with love is like.
We must be like that.
And then, I think I just talked about it first
That I should not join others in criticizing mischievous people.
That is traditional wisdom from our ancestors.
They say that a [Christian] believer…
Back then, they didn’t talk about believers, but obedient people.
Instead, they called believers obedient.
These days, they call them [Christian] believers.
Back then, however, our ancestors called them qanrucunalriit
They referred to someone who did not do whatever he wanted
but adhered to his instructions as obedient.
These days, however, we are called believers,
call that obedient person [a believer].
They told us to be like that so that we would stand [alive] for a long time
and that we would be given long-lasting strength.
These are evidently instructions saying this,
After they instructed us, they would say this:
“A person instruction whom he loves so that [s]he will live well.”
Jesus further explained those with his words
saying this to his disciples in John 6 verse 63.
John 6 verse 63, Jesus explicitly said,
“My words to you are breath and life.”
Here is wisdom from back before our ancestors before there was a Bible:
If you, a great hunter, come upon misfortune that you cannot survive
If you flustered and do not remember the traditional wisdom you heard
If you do not remember them, you will die by your own fault.
Yet even if you come upon misfortune, if you remember traditional wisdom
The wisdom you remember will give you strength and save you from that.
That is apparently how these instructions are breath and life.
We must adhere to them.
They would also tell us this:
“Quit being so noisy. Do not act so mindlessly.”
They would also tell us that when we made too much noise in our homes.
Behold the precious young people these days
They even fill a huge plane and bring them to other villages
to make a lot of noise.
They say they’re bringing them to play basketball.
Yet there was this instruction among our ancestors:
If you bring this growing boy do other villages,
he will be mischievous.
And even in other villages where he has never been or seen
He will be able to be noisy there without shame when he arrives.
They say that’s what one who was brought to outside villages
when he was growing up has always been like.
Because those ancestors have seen that
They tell people not to bring a growing child to others’ houses
in their villages.
Or, they tell people not to bring them to other villages.
That is the instruction of our ancestors back then.
They say that if we want a mindful child, we will adhere to that.
We would not bring our children whom we love to other’s houses,
and we won’t bring them to other [villages].
They say that some would say this:
“That person is sensible, wise, and articulate.”
They say that’s what people who were not taken to other places
when they were growing are like.
Those are true pieces of wisdom from our ancestors.
Our ancestors back then teach things, true things, that they have seen.
There you have it.
And then they said that even if we are short on something as we live,
we should never take a person’s things or their traps.
They told us not to steal, or to take another person’s catches.
They said this:
“If you take that mink or fox
“Your caretaker, God, the Spirit of the Universe,
will let what was prepared to be yours be taken.
“If you take that, you will take one
“But God will exchange what was supposed to be yours to the
one who owns the trap that you’ve taken.
“You will only catch one.
“You will transfer what was to be yours to that person.”
That’s another piece of traditional wisdom.
And then some would also say
The legs of some who steal too much get crippled
Or their arms get crippled.
They say that shamans used to do that with their tools
to the people who did that a long time ago.
They crippled their legs, and crippled their arms to make them suffer.
Those shamans made them like that with their tools
because they were unhappy with them.
That’s why they especially warned us against taking a person’s things.
Behold the people these days.
Because we do not teach that starting from when they’re growing
They run off with boats, and they steal a person’s boat motor
And they would steal a person’s entire drift net from his boat.
They’ve probably become like that because they don’t hear about
the consequences of stealing and how dangerous it is
Because we don’t admonish them against doing that.
And yet our ancestors strongly warned against it.
But they also had this traditional wisdom:
Let us try to make every one of our fellow people happy in our lives.
They said to look at these people who have always had things,
and they gather what they need.
They say that they’re like that through people’s gratitude.
They say that gratitude is good.
And then I read this in the Bible:
Giving is more of a cause for gratitude than receiving.
It’s a cause for gratitude to receive a gift
But the Bible says that giving is more important
Because it says this: “Giving is more of a
cause for gratitude than receiving.”
That’s why our ancestors told us to help our fellow people
as a form of love if we have anything to spare.
They say that out a person’s gratitude
It’s like a person’s body is given strength.
God probably does that.
They also told us to serve others in our lives.
And they say this: we will not deteriorate from our soles.
They say that.
They say that as we serve, we will become stronger,
and sicknesses will not touch us.
Even if others are sick during an epidemic, they will not touch us.
That’s is the promise of servitude.
A person will stand [alive] for a long time with any afflictions.
This also concerns servitude: people are thankful.
Or, if [s]he gets water or chops wood, an old woman or old man
can be thankful for that.
They say that his gratitude will uplift that person.
Those are our ancestors’ traditional wisdom.
I’ve said a lot by now.
Okay. Well, thank you for coming.
This is all for now.
But someday if we are able, we should gather and talk
if you have something else in mind as you go along.
Thank you.
I will come if by chance I think of something that must addressed.
Thank you. May our caretaker bless what you have heard.