Then when he started making blackfish traps, he instruced me on the [asgurcuutet].
When he used an [asgurcuun] there in the Qissunaq river, he would instruct me as he fish trapped.
Also, when the creeks inland from the main river snowed in the winter, he set the blackfish traps.
They would [be set] all night [?into the day].
When I started going by myself, I would always try to heed his instructions.
Then one day, I set willow ptarmigan snares downriver from us on the banks of Qissunaq, and stuck the stakes.
Then when I went to check on my willow ptarmigan snares, I found something black moving as I was about to reach it.
Apparently, a mink had gotten caught.
I found that while the snare was also just twine, it didn’t cut it.
It had gotten snared in its middle.
Since I didn’t know what else to do, I looked for a club since I watched him kill minks.
I took its neck and twisted it as I used to watch.
But it didn’t just die.
They twist though they’re held, but [die] when held on either side.
He’d tell me, "When they can’t die like that, it’s better to kill them by pulling their hearts." He instructed me.
I started doing that.
When I started trapping in the wilderness and mink is alive when I reach it, I’d pull out its heart, and they die right away.
However, when I come across a fox in a steel trap, I would watch him lift its head up and kill it by its neck.
I do it like him.
Then when I started traveling with a gun, he would instruct me when the weather was good while chasing a fox
"Should you catch it when the weather’s good, bring a little knife and skin it there.
"Don’t weigh yourself down with its flesh and bring it home."
When I first did that, as I used to watch him
Without cutting the tail, he would somehow bite the tail and pull it out.
The tail would come off without a problem.
When I first did that, I tried biting the skin here.
When I pulled the tail, I think I only took off the fur, but the skin was left.
So much of the tail fur stretched.
I wasn’t happy. After I gathered it, I brought it home.
And I cut that tail, cut the bone, because that’s what he used to do.
When I arrived, I had my mother sew them on after I removed the skin.
She sewed the fur on and made it into a tail.
He finally instructed me to cover them with something and bite deep inside
Until those skins come off.
However, when I catch a land otter, I can’t kill it when it’s alive.
It doesn’t easily die, land otters.
When I keep bashing them, some of them finally steadily die.
Non-aquatic animals apparently drown right away in water.
When I started, I followed his instructions on hunting.
And even if he’s gone, he instructed me to do that according to his instruction.
When Peqiciraq’s father starting going with me before he passed away, Peqiciraq’s father downriver
He brought me deep in to the wilderness far away by dog sled.
I followed him.
We’d go around [?] and hunted.
And when we went down there, going around Qucilgaq, we’d [hunt] there.
Okay, keep speaking, don’t stop. (What?) Keep speaking.
When we went around Qucilgaq by dog sled, nothing would happen.
But when I went with him in the spring by kayak, because he would set up spring camp downriver from us where they called it Quuqaq
When my late father arrived, he told him
"Take him downriver. His brother won’t travel with him, " referring to Eritailnguq.
"Take him to your village downriver. Go downriver." He told me to follow along.
When we went around Qucilgaq by kayak
When we first did it, we’d look for portage routes.
When we cut inland through there and came up on a lake
We’d look for portage route through there, to the headwaters of what they called Elurtuli.
When we went down to it, since the currrent was strong, we went downriver.
And when it widened downriver, we started rowing side by side hunting for muskrats.
As we went, we’d sometimes pass land otters swimming there.
Then as we saw land otters, we appeared on them going up to the land through the snow.
There were four, apparently with their mother.
He said to me, "Okay, they’re going through there probably because it’s a portage route."
We followed them.
I took my gun, left my kayak, and followed them.
When I saw them upriver, they went to a pond. We went around the pond.
When they went out up there, we went to them.
I arrived there and found tracks on the portage route. And they went down to the river again, here to Elurtuli.
They noticed me when they saw me.
Those land otters [?] when they appear.
When they appeared coming closer, they growled, even their mother.
I shot it, but didn’t instantly kill it.
When he didn’t go, since he went up to the grassy area across from me, I went to get my kayak.
He was waiting for me.
He said to me, "If they go down to the river, it’s part of this. I will go around rowing. You portage through there with them."
Though their mother died across there, I hoped he’d come across it.
I crossed. I portaged through the route.
When I got to it and lowered my kayak, I saw that it hadn’t died yet.
When I reached it, it went down, but it wasn’t doing very well.
Since I had a .22 and it was close, I shot it again and caught it.
Its young, however, were popping up around me here.
I tried shooting at them.
Since I was in too much of a hunting frenzy, they ran away from me. I lost them.
[I only caught] their mother.
I waited for my companion.
He tarried since that point was far.
He made a [gun] popping sound over there not far away.
He said when he arrived that he passed one land otter there and shot.
He said to me, "I think it’s one of those young ones. It’s not young. It’s big."
When I lost those young, he said to me, "We should go inland and set up camp on the tundra since we rowed all night.
"Let’s set up camp inland on the tundra and bring up our kayaks." We unloaded and brought them up.
We gathered willows there. We made a kettle of hot water and drank something hot. The weather was calm.
As we were there, he said to me, "Look, something that’s not a muskrat appeared downriver. The wake of something is coming from downriver."
I saw that it left a big wake. It wasn’t a muskrat.
When it appeared and went inland, it didn’t appear again.
He said to me, "Take down your kayak and check where it went downriver."
I reached where its wake ended, and found a portage route here.
I docked there, took the .22, and went inland along it.
I went down to a pond far inland, and something black down on the ice would move.
It was that thing.
It would split into two, then come together again.
That one who had shamanistic powers whom they called Qupanuaq
He’s excercised his shamanistic powers in front of me more than once.
One time, I followed people to Cuukvagtuli, and he was there.
When they had him call upon his spirit helpers in the community house, and my late father went since he was a singer
They drummed side by side since they sang in the community house.
I fell asleep [betwen] those two drummers.
I fell asleep between Nick Beans beside me, and my older brother.
I woke up to the community house here cracking loudly, the center beams up there splitting and caving in.
That was all I awoke to. I had apparently had a lucid dream.
With the pounding drums, I heard them as the center beams up there cracking loudly as they split.
I had the thought to run out.
I got up as he was saying his shamanistic incantation at the door, with [the patient] covered with a seal gut rain parka.
And these two dancers were standing.
They said that when I reached the shaman incanting, I took him here, pulled, and he fell on his behind down on the floor plank.
They said since my later father couldn’t do anything, he told me, "My goodness, he didn’t do something good to you. He scorned you.
"He’s sleepwalking again. He sleepwalks. He did that to you sleepwalking."
They said when Qupanuaq sat up, he said, "If he’s sleepwalking, if he did it in his sleep, he didn’t scorn me."
He said it was fine. He said he was fine.
I regretted it. When I went in, I ran out.
But Nick Beans didn’t say anything to me. I reached him and found that he was nodding as he was sitting.
It turned out he couldn’t laugh because there was a lot of people in the community house.
He only did this, not staying still.
He found it funny, but couldn’t laugh.
I lay down again and was asleep for good.
And the next day, they didn’t tell me there.
Only when we returned to Cuqartalek, Nick Beans told my late mother the story
Since he watched me making Qupanuaq fall on his behind then.
They said it was hard because they were quiet. They couldn’t laugh in the community house because the shaman was practicing his powers in front of many people.
And when I reached the two dancers, I pushed them to the side and ran out.
Since I was barefoot, when my feet got cold in the door of the entry porch, I woke up.
Someone behind me pulled me from my back. I looked back and saw that my late older brother was pulling me inside.
I felt very awkward because I couldn’t do anything since I sleepwalked there.
Only when I arrived did Nick Beans tell my late mother the story.
We women had traditional wisdom not to wanter in the evening, and not to have guests.
This was important [wisdom] from my mother, my mother and father:
They said I shouldn’t listen to people speaking bad things.
Then if I see someone giving instruction, if I see something giving instruction
They told me to go and listen to the one speaking about admonishments.
They were peaceful back then.
But these things that traditional wisdom speaks about
We come to the time spoken about. You, live carefully.
Try to be careful
So that you will not be surprised but recognize what you come across, and not be taken aback though you do not find it right.
And this man or woman that speaks harshly, one who speaks loudly
They do not like that.
And speaking harshly to this young boy with people listening without regard to how he will react
They said something was wrong with it.
These days
Because I remember our traditional wisdom and struggle with my grandchildren or my children here
Since I remember it and struggle
I think that person who shouts, who speaks loudly, is not good.
In my earliest memories, the poeple back then used to tell me
That I should try to live mindfully and wisely.
Then when I grew up and started traveling here, and went with those traveling by dog team, they would tell me this:
Watch, they said, when I became able and start catching animals from the wilderness and from the ocean down there
They said if I keep this one sealskin with me
Watch, they said, there will be more, and when they eventually become enough for a kayak, I will get a kayak.
Then they said that if I catch a mink or a muskrat in the wilderness inland
Watch, they said, if I save the money without handing it over right away
They said I would do well if I use it for something later when I add to it.
"If you are mindless, you will go forth coveting those around you
"Though those around you get their hands on what they need."
Since I’m apparently mindless, though those around me got their hands on things, I coveted them for a long time.
He apparently didn’t save up what money he got through checks.
If he saves what money he gets though the checks are small
When they amass, he’d be able to pay for a snow machine.
And he’d be able to pay for a boat motor.
It’s no wonder they told us that letting what money we have pass by, letting it pass by right away by spending it
Getting things we want inside stores, giving in to our first inclinations too much.
They said if we let what little money we have pass by, we won’t have things.
We won’t get an expensive boat, and we won’t get an expensive motor.
And they said if we drink alcohol, we will not wear expensive clothes
Becuase, they said, we squander what we would have traded for what we need.
As I’ve become an old man like this, I’m seeing that traditional wisdom that was passed down to us.
People back then didn’t give random instructions.
Instead, the give instruction on what they’ve experienced before us.
And sometimes, they wouldn’t hide their mistakes, and admonish us against committing their mistakes.
The many pieces of wisdom of our instructors, one among them would add this wisdom when they wanted to, what they call jealousy.
They said that a jealous shaman envies a person who is living and subsisting well
They curse them to be bad hunters, or break the wealth of those who were going to live well.
They have very malicious intentions.
Then these other pieces of traditional wisdom:
They said that though those among us depreciate us, saying we young people here are lazy
And at night, since I stop going out at night when it gets dark because I lost my mother early
They would give me a harrowing promise, that if I’m lazy like this that I would be a beggar.
They said that that would bring me misfortune if I’m lazy when those around me take husbands because I desire what they have so much.
But our thorough instructors would tell us that.
Among those around us, we shouldn’t act senselessly, [?], be unobservant, or be foolish among those around us.
When they got up, they’d always tell us
"When you young people also have children
"Though your child seems small, or if you admonish them when you put on their skin boots, ’If you peers do anything to you, run away [?and do not fight them].’
"Watch, they pay attention."
They said that our elders keep what they’ve heard in their earliest memories.
They would tell us that a married couple living on their own back when there was no Western contact
If their father finishes a sled
And if he finishes the wooden sled, and keeps a small axe and ice pick
They said they will have things at hand though the family’s dear father is poor.
And they said that if he keeps the fishing tool that catches sticklebacks
And they said that if he makes fish traps that can catch fish out of straight grained pieces of wood
And if he sets fish traps that can catch minks
Though he’s poor, if the family’s father is like he’s rich [in food and tools]
He will take care of his children with abundance though they have tattered clothes all the way until they become strong.
This was the traditional wisdom passed down to us before Western contact.
I also used to see people like us who are poor.
You see, only some who have male children falsly say that they are poor.
When their sons start hunting fur-bearing animals
Their dear father would quickly get rich when fur was expensive.
Also, when they bring in animals from the [ocean] down there
We forget they’d been poor, and covet them.
When their father takes good care of them by not letting what they obtained pass by
Instead, giving them away when they’ve amassed.
Then they’d say that there may be brothers in this family who are five great hunters
And they said a married couple may have one son.
They said that their son here wants to be like the great hunter brothers.
If he’s not lazy and competes with them without their knowledge when hunting
They said he would get as much as these five great hunters.
They said it’s easy to compete with great hunters without their knowledge.
They said that these brothers argue.
"Tell him to drift net; I don’t want to drift ent." "Tell him to gather wood; I don’t want to gather wood."
They said this is what it means when it’s easy to begin [competing with them].
They said that even this one person can be like them.
These are the things they told us in our early memories before Western contact.
And following the growth of these unmarried young ladies, they would cover them with instructions and admonishments.
And they would admonish them against ever going to meet a young man at night when people aren’t watching.
They also told us not to meet with young ladies at night.
They said that if we’re confident in touching a girl’s flesh because people aren’t watching, we’ll kill ourselves.
We pretend to have a wife.
You see, they would speak of that to make it scary.
And when these women menstruate at home, they’d tell them
"Now, from here on out, you go forth.
"Never pass an unmarried young man, a boy, upwind from him, but over there downwind from him.
"When he smells your emanations, he will keep smelling it. Eventually, it ruins him."
Wouldn’t they tell you that?
They would tell us.
Don’t you recognize that?
No, I completely recognize it.
They say he smells her emanations.
They’d tell us to love our spouses, to attend to our husbands
And never be unfaithful.
And if we women start going out without our husbands’ knowledge
They said we’d eventually be pregnant from someone other than our husband.
When they instructed us in our earliest memories, we found that they would pry out extremeply improper things as they spoke to us.
And when they’d watch us, we who are listening would think like this:
"Wow, that one across there apparently knows us, has seen us."
They spoke to us as if they completely knew us, as if they truly had seen us.
It turned out that those who wished to speak would cleanse their hearts of their experiences.
The dear ones would speak to us so that a person would go [through life] well.
And when we have these dear children
They told us to never bring them, and not to hold their hands to have them visit other houses.
They said they’d become mischievous.
They said their misbehavior would exacerbate our destitution for the mother who stays with them at home.
Our father travels to try to subsist for us.
They said we women should be thankful for whatever he catches and welcome them.
Or if he gets a little money, we woman should not be angry wanting a beautiful dress, or some beautiful shoes
Because they said we’re standing here with wonderful clothes they’ve gotten us.
They said those are detrimental for our spouses.
Those things they obtain, we should work skillfully with what our spouses obtain.
As our dear spouses work dextrously, help them.
They said we shouldn’t squander those things, taking his money and going.
And as we go, when we come across socially inappropriate things, or drink, or something
They’d admonish us against all of those dangerous things.
And they told us not to be like that in front of our children. They said we’d teach them.
May a person live without exacerbating [problems] like that these days.
That was their harrowing promise
They said if we misbehave when our parents who instruct us, and our elders instruct us
They said if we we misbehave, we’ll become insensitive.
We stop paying attention to our teachers, our instrcuts, who tell us to live well, not to hinder those around us.
Instead, they said we should be good and look nice sitting at home
So, they said, our house will be nice to be in.
And if a helpless guest comes in our house, try to make them feel at home
If we live without, you know, being mischievous.
When they said that, though we wanted to, yet we would sometimes come upon things.
We do not fulfill our desire to do well.
And it would very scary to be impregnated at a young age, to bring forth a child.
They said illegitimate children were very embarrassing.
It was an admonishment.
This is the misbehavior that our elders back then spoke of.
You young people shouldn’t do these bad things that are admonished against.
Do not follow these Western ways too much.
And since they speak of marijuana, that it has negative effects
Don’t use those.
You see, we only have a short life like this.
Though our youth and earliest memories seems close, yet we weaken like this and can’t do anything strenuous.
That’s what you should be careful like that, not only following those bad things.
If you are buy, subsist, and try to earn money with fervor, we will be thankful for you.
Instead, use the money you earn for yourselves, your houses, use them for help, and for clothes.
And since I don’t know how to speak English, I am not in awe of it in any way because I don’t use it.
Only when they really want me to, and when my spouse across there goes with me, I take something
Because I have no idea how to give out this [money].
I’m very thankful. I’m thankful that I don’t know because I stay peacefully.
It’s not good for you to abuse this alcohol.
Instead, this alcohol only leads to trouble.
Also, when a person drinks too much, they go the wrong way and bring themselves to misfortune.
The other one also, smoking...
Close it.
That other one, smoking, only goes to the mind, along with this body.
I don’t use it [or know] what it’s like, but because I hear about what that smoking is like
That it only destroys the mind.
Also, that one who smokes too much starts sleeping all the time.
That’s what I hear when they smoke that.
I think that truly does happen.
One who smokes too much sleeps all the time.
[They] also [become] forgetful, you know?
They forgot what to do. And after they put something down, they immediately forget them.
One of my sons like that, though I admonish them
Since they sometimes use that
I harshly scold them to the best of my ability.
From us, one of them told me yesterday, I think it was [?Ayapqu]gcaraq
From us, it seems that starting from my time, the way a person goes [through life] has changed.
Right?
Our descendants have become Westernized.
They’ve become Westernized, and some can’t understand Yup’ik anymore.
Instead, they’ve started speaking only in English.
And now, though we speak about how a Yup’ik life should go
How will we teach those who’ve learned English?
Will they be able to enthusiastically start our old way of life again?
Our lives where we struggled.
And we’d travel by dog sled, and gather wood in the Akula region by pushing our sleds without dogs.
And we used to travel without dogs.
And our shovels were not sophisticated, and our axes were not sophisticated, we who came before you.
Now, especially when I imagine our elders, they probably struggled even more.
As we went to becoming Westernised along with their tools, it truly seems that things have become easier.
And now, though a place is far, we’ve started reaching it right away
The place we’d steadily start going to from the early morning.
You understand?
We who are knowledgeable about our ancestors’ wisdom will not keep them to ourselves
Because they help us to stand on this earth for a long time.
Do we wish an early death on our children whom we love?
If we love them, we must especially tell them about our ancestors’ traditional instructions.
Then, we Yupiit are instructed to welcome all of our fellow people well
Without discrimination, but as a whole.
No matter who they are, the people of Alaska are asked to stand together with one mind.
Part of these, some of these religions say this:
"Our religion is good and powerful."
That’s not the case. That’s not what it’s like.
We should not destroy our ancestors’ community mindset, or abolish it.
This community mindset, our ancestors have said since long ago that it’s a form of love.
If we don’t practice love as we live here, how will we be saved?
We have no other salvation.
Our ancestors practiced love.
And they were saved as they went because they practiced that to all of their fellow people without discrimination.
Though various religions try to divide us, that division is not good and leads to unrest.
Only if we practice our ancestors’ community lifestyle will we stand peacefully
And our faith will be complete.
We people of the earth have a solid foundation with this ancient traditional instruction.
And our solid foundation here is worthy of great respect, and will not lose that.
Here, in what elders we have today
That is where the cause for respect is.
What is worthy of respect gives a solid foundation for the people of the earth.
And they know the one that gives them their solid foundation.
Since this ancient thing that’s come from long ago is our solid foundation
And since it’s our support for life, we who are healthy are standing here.
And this is what we’re like:
We value a person’s name, their Yup’ik name.
We also value speaking in Yup’ik because we’re Yup’ik.
That especially, calling each other by our [Yup’ik] names, is a cause for great thanks.
Then, we Yupiit also know this:
Welcoming each other, and socializing with each other with this right way of socializing.
Our behavior like this among ourselves is very important.
And its need to be respected is always like that, and never loses it.
People back then would look at the snow.
When there’s a lot of snow, and the ice, when there’s a lot of ice
When there’s ice between layers of snow, when it’s been repeatedly warming up
When there’s a lot of snow, and a lot of snow upriver from us, there’s a lot of melt off. They’d say there’d be a lot of melt off.
Did you see a snowier time when there was a lot of snow?
There used to be a lot of snow back when we were small. There used to be a lot of snow here.
And the buildings down there, the mission house was the only tall one, and it would reach the roof going down.
We’d climb up there and slide.
And we’d shovel the doors of the porches like this into a den.
How, with February ending now, how would they prepare to go to spring camp back then?
When they were going to go to spring camp, they’d start preparing in April.
And they’d prepare their food supplies for the spring.
They’d go set up their tents, and...
Watch, I’ll slip into English.
And, you know, they’d bring their boats, and their open canoes.
They’d bring things they’d need to use in the spring camps.
Then when the middle of April passed, we’d move.
We’d arrive to our settlements. It was very good and pleasant.
Then these days, they also say this:
They said a woman with femal children, watch, that woman will watch her mother in the home.
Then they said that woman, her child, will be able to replicate her chores, what she does.
These are true.
And now, I have nine children, five girls, four boys.
And these five girls are all different. You know, they’re different.
And I love all of them very much.
Then when I started making things, and when I started sewing
And these grew up, my daughters started living on their own
I’d make them things, and sew things for them.
I sometimes go in their homes, and what I sewed is on the floor. I would feel unhappy.
Apparently, they’d leave leave on the floor what was supposed to be kept well.
I’d go into one of my daughter’s, [and it’s] neat.
Oh my, what I made would be treated with love.
Then when I do that, these among my children of five girls, two of them, I won’t say their names
They’re neat from what I’ve seen, what they call neat in English.
They’re good.
They’re all good.
Then I realized this: they take great care of the clothes I sewed.
Because the other takes especially good care of them, since we see them when we go into her house
In the summer, the clothes I sewed, parkas, skin boots, furs, fur clothes, I never see them in her house in the summer, nothing.
She put[s] them away.
You know, she puts them away.
I know that in the West, furs have appropriate places to be.
It’s not hot, it’s not cold, maybe meduim, and the fur is good.
You see, when these skin clothes hang for years and years, they become unusable [?from wearing out].
And when I take this parka, it rips. [?It wears out].
They said that if I see one of my peers in misfortune as I travel in the wilderness
I should help him with whatever I have.
That’s how we were instructed.
Or if he has no bullets, or is without food, I should give him some of what food I have.
They’d also tell us this:
They said that someday, if we lack something one day
When we lack something, we will not be [?robust].
Theys ay having an empty stomach is not enjoyable.
They say that one trait among every person is that the greatest suffering is suffering an empty stomach.
We become weak, and [?without vigor].
Also, if that person does not keep food, or throws food away though it’s edible
When it comes into his mind, when he regrets what he forsook, how unfortunate.
"I should’ve eaten that instead of throwing it away."
They said that’s what it’s like.
They say he begins to covet everything in his mind in his hunger like this.
This is the important wisdom that we pass down.
Also, in the winter like this during the cold season
Since we especially struggle when we hunt
They told us not to travel without anything.
They told us not to travel without a shovel and an ice pick.
We should also know the names of these rivers.
They said that one person, you see, during a famine may stand around a place with a lot of fish if he doesn’t know its name.
The people back then would name all of the subsistence areas in the wilderness
The place with various edible food.
They said that if a person doesn’t know that river’s name, he doesn’t know that it has fish though it’s indicated.
That’s why we’re told that we should know the names of things on land, rivers, and lakes
The places to hunt, to subsist.
This is the traditional knowledge we pass down.
However, we should also indicate the ones that always have fish.
Say that Ecuilnguq upriver always has fish.
"I also hear that the area around Qagatmiut inland always has fish."
Say that the flowing waters in these mountains, fish don’t stop going to the waters flowing from this mountain.
"This churning water does not die out in the winter when I go to it."
They tell us to go there if we know them, or fish, or set drift nets and subsist.