Alrighty.
We’re rolling.
Ready?
Yes.
For the record, Nicholai and Olenka K. Nicholai of Kwethluk.
Qugiciq and Angut’aq.
Okay.
So, we came here to Kwethluk to ask about things of old.
Please ask your spouse this:
Did people long ago... no.
Were there a lot of settlements where people gathered her in the Kuskokwim?
You know, what are they now?
Urucararmiut, Bethel, Napaskiak, Oscarville, Tuntutuliak, Napakiak.
There are only several.
Were there a lot a long time ago?
He said, were there a lot of villages when you first became observant?
No, there weren’t a lot of people.
You see, when I was a boy at some height, I was probably this big, but I was observant, well, I had became aware.
Down around Wass’ house, the furthest upriver.
And there was nothing here upriver from there, except for those wooden human figures.
That was all there was.
Graves.
Then (Graves.) since Dutch’s house was the furthest upriver
We had a house down there toward the water from there.
And my late grandfather, Kukikcaq, was the furthest upriver. That’s what I observed.
Those there, and we were not spread far apart.
Then here right behind it, right behind our house like this
The late father of Vera down there had a house, with my female blood relative as his spouse.
They had children.
Around that time
They celebrated Russian Christmas in my presence.
Then before anything happened before dawn, they had nothing left to do.
We celebrated Russian Christmas together then.
And out there when they came in, there didn’t seem to be anyone outside the house we went into.
We would go with the singers going first.
And they finished before dawn (I see.) without any mishaps.
Ask if those...
Over there...
Oh no, yes, what?
When those crosses on the graves over there were not present
Down toward the water in the trees was the house furthest downriver.
Over there, do you know Paniluk?
Her father had a house like that among the trees.
He was apparently my great-uncle.
When I went in, though he teased me, I didn’t react because I didn’t know the custom.
It turned out that he would tease me.
There was also a path through the thickets for sleds.
It went down downriver on this side of the mouth of the river.
They wouldn’t use sleds down [toward the river].
That’s how I know it.
Please ask him, what did he think when he first saw these Caucasians?
He asked, what did you think when you first saw Caucasians?
I first saw a Caucasian, I went to school for a very short time.
It turned out that woman was going to be our teacher. They had called her something. I forgot.
Oh my, that woman.
In the fall at that time, the students, I would go over with my fellow children.
Then they ended it because they always climbed.
When we traveled at that time
Apparently, it was down to the headwaters of the river by Quinhagak
When we had apparently traveled there.
There, we didn’t go downriver, but stayed there.
Apparently, when the one they called our mother was alive.
I don’t know when the other passed away.
But I have an early childhood memory in their, you know, graves.
When I told that story, they told me
They said that the one I saw was my father.
But I didn’t know what happened to him.
It turned out that when we went down to the headwaters of the river by Quinhagak without going downriver
We were there all summer.
I was there with my family.
There was no one else with us.
Because fish would go there, they fished when the fish came, and we had a store of fish.
It’s not like this [river]. Fish don’t come early there.
Apparently, fish don’t come early there.
We were there for five years. It seemed to be five as I remember it.
And I grew up to be in my prime.
I started hunting.
I started traveling by myself without any companions.
We also came here in the winter by sled.
We reached [?] inland, these spruce trees smell strong.
When we reached [?], I smelled the scent of these spruce trees.
It turns out they smell strong after being in a place without people for a long time.
At that time, the one they called out mother had an ailment in her blood.
We were here.
And in the fall, she passed away before it froze.
It’s terrible. I still remember my late mother to this day.
It’s terrible.
It really seems that my eyes are closed.
And I stopped hearing little pieces of traditional wisdom after she left.
But before she passed away back then, she would always speak to us who were alive
After she passed away then, also because I didn’t go to school.
One day, I decided to [?], and traveled because I would walk downriver to Napakiak.
And though I saw my fellow boys here, in my mind, I didn’t want to play with them.
When I reached Napakiak, I stood toward the river from that house and stayed.
As I stayed there, a woman came out. She wasn’t young and her hair was gray.
Then she went in, and I finally went to go in.
Then when I went in, I found that there was a man in there laying on a bed that wasn’t elevated.
When he saw me, he watched me and asked what I was there for.
I shook his hand.
He looked at me and asked, "What’s this? Where are you from?"
Then I told him that I was from Kwethluk.
When I said I was from Kwethluk, you see, he stayed still then got up from his bed.
When he got up, I sat across there across from him.
At that time, I didn’t understand that.
Without a small voice, he said to me, "Person of Kwethluk, the people of Kwethluk."
After he said, "The people of Kwethluk," he talked about the poeple of Kwethluk.
He knew some of them.
He knew some of the ones I knew, and didn’t know some of them
Because apparently, he wouldn’t come to Kwethluk often.
He talked about when he came.
They always invited him to eat, they never let him stop.
Ask him to stop for a second. The battery is low.
Okay.
Are there no more great hunters these days?
He asked, are there no more great hunters these days?
Around these parts?
This time.
There’s no more what?
He asked, are there no more great hunters?
Well
People back then, I know.
There’s going to be no more of the ones I observed back then.
Only one small man.
Do you know Nutarar? Do you know Amaqlicuar?
He’s become a little old man, got small. That’s him.
The elder of Kwethluk. There is no other elder.
Only [?] who are all young.
That’s him.
And just now, I went out and saw the poor guy sitting outside outside of the store.
He’s gotten small. How big is he now?
He had a lot of family, but [families] pass away.
But he has a woman for companion down there, his sibling.
I saw them when there was a lot of them.
They were mostly men.
They weren’t sedentary, were never sedentary. They would always travel when people always hunted.
And the poor one over there who stays all by himself
Ayapan’s child, Cucuaq.
He also had a mother that was the female relative of Amaqlicuar.
That’s what I know. I knew him
He had a younger sibling, Anerniralria.
Some days, he would play with me and I would go to his house.
He would walk around no different from myself. I would play with him.
Then Olenka.
(Do these young people...) The mother of that one who stays all by himself...
Oh, okay.
These days, do young people not hear traditional wisdom anymore, and why?
Indeed, they don’t hear about traditional wisdom anymore.
Why?
They don’t hear people teaching anymore.
For us a long time ago, you see, whenever we did any little thing, these two would start speaking.
Now, they don’t know about traditional wisdom.
They only tell them in church.
And this Yup’ik language, it seems that some elders say that it’s like it’s slowly getting lost.
Because it the ancient language of us Yupiit.
When the churches first came a long time ago, and brought forth this Bible
And they showed it to these Yupiit to try to make them understand.
They said that when Yupiit understood it, they found that that Bible was the same as traditional Yup’ik wisdom and traditions.
I mean, Yupiit...