Hello, I’m Mike Williams. I came from Akiak here.
But I work with mental health services.
Some time ago, we held a large gathering here to talk about traditional Yup’ik medicine
September 17 - 21st.
We met with this in mind: to strengthen our way of life in our lives here.
To improve these things here
To have our young people learn about the old Yup’ik way of life.
Also, we want to take care of and work on Yup’ik medicine that they used in their lives long ago.
They should learn about these old Yup’ik healers
Yup’ik acupuncturists, and the things they used back then
And write and put down these plants so that we will know them.
Also, we should learn these.
We should teach and learn these things that Yupiit used as medicine.
We also want these hospitals to use these kinds of medicine that Yupiit used
Here around us.
We also want these white people that came from downstates who work inland in the hospital to know about these kinds of Yup’ik medicine.
And these elders, those who’ve become old men and old women
We want their care to be better here
We also looked at how we don’t want them to be sent away from here.
Now, Noel Polty who came from the Yukon here, will explain to us what Yupiit used as medicine.
Now, I’m going to say something true that I have experienced.
These things that I’ve scattered here are Yup’ik medicine.
I’ve taken them. I’ve taken all of them.
I’m also taking these pills here.
I am taking all of these together now. You see them.
These are [?] pills, and these are [?].
These will especially help a sick person. I am telling it without hiding it.
Okay, then the wormwood here, we see these now.
You’ve seen these wormwood plants before. Here they are.
If you have pains, if you have pains here on your body
Take this part off like this
After removing it, and if you want to pour tea on it, put it where the pain is and wrap it.
Use them to treat your body pains.
And if you have a lot of room, put that here too.
Personally, after I steep these in water as they are like this, I apply them here like this.
I used them like this.
They help me.
When this is in pain, I use these. Here they are.
This, after drying it and it gets dry like this one
When it gets dark like this [one], when it gets dark like this
Then crumple it like this. After crumpling it, add in Wesson oil.
Take this off a part of it and put it on an infected wound like this if it’s infected, and cover it.
All night, it will remove, pull out the infection inside right away.
And nothing [else] needs to be done, doesn’t need to be cleaned since it was pulled out.
Also, if your body here is itching like this, itching terribly
After putting this in hot water, use it to wipe like this, wipe one’s body like this.
Also, if our heads are itching, tending to [?], put this kind here like this.
After putting it here, one should put a canvas on it and sleep all night.
He will wake up the next morning with that having pulled out the infection from his head in his sleep.
You know this, you know, that leaf tobacco, "cuyaq."
If one also has a big wound, if some person has a wound, or else if it’s two inches long
If there are no doctors, but if he has these blackbull leaves with him
Without any other alternative, after filling that tobacco leaf with water, if he also puts it there and binds it
When it gets slack, when it gets white, it will not bleed.
It will also heal well.
And this, when we had toothaches, you know, when we had toothaches as small boys
We would take a piece of beaver castor, and they would have us bite it down on our teeth.
We used those for toothaches.
Also, a long time ago, along with using it for toothaches
I had these two smell this scent, the beaver castor scent.
There were two of them, this one smelled them, and the one over there smelled them.
They smell the same like that, and they’re like Western toothpaste.
They also numb them like that.
You see these, this black thing. You see, this is black.
They’re what they call beach greens, the odiferous things they use from the land.
They smell strongly of those, and they’re good to eat, [?] very much.
If a person has a sore throat, his throat bothering him, if he has nothing as he travels in the wilderness
He should eat one of these, and swallow its juice.
Also, if one has a cold, if he is lost, when he eats this, though he eats and swallows it
It will emanate a scent inside
Like those, you know how Vicks emanates a strong scent? This will emanate a scent like that.
They call these beach greens.
Then these too
These especially.
These are different. You see these here.
This here is fresh.
This is freshly boiled. This is the liquid from this [plant]. This is what it’s like when fresh.
This is the male and female parts of wormwood.
It is potent when they’re boiled together.
And it has this color because it’s not fresh, because it was dried.
These two, if a person has stomach problems inside, if something in his stomach is bothering him
And if he has stomach pains, or has a bad cough, or if his back here is bothering him
Or if he has malignant growths, those itchy malignant growths
If he doesn’t eat this, not as it is, if he boils it and drinks from here
If he drinks as the one across there said this morning, drinks in the morning, and drinks in the evening.
Then if he finds that too weak, he should add these like this
If someone drinks from here, if he drinks one cup from here, he will get dizzy.
These are strong when added together like this, with this added in.
But though it’s strong, when a person gets used to it, he drinks it as if thirsting for it.
Personally, I always drink a cup every morning, only from this potent one.
Look at me now.
I had been underweight, now I put some on from this.
I feel the full effects of these [traditional] medicine and these pills working together.
Then this is like these two, boiled like this. This has been boiled.
Some peopel from here call them trees, and we call them willow shoots, those willow shoots out there that moose eat.
Then boil it like this also.
To children, this is also very potent to children.
If he has sores, and cannot use his mouth, immediately pour it in his mouth, and it’s fine if he swallows it.
Use this for children with sores, and pour it on the sores that he has on his body, pour it even if they bleed.
It will also heal him right away.
And we adults, though we are adults, sometimes our mouths get sores as we go.
We drink, and we’re immediately not thirsty anymore. Using these is strong, potent.
Also, if a person’s body is itchy, like this too, like this
He will use it on his body when he takes a steam bath, or on his head..
And you know how their hands are so itchy like this that they can’t take anything like this.
Wash them in this as well, then after washing them, you don’t need to apply anything, just wash them like that.
This kind will also heal it, the, you know, willow shoot broth.
This is what I think:
These Caucasians would give us [?] shots. When we have various sicknesses, they look at our ailment and give us shots.
Then I think
These, this is like [?], the shot they give, because it has many uses.
It also heals some who are sick. It also sometimes quickly heals those that it is meant to heal.
But if that person believes in it like this
Like me, I highly value this wormwood here because it helps me.
I like to drink it, [beliving] it as much as those shots, because it helps.
Like that, Caucasians also value the [?] shot because it helps them.
Those [plants] also help me.
If these kinds of medicine work together, Western medicine, and our medicing, you see, it’s good.
Do not belittle Yup’ik [medicine], and do not belittle Western ones.
Me personally, I think like this:
These are God’s creations, having them grow on the land.
The land is filled only with what God created.
God made these to help us Yupiit, so that we could use them for healing and medicine.
We look for the successful ways to use them by ourselves.
Through that, we must use them like that.
Through what we made, I cannot make wormwood.
This is God’s creations for me to use, and for all of you to use.
Okay, I want to thenk Dela Keetz who came from Kotzebue in the [Iñupiaq] Malimiut region to show us these
Yes, their [traditional] medicine.
I thank her for showing us these.
I’m Dela Keetz from... my hometown is Noatak
Around 75 miles from Kotzebue, inland.
I’m Dela Keetz from Noatak, 75 miles away from Kotzebue..
My family and I moved to Kotzebue in 1963.
But the people don’t know. I never try to show to the people the way I always help people at home.
I work at home, my hometown, try to help people all my life.
But though I was there and helped people, they didn’t know me
Because I work at home in our village.
Because I try to help people, I am thankful when they get better, as if it were my own body.
My heart, always happy, just like I have a joy, happy all the time.
They’re just like my own body.
That’s why I love to help people, anyplace wherever I go.
I doesn’t been trained.
I never trained in the hospital, or in no place.
Just by my own experience, and from the books I’ve read when I’m in school.
I was so interested.
I wasn’t trained, and I wasn’t trained in the hospital, or in other places.
But I work with what I know from the books I’ve read in school.
And with what little I understood when I read about what I found interesting and fun
Because we didn’t grow up speaking English.
When sometime happen to us, when it’s injured or accident or anything
We should help this way or that way.
Especially, be clean.
But when we started reading, when our teacher had us start reading
I used to be interested in how our bodies work, or how they work when we get into accidents or get hurt
And how we can be helped.
And how to take care of them, or if they have large wounds.
More importantly, they were instructed to work with clean hands.
That’s the way I learned.
Even though I didn’t write them down, I remember them.
I also always remember what the teacher had us read.
When I try to help people through that, I try to help them through those things that are in my mind.
I never forget it. It’s in my mind all the time.
That is why I always help people when they need help.
I’ve got lot of things
Just a lot of things to say.
But what I do, I learned from myself.
I hurt myself one time and fell over.
And I’ve never went through that way where I fell.
...in my life.
I shoudl be careful when I use ulu or knife when I cut.
Then when I get cut usuing an ulu or a [Western] knife, I am also careful the next time I use them like that.
Just like that.
And when I hurt on myself
Like one time...
Once, when we were playing, I hurt myself.
When we had a wide mouth contest, I opened my mouth too far trying to win.
...make more wider mouth like this.
And I so want to win.
I open my mouth wide, and I can’t close it.
It’s [?], it’s [?].
I try, I try to talk, I can’t talk.
And I couldn’t fix my mouth, and I couldn’t speak.
Then without the knowledge of people, I [?worked on] my jaw though it hurt.
So then I push it out while I was open...
I pulled them, then when I pushed again, they went right in.
I put it back in.
So, I know how to work on it.
I also know how to set jaws back like that.
Once, they called me to go help in Shaktoolik from Kotzebue.
Then when I went to Shaktoolik, because that happened to a girl there
Because their health aide, their nurse, could set [her jaw] back, (s)he had her go to Nome.
It may have been three days that her mouth was open, unable to eat or speak.
I traveled with her. When I arrived at Nome, I foudn that her mouth was open and she couldn’t speak.
She couldn’t fix her mouth.
There were women there, and a lot of children, and they were even crying.
Water running.
She can’t talk. She can’t close his [her] mouth.
And then there was ladies with lot of babies.
"Who’s this baby is this?" "That was mine," a young girl say. "You better take this crybabies out."
I asked whose child was the one that was crying.
One of the young girls said it was her child.
It turned out that it was the one who took the place of the nurse in Shaktoolik.
When I told her to take her child out because I didn’t want to work in a noisy environment, she took [the child] out.
Apparently, she was curious about how to set [the girl’s] jaw back.
Take her out running next door.
Before [s]he come back, I fix it already.
"Ah, you fix it already? I was going to catch you [?]."
I show him [her] how to. She so want to see me; she so want to watch.
But before she came back, I fixed them again.
Then when she came back, I instructed her how to set a jaw back if that happens.
Just as you hold a small spoon to put sugar in your cup, hold the jaws to the side like that.
And hold their head tight.
Pull it outward. They set right back when doing that.
Just lift it up little bit. It’s easy.
Don’t have to sent it to, way off to hospital.
Don’t have them go to the hospital.
Then one time, when they held a large gathering in Anchorage, they chose me to speak.
Then I spoke about what to do when your shoulder gets dislocated.
And I talked about when you hurt your shoulder.
If you hurt this side, left side, can’t lift your arm, be hurt, it’s hurt, don’t want to lift alright.
If you hurt your left side like that, [unable] to lift your arm up
It may be painful, but if you don’t want to go to the doctor, you can pull it up with your other arm and set it
Because I’ve done that.
I hurt my shoulder
Then I tried to pull it up as I was standing. I pulled it up with my other arm, and it set.
Then I kept it limp.
Then I moved it around.
When I tried that, it got better, got set back in.
You can do it by yourself like that too.
When they held their meetings, one of the men fell on the stairs, hurting his shoulder.
He remembered it, "Didn’t Dela tell us to do that?"
Then when he tried to set it, he set it back there where the people who went to the meeting were lodged.
Now, I also want to tahnk Marcelas williams who came from Native American territory downstates, a Native American healer.
He will also talk to us about these, but Joe Albright will provide translations.
...villages along the creeks, that’s where these medicine things grow.
He siad that back when they were going inland to the villages, they settled on the riverbanks, because those medicinal plants grew on the riverbank.
When the white man found us there, they called us Cree Indians because we live by the creeks.
He said that when these white people found them, they called them River People
Because they were setlled by the rivers back there.
If you have some children, infants, sometimes look at the base of the spine.
And if they got a blue spot right on the base of the spine, right along in here, then you and I are related.
Then, he said that if you watch your children
Here on their backs right above their midsection down there, if you see a blue spot
He said to know that we are related to them through that.
Don’t look mine. He’s too old.
He said not to look at his clothes.
The little guys. Look at the little ones.
Everywhere, wherever you go, all kinds of people, black, yellow, brown, white, blue, green, or whatever
We all share something in common: we are either healthy or sick.
He said that everywhere on the land, or if you go anywhere in the world
He said no matter what people are like, even if their skin is black or white
He said they’re the same. And what they’re like, they all suffer from sickness.
Even among white people, there are different kinds of white people within that group.
And even though we call these people white, they’re not exactly the same.
They’re not of the same origin. The ones we call white are not the same.
To ones in Washington, D.C., we call them from the Paper Tribe.
Everything is done on paper, [?] and all that.
He said that the people from the city downstates that he mentioned, they’re called the Paper Tribe
Because they work with [official] paper[work].
There are some referred to as hillbillies, and they also have folk ways, folk medicine.
It seemed that he called what we hear about a hillbilly
They are part of the ones who practice [folk] medicine.
[?] of mankind exist wherever they live.
They always learn something from their area.
He said that everywhere on the land, they are the same in that they can learn something of their land.
If all of my people moved over here in this part of Alaska, they’d all probably starve to death this next winter.
He gave an example. He said that if his people moved here to our lands, they’d probably starve to death.
And if you all came to my country, you might melt.
And he said that if we went to his lands, we would probably melt.
But in this time, we learn to adjust, we learn to adapt, we learn to live off the land.
We learn for things that you can eat, thigns that you can use for medicine.
But he said that even if it doesn’t happen right away, a person keeps learning slowly.
He can also learn what he can eat from the land
Or he will also learn what he can use as medicine from there
In the workshop we’ve been having, attending
Each one has some knowledge about the land, and we’ve been sharing this knowledge all week.
Now, as we’ve been having these meetings, we’ve been hearing about what people know and have learned
The things people found out and learned about in their lands.
I’d like to just stay on for a long time and learn many of your ways.
For instance, we have lots of teachings in my tribe, similar to yours.
When a woman is expecting a child, when she goes out the door and changes her mind, we tell her not to turn around at the doorway.
Go on through, and then come back in.
Now, he wants to stay here from a long time so that he can learn.
As he’s been listening now, he sometimes recognizes his people’s teachings and instructions back home
And what he talked about today, it is in accordance to our ancestors instructions here.
He used this as an example:
He said that back at his home downstates, his people have this traditional instruction:
When a young lady is pregnant before giving birth, if she things of going out, then changes her mind about wanting to go out
Ignoring her change of mind, they tell her to go right out.
He said his ancestors have that traditional instruction.
We have learned much from the white man, good and bad.
He said that we’ve learned much from these white people among us, good and bad all the same.
Among all people, there are some good, there are some bad.
He said it’s like that, with people being different among their own.
He said that people are like that, as he said.
If we look for something bad in other people, that will be easy to do. There’s something bad in all of us.
But it’s another thing to look for something good. It’s the better way.
Then, he said that if we [?] those around us [?looking] for something bad to be shown in those around us
He said that’s easy.
But there is also a place for something good.
Another thing that we all have in common is destruction
By nature, and by man-made destruction.
He said that we will find out and hear about this.
It’s been shown that a person can be destoryed through something
Or that he cane by destroyed by man-made things.
In nature’s destruction, there’s floods, tornadoes, hurricanes, earthquakes, fire, and things like that.
He just mentioned the ways that people can be destroyed through natural phenomena
Through those, earthquakes, and volcanic eruptions.
Through those, or through floods, people can be destroyed through those.
Man-made destructions, there’s a lot of things. The list is too long.
There’s bombs, [?war ?].
World powers can’t live together. They must try to dominate one another.
He said that there are different ways people can be destroyed by these man-made things.
Many people are also destroyed through bombs, or through war.
Trying to take over and dominate those around them, many people are destroyed through that.
This earth on which we live is known as a planet. It is a planet.
He said that our land where we live, I don’t know how to translate it.
But if I say it, you students will recognize it. The place we live is called a planet.
There are nine in what we call solar system.
There are nine planets in this area around the sun.
He said there are nine planets like ours here around the sun.
So far as we know now, this is the only planet that has life.
He said that in all of their examinations, though there are that many
He said that where we live now is the only one that supports life.
With all the different people over our earth
We have a very unique place. This earth is very special.
The Great Ones above saw to it that this will be a special place for man to live in.
He said that as they examined our world
And though the other planets like where we live now are planets
But the One Above who watches over us knows that this place of ours is the only one viable to live in.
Many people refer to this earth as Mother Earth.
He said that many people refer to our earth here as a Mother.
My tribe has an endearing term. We call it Grandmother Earth.
And his people call it Grandmother Earth.
It makes us sad many times to see our Grandmother’s face all spot up, gouged out, without putting anything good back into it.
He said that when this Grandmother is mistreated and [?gouged]
It’s sad to see.
Every little thing has life. Even a little blade of grass, a little weed has life.
Little tiny bugs, animals, birds, fish, everywhere there’s life all around, and we respect them.
He said that everything we see on this land where we live
He said that everything, even plants or little birds, everything has life.
They’re alive.
He said that we who know about them treat them with respect.
I have learned much from the people from different villages.
They have learned much from this Mother Earth, something they can use in what we call Yup’ik medicine.
He said that as we’ve been meeting, he has learned a lot that has been demonstrated through different peoples
The plants that grow on Mother Earth that are useful for us who populate this earth.
The white man has a word called "poverty."
He said that our white counterparts have a word that he just said in their language, "poverty."
In my understanding, if I’m not understanding it wrong, it means to be poor.
Poverty usually means somebody without means, income, money.
Since poverty means to be poor as I just explained
It’s a word used for someone who is short on everything, one who lacks.
But there is another poverty:
If you have no old people for many knowledge that they have, they don’t share and go on and
We are left without nothing, without guidance.
That would be a terrible poverty.
He also said that a person may be poor in worldly things, being short on [material] riches.
But, he said that this is another part of how a person can be poor:
When many elders do not explain to their descendants things that they should learn, that they should know.
He said that’s part of being poor.
If you sit in on meetings, you will find that you are very rich.
If you could sit in on our meetings, hearing these people share their knowledge
You will find that you are very rich to have people with this kind of knowledge.
He said that if you listen to the poeple who’ve been speaking as we’ve been meeting that we’ve been listening to
He said that you would find through that it’s like we are rich.
People have been explaining things they are knowledgeable about and know since we’ve started.
Through a person’s knowledge like that, he will be like a rich person.
In sickness, it usually is in the body or in the mind.
He said that in sickness, a person is sick either in his body or in his mind.
There is another part of us to make us whole, and that is the soul of man.
He said that we have one thing of our own.
If you know the ancestors’ concept, you will recognize the soul.
We explain that as the part of us that doesn’t die.
We rely great things upon what this soul tells this body and this mind to do.
He said that many times, we depend on our soul
Including when we think about the things we sorely need something.
We feed our bodies, clothe it, wash it.
We exercise our mind. But what about this soul?
He said that we do things to our body to protect it, feed and groom it.
But, he said, what are we going to do with the part of us that doesn’t die?
This soul, in most every one of us, have experienced poverty
Because we don’t nourish it, we don’t feed it, we don’t exercise it.
He said that many times, we cause our soul to be destitute
Only because we don’t feed it.
As I look around form the very smallest to the very oldest, all of us have souls, and you are beautiful.
He said that as he watches from here, from your very little children to your elders, he said that all of you have souls.
He also said you’re beautiful.
All of us have much to contribute, much to give, all of us
And be helpful to one another.
He said that all of us can help those around us
And we all have gifts we can use to help those around us.
There was a story of a man who worked on the railroad, come home every other day.
He said that there’s a story of a person who worked on the railroad.
He said that that person only returned home every other day.
He had three children: one boy, a girl, and another small boy.
He said that that person had two male children, and a girl was the third.
The two older children, the boy and the girl, when they see their dad coming home
They run out into the field, pick pretty flowers to give to their daddy.
Then he said that when the two elders of his children, the boy and the girl, [?].
He said that when their father came into view, they’d go out to meet him.
Then he said that they would pluck out pretty flowers, and give their father [flowers].
The little boy was paralyzed from waist down. He could not walk or run.
He said that that youngest boy’s waist was paralyzed.
He couldn’t walk around like the other two.
And little pieces of wood.
When the older boy and girl get the flowers picked
They’d run to meet daddy. "Here, I picked this for you," and give it to him.
He said that because the first two were active and healthy
After taking flowers from there, they would run to meet their father
Telling him that they’re giving him [flowers[, that they had picked them for him.
When dad walked into the yard
This little boy that can’t run, can’t walk, wanted to give something too, little dirty stick, little dirty rocks.
But in his own way, "Here, daddy, here."
He said that because their youngest sibling unfortunately couldn’t do as his siblings
Without meeting his father when he appreaed, he would gather those little rocks and little sticks.
He said that he only extended his hand to give his father those gifts when he arrived.
That’s why I say everyone has something to give one another
If that one thing that we can give is love from our hearts.
That’s why he just said this:
All of us, with no exceptions, every one of us has gifts to give those around us.
He said that this [is what we can give] if we have no other gifts: only to treat those around us with love.
It iis love that unites us together.
Regardless of color, we eat.
When he pray, he pray to God, "Thank you for this."
When you partake of this food, each one, even a small portion, partake of it
We all became blessed as one people.
Then he used this as an example of how we are united, though we act as if we are separate:
There were a lot of different foods here, all completely different
But he spoke of my prayer to God, being thankful for this food and asking for the to be blessed before we received them.
Then even though they were completely different, all of us who partook in that received the things that were blessed for us.
Many times, I feel lonely. I’m not along, but I feel onely sometimes.
I have a father that died first.
And then my son was killed when he was 17 years old.
My mother lived to be over 100 years old
And I buried her not too long ago.
They’re waiting for me.
But until that day comes when I will go to meet them
I want to make the most of this life while I’m still living here today.
He said that now, he sometimes feels lonely and sad.
He said it’s because he had a father, and his father passed away.
He knows [?], he knows that they’re waiting for him.
But, he said that what exacerbates [his loneliness] is that he had a son who was killed when he was 17 years old.
Then, he said that he had a mother who eventually reached 100 years old.
He said that he recently buried his mother, but he knows she’s waiting for him.
That’s why he said that he awaits the day when he will see those that he misses so dearly.
He said that for that reason, he has a desire to work as much as he can on the earth while he’s alive.
You have helped to fill the emptiness in my heart
And I am grateful, and I thank God for all of you.
He said that he speaks of this now:
He said that it truly seems that you have filled what was empty [in his heart].
He said that for that reason, he thanks God for that.
God bless you, one and all.
May God bless you all.
Okay, now I will go over what we established when we held our large gathering.
We established these meetings where the ones who would speak to people would gather.
Also, if we in these villages start having these elders become instructors
These old men would speak to these young men
And these old women would also instruct these young women about our way of life.
We also want these schools to do this, without refraining from doing so:
We want them to teach about our people’s lives back then.
We also want YKHC to greatly consider the negative effects of alcohol
Because it is a problem.
We also want to improve [the care of] the elders here around us.
We want the care of our elders here in the villages around us to improve.
Also, these people marry close relatives and have abnormal children.
We also met about how we don’t want these people to marry those to whom they are too closely related.
We also met about how we want these people to keep holding meetings.
We will not repeatedly meet about these Yup’ik types of medicine.
We also met to work on Yup’ik instruction for people.
I want to thank these people who came.
We also want to thank the people from Chevak who Yup’ik danced for us.
I also want to thank these people:
Kay Nukacuaq who came from Kipnuk
Edith Kawagley from Akiak
Wassilie Evan from Akiak
Betty Onton from Newtok
Lucille Westlock from Emmonak
Joseph Qilanaq from Chefornak
Helen Smith from Hooper Bay
Joseph Olsen from Hooper Bay
Paul Beebe, Quinhagak
Annie Patsy, Mountain Village
Mary Andrews, Mountain Village
Phillip Foxy, Qerrullik, Kotlik
Jasper Lewis, St. Mary’s
Noel Polty, Pilot Station
And Gusty [?McKell] who came from Stony River.
I also want to thank those who work at KYUK because they helped us a lot.
I also want to thank other people who’ve helped.
Thank you for listening to these traditional Yup’ik medicine.