This hand has become dextrous, and this is getting dextrous.
Oh, thank goodness. (Yes.)
But now, they are too weak to grab things, unlike before.
That’s why I don’t grab anything heavy.
But my dear grandchild takes care of me.
Where’s he from?
My grandchild is from here.
He has a mother. His mother has a house down there.
He’s my grandchild.
Last year, I was not comfortable with this when it was paralyzed.
It was weak.
Even now, I am still careful about grabbing anything heavy with it.
I wonder what would’ve happened to you if he didn’t take you to the hospital?
I don’t know. Well...
...now, get a good shot, and...
What’s your Yup’ik name?
I’m Cuukvak.
My late mother would always call me Cuukvak.
We will show these story about cloudberries and how they pick berries in recent times
How people pick berries for Eskimo ice cream.
There you have it.
Did you also do that when you were small?
Me, my mother was alive, and my sister was alive, Mary Evon’s grandmother down there
I’m related to those dear ones down there.
She’s their grandmother. Their grandmother.
Their mother is my older sister’s adopted older sister.
Would you pick berries?
Yes, we would pick berries.
Oh my, I would wish to go with them as a little girl.
My mother would refuse me saying that I would start crying and that I was too slow.
I would sometimes stay behind.
When I was insistent sometimes, she would take me with her.
How would you travel to pick berries long ago?
Long ago, we would travel only by walking.
Down toward the water from Bethel, there was a large expansive sandbar.
And the creek here was Kepenkuyagaq. Then toward the water from there was the Kuskokwim.
Because it was a big sandbar, we would go downriver under Ekvik.
And through there, since there was a path up toward the water from the hospital that was shoveled
We would go up through there.
And then when they went home, they would go upriver under Ekvik again no other way but walking.
How did they make their first Eskimo ice cream? What did they use to make Eskimo ice cream?
They would make Eskimo ice cream out of, you know, a little tallow.
And people I used to see back then would render tallow.
It turned out that my mother would be the one to make Eskimo ice cream during dance festivals.
As I was playing, I would go into that little house, a little food cache, to find my mother making Eskimo ice cream.
She would help by bringing something for the people in the community house.
Okay, when the men would stay in the community house long ago, would you prepare their food?
When they asked me to invite people from the community house as a little girl, I would constantly invite the wrong people.
When Agayuur’s wife asked me to invite him from the community house
Because there were a lot of people sleeping in the community house, I would wake a random one.
They would wake up and this would be a different person.
I would then tell him that Oscar was invited.
They would then go to him. I would go out and leave them.
How did they prepare, I mean, how did they store the berries that they picked?
They would store them in containers, then put them into barrels.
They prepared the berries they picked for storage in barrels
So that they wouldn’t be affected by anything repulsive.
Yet all winter, the people back then would always make Eskimo ice cream.
They would feed us Eskimo ice cream.
Would they make them with different things?
Yes. (Separately?)
What?
Would they make some of them differently?
I don’t know. Well...
The cranberries would be a little different
As I have seen, when I took a husband and started traveling in the Akula region, I would pick cranberries.
As I have seen, I would put it fish roe, you know, even pike roe.
I would put in fish roe and crush them in a bowl, completely crush the roe.
And then when it was time, I would add cranberries
Then I would crush the cranberries.
Then I would whip it to have it increase in volume occasionally adding a little seal oil.
It would increase and fill the old wooden bowl with a lot of Eskimo ice cream.
Would they say...
They called those qerpertat.
Do they still seem to make it today?
Yes, they still make some today.
They make it because they know how to.
Do you get cloudberries now?
Ever since I’ve stopped picked berries, I haven’t gone, and I’ve stopped going to berry picking grounds now.
But when my grandchild and the others arrived and brought me cranberries they picked in that container, I made that as I’ve seen it.
I made qerpertaq as I’ve seen it. I knew how.
Do those have different names?
Or, here are the different names for Eskimo ice cream:
Yes.
Crushed fish eggs and berries
But what’s tenguggluk?
Tenguggluk is made from fish guts, salmon liver.
And then cutting some of their parts
After whipping the livers for tenguggluk
How does it go?
They squeeze the small fish livers then whip them.
Do you get it?
(Yes.) They would fill the bowl, add berries, and mix it.
But they would add seal oil.
I see. (Okay.)
Do you have anything else to add?
I’m not sure.
I don’t think I have anything else to add. (Okay, thank you very much.)
As I have seen, when I got married and we started traveling
I would try to pick cranberries when my children were alive.
I would also be worried about them and pick cranberries.
However, I would crush them to make Eskimo ice cream.
We and the children loved together along with Lloyd, Old Man Lloyd and his wife.
Lloyd Nick and his wife.
We also lived together with Helen and her daughter.
And then when I was making Eskimo ice cream somewhere here
Those children would come here to sit and watch, occassionally tasting it.
And when I added berries to it, they started eating. I ignore them and made the Eskimo ice cream without saying anything to them.
I would say to them, "Stop when you’ve had enough Eskimo ice cream. This is almost done."
Thank you. (Yes.) Thank you very much. (Yes.)
After I set it down there, I would look back and go out.
My male cousins would say to me, "Dance, dear ones."
Oh my, I wouldn’t raise my hands to dance but go out and disappear.
What does ingulak mean? What explanation does the practice of ingulak have? What is it?
They hold the Ingulaq Festival towards fall like this.
I’m not sure what it means. I myself don’t know.
(Would they do it after cloudberry season?) Yes, after cloudberry season.
But there was a lot of Eskimo ice cream in the community house.
They would always take them to the community house.
Even though there were a multitude of guests, they wouldn’t lack anything.
Would they know how much berries they picked by making a lot?
Yes.
I see.
Is that all?
Yes, thank you very much.
You didn’t ask me to speak too much.