When spring starts, we’re going to talk about that.
When those playful times are over when spring starts like this
Those who were going to travel like this, those people long ago
who were going to travel
This was our first tradition for the young ones who did not have kayaks yet
When we were boys, they were the same as these helpers
Even though [the orphans] also played
Even though they played during this time, they didn’t for a long time.
This, being hungry like this, made us [return home].
And then we children here
When one of these hunters happened to catch ringed seals
we would be extremely excited
Because we would be full for a time.
However, we would gather there in the community house
where we would listen to traditional wisdom.
One who caught ringed seals would bring the stomachs
to the community house.
That was also accompanied by berries cooked in blood.
Every one of us in the villages would be extremely excited for that.
Another tradition among those hunters was that
they did not waste any of their things.
When they hunted them, it was like they were hunting
for their people, their villages.
And then those who had become elders especially
supported their youth who were trying to make a living.
They wholeheartedly supported them.
After they worked with them all winter with their traditional wisdom
They would wholehearted support them, not wanting those
who were trying to make a living feel defeated.
You see, a long time ago, back when we were growing up,
they were not like how it is now.
They didn’t have everything available to them.
And in the mornings like this, we would not get up being satisfied [with sleep].
Back when we were struggling for food and tools,
we were not like how people are now
But we grew up being pitiful back when we were growing up.
We didn’t even have a lot of clothes.
Instead, we who had no fathers carried a lot of sorrow.
We did not succumb to our minds, but were persistent and obedient
We were in need of teachers for how to do well when we grew up.
Back then, hunting was only for men.
We also wanted to be like those who were somehow good hunters.
But the people back then lived very hard lives
back when we were growing up.
They also used to envy those big bearded seals down from the ocean.
Those elders back then would not have us be lazy
in the winter before we made our own living back then.
Especially in the winter like this, we would always have a shovel
obeying their traditional wisdom.
We only tried to keep putting animals to catch in our future.
They would let the minds of those who were on the verge of becoming
hunters convince them to live life easy, but they would
urge those who were stubborn.
We also did not think about being paid with money,
but thought about how we would be paid with food to eat in the future.
You see, it does not make one disinclined when one
is hardworking or fixes things
And even if these doors weren’t ours, we would also help with their doors.
Everything we did was to help others, those around us,
who were trying to survive.
We did that so that they would uplift us in their minds.
It would be true,
I also do that now when I am grateful like this,
when someone helps me and makes me grateful
I do not wish for them to feel defeated, but I push them
to do well in my mind.
If you do that, wisely being hardworking, your time to
make your own living is well on its way.
That will help whomever is wise.
When these people [have sexual relations with girls within a year of their
first menstrations], you know, the paths becomes bad for hunters, and there
is no path to go to hunting grounds.
It is as though that is correcting that within us
so that we could make our own living.
That’s how we grew up back then, obeying instructions
without succumbing to our mind’s desire for an easy life.
Since we did not succumb to our mind’s desire, that helped our bodies.
That used to be of help.
But when we were clumsy when were striving to be hardworking
sometimes, we would be emotionally pained as we tried to make a living.
We didn’t sit like this when we traveled back then.
These days, you young people are becoming spoiled.
It’s also because you sit when traveling.
However, if your parents and fathers somehow do not raise you
[in the old way] like that, some of you probably will not do that.
But if you [are afraid of] that, you may definitely be like your parents.
He just told you about what would be useful.
After experiencing it, those teachers would
talk about it after using it.
And this traditional wisdom is not new.
It has come from a long time ago.
And we who try to pass on that traditional wisdom,
it has also come to us.
That traditional wisdom from a long time ago.
This traditional wisdom comes from a long time ago
Because this traditional wisdom is for improvement,
self improvement for us, and improvement for you young people.
And so, we will not move to subsisting down in the ocean,
how to subsist.
We will also point out how their tools worked,
their handmade tools.
The things they used when they subsisted.
And then, you young people who are obedient here,
I am going to add this:
We are reluctant to part with you young people when you’re
going to travel, as if you are going to come back from over there.
And then, you must travel like that, trying not to destroy the future
you have yet to come to, trying not to destroy it.
Some young people here destroy themselves now.
No person destroys him, but he destroys himself.
He also destroys himself including his future
that he has yet to experience.
For youpl, they are not [fun] even though there are a lot.
If youpl¬ want to live according to our2 traditional wisdom,
our traditional wisdom [is not fun] even though there
are a lot now.
Even if you do not use them sometimes as you adhere to them,
if you get lonely, your minds will be filled with what
you must use, what you must strive to use.
However, if you try to hold on to everything fun, you will not
gain anything, and your minds will not be filled [with wisdom].
Now, when those who help us, your fathers, go down to the ocean,
youpl¬ probably hope that they would catch some of this food.
Food becomes scarce these days, these days.
You can’t do anything anymore. And sometimes, you can’t play.
Also, when these strong hunters, those who are strong without stopping,
even though they are not without food these days, they become skinny.
However, as they were standing on their legs and struggling,
they became like that.
And back then, they would work extremely hard as they struggled.
And when they traveled to villages like this,
they would travel with their kayaks.
Back then, they would chisel a lot of ice.
They would struggle, moving them using their legs,
not sitting like this.
They would use their legs to push forward, even if it wasn’t
always that, even if it wasn’t only for spring seal hunting,
because it was how they survived.
You see, a long time ago, we2…
Back then, before we started hunting by ourselves,
we would always work on subsistence.
We would listen to the teachers telling how how we should be
concerning subsistence.
And then when they started hunting, the ones whom the animals
were afraid of would be revealed when they subsisted.
However, those who did not work on their minds would also
be revealed through their subsistence.
Being incompetent is not enjoyable. I also know that when
I cannot catch food, it is not enjoyable.
They wouldn’t be set up with women, they wouldn’t
take wives before they first caught bearded seals.
But when they caught bearded seals twice like this, this young person
would not keep it twice, but would distribute it among people,
takelmurluku as they call it.
They would do that twice, including the skin.
And then when he gets married, they would be afraid that his wife
would distribute thin skins.
And even though that had been done with two bearded seals like this,
when he takes a wife and catches another bearded seal,
they would have them distribute them including the skin.
We envied those at that time.
But when they had looked for things for themselves, I think they
were like that when guns were scarce, and it seemed that
animals to hunt [were not plentiful].
Also, those days, when the ocean’s wasn’t very deep,
they would also chisel the ice at that time.
And these days, our places where we would stay on the coast
when we traveled down to the seashore where the land would
be far inland is now down in the ocean.
Where we would stay down there is probably a mile out from the shore.
Back then, it wasn’t like how it was now when we
first became observant.
Or, back when they didn’t use guns, when they only harpooned
After they would approach the ice during flooding season,
when the ice was going to come off back when they didn’t use guns
But they would stay ready with their tools.
And then as they were set in place, the animals down there
would start surfacing.
But, they said that they would try to scare it off like this
with their atlatls.
They said that when it would be scared away,
they wouldn’t harpoon it.
However, they said that one that stayed even when they tried to
scare it off, only then would they harpoon it.
That’s what they used to do back then.
And they said that when they surfaced like this, they would be
able to see water dripping from their whiskers.
But at that time, even though they had a lot to catch,
some of them would be in need because they didn’t have tools.
When those hunters would subsist like that back then
They had a lot of suffering, there used to be a lot.
And the walrus bladders that would be filled with water like this,
they would have to keep it warm when they had no more water.
When they had no more water, after filling it with snow,
they would put it against their flesh inside to thaw it.
That’s the only way they would get water before the snow melted.
They had a lot of struggles.
Also, when some of them subsisted like this, this subsistence
is something that came to us from long ago
But it hasn’t come to these people here.
They would use their arms to subsist down in the ocean, using their arms.
But in making their oars, in making what would be their oars,
they would be instructed to make one lighter, and the other larger.
The things they would hold would also increase.
And this gaff, what they call legcik, was essential.
When they did that, even though animals were available
down in the ocean
Even though the animals are available, they sometimes do not get any.
You do not catch anything down there without struggling first.
Only after struggling using his arms, after using them for a long time,
some people who subsist catch them.
And then when they did that, after taking care of his kayak
And then they would struggle, struggle to try to put
their kayaks inland where it’s not dangerous
When they catch those that they hunt.
Then they would put what they had strove to catch
around their kayaks.
And if he’s alone, it would take some of its liver.
He would run to the village with his legs.
But they had snowshoes. They always had snowshoes.
And then the villagers would come out like this,
watching the one who was appearing on foot.
Not one of them wanted to be anywhere else.