You know, some of these children don’t like doing things, and some do.
Oh my goodness.
I should be on [?].
Yes. (Good.) Yes.
Will you ask me questions?
Yes.
I can also speak some English even though I didn’t go to school for long since I used to stay with Caucasians.
Where with Caucasians?
With Cakayak and family, John Samuelson.
I’ll talk about it.
The Caucasians in Nunapitchuk. (Did you grow up with them?)
No, part[ly], only sometimes.
Where? Was the Samuelson family at Nunapitchuk?
Yes, they lived there.
They moved from Nunacuar to Nunapitchuk. There, Cakayak traded.
After he bought that?
He was a prolific trader.
And he had very many of what they called his merchants.
He had a trading post there in Nunapitchuk.
[That was] when Nunacuarmiut exiled him. Villages used to exile people.
And he went to Nunapitchuk.
You know, they exiled people. They probably still exile now, kicking them out as they say in English.
That’s what happened to Cakayak from Nunacuar to Nunapitchuk.
It’s probably different now. It was like that back then.
Why did they exile him?
They exiled him because he would fool around and had many children.
Speak briefly on that.
I won’t talk about it.
Cakayak was good.
Indeed, he bore many children, he sired many children.
That’s why they exiled him.
Villages don’t exile good people.
Only when they do something wrong.
Now, please speak about things you remember back when you were a little girl as you remember it.
I just said that I was born over on Nelson Island, but I don’t know [exactly] where I was born.
Then because they travel like this, you know, move, nunalinqiggluteng
My parents apparently came here to the Kuskokwim.
I’m not sure why they did.
Then in Oscarville, Kuiggayagaq, our older brother was Cakayak’s late father’s, Oscar Samuelson, helper.
And our mother would work on fish there with Oscar Samuelson, Cakayak’s late father.
Then we were there all summer. And when fall set, we went up to Kasigluk in the Akula region.
We were there. You see, I wonder how many years we stayed there in Kasigluk?
Because people were apparently fickle, for our eduction, my parents... those poor people were apparently fickle.
We moved to Nunapitchuk, it turned out because they were going to get a teacher. They didn’t get a school right away.
Back then, what did your parents think of going to school?
Did they support their children having a Western education?
Please talk about what you heard about that.
I don’t know what I heard.
Because my parents probably supported our education, they moved us from Nunapitchuk to Kasigluk.
There was also a village in Nanvarnarrlak over from Nunapitchuk.
Then the school... no, when a school was built, they moved to Nunapitchuk.
Just when we moved there, the teachers were in houses. There was no school.
And we’d have school in the old church inland. It was upriver, upriver from us.
But I wonder how many years? It seems that we went to school in the church for two years or one year.
Then when that old school inland was built, the ones in Number Two from Nanvarnarrlak inland moved to Nunapitchuk.
It was a big village, Number One, Number Two, and they had those names.
Probably because they were supportive, those villages also moved to Nunapitchuk.
Like that.
Now, these elders, and probably your peers, say this:
When they went to school back then, their teachers would tell them not to speak English, I mean no, in Yup’ik.
They were very strict. What did you do?
Like that.
And they’d punish one who spoke [Yup’ik] by sending them to the corner, and they’d face the corner for several minutes.
That’s what they did to us.
Then they also wouldn’t let us eat, no lunch.
Would they eat?
That’s how they would chastise us.
And it seems I also heard, but I never saw.
They said they would be spank them with those things. You know, spank.
I don’t know about them.
Now, it seems that we are more focused on school than when you went to school.
Now? Yes.
They go to school for a long time probably because they focus on it.
Our first teacher then was also Yup'ik.
You know, [?Anrok], Sam [?Anrok]. That one.
[S]he was accompanied with their daughter, Ruth Hall. She became Ruth Hall over there.
They were the first to become teachers in Nunapitchuk. The very first ones, parent and daughter.
Apparently, they came from Unalakleet.
Like that.
That’s how they would chastise them.
And they wouldn’t chew tobacco in  school.
Before we started just now, you said you were going to say something you never heard of.
Yes, we haven’t gotten to that yet.
So now, (Okay.) please talk about it. (Okay.)
I... are you recording me now? Okay.
Okay.
Because people are too wealthy tehse days, you know, since we’re now wealthy, I want to say something.
We were poor.
I was also poor with my parents...
And yet we were happy, we’d eat, just happy.
Yet we were [poor] like that.
There was nothing in our houses.
Only two small boxes down there... and, you see, I didn’t see any shelves.
There’d be two small boxes down there.
You see, my mother would open them when they were going to have hot drinks and take out cups, then we’d have hot drinks on top of them.
And it seemed we wouldn’t was dishes. I don’t know.
Since I’d always visit others, you see, I didn’t take care of them too much.
Then these days, people are excessive.
In Yup’ik... will you translate what I say into English?
You see, I especially want the youth to hear this, but because they always speak English and don’t speak Yup’ik, they won’t understand a lot.
It’s probably fine if I periodically do some of it in English.
These days, our houses are very excessive.
We’re rich right now.
We have everything in the house.
We have everything. It seems we’re Westers, yet we’re Yup’ik.
Then I mostly stayed there with Cakayak and family as a girl, where Johnny Samuelson had a trading post in Nunapitchuk.
You see, his wife wouldn’t do much, you know, seeming to always be careful.
You see, I would always was dishes. And I didn’t have my first menstruations [at] maybe 10 years old, or nine, at that time.
And I’d always wipe [dust] off of things because his wife would tell me to.
Apparently, because they were Caucasian.
Well, half breed, since her husband was half. I’m not sure what his wife was.
I grew up like that.
And when I went home, since I didn’t always stay with my family, when I went home
I would do the same in our house as I did at the Caucasians’.
I would fix these things. Apparently, I’d also dust things out.
You see, I’d do them well.
I learned from them.
These days, there is high school, [and] college.
I think, "These people absolutely know things, including how to clean up inside the house."
That’s what I think. Being like that, I learned it from being among Caucasians.
Then these days, that old lady there in Nunapitchuk apparently wasn’t a very old lady at the time.
I would visit her.
You see, I’d go in and that woman would be steadily washing her dishes.
And she’d steadily wipe her kettles like this on top of her stove.
Then when I went in, since that woman had burnt sugar cantly, you know how people make burnt sugar candy.
It seemed to me that there was no candy back then.
That woman would give me burnt sugar candy, and I’d put it in my mouth.
It tasted sweet and delicious.
That was the reason I’d want to go to that woman.
Sometimes, that would would say to me, "Cuzz," because I was her cousin, "Cuzz, if you became able like me and get married, do what I do.
"Watch, you will have things.
"If you don’t wash things in your house," I was a little girl, "if you leave them, watch, dust will cover them.
"When it eventually gets bad, you don’t keep it anymore and throw it away."
And that may be new, but dust and dirt covers it.
Then it becomes undesirable and you wouldn’t want it anymore.
You see, that’s what she’d tell me.
She also told me this: she grew up somewhere, children’s  home, Moravian home.
It was probably among Caucasians.
She said she learned how to clean up the house from there.
Oh my, these days these teenagers, they’re smart.
They know how to clean up the house. They know how to do everything.
But they just sit and watch TV all day, maybe.
Lazy, never do anything.
There you have it.
That woman who became and old woman’s instruction...
Oh no. Oh my goodness.
It’s okay.
Ready?
She’d say this to me: "Cuzz, watch, someday you’ll get a husband."
Uingelleq, have [a] husband.
"Watch, you will do that.
"Then when you do that, if you don’t wash your things, you won’t have anything.
"And watch, your husband may be a very good hunter, watch, you will be destitute."
That’s what she’d tell me.
It turned out, you see, that things need to be taken care of in the house, you know, need to be taken care of.
These days, I thought I’d become knowledge about that back when I would stay with Cakayak and family.
I had gone to school, but it seems, I mean, since I didn’t go to school for long, I didn’t learn much.
Then these days, they also say this:
"A woman with female children, watch, that woman will watch her mother in the house.
"Then her work and what she does, that woman’s child can copy her."
These [words] are true.
And now, I have nine children, five girls, four boys.
And these five girls are all different. You know, they’re different.
And I love them all very much.
Then when I started making things and started sewing
And my daughters grew up and started making their own living.
I’d keep making them  things and sewing them things.
I’d sometimes go in their houses, and what I sewed would be on the floor. You see, I’d be upset.
It turned out that what was supposed to be kept well was on the floor.
I’d go in one of daughters [and the house is] neat.
Oh my, what I made would be treated with love.
Then when I did that, among the five girls of my children, two of them, I won’t say their names, are neat from what I’ve seen.
Neat, as they say in English.
They’re good. All of them are good.
Then I realized this: those two would take great care of the clothes I sewed.
Since the other especially cares for them, when I go into her house because we see them
In the summer, the things I made by sewing, parkas, fur boots, furs, fur clothes, I never see then in her house during the summer, nothing.
She put[s] them away.
You know, she puts them away.
I know that in the West, fur [clothes] have places, suitable spaces.
It’s not hot, it’s not cold, maybe meduim.
Then their fur is good.
Look, when these skin clothes hang for years and years, they’re no longer suitable to wear [?from wearing out].
And if I take this parka, it rips. [?It wears out].
Then now, I’m speaking about what I don’t hear in these TV’s.
Many would speak of those long ago.
It’s important these days because people are too wealthy, since things are God’s gifts.
Things in the house are God’s gifts.
A woman must take good care of them.
You see, some men do [that].
Now, I have different sons-in-law.
Some of their husbands likes to help their wives.
Some of my children are like that.
Some of their husbands is sedentary.
His wife is hot and works around him.
And her husband doesn’t help her because he’s a man.
It’s because men are supposed to work out there, outside work, and woman in the house, inside work.
But because people are different, my daughters have different kinds of spouses.
Some of their wives, you see, I really like those spouses who take care of their spouses.
My goodness, that person’s so good.
We tell them [that].
They are lovable.
Those who are sedentary like this, how should I say it?
These days, they say, "Weird."
I don’t understand this word "weird."
It seems that one who’s sedentary like that is weird.
You see, when I speak, I add in some silly things.
I especially wanted to talk about this.
How teenagers these days don’t really do anything, I [am] sorry for them.
And their mothers would keep working, while her daughter here lays down and reads.
It’s probably because they’re fluent [enough to read] books.
And some what they call video [games], ding ding ding ding ding.
[S]he sits down for a couople hours when they should work, standing up and helping their mother or father.
I’m speaking of these things.
And because they’re with God, we must take good care of God’s gifts in the house.
That’s what I especially wanted to, you know, talk about because there’s way too much work to be done in a house these days.
It’s unfortunate because we’d eat, and when we’re done, you see, the table would have a mountain of dishes.
Or in the shelves over there, so many dishes to wash.
Then this mother keeps working.