Ah, I will not date him if he has one eye.
I mean it turns out we thought the same thing to the ones he talked to.
These cousins of mine had thought the same as I did.
That's all how we were, poorly.
We believed what were told by speakers without doubting much of it.
There are those who are hard to talk to.  How did they know by observation their journey ahead?
The ones who were hard to talk to were talked to but when they didn't use their advice they would say this about them.
Ah, be just the the way you are.
When you reach in your mind something you like and take apart your advice.
You heard it, you didn't follow but wish you had.
What, what is an example you can expound on it further.
What did you see, you see
hearing the advice of the speakers then
what is that with an example?
Do you mean of one who is hard to talk to?
Yes, the one who is hard to talk to as they mentioned of him.
You saw with your own eyes, one who did that.
What was it that he wanted to undo?
The ones who were hard to talk to didn't listen and that's what I saw.
I knew they were unhealthy, wanting to be able to do what other's can and will get done for their own stomach and body.
That's how they were with their advice they didn't heed.  Those who didn't listen on their own of given advice.
They lived sickly, not successful, well like they didn't have everything and lacked it all.
And, so they didn't live long.  They didn't live long those who followed their own mind and action.
They didn't live long.  See,truly it's very correct what they use to tell us.  They didn't live long.  They didn't live long.  They would be sickly and suddenly they're gone.
Now, now today today so you've arrived at today.  In this day and age now,
with your observation of the distant past on longevity.  On those who hard to talk to, are they any different living today?
Today?  Yes, in our day, for us today are they dying faster or how is it?
(Living) It is faster on the ones hard to talk to, faster than the ones who follow their advice.
They are faster. Their living is faster.  Faster on aging for women and of men aging faster.  You see (it).
That's how it is on this.  Like that...going at different pace.
However, those who heed and follow their advice go through it slowly or so it seems.  Slowly or it is that way.
You see it.  Anyway, awhile back that poor father of yours prays... he comes to pray for me when he arrives in Kongignak all the time.
When he came in to pray for me he said to me gratefully, "My poor cousin, I'm grateful you're looking good and shows your mind is well. Thankful you look good."
I tell him, "I use what I heard to be as I am.  If I live with my loneliness I will not do anything for myself.  I'll only hurt the ones who I leaned on for deep support.
If I lived in pain, I would put them in pain also.  Now I bring myself up to where the ones who have cared for themselves mentally.
I find self care on top of it.  I am how I am even though I'm where I am standing.
He said, "Yes, exactly. You have presented what it's like for someone to be at.  Truly you have presented a persons life.
There could be someone who is lonely, gives into that
who gives up for loneliness goes through a fast journey."  His comment is exactly describing it.  He's still a child, that one.
To me he's still a youngster, that's to me.  He was just a lad, recently.  I said to him, "Look at that.
As you see me right now.  You were born later finally no more or less.
You make me recall this short saying which stays with someone who didn't misunderstand it as you say that.
Very well.  And you know you're the only one living now, in no case don't regret your loss about that, my poor cousin."  I say to him.
"Don't regret your loss that might have been prevented by appropriate action."  Poor, he say's 'yes' and nothing else.
If there's one to pass on to us who are behind you, can you tell us what you especially would pass on.
What I have already said, I do consider that will be like true passing on.
Ones who don't listen lust like the ones before will be like the ones who didn't listen.  He will be like someone who doesn't listen who won't have what he needs.
But, then there's one who is easy to talk to who will have blessing ahead of him.  It's available in his journey as he comes across it on his many travels.
That's how he will be if he does not doubt.
But those doubtful of their advice have not much of what they want,   They do experience more need and it stands out.
And on using (recreational drugs) nowadays it takes away from some people what they would have provided.
Seems like they trade what they need to using, trading alot of useful items to fool around with it.
Poor thing! On using of recreational drugs/mistreatment using alcohol and smoking drugs consequently its like a warfare of self because of using them.
It's like they give up their life with that.  It wasn't their time to be unaware of themselves.
It's become a habit with that, this alcohol coupled with smoking drugs.  It's a foolish habit.  Their lives are cut off from that, too.
It's just like cutting it.  Its something one does not wish to part with for us left behind. Big but have to part with.
Now at this time using to us has become a lifestyle by all of the village inhabitants.
All of the countries population...attempt to use this so called alcoholic beverage.
Before them, we drank home brew.
It was our alcoholic beverage.  My husband returned from white people and he arrived with a big bag full of potatoes.
And he also came with two big bags of sugar and one of them was to be used in the potatoes.
And me, there ready for his coming cooked and mashed those potatoes and after mashing when I filled the barrel...
just like that I learned the process. I filled that barrel thinking of the drinks in containers.
I covered it with a seal intentine, tightening it with a cord.
It had a cord.  After awhile that cover of the barrel starts to inflate.
It is inflated for two days and its third day it comes down a little.
So it goes down and once down we opened those potatoes had sunk to the bottom.  The top of it was very clear.
Oh, we ladled it onto containers.  We filled tea kettles.  We filled big kettles and pots.  Filled them with covers.
The rest of it we added and mixed with a cup of sugar.  It spread quickly.
And, so we used those and used them as it became what it was but they didn't get like these today.
Their love didn't change.  They didn't hate.  But liked one another, like that.
So, we quit brew...one time I...we always cut fish down river on the tundra.  One time I said to that Acill'aq.
"I am not going to go to my invites with drinkers.  I'm about to quit.  It's plenty that I used alcoholic drinks."
He said to me.  "If you quit, I will quit, too."  We quit then in by telling one another.
We had invitations but ignored them out there"  They were about to have it, people of Canineq.  So there
I quit from that point on.  I quit long ago.  I was still very strong living at that time.
So, I quit a long long time ago.  We both were done with it at the same time.
Oh me, my dear cousin in case you have a lady partner it's a great idea to agree and be together.
To be in agreement as partners, it's a great thing.
You see, my poor self is thankful having no regrets towards my previous partner.  Only gratefulness.
I think of how fortunate after he went ahead of me how fortunate I didn't go against his order.
Thank goodness I was his partner hardly going against his order or command while I could see him.
I am thankful that we didn't go against each others will, so thankful.
He was also, at that time, he was about to leave his body.  I had no idea as I watched him.
He said to me, "Fix my pillow over there.  I'm getting sleepy so I am going to sleep."
Just yesterday in the evening, up above he'd say, 'Jesus'.
To me that person up there is moving at such a a good speed.  He's is going above at a certain speed looking to area below.  He would look sideways turning his head.
That person  It was evening at that time and he says, "Jesus is coming in. "
"He came in."  When he came in, he talked to Jesus happily.  Shortly he said, "He just left."
On that moring he stopped breathing.  He layed down.  After he laid down, I sat at the end of him.  I put a blanket on him when he wanted to lay down.  He said he was sleepy and will sleep.
He perched his neck up and said to me, "Poor you, I became your partner back in time because I wanted to but, I'm sleepy now and will go to sleep.
He never said what he was going to do.  I'd think, oh my I thought he slept all night.  I sleep attending to him.
I noticed his breathing was getting quiet.  He would breath in and would let it out.  His throat had no saliva whatsoever.
It seemed he was going to sleep and fell asleep.
As he made me watch him, his face was about to return to look as he was young.
The look on his face was very good.  As if he's not an old man anymore. His face was very good.  He layed there like a young person.
Also, your poor cousin he took to fix his body.  I believe they made him stay three nights in that downriver house.
On the third day it was getting close to evening, he was brought to the church.
The next day we went up and I saw, my, your cousin had returned to his youth when he had no children.
He looked even better than how he looked at the house.  So youthful...who wouldn't think otherwise, how young he looked.
It was shared that he looked like when he didn't have any children.  His good look had returned to when he had no children.  It was very good to view him.
Oh that situation, we didn't know what was happening next.
He had his children sing church songs because it happened on a Sunday as it came to closing of oneself.
Your other poor cousin was holding his feet below him.
And, his other children were closed in on him and singing.
So, as they ended one song and stopped, he said to them, "Sing that song, Aleluia."
So, they know the song all those children of his.  They sang it.
One of them held his neck with his arm, that poor Ap'ac.  She's here to have her baby.  Apac is one of his children.
She embraced him around his neck and pulled him up for me to see his face, smiling.