When I was young, I grew up in the community house.
Then, you know, I would always sleep by my father in the community house
Among many people like this, you know, the community house, you know it.
Cuukvagtulirmiut also had a community house, our competitors.
By my father.
Then above there, the community houses had sleeping areas, bedding, two feet
Two feet of wood.
Then when it was time, I’d go down to the nateq, the floor
The floor planks, you know, to the floor.
I would sleep, and we wouldn’t mind.
These kinds of small gloves, or, we would use those traditional Yup’ik gloves as headrests and sleep.
Right, it was nothing to us a long time ago, you know?
That’s how we lived.
My grandfather raised me.
He didn’t raise me.
He wouldn’t let me sleep in the morning like this.
Apparently, he did that so that I would live well.
And when I slept like this, he would come wake me up [shaking] these.
Then when my grandfather said from the floor, "Quickly go outside"
He said I’d feel better outside.
When I went out, I’d feel better, awake, and no longer sleepy at all.
And to this day, I never sleep in the morning [?].
I should say some things in English.
These days, I don’t hear anyone instructing anymore.
Since it’s gone out like a light in us who’ve become elders, it’s like our traditional wisdom is sleeping.
In our traditional wisdom, they would especially tell us to revere our land and the water.
Revere it.
In other words, this is what our instructors were like:
[Revere nature] as much as our own bowls.
These days, it’s not like that. It’s become different.
What does that mean, "as much as our own bowls?"
This is how I understand it:
Our bowls when we eat, at least, since a person had one bowl in the past back then, (s)he watched their bowl carefully.
They treated it with love, reverence.
I think that is a metaphor
That we should revere our land and water as much as our own bowls.
This is part of the traditional wisdom of the people long ago.
They also used to say
They said that a boy should not be with a girl before he takes a women [as a wife].
We are destroying ourselves these days.
We are destroying our lives, and we are destroying our bodies.
And with this, I also used to heavily abuse alcohol.
That is what destroys our bodies.
Also, when a person does something bad, it is known all across the land
Especially back then.
Since they weren’t so terribly mischievous back then
The occassional one who [misbehaved] would be conspicuous.
These days, though they [misbehave] every day, we’ve become different
Because we elders don’t say anything anymore.
Back then, they would instruct them, even if it wasn’t a lot, not taking things lightly.
To anyone listening, I am speaking of things that are not unbelievable, that are true.
To my cousins out there, my name is Kunuin from Qinaq, who has moved as Tuntutuliar.
I moved to Tuntutuliar in 1945.
Today, I am thankful that KYUK invited me.
I’m not completely well. I am going to sing a song of gratitude so that my problem may pass.
Let us desire to walk well together in the light of the sun.
We’re thankful tagi-yara-ya
We’re bowing yagi-yara-ya
Ii-rri-rri-yarrai
What a cause for gratitude agya-rrai
We’re thankful tagi-yara-ya
We’re bowing tagi-yara-ya
Ii-rri-rri-yarrai
What a cause for gratitude agya-rrai uu!
There you have it.
How was that?
My earliest memories are in Qinarmiut.
In my earliest memories growing up, there was nothing [Wester] in Qinaq, and there was no Bible.
There were no Christians.
My earliest memories are when my next younger sibling died.
I’ve had consistent long-term memories since then.
I got to know the people in Qinaq.
I’ve had consistent memories since then, observing the people. I was from Qinaq.
Then, you see, when I became capable
There were scarcely any Caucasians, but they had one resident Caucasian whom they called Klondoke Johnson, whom they called Paru in Yup’ik.
His four children were our fellow boys.
Two are still alive, no, three.
But I was scared of Paru. We were scared of Caucasians; they were strange people to us.
When we saw them, "Oh my, I won’t walk around." They were scary.
The people of Qinaq lived there, and they didn’t have a school.
And when I grew up and went in the community house, when I was at the community house
I was scared of Akagtaq, the grandfather of the one whom I’d apparently marry, the one whom I’d apparently marry downriver.
When he was in there, since my grandmother was his friend
Since my grandmother [?joked about] him, I was scared of him thinking that he really used to eat people.
Apparently, it was because I was her grandchild.
I really believed her, and she said he had ears in the soil.
When she was at their house over there, she said she’d hear what was going on over there [in the community house].
That’s why when I remember her, just real quickly, I say today
"I wish I could have that one that said she had ears in the soil make a phone call far away under the mountains."
That’s what they were like.
When I started being at the community house
The people, back before I started going to the community house, you see
People like this, when their little sons or daughters [first] caught something in their lives
When their little boys made their first catches with arrows
They would remove the flesh from that little bird, hang it to dry threaded through a branch, prop and hang it to dry.
Then the next winter, they’d have a feast for him.
They would do that every year.
Then me, in our old fish camp inland, downriver
Downriver from Tagyaraq, when we wandered inland as I had started running
You see, this ptarmigan that had taken off fell.
As I chased it, it would take off, then fall.
Eventually, I tripped and took it.
Though it tried to fly away, I didn’t let it and killed it.
I didn’t know what became of it.
Apparently, my grandmother hung it to try on a tree like that.
I didn’t know and never saw it.
Our winter camp Iingirayuq downriver
Three families like this would set big fish traps.
They would fish for whitefish, broad whitefish, whitefish with pointed heads.
And my father’s fish trapping spot under the land down there would have a lot of fish.
The next winter, you see, Qinarmiut sent invitations to Eek and Apruka’ar
Since they did that when Apruka’ar was populated.
The guests arrived.
You see, they would make Yup’ik ice cream in huge bowls
Traditional ice cream with tallow, rendering fat from seal blubber with heat, cutting them up back when they’d make Yup’ik ice cream.
Then, you see, they told me to go to the community house, that I should go with them.
I went out to find my father’s sled filled end to end with food.
This huge serving bowl had Yup’ik ice cream.
You see, the ptarmigan I’d caught last summer had props [on the wings] and was staked into the ice cream.
Apparently, my father held a feast for me.
I didn’t go to the community house. I was distressed, scared of that cannibal.
I didn’t go with him because the one whom I was afraid of was alive back then.
That’s what they used to do.
We started sleeping in the community house.
That big community house, I’m not sure how big it was.
Then the young people and our elders lay down for bed, there’d be no room.
When going in late, sometimes when I had no bedding, I would lay on my below the front of the door and sleep.
Like that.
Some mornings, however, I would wake up to someone instructing up there.
One of the old men woudl already be speaking about instructions, traditional wisdom, how a person should live
How a boy shoudl live, what is in store for the future, what is true.
When we got up, we wouldn’t make sudden movements getting up, and listen to that one giving instruction.
They wouldn’t force us awake.
That happened every morning.
Then during the day like this, when their fire bath died down because they’d have blazing fire baths
They would give instruction about life, the encroaching future
When a boy is [married to] a woman, oh my, and it was a long way off for us.
Apparently, they gave us a guide so we wouldn’t be lost.
They tell stories about how before that
Before we were born, when those old men were boys, they would strongly practice traditional instruction.
They said that when they were going to give instruction in the community house
They would [block] the door with a piece of split spruce.
Do you know what cigyak is?
You know the wood to make fish traps?
Where is it? Wasn’t there one here?
Fish traps, they have split spruce that are this wide.
They put it on its side crosswise [from the door].
And only then would they speak of traditional wisdom.
Then they said that because people are different like this, because boys are different
They said that one of the boys would go out of the community house, even breaking that [split spruce].
They’d start speaking about him, "Oh my, the traditional wisdom doesn’t call him."
They said that a person who acts improperly does that.
Then the women separately out there in the houses, the [?elderly/knowledgeable] old women would would instruct them
When a girl takes a husband, how she should take care of her husband.
I caught them [instructing] there in the winter camp, and the door was blocked off with grass, woven grass belts to keep out the draft.
Then they said that one of the girls as well
I observed that in one house, three families would mosty live in the same house.
It would also be occupied by four families.
They said that one of the girls would go out.
Then they’d speak of her.
They said that one of them would even take of the grass belt block, the grass that was tacked there.
They said when she did that for the third time, that old woman would give her her fate
"Let her do that, so she’ll be the person of the threshhold."
Do you know what a caniqaq is?
Where is it?
The threshhold of the door out there is a caniqaq. They call it a caniqaq.
And the back wall of the house way in there, in front of the door is the egkuq.
This is the threshhold like that when they had sod houses.
"She will be the person of the threshhold."
Oh my, they explained that people who subsist use the threshhold. "She will be the person of the floor."
Apparently, she pointed out her exact future.
She loses her mother and father, stays here, stays here, because she doesn’t heed traditional wisdom.
Then the one who would run out from the community house out there
They said when he does it for a third time, an old man gives him his fate
"Let him do that, so he will show his nice teeth at the end of a snowbank."
Do you understand it?
This is what it means:
Every [?], when they predicted famines from bad weather
They said he starves to death here, do you know what a qengaruk is?
Snow[bank].
Over at the end, his teeth are very white.
They say the poor guy starves to death. They say he shows his nice teeth.
Tha’ts what they were like.
They put skins on two drums.
Then when it was getting dark, they’d beat the two drums.
My father, and the father of the old lady downriver would sing opposite each other, but I didn’t learn their songs.
I never learned them when I had too much fun.
I have some incomplete knowledge of some songs.
When this is over, I’ll sing one I know in Yup’ik.
They would sing loudly.
Then eventually, a woman would go into the community house holding a ceremonial nerukar bowl [of food].
After she put it down on the floor plank, she would dance what they called an Ingulaq dance. And she went out when she was done.
Then before long, a woman would come in with a bowl
Eventually down there, the floor planks would be [?slanted] like this, the fireplace in the big community house.
And the floor planks like this would be filled with small nerukar bowls.
And when they stopped coming in, they put the drums away.
The people of the community house would eat what was absolutely not Western food
Little fermented fish heads, aged salmon egg ice cream, moss with aged seal oil, whitefish egg ice cream, dried fish.
We little boys would say, "Moss with aged seal oil is good," what they call puyat [plural].
Moss with aged seal oil, people always had puyat.
The moss, soak the moss in seal oil, the moss from the land.
They say Urucararmiut [People of Moss] here.
They soaked moss in seal oil.
And when they were going to make puya, they would crush that soaked moss, occassionally pouring in seal oil.
It was very white, and a little congealed.
But those puyat need to be eaten quickly right away.
They said it’ll "fly away."
When left, the berries separate, and they say it "flies away."
Like that.
Such good food, even little fermented fish heads.
In the winter, the one they call Itruka’ar, the "Inviting-In Feast."
People from here call that dance festival Itruka’ar.
What they call Itruka’ar has shaman songs.
When they celebrated Itruka’ar, I used to see those shamans.
They dance those songs, with two women, and a single man to accompany them.
And these people who wanted to [would dance songs] they knew even though they weren’t shamans.
My late father would write songs because they said he was skilled.
That’s what this Itruka’ar celebration is.
They would practice what they called the Itruka’ar celebration.
This other one, the Messenger Feast. Now that was a dance festival.
When villages held the Messenger Feast
This host village like this
Let me give this meaning: if you want to send an invitation, if you have a request, you would send to men, kevgak [messengers], to Tuntutuliar.
Tell them and instruct them [on your requestions], like that.
When these two messengers traveled
The request of a child’s father from their home village, they would get and invite his cousin at their destination.
Then he would [make a request] the same way, like that.
They would have some requests when they held the Messenger Feast
Guns, steel traps, a sled, they would want various things.
They’d also ask their cousins to help them.
Then when as they had more Western contact, they’d ask for huge tents.
They’d want tents.
They’d also ask him to [?bring] a gun so new that it had the color of feces.
They said, you know, diarrhea with crowberries is black. That’s why [they say that].
That’s what the dance festival, Messenger Feast, was like where I was born.
I also participated in the Messenger Feast like that.
The people back then, our ancestors, practiced shamanism.
Our ancestors back then didn’t live any which way.
They practiced that shamanism with complete faith.
The ones who try to help a sick person’s body, those without malicious intent, those who do not think maliciously of others
When people practiced that shamanism, they practiced it correctly with faith, and abode by their laws.
They set this time period: they tell the one they’re trying to save not to use a knife for five days.
Like that.
Look, they said, since one of them is true
You know, let me come closer to tell it
You know that Satan was God’s partner, that head angel?
Then since it’s true, he obeys one who believes him.
But they didn’t practice it frivolously in any old way.
The one they’re going to use their shaman power on, I used to see shamans call upon their helping spirits with drums in the community house.
Then they said that in the past back then
They said that two shamans would bring in the one they were going use their power on side by side into the community house, a woman and a man.
Then they said that when (s)he was sometimes [healed] well, those two worked together on his impurities
They got rid of all of his impurities.
They said the one who couldn’t walk coming in would walk out.
They got rid of all of his ailment.
Like that.
We had a traditional isntruction back when we were young
Especially about a shovel, or an ice pick, a walking staff
They also spoke about that staff as a life[line] for a person.
Also, this was one of their important instructions:
You know, [what we call] imarnitet in Yup’ik, people used to use those seal gut rain parkas back then before they had Western raingear.
Then for those of us who were born after Western contact
Our parents used to instruct us to especially keep our raingear with us even if the weather looked good.
Since the weather sometimes doesn’t end the way it started in the spring or fall
They would tell us to especially have those with us.
If we don’t have a walkin gstick, since we fumble around, and we don’t know how dangerous something is.
Or if we travel in the winter, they would tell us to always carry a shovel though the weather is good.
It turned out that if we got into misfortune in the wilderness, or a blizzard starts on us
When the weather turns on us, they also instruct us not to stop at a small snowbank.
But they also said that if we don’t have a tarpaulin
If we have a shovel, dig into a snowbank that’s already formed
They told us to stay in that.
But also, we should get a wooden [staff] to poke a hole in that.
When it gets hot, poke holes to let the [stale] air out.
Those were the important traditional instructions given to us from our ancestors back then.
I had this thought last spring on the verge of summer:
"Oh my, one of my old hunting grounds inland, when summer sets
"Let me go see one of the places I’d walk around with an open canoe with a small motor."
Then when there was no more ice in the summer, we portaged through Tevyaraq upriver from Tuluksak to the headwaters of Elaayak.
We went downriver from there.
When we came across a larger hill as we went downriver, I’d stop and look from that vantage point.
When I went to look from that vantage point, I’d come across this empty pop can.
And as I traveled this river with a boat motor, I would see a plastic [bag] draped over tree branches.
It was stuck there.
I kept seeing those.
And I didn’t think anything when I first started seeing them.
Eventualy, you see, as we were far downriver over there, because there were empty pop cans in every vantage point I looked from
I had the thought, "Oh my, look at how messy our children are, not like our ancestors."
This are the most prominent: empty pop cans, plastic bags
In their berry-picking grounds are also diapers
And their camping grounds are always filled with debris, without those being put away.
Long ago in our ancestors’ time, you see, this land was pristine.
There was no debris. There was none of that.
There were no empty pop cans, metal things, plastic things, or used diapers.
And eventually, there were also old drift nets
Here on to the headwaters of the Kuskokwim, and in Akula inland, [nets] that were set all winter.
They’re polluted, pollute nature with fish, and pollute the land.
And yesterday, when Matthew Beans was telling his stories, he told this story:
He said that when he travels to villages by plane
When he gets close to villages, he sees a lot of those plastic bags and cardboard things, when he gets close to villages
The things the wind blew like a blizzard.
I had this idea last spring when I saw too many of those when I traveled through there:
That I should talk about those in church, or that I should point those out even if it's not at church.
Our ancestors were clean, always keeping their land here cleaned up out of reverence.
And as they did that
They also didn't pollute their water out of reverence, the Kuskokwim, even if it wasn't the Kuskokwim, the lakes and creeks.
They also didn't let their hunting-gathering lands become polluted.
Our ancestors always kept it cleaned up, saying this: "The Spirit of the Universe is watching us."
They say the Spirit of the Universe watches us, without leaving anyone out.
Those who are knowledgeable read the Bible, and I read it too.
It says this in Psalms 24:
"To Jehovah belong the earth and that which fills it, the productive land and those dwellingin it." [NWT]
How pitiful, we who pollute our land these days.
Calling ourselves believers, will we be believers who pollute our air and lands?
I pondered and realized that we believes will not have [polluted] air like that.
Our land, where we stay in the winter, and our hunting grounds in the wilderness
We must keep it like a cleaned up house
And our air, our hunting grounds, our fishing grounds, and our Kuskokwim River.
And these days, as I go on the Kuskokwim, I would see an empty pop can drifting down here.
And yet, it’s our food source, and our income source.
How foul, what will happen when it rusts?
You see, our ancestors back then said this:
They said that these fish are easily repulsed.
They said that if there’s anything bad in the river, the fish won’t go in it because water is their livelihood
Because they know that if they go on it, they’ll die before they reach its headwaters.
They said fish have never been able to go in polluted water since a long time ago.
Taking care of the land and taking care of the water
Starting from from our ancestors long ago, they have admonishments of what they’ve understood over the course of millions millions [of] year[s], true things.
They only have admonishments about true things, what they understood, what they’ve seen with their own eyes.
Since it’s like that these days, let’s take a look around.
Things are depleting, and fish are depleting these days
Because we don’t revere the water and our lands, because we’ve polluted them.
Can’t we incinerate these?
Or, we must leave cover them up under the land to keep our land cleaned up.
You with good houses know that you don’t want your house to be dirty.
These are more important: your land, your air, your hunting grounds.
You must carefully watch than more than your own bed in your home, and keep it cleaned up.
Since our land is polluted these days, God cannot bless it.
He decreases things, decreases fish populations, and seems to decrease these plants.
He cannot bless a polluted land.
Let us not put it upon another person or to the West, but to us who live in this land.
Cleaning those up, and watching them, let’s put it upon ourselves, not shift it to someone else.
As wou don’t watch over it, and as we don’t instruct our youth to utilize it reverantly, we’ve let it become like that
Because we keep [knowledge] from our youth.
From here on out, let’s instruct them to keep the land clear, and pristine.
Undoubtedly, when our land becomes pristine, God will bless it with abundance like our ancestors.
He will not let anything become scarce, but what we use here in this land will be available.
Birds, little animals, caribout, and minks can [be plentiful] like that.
In our ancestors’ stories back then, they say
When their fish traps were full and couldn’t take in any more, they’d stop catching minks.
Everything was in plenty back then.
Since the land was cleared up and pristine like this, God blessed it like that.
Every kind of meat had an instruction.
They said to leave the excess that we won’t use in a pit.
And if we see a caribou bone, or some other animal bone in the wilderness
If there’s no lake nearby, they said to leave it buried into the land.
If there’s lake nearby, they said to throw that bone into that lake.
Our ancestors had that instruction to keep the land that they saw pristine.
I got the intention to say that when I returned home from my travels last spring.
Our caretakers [did not let us] let it be this polluted, the creator, the owner of the land cannot bless it.
Since I am thankful for this to our youth here, I want to give this one more instruction.
When I first got married
When I got married, or when I also had children
Since my father downriver wouldn’t hold back when instructing me back then
He would instruct me like this: a child, should we happen to have children
He said not to ask them questions though they come in crying, or ask what happened and who did it.
He said not to feel defensive over them.
Watch, he said, if we defend them, that little child will become able to have us believe [lies].
As we go, they could make us upset at one of our friends.
Then when it’s time for them, they also go to school now.
He said that (s)he will not listen though people admonish them, because he said we are their defenders.
Since I especially wanted to say thank out of gratitude for your coming, I just spoke about it.
Well, to this thign they talked about, especially now
They didn’t have absolutely none of these when we were born, because we were born after Western contact.
But when they got these fast motors, that especially
Getting these traveling implements and vehicles are especially what’s making people drop [dead].
Also, them using mind-altering substances probably makes them do that too.
Back in my time, all of the stores down there in Bethel sold liquor.
But since they didn’t have fast traveling devices back then, though they [sold it] like that, they didn’t know [of any accidents].
We do instruct our children here, and I also speak to my children
But these days like that, and like my parents
I watched my late parent [give instruction] and myself.
But now, I can’t [instruct] them exactly like him.
I did that because they might feel offended, or that they might go the wrong way. Turns out, I made a mistake.
Yes, if I love them, then I must not hold back talking to them about every danger
So that they will remember them.
Many times now, those who separate from their parents do not live right.
Also, those who do not practice the traditional wisdom passed down to them are like they’re [lost] underfoot.
And though one tries not to be heard of in other villages, it’s like that person is shuddering at the top of a pole when they don’t practice traditional wisdom.
However, one who practices their traditional wisdom is like they’re not there, and like they’re not there even in neighboring villages.
Taking care of the land, and taking care of the water
Starting from from our ancestors long ago, they have admonishments of what they’ve understood over the course of millions millions [of] year[s], true things.
They only have admonishments about true things, what they understood, what they’ve seen with their own eyes.
Since it’s like that these days, let’s take a look around.
Things are depleting, and fish are depleting these days
Because we don’t revere the water and our land and pollute them.
Can’t we incinerate these?
Or, we should leave them buried in the land to keep our land cleaned up.
You with good houses know that you don’t want your house to be dirty.
This is more important: your land, your air, and your hunting grounds.
You must especially watch over it more than your own beds at home, keeping it cleaned up.
Since our land is polluted like this these days, God cannot bless it.
He depletes things, depletes fish, and seems to deplete these plants.
He cannot bless a polluted land.
Let’s not put it upon another pesron or the West, but upon ourselves who live in the land.
Let’s put it upon ourselves to clean those up, to watch over them, not move [the responsibility] to another person.
Since we don’t watch over it, and since we don’t instruct our youth to utilize it reverently, we’ve let it become like that
Because we keep it from our youth.
From here on out, let’s instruct them to keep the land clear and pristine.
Undoubtedly, when our land becomes pristine, God will bless it by makes things plentiful like our ancestors[’ time].
He will not make anything scarce, but what we use here on this land will be available.
Birds, little animals, caribout, and minks can [be plentiful] like that.
In our ancestors’ stories back then, they say
They said that when their fish traps were full and couldn’t take in any more, they would stop catching minks.
Everything was plentiful back then.
Since the land was cleared up and pristine like this, God blessed it like that.
Every kind of meat had an instruction.
They told us to leave our excess that we won’t use buried in pits.
And if we see a caribou bone, or the bone of another animal in the wilderness
If there’s no lake near it, they said to leave it buried into the ground.
If there’s a lake near it, they said to go throw the bone into that lake.
Our ancestors gave that instruction to keep the land that they saw here pristine.
I got the intention to say that when I returned home from my travels last spring.
With [the land] polluted like this, our caretaker, and the creator and owner of the land cannot bless it.
There you have it.
Then also, you see, cleaning up this land is very expensive.
Over there, you see, this year, I see people earning money by cleaning up the land.
And yet they’re called cleaner uppers.
They only have their eyes on money these days.
In our ancestors’ time back then, however, they didn’t look at money.
Instead, our ancestors back then kept their eyes on how they could live for a long time.
They were like this:
In their villages, they didn’t let grass grow.
They’d clean up their villages after letting the grass grow.
Then in the winter, they always shoveled their paths.
Our ancestors also always shoveled their paths for hauling water.
Because they were like that, their land was blessed.
And those who cleaned up
They said this:
"Live your life with a propensity do [clean up] debris, to clean up without thinking of money. Cleaning up is expensive.
"So that in the future, when you look back, you will have food every time.
"Then as there is food like that in your future, you will live for a long time on earth."
That is the promise of cleaning up.
It’s no wonder that in my earliest memories back then
I saw old women and old men walking by supporting themselves on their knees, unable to stretch out [to full height].
They were such old men and old women that they did that.
It turned out that because our ancestors, even women, would clean up their village
They would live a long time, and start walking by supporting themselves with their knees.
That’s the reward for one who cleans up.
Then they would tell these stories:
They say this man in his prime was not like his peers, lacking. And his name was Picuilnguq [Bad Hunter].
And though he hunted, he couldn’t catch anything.
They say that some of those who desire to be like these good hunters
They start cleaning up their villages though no one tells them to.
Being ashamed of being bad hunters, they start cleaning up those villages.
When they do that, when they practice that
One who does that becomes a better hunter than those who are called great hunters, and those who catch a lot, when he cleans up.
This is what it is: since God is thankful for that person who cleans up his land, he rewards him with what he wants, and he receives that reward.
He will make him like that for the length of his life, living without being in need.
Cleaning up brings great rewards.