Through this, we used to try to get land and river animals, and fish.
We would obtain [animals]. When we tried to gather and strived, we would get things.
And the one who didn’t try had nothing, was poor, and had no food.
That’s how they talk about that person that doesn’t try to gather.
But they said that the one who strives gets things.
In our time back then, the widoes, and, you know, the ones we call poor
And orphans
There were those kinds of people at that time who had no money to take care of them
Because there was no welfare at that time.
But the people that were able to do things themselves, who could catch things from the wilderness, the ones who subsisted
They are good at hunting and gathering, and gather food.
They said that those people were given the gift of catching things by the caretaker, God, who had them receive those gifts.
Our parents would always say this to us:
"When you are [on your own], when you start taking care of yourself
"For the people, if you have some of your own, if you get things that are of help
"Give as much food as you can for one who has no food
"Especially for widows, the poor, and orphans.
"And not only with food, if you have clothes for him, and spares
"Help him with the clothes he [needs] if you have any.
"If you can help that person if you have any to spare, you must do that."
Those people would also tell us
Not only that
Some mornings when I was young back then, my mother would tell me when I got up
"Now, go check on the people out there.
"[Some] will have no water, no wood, they will lack something.
"Go to them and check on them, including the women and those who have no providers."
So, as she said, since I knew that those women and those without providers needed to be [helped] like that
The ones who couldn’t get wood and water by themselves
I went to them and helped them with my physical power even though it wasn’t food.
Being without wood, because they also said that wood was for food preparation back then.
They said that wood is like food.
THey said that one cannot cook food without wood.
That is what I wanted to share from those who raised me, telling me to do that
"Now, go check on the people out there, and help them with what they lack.
"Also, if you have any food, and you know someone [who is without], try to give that person food.
"You see, that person’s gratitude towards you is very great."
Watch, they said, our caretaker, the Spirit of the Universe will exchange his gratitude in greater amount.
This is all for this sharing.
To help and give each other what they lack, depending on how much [they need].
This is all I have to say about this.
Okay. I just wanted to...
Helping each other is an ancient practice.
And back then, those who helped others wouldn’t want to take payment. The people long ago would help others without payment.
They would help others without needing payment.
The families, relatives, would stay together in houses, in one house.
At that time
The families, relatives in one house, a large house, in a sod house that had wooden furniture
They lived [there].
Across there, the two who made their own living up there, and here the two with children, four of them would live in a house like that.
I was also born on the cusp of that time, when they lived in traditional sod houses.
Relatives were tight knit. People back then loved each other.
And now, my ancestors are from Qinaq.
I am from the same village as the one from Qinaq who stood up and spoke this morning
That boy who was the very first one to open our meeting.
My ancestors, my parents were from Qinaq.
Back in my earliest memories, that village had one resident Caucasian.
That village is part of my first memories, where the houses were across the river from each other.
That village had that man as their one resident Caucasian.
It is unfortunate that helping others is no longer practiced these days.
Though these young people are able, they cannot help those who cannot provide for themselves to prepare.
They can’t do it without payment, any small payment, anymore.
Apprently, those people back then practiced love.
And those who can’t fish, and those who don’t work and can’t drink Western tea
All winter, they would have people eat the gifts they were given.
And in my earliest memories, my earliest memories of when I was very small and my father passed away.
And after that, from the place where I had my first memories
My maternal aunt’s husband brought us upriver here to Elumarvik.
I also stayed downriver at Elumarvik until I became aware.
And ever since then, I’ve had become fully aware.
People took care of us, with my mother having no providers.
The gifts were cause for great thanks, food, and clothes
Clothing that covers the body here.
People’s gifts were extremely great in my mind.
I was extremely thankful for them.
I would covet families with fathers, those with large familes, with many siblings.
The people’s helping others, taking care of others, helping each other
Those people back then who helped others gave me something to say today.
I am extremely thankful for them.
Now, you see, you know you say that people’s behavior has changed these days.
We know what has changed.
Relatives, close relatives do not act as relatives anymore.
And they don’t know some of their relatives, their mom’s relatives, and their father’s relatives these days
Because the way people [used to] love each other has changed now.
And then when I asked after that time, " How did those people in that house live?“
My mother would tell me this:
"In the live those people lived, one didn’t have any possessions, and this one didnt say their food was running out, and no one said [food] ran out.
"The extremely close-knit family ate from one store.
"And no one refused to share."
She said that those relatives helped out their relatives as much as possible.
They wouldn’t refuse them anything, and even if it was their only one, they would have them use it without payment.
These days, you see, every little thing needs payment that should be given as assistance, as gifts.
We also had traditional instructions.
Even though we were women, just women, and though we couldn’t buy anything, they said we could help people out.
I thought this when I heard this: "I wonder what I will use to help others out?“
My mother said this to me:
"If you say something to someone who feels hopeless, you will help him if you tell him something good."
Then she also said this to me:
"The one who has torn clothes with no one to sew them, if you sew the torn parts closed, you will help him."
You see, this is how we helped others in our lives back then when we had no money to help others.
That’s how we helped others
And because I used to do that, sewed close these [torn clothes].
You see, someone can learn to do it if they start this.
Then when they see torn [clothes], they will think, "Let me fix this."
One learns that way. You can learn anything.
When I did that, I learned how to do it.
Even if they’re Caucasian, no matter who they are, when I see them, I want to [help] them.
And I think, wanting to sew that tear closed
Because you can learn to do anything.
There are many ways you can help a person.
We understood a lot about a part of helping each other through food
Because we would help each other in our time back then, giving to each other.
And because people would have great scarcity of food in the winter, those who don’t catch anything, don’t fish, and are unable
Because through that, we go down to the water until they have food.
But now, we’re going to move on to this subject, helping each other
Helping each other.
Helping each other in accordance with something.
Or in vilalges, we sometimes practice that.
Sometimes, one of our own has a great job to do
Or trying to build a house
Or because they had wooden houses, because they didn’t have plywood at that time, and because there was no plywood at that time.
But because people here on the Kuskokwim would gather wood to make houses
Because people aren’t using those too much anymore
And though they used what they called mud houses in my time, because they had those at that time in spring camps, fish camps, and winter camps
They used those for a long time.
But in these villages, when these small vilalges work on things, they ask for help because they find them difficult
And because these logs are not light, and we didn’t have machinery to pull them at that time
Because they only took [and hauled] things by hand.
Also, it’s because they speak to each other to notify those around them when they do something that requires help.
Then those people who live in that small village
THey tell us to come even though they’re not working on something great that requires us to help.
When those adults work together on something and they order us to do things
We get that insignificant thing, and when they order us to get some tool or something, we would get it.
We’re like the arms of those adults when they work on something
Because when they’re going to make houses, they bring those inland to where they’re going to work on it, bringing them inland from the water here.
Or also
A long time ago, these villages would ask for help when they were going to work on this community house
Because making a community house was a huge job, and it needed huge pieces of wood for the structure.
They would invite villages, kelegluki.
When they thought that they didn’t have enough people, they would invite other villages to their own.
Saying that they were going to work on a community house, asking for help.
Then that village that was invited arrived, they arrived because they were invited there.
The wood they were going to use was already ready down there.
Then the several villages, even two, that they invited worked together, helping each other.
They worked together on that huge sod house, that community house.
And because they would cover those community houses with sod
And because they would cover them with sod after they put in grass so it wouldn’t crumble when the wood they put on their sides were finished.
They worked on that like that until it was finished.
But when it was finished, the villages they invited, the gathered villages
They would have what we call today a potluck.
At that time, they would have a feast, a mini Messenger Feast potluck when that community house was done.
Then they would dance as a form of payment to them, giving them a joyous time.
After they had given them a feast, when it was done, they ended it with that feast.
They had a potluck, enjoyed themselves, and even danced.
It was like a [community] corporation, helping each other.
Because they would help each other like that with one person’s job
With what they were going to do like that, they would help that person.
They even told us to helo like that, staying with them [in case they needed anything].
Also, these villages, even though they weren’t [going to help] that one person
When they bring up something that needs help when this village wants to do something
They would say in the vilage down there, also because there weren’t a lot of villages
After the Moravian mission first started
The people helped each other, and these missions’ plywood [houses] got built.
Starting from the missions, we made boardwalks upriver to what they called the big store.