So, before we had cake mix we had mixed eggs to it.
Aanaq (granddaughter) aqumniartuq.
I'll add more water again so it can be ready.
Are salmon berry named from salmon due to color?
Or, because they are the same?
I don't know.
I do know of blueberry.  Like the eyes of cranes?
I don't know why berries are berries.
Like a blue berry, two blue berries.
Or, did they name them salmon berry because of the summer salmon fish.  Salmon berries ... maybe.
They grow just at the beginning of fall.
We don't make these fried bread regularly.  Only once in a while.
Yes, we usually made it in the morning after staying up all night at Nalqigliq
Early in the am I went home and made it.  You know, for my mom and dad's breakfast.
I'd think... I was up all night I want to contribute, thinking of paying back.
I wanted them to be grateful and so I went home and made fried bread.  And, Carrie would do the same, make fried bread next door to us.
When you stayed up all night what did you do?  When I think of the nights we stayed up, we didn't do anything mischievious but we were pretty quiet.
Next to tents, we tried our best not to make any noise at all.
But, over yonder inside the trees we had a play ground on a clearing..clearing an area.
We played there at night.  And there was Maklaali who would play some music.
That father of his had good singers. You know, they held a big party.
From Nalqigliq three of us went along as girls.
We went with Samil.  Sam Mili, that one.  His boat was a sail boat.
You know they used sailboat to travel back then.
So, that's where we modern danced.
And, we joined them.
When we went back to Nalqigliq, we did the same at night with him as our singer and danced (saatis style) at night.
We did that seems like.
That's how you always had to do it.  I heat my oil, too I will use.
So, now you're making a video of me.  Yes
So, back in the day...they used rendered animal oil to make fried bread.  I wonder how...and rendered animal oil is strong.
Now, I only use wesson oil.  So, I don't use other than wesson oil...if I don't have wesson oil, I use shortening.
But back then, rendered oil.  Tundra people, back there...(plane noise)
I forget that that there is no TV news.  Yes...When we lived here we always had TV news every day.  It's different now with radio only.
Will you have tea?  Yes, what is in this?  Well water?
Marie was making jam yesterday when we called her.
I wonder what kind of jam she's making.  Probably blue berries.
His fishing helper isn't working out.  And, he had a court summons.
But, Raba just told me he is staying with them.  She has a place across from it.
Penggartuten-qaa? (at camera guy). He is the only guy here, so maybe that's why he's hot.
It's hard to sleep.  Oh, too hot?  Yes (incomplete sentence due to editing).
Do they pick cranberries here?  I do not know.  Maybe they haven't.  Or, I don't know.
Over on the other side at Manokotak they make cranberry after cooking them.
Are they not quite rip or when they're ripe?  When they're ripe.  They call them cooked berry.  Yes
My mom when she lived there use to make cooked berry.
Why are berries over there....
I thought you were going to do that.
This might burn.  They burn easily.
Murilkelluku una.  Cukaluteng uulartut.
We use to say our parents were pretty elisngaq.  And just like this they ate fresh fried bread with their hot coffee/tea in the morning.
Just finished right before.  And before they have tea in the afternoon they make another batch of  fried bread.
So, I saw fresh was best, and they ate fresh all the time.
Having no place to get them.  But those out there, and my next door neighbor does fish.  If I ask for some he may give me some.  My white caucausian neighbors care about me.
And that one out there, Shorty planted grass seed on my lawn.  But, Sue's husband when he was here added mud and a shop. He sold it.
It ruined it outside with sand piled up here and there, any which way.  And, Shorty is not even planting seed for grass anymore.  He use to cut the grass all the time, always including me.  That's why I like him.
He works very hard.  He works all the time.  I know he will work on his flowers when he gets home even though he's dirty.  I tease him sometimes.  That man, he really doesn't know what rest is.  Always working.
Do those apartments have people staying in them?  Yes.  They're always occupied. In the day I think they work.  They must be expensive.  Yes, they are expensive, $800 down is what someone said. And, there are people in them all the time.
Ana, ah, lets just use tea bags.
Sugar them up, have some tea.  (Great-granddaughter says, 'naspaayugtua') They are excellent hot.  Can I get a tea cups.  Can I set cups?  yes
Get yourself a cup, it boiled.  (question unclear) She (Ana?) is looking for work.  Very good (fried bread just finished). Wages are very low for lower 48.  I found that out last winter.  They have lower wages.  Maybe here, things (incomplete due to editing)