And when we washed their clothes, our mothers would have us separate the men’s clothes
And they had us separate us women’s clothes, because they greatly respected them.
They used to do that because of the hunting that you just talked about.
A woman’s clothes must be washed separately, only women’s clothes [together].
I also did that. I do it because I have many male children.
And, we don’t put the men’s clothes into that water used to wash the women’s clothes.
They would have to fill them with fresh water to wash the men’s clothes.
They would instruct us like this: not to take care of them altogether out of respect.
One day, I asked, "Why do you have them [washed] like this?"
I used to ask my mother about what I didn’t know.
Then my mother said this to me:
She said, as you’ve been speaking about now, that they do that for their hunting, so that they will be good at catching animals in the wilderness.
I’ve said what I wanted to say about what I understood since we’re almost out of time.
Then we women who took care of food would treat what the men obtained with respect.
Whether fur-bearing animals, no matter what they we were, we took care of what men obtained with respect.
We tried to practice that instruction.
We didn’t make a mess of them.
We didn’t make a mess of the bones, the craps, and the guts of what they caught as we took care of them.
I would ask my mother about everything, because I was my mother’s only child.
Since I didn’t have a lot of relatives, I would ask about them.
Then she would say this to me:
She said that if I make a mess of what my spouse caught too much
She said he will become unlucky in hunt, and won’t be able to catch anything in the wilderness anymore.
She said that will happen if I make a mess of them.
Animals he hunts will not give themselves.
And I believed them. I believed that happens to them.
I also just said
Since we women who subsist are not sedentary, since we try to gather from the wilderness, we also had practices.
Out of respect, we would be told not to go to a person’s place, a person’s gathering place.
Since it was that person’s gathering place, it required respect so as not to offend them.
We would only go to our spots, not in any random place.
I also used to hear people giving instruction
These men who hunt
Things that will spoil, they do not put anything that will spoil there in the fish trapping spot, and drift netting spot.
They said that if a fish spoils in that drift netting spot, the fish will be low the next year.
There will not be that many [like the year before].
And that implement, the fish trap that is set there in a creek
They said the person who subsists in that creek reveres it.
He doesn’t want anything to spoil there because he subsists there.
They said that if an animal, or some other thing they caught, spoils around the fish trapping spot
The next year, it will not be as plentiful as it used to be.
You see, we didn’t doubt those back then.
People back then respected everything, even the wilderness and even the land.
As I just said, before the land started looking unpleasant
Before it was covered with cardboard and empty cans, the land was pristine.
And the area far out around the villages would look good.
These days, you can tell every area that a person came across.
The place a person had come across, they would throw things, and there are their trash, what they used.
These days, the land has become like that.
It’s not pristine anymore, including the wilderness.
I think they don’t respect it anymore.
That’s all for that.
Okay.
She says that...
...plants, rivers, (And lakes), and lakes, those things.
We revered and respected them.
Yes.
Back then, here on the Yukon, here on the Kuskokwim, and likely on the Yukon
Yupiit have a traditional instruction to preside over this river with reverence.
They said that for us, in the spring or in the summer too
We have an instruction from our ancestors back then that in the summer, we should never throw white-fronted geese from the summer of the previous year.
They said that when the food from the last summer are thrown there, fish won’t stay there.
Like those creeks that she just spoke of, that area will not have good fish populations.
But they said not to throw those things from the previous summer into that water.
They said we should dig and bury them in a pit there, and not have them be visible.
But they said we can throw the guts and intestines of these fresh fish down [in the water], but where people will not trod.
They said to dump them in a deep area where people won’t trod, and where it doesn’t get exposed at low tide.
Now, they’ve started throwing things, turning the bank into fish [waste], because they don’t heed traditional instructions now.
That’s is how we should reverently treat the river, the huge river down there.
Okay, as far as the rivers in spring or summer
The rules of their forefathers were that they were told not to throw
If there should be leftovers that can’t be eaten from the winter, that you do not throw these into the river.
If you do, there’s a chance that the new fish will not come to that river.
In case they might misunderstand that since they don’t know, and this person is from Fish and Game.
We cannot throw food away.
And I haven’t heard of a Yup’ik person throwing [food] away to this day.
But the Caucasians among us throw food away. That’s all.
He didn’t want any misunderstanding of throwing away.
He’s saying that the Native people as a whole are told that you don’t throw away food.
He just wanted to make that clear because he doesn’t [?] they do that.
But he has seen, you know, people, you know, who don’t have that kind of rule, throwing fish away, just the way they are.
If you treat something with respect, even if it’s food
How, you know, you used to cut them with as much respect as you had.
Or can that fish be cut in any way?
We had admonishments concerning fish back then, and it probably also concerns marine animals down there.
We were told not to cut fish with axes, but to cut them with ulus if they’re thawed.
They said to only use those [ulus].
We were admonished against using axes on those fish
Unless they’re cold, and the dogs who’ve come on land are going to eat them.
They also admonished against using an axe on them in a river.
They said not to use an axe to cut that fish that’s come up down there or in the Akula region. That was an admonishment.
That’s what that’s like, not to use an axe in the Akula region or here.
They didn’t like using axes [on fish].
Our caretakes said they [?inforn other animls], and that there are no more fish there when we are sloppy taking care of those fish.
Yeah, he has that answer.
Eliza, "piqertuaraqan [when he uses an axe]?"
Axe.
Okay, okay.
There's a way that you cut rather than hitting motion like an axe or whatnot
Unless they're frozen and can't be taken any other way.
Then you show respect if it's thawed.
Dried fish, dried fish that we call neqerrluaraat
When we have leftovers, we give them to someone with dogs, a person with many dogs.
We give them as gifts.
And he also wanted to say that if they have leftover, like with...
Various plants, and those berries
But we leave what we didn’t pick though there are a lot of berries, you know, what hasn’t been taken.
When they leave some, they will [return and] get the berries.
If one walked inland, they’d carry them on their back.
If one gets a lot, they will leave them there where they will not be tampered with
Then go and get those berries.
Or if a person has help, they will not leave any behind.
Also, even if there are a lot of berries in the wilderness, they were told not to intentionally stop on these salmonberries [cloudberries] and crowberries.
Instead, step over them as if avoiding them.
Though one may try not to, we step on them when they’re too many.
Also, those plants that we eat
Sourdock, sourdock, and wild rhubarb, and berries among trees
You probably don’t know some of them, high-bush cranberries, red currants, black currants.
We also pick those berries from trees.
However, some are admonished against.
You probably don’t know baneberries.
This plant has many berries clinging to it, and is red.
They call those "crow’s food [baneberries]."
If we eat those, we will get sick.
Also, we are admonished against eateng that thing muskrats eat in the wilderness, what we call poison water hemlocks.
Those are deadly, poisonous.
Being careful with those, we should point out to our children that they’re bad.
We should also point out those plants that are edible.
Even those wild celeries that we eat
And how we eat greens, what they call spinich in English
They have different ways of gathering from the land, including those fireweeds.
Also, when the leaves of these trees newly growing
Also eat those before they get hard.
Pull those out with your hands and eat them, chew them immediately and eat them.
Those are good when they’re newly grown.
Those are the plants we eat.
You probably know some plants.
You probably know some things.
I don’t know some of them.
What are the things they call water lilies in Yup’ik again?
I didn’t understand what you just said in English.
You know, those things with large leaves that float in lakes and oxbow lakes.
Those things? What do they call them again?
I know them. (Its name is obvious.)
Might be paparnat.
Paparnat.
I don’t know how those are used.
I don’t know either.
I spoke of some of the plants that I remember.
Will you add to what he said?
Let me add a little.
Okay.
What [he said] just now are part of the plants in this paper
And these plants just spoke of, and these.
Something, they didn’t need an excessive amount, and we didn’t need to gather a lot in our time
What would be wasted, if it’s going to be wasted if it’s too much, some of what we obtained would be wasted.
They would only have us gather what was suitable for us, what wouldn’t be thrown away, and that we would finish.
It’s because people back then respected the wilderness
And they respected the areas where they subsisted as I just said.
They told us not to gather too much that would become surplus.
They said not to take what would become surplus.
It was like they feared the wilderness, though it was wilderness.
When I didn’t expect it, they told me over the phone to speak with you.
I see.
I’m happy now.
Okay.
Over there, Ayalpik told me when I went to go eat at Ayalpik’s
They told me to speak to the students
But I didn’t speak to them.
I didn’t speak to them.
This, no, don’t take it, it’s okay. It’s for the camera here.
Start by telling a story.
Now, I’m going to speak.
As they’ve asked me to, I’m going to tell a story of my earliest memories.
I’m going to tell them about my earliest memories.
I will also talk about their traditional instructions.
Young men, or girls...
Now go.
Now? (Yes.) Okay.
Boys and girls, I want you to listen to our traditional instructions when we were small, and when I was a little boy.
They used to instruct us first and foremost to love.
Love is in the Bible as an instruction, that we should love one another.
Look at that.
However, the women, old women, old men in my earliest memories
Without anything around them, and not knowing the Bible
Yet they instructed and admonished against everything that was written in the Bible.
This is the first, the first [instruction], to love one another
Something we should remember.
A boy or girl who stands with the traditional wisdom passed down to them does well, stands in the right.
However, one who forgets, doesn’t follow, or practice the traditional wisdom passed down to them
(S)he gets in to what they call [?bad spots].
Their peers, those around them, their fellow people criticize them.
They look at their [character] and criticize them.
And some don’t hold back with them.
However, they don’t do that to an obedient person, and one who remembers their traditional wisdom.
There’s no one speaking unfavorably. There’s no one speaking unfavorably.
All of their fellow people treat them with compassion.
Now, these days
I don’t hear those pieces of traditional wisdom.
But I’ve heard those pieces of traditional wisdom passed down to us through people speaking here on KYUK.
Though villages stay separate, they speak of one traditional wisdom
That we should love one another, to put love first.
Their admonishment was that we should never take what’s not ours, what we call stealing.
They strongly admonished against that.
Then their instructions concerning these people whom they called decrepit.
They would call those who are no longer active and healthy, decrepit.
They were told to try to make them feel only gratitude.
They said to never make them feel offended or sad.
Instead, try to make them feel happy by duming their honey buckets, or hauling water.
Those were their traditional instructions.
What the meaning of that instruction? What meaning to they ascribe to it?
They said those who make others happy will stand for a long time.
He will live for another day for a long time.
That’s the outcome for one who practices making others happy.
They said he will stand for a long time, living to see another day.
That’s how they explained it.
They have a lot of traditional wisdom.
You see, they also used to speak in metaphors, using these things we know as metaphors.
One time in the summer
We see fish appearing, and we don’t recognize them or know what they are though they appear.
They would also use that as a metaphor, a parable.
They say that one who offends those around them, or makes them sad, or makes fun of them
The meaning [of that metaphor] is their lifespan.
The length of their life is not recognizable like the fish that appeared.
Oh my, how little is the length of that life.
The lifespan of one who disobeys wisdom is like the fish that appeared.
There's an accompanying one, wood.
Sometimes, there are good pieces of wood, with its surface looking good.
It's straight like this. It's good.
The inside of that piece of wood, however, is very twisted and can’t be split.
Say that that jealous people who do not root for those around them are [like that].
Jealous people who don’t root for those around them are like that.
They only want those things for themselves, not for those around them.
They say that their mind, their mind inside is like the twisted piece of wood.
They don’t love those around them.
They’re like a twisted piece of wood.
They would instruct us through parables
Those things, those old men and old women [would teach us].
Also, the old women would refer to the girls who’ve had their first menstruations as young ladies.
Those who haven’t menstruated yet were girls.
And these small [males] were called boys.
And they called one who was almost ready to take a wife, a young man.
They would instruct them.
They would instruct them on proper behavior, pointing out proper behavior.
One who remembers, those who remember, those who remember traditional wisdom live right.
They [live] well.
They stand in the right, and those around them do not speak unfavorably of them.
Those around them do not criticize them, those who practice traditional wisdom.
They’re like that.
Please tell us about growing up in Eek, what they were like back then.
Why do they call Eek Ekvicuarmiut [People of the Small Cliffs]?
In my earliest memories, I found that Ekvicuarmiut, [formerly] Ekvicuaraat [Small Cliffs] downriver was wilderness.
I started seeing them as a little boy.
It was a wilderness with no settlements, no people.
But were the Iinrayaq River across there goes out downriver to Eek
Iik has the same mouth as Iinrayaq across there.
Close to the mouth, well, at the mouth, there was a village with the name Akilirarmiut.
They called them Akulirarmiut.
When they relocated, they became Ekvicuarmiut, the village of Eek.
Ekvicuaraat downriver used to be wilderness.
And no one salvaged them.
You see, the beginning of when they were established as a village was Uyaquq.
How was Eek established as a village?
Like that, Uyaquq, where was he again? I think he was upriver.
Then they brought him downriver, since over there, there were, you know
Since there were Moravian priests, they had him brought downriver to there.
He went to Akulirarmiut downriver.
Then when they arrived with him, they made him a house through the Ekvicuar village.
Then Akulirarmiut relocated there and became Ekvicuarmiut.
Only when Uyaquq went to them, they followed him to the Moravian church.
Though [the Moravians] would go to them, they wouldn’t comply [with the church].
Did you grow up when it became highly populated or when there was few people?
There were quite a few people.
In my earliest memories, there were pretty many people.
Villages would have a lot of people.
But they’re deserted now.
And Qinarmiut here is now deserted.
But Tuntutuliar downriver that didn’t use to be there are the only ones.
Also in Quinhagak, the first people who were at Quinhagak are gone.
Only those who weren’t there and those who were boys live downriver in Quinhagak.
Some villages are now deserted there.
There also used to be the village of Apruka’armiut toward the water from Eek downriver, not far from the Kuskokwim.
They say it’s gone now. It’s already deserted.
All of them, all the people who were in the villages in the past are decreasing, decreasing.
Now there are only those who were young back then.
Napaskiak downriver is only popuated downriver by those who were young back then.
There are no more of those first people.
And downriver in Napakiak, there are no more of the first people.
Only those who were young, only some of them were born way back then.
Some of them are from way back then.
Those the same age as you?
There are no more who are the same age as me.
Downriver in my village, there’s no one the same age as me. They’re all gone.
You’re the oldest?
Yes, I’m the only oldest one.
And my spouse went to the hospital over in Anchorage.
In your opinion, what has [helped] bring [us] to this day?
In my opinion, God has brought this day.
They say that God gives that person a certin number of days to live when they’re born.
Then that person stands [alive], then when they reach their time, they pass away.
That’s what would be in my mind.
When summer sets now, they start traveling by boat.
And a long time ago in the past to this day, we Yupiit have started using these life jackets of our [Western] counterparts.
What can you instruct those going boating all summer that they should watch out for?
Now, they have floatation devices to keep a person afloat.
One should not be without those.
And since they’re not heavy, they’re easy to travel with.
In the summer, now they always travel in the summer.
Back in the past, however, there were none of those life jackets.
And they wouldn’t travel by boat, but row kayaks.
That was their traveling device, the kayak.
Now, however, they have boats and boat motors.
They have an easy time traveling.
That’s why you should keep those life jackets.
Now, we know, we now know that a person’s potential misfortune is right in front of them.
You know, after someone is happy, and bursts out laughing, then when they leave their peers, they disappear.
You see?
A person’s potential for misfortune is always present. It’s right in front of them.
That’s why you shouldn’t forsake these instructions about these Western things.
And keep those life jackets with you. And they’re not heavy to keep with you.
And even when using them, they’re easy to use since they keep you afloat.
And traveling with boats now
We always hear about people drowning now.
Please speak about those.
Okay.
Compare drowning when going fast and slow, which has more drowning incidents, and why.
Now, please speak about that.
Back in that time, they traveled with kayaks.
Then when the wind picks up on them, they had light pullover garments made of bearded seal intestines
Seal gut pullovers that they put on.
[Cover] the kayak cockput with that, you know how they’re round?
Did you used to see kayaks? (Yes.)
You know how they’re round?
He would cover the kayak’s cockpit with his hem.
Then they would bind it with a handmade rope of sealskin.
They called that securing it with a rope.
Though waves do this to him, it cannot go in his kayak.
That’s what they did.
Water cannot go in his kayak because it’s in his hem.
Then these boats haven’t sunk.
But this thing they abuse, what they try to abuse brings them to misfortune.
What’s called alcohol is the cause of their misfortune.
When that didn’t exist, no one met with misfortune.
We didn’t hear of anyone getting into misfortune in the summer, anyone drowning.
Now, every person of the villages don’t want their youth to abuse this.
Even those who aren’t young abuse it.
It’s like it scatters them [their lives] like this.
That’s how I compare it, like scattering them [their lives].
You know, when we scatter things, they scatter, and what we call saltshakers scatter [salt].
It truly seems when I ponder that what they abuse makes their [lives] scatter.
People back then didn’t know of any [misfortune] when that didn’t exist.
When that didn’t exist, they wouldn’t come to misfortune.
And their means of travel back then weren’t big like that. Kayaks were their only means of travel.
This one too: now, we always hear that traditional wisdom is not heard anymore.
In your observation, why don’t our elders speak about traditional wisdom too much anymore?
It’s because the people back then, there are no more of our elders.
Because traditional wisdom had no more of our elders to speak of them, there is no one who speaks of them.
Some of them probably know about them.
They probably hear of the ancient traditional wisdom.
It’s because no one speaks about it anymore.
Look, the people I was born in time to see
They would speak of their instruction without changing it, where one was one and the same [every time].
When this person gave instruction, (s)he would speak of it.
Before long, when another gave instruction, (s)he would speak of it.
Because they don’t have those who’ve become elders to speak of them anymore
They don’t speak about this traditional wisdom because those who spoke of them are almost gone.
Our elders always give instruction like this.
They give instruction. It seems they place [the blame] on young people, saying that we do not heed advice anymore.
Why is it like that now?
Now, you see, we’re doing what they spoke of.
We’re doing what they spoke of.
The one is given instruction, (s)he cannot practice it.
After one listens, they go and leave it behind.
Some of them would speak with that in mind.
This is what they spoke of.
I also used to hear that people would stop practicing traditional wisdom.
I used to hear way back in the past that when they have no more instructors that they will stop practicing traditional wisdom.
Now, do you think that what you heard about people not practicing traditional wisdom has come true?
Yes, yes, it’s come true now.
You see, it was like people back then knew the far off future.
It’s like they knew.
Something that you want to leave with us, what kind of instruction would you leave with us young people or those of us who are listening?
Yes.
What would you leave with us?
I leave with you what I want to leave with you.
Now, love each other, young people, love each other. Do not offend those around you.
Be like a family.
Now, you see, one easily goes the wrong way when [disobeying] traditional wisdom, or starting from being offended.
[Men and woman] the same way, even women have become like that.
They go the wrong way when they are offended, go wrong because of that.
But like this, you see, if you do not try to offend those around you, your fellow youth, or even if they’re old men or old women
So it’ll be like you’re in a safe shelter.
Remember this even when I’m gone.
Yes, thank you. Thank you for telling us stories.
You’re welcome.