And then, because we people are not the same
Since we are not the same, it will be like some people do not see and do not hear what they have said.
They would talk like that about a person who is like that.
They said that in the future, he will not be Cup’ik, will not be Cup’ik.
However, they would closely aboserve the one who followed their traditional wisdom who is inside that community house.
They said that one who closely follows traditional wisdom like this would live for a long time.
They say that it will be as if his breath squats down [?stays] if he is obedient
And he does not put down those around him, and he doesn’t talk down to those around him.
Those who spoke would tell that person to treat everyone the same, even if they’re young or small.
All of them would tell me that if I am a bad person, and if I disregard children after [?receiving money for them]
My husband would consider my behavior and leave me.
And then men also, they said that if a man is too mischievous
They leave those who do not take advice when they also disregard children after [receiving money for them].
And then they scatter and are unable to take husbands.
And then a man can’t take a wife since people know about him.
We also hear about these things, our food, and what we women sew into clothes, that no one will do it for us.
They said we must work for them ourselves.
If our child has bad behavior like that, and is disobedient, and a liar, no one out there will take care of that for us.
We will only do it ourselves.
Yupiit back then have traditional wisdom concerning boys.
They say that a boy is able to change.
They say that he will become repulsed with his life.
They said this, and I was especially afraid of that back when I started observing the traditional wisom.
However, they said that if a woman is like that, it is more difficult for her to change her life, her ways.
You know, if we do not try to change them [for the better] starting from when they’re small.
They said that she may change, you know, back when we didn’t choose our own husbands, when they didn’t choose their own husbands.
They said that she may change when she moves into her in-laws, but she will take upon her former ways again.
Through that, they would evidently try to teach and instruct us women from the beginning.
And then, even if they’re disobedient, or do not heed [advice] on alcohol, to talk to them.
And even if he comes to, do not treat him badly because of his alcohol use when seeing him.
Instead, show them our love. Try to let them know our love, you know, our mother’s love.
Also, do not treat him badly as he’s drunk.
Also, if he does that in our house around us, do not run from him.
He may act scary, but he will not do anything if he has no one to go against him.
Also, after he’s drunk and did something bad, you know, in that house, at least this is what I’m like.
Try not to run away from him, try not to leave him. You know, I’m more afraid of what he may do behind me.
And if one is offended, and we leave him all alone there, one of them will be offended.
Or else, he may take a weapon and try to hurt himself.
And the next day if my child had been drunk, console him the next day, and don’t scold him right away.
Console him as I did before to try to make him happy, and ask him what he’s going to do. Just that.
With his being drunk the day before, do not first bring up his anger if he had become angry.
And if had been scared, do not bring those up, but console him.
And they say now, and I see them being hungover, yuussugluteng.
And if one of them is hungover, he seems to be irritable.
Only when he stops that and starts having fun, starts doing things, when he can speak well, well, he doesn’t seem to be able to speak well when he’s hungover.
And when he starts to speak well and doesn’t expect [to be scolded] anymore
Then, one should talk to him about what had happened the previous day.
And do not scold him, but speak kindly to him.
Explain to him, clearly explain to him how you were scared and how you would leave your fear without scolding him.
One of them will be very regretful then.
He will regret it. And tell him you love him, and show him your love.
They would instruct us on hooks for dragging caught seals that they put on gaffs. You seem to know it. (Yes.)
They said that if we travel in the ocean, to keep that hook in possession without leaving it behind.
If we go somewhere or go to look from a vantage point, we shouldn’t leave it, but use it as a staff.
With his potential to get into misfortune, when he takes that gaff along with him, that [saves] him.
One day, my grandfather, my father’s father, went to look from a high vantage point where it was a little shallow.
As he was looking around from up there holding that, they started caving.
When that happened and he also wend down, as they were [?crumbling], he did this with his gaff.
He hung on to that, and didn’t go into the water.
That has also saved me twice.
That is the instruction on the gaff, the instruction.
The other time, when I was going to go in as it collapsed under me, that gaff pulled me out.
Also, when I was traveling with thinner ice in my path, had I not had that in my possession when it was snowy, if I sunk, I would have fell in right away.
That’s also the instruction concerning that. I did this and it kept me from sinking.
When this money is gathered, it’s good when it’s gathered there
To things he need to use, [culukarkat], or boats as it’s gathered, if he gives it to help a person.
That’s why these days, when a person is paid, that money makes it make or break for them now.
When a person gets money, for the ones I see outside, getting drunk is the most important for them.
If he uses it the wrong way to get some substances, and if he travels to places where they have them, he uses it for those things.
It sometimes brings him to misfortune.
The people who spoke on this told us that sleep and laziness keep us destitute.
Those two.
They say those two deprive people of things [they need].
But one who is knowledgeable about traditional wisdom, [raised right], a person who follows good things
The ones I saw doing that were not in need of anything too much.
They were also good hunters because they followed that good instruction.
There were often things up ahead for him.
When we were growing up, because we didn’t have things premade for us since we only tried to make things out of what we caught
They would tell us that, to try to be good at hunting and catching.
They told us about that, that one who lives without being in need of anything lived as a good hunter, not a bad hunter.
If someone works for something, especially one who works for alcohol, and even one who works for smoking
To me, it seems he must believe in something, and seek help.
If a person has absolutely no faith, he will have no strength though he tries.
Believe one of the two. Believe in the ways of the church.
And if you cannot believe in the ways of the church, Yupiit speak things that are no different from the instructions of the church.
Believe in Yup’ik wisdom if you do not wat the church’s ways.
Believe in Yup’ik wisdom, try to adhere to it, and try to obey it.
A Yup’ik will not mind, you know, if person asks an elder about instructions, asks about what do to in the future.
To me, he will be very thankful. To me, he will be very thankful if he asks him.
Even though I am not working anymore now, when people ask me, I am wholeheartedly thankful inside.
That traditional Yup’ik wisdom, especially now that I am an old lady, it seems that that Yup’ik wisdom comes to me more strongly.
It’s because they’re no different from the church’s wisdom.
They are very strong and very good traditional wisdom to me, that Yup’ik wisdom and instruction.
When I spoke to them, I would tell them, "Since I love you, I have always refrained from drinkins because I don’t want you to feel helpless."
It’s also because they see their peers have alcoholic parents.
Also, they bring them in in shame wanting to feed them. They say their mom and daddy are drunk.
I would be extremely thankful inside that they were compassionate.
I would them about that like that: "Since I love you, I didn’t raise you by making you feel helpeless.
"To pay me back out of great love for me, remember that I do not want you do abuse that alcohol, so keep away from it."
That’s what I tell them.
These days especially, they are getting more difficult like this:
It truly seems that these poor people are caught in the middle of Yup’ik and Western cultures
It’s like my grandchildren here are caught between them.
But despite that, in some places here, our grandchildren, at least my grandchildren, are starting to speak only in English.
I try to speak to them around here with whatever [English] fluency I have.
It truly seems that they show that they do not want to listen, or they also indicate that they do not think they are true.
But even though they do that, we must try [to teach] them like that.
Especially also like that, we must not [give up] like that because they don’t want to listen.
Even if he doesn’t listen, he will someday have regrets about one that encouraged him.
He will someday think that he was shown love.
When I was growing up, I used to think that those who taught me like that were not showing me love.
It turned out that they spoke to me out of love.
With that in consideration, I try to speak to them now.
These days, there are also a lot of our young people that take their own lives.
They end their own lives.
Or the fight and kill each other, kill their peers.
Truly, we do not want to lose a young person, a precious young person, who takes his own life.
About our young people, we people are not the same.
Some people are treated badly by their parents, or when they are constantly told that they are doing something wrong, they lose their will to live, not wanting to live.
And then when a person does that and starts to think of himself as bad, he considers his conflict and takes his own life.
But even if he ends it himself, he will not awake to paradise.
Instead, he will awake in a bad place that he set for himself. And it will definitely happen.
So, no matter what our children do, let us parents not excessively blame them, as they call it, blame them and start treating them badly, but with encouragement.
Let us only admonish them with encouragement.
It’s unfortunate these days that every young person has taken upon that way, and even those who are not young do it.
You see, there were a lot of legendary little people, and those carrying signaling gaffs would appear.
And when that one with the signaling gaff was going to reach the village, he would disappear.
And when he disappeared beside them, there would a certain number of sleds going down to the ocean.
After the people from this village who were at spring camp went down to the ocean, those little poeple would be ahead of them.
They were all ahead of them.
After those sleds went to the ocean, they would go inland. Their sleds were red, filled full with animals.
And then right when evening set, those sleds here would go toward the two mountains.
Right when evening set, there would be one with a signaling gaff who was from this spring camp settlement.
And then there was a community house outside of us, a big community house, quite a big community house.
Our grandfather, whom they said was Elnguq’s father, came and sat up there on the community house’s flooded entrance.
He kept singing to that person with the signaling gaff coming inland toward us.
And we girls and boys listened to him as we held the ones we were hugging.
Oh my, we eventually learned his song.
You see, he would sing like this, watching that person with the signaling gaff:
"One with signaling gaff raya-yarra-iya, aa-iya the many [?little boys]
"Spotted seal-spotted seal-spotted seal-spotted seal, bearded seal-ssiya-yarra-iya
"Aa-iya, the many [?little boys]."
We who listened to him completely learned it.
And when the one with the signaling gaff arrived, when he stood before him with intent, he stuck his gaff here and told a story.
He told the ones who would get them that there were things to get.
Oh my, sleds as many as the little people who had gone ahead of them would go to the ocean every day.
It turned out that they had shown how many would go as they went ahead of them.
I bested a shaman in my sleep.
I came to, let me tell you the story.
I came to in the wilderness, sitting all by myself on the ground.
When I heard something and turned my head this way, I saw a door here.
There was a right arm approaching, constantly touching the land here.
I thought, "My goodness, this is not something good."
Then, before it reached me since it was a little far, I prayed as I slept down there.
I prayed for the Lord to help me, and that I knew that I had nothing that could oppose this thing that was going to reach me.
I said that I had not the same power to oppose it, but to give me strength.
I asked to be given strength for this.
When I was done, I opened my eyes as I was sitting with outstretched legs liek this, and my knife, my huge knife, was between my legs.
How did that come? Despite my being in the wilderness.
I grabbed it.
When I grabbed it, I saw that it was going to reach me.
You see, I faced it head on.
When I faced it as it was going to reach me, I knelt here and took the knife on the handle like this as an opponent.
When I opened my eyes after I had prayed, I felt different and seemed strong.
And then when the right hand came here
I did this with the knife and put it here.
It started crackeling. I shut my eyes tight as it was crackling.
You see, as it was crackling, it stuck into the ground.
It also cried out, and it seemed that the metal was crying out as it seemed to retreat.
Oh my, I turned my head and the arm was gone.
They say this to us: these days, we have the breadth of mind as a fingernail.
Our will of mind is easily destroys, and we easily go the wrong way.
Indeed, those we were born in time to see would speak to us without thinking we’d get offended.
And they would speak to us as if they really were scolding us.
One of you probably recognizes it when I say this: let us encourage each other while we do not consume alcohol.
They would speak to us without worrying, and they would speak to us as if scolding us without thinking that we would somehow get offended.
After they had spoken to us as if they were scolding us, they would say this after when they finished:
"The one whom a person loves... a person does not teach one he does not love no matter what they’re like or if they’re misbehaving.
"A person teaches one whom he loves as if he is scolding, without thinking he will get offended."
I grew up when alcohol was scarce, and I didn’t see anyone drunk.
And then later, before I wed, I started seeing people who would get drunk.
We’ve heard from the beginning that alcohol brings misfortune, and it is truly more powerful than sickness today.
This alcohol has become stronger.
And other things, medicine abuse is also stonger than sickness.
Since they are facing very hard times these days, people aren’t leaving here anymore.
Instead, there are now a lot of people leaving here to abuse alcohol, marijuana, and other things like medication.
And sometimes, we hear that a lot of them gather to travel.
Oh my, it truly is not a good thing for people who abuse alcohol.
Now, we are discussing alcohol.
This is not the first meeting I’ve attended.
When I attend meetings, we fight against alcohol.
And from what we hear, other people aside from us also fight against alcohol.
It’s distressing because it’s a bad thing.
One who begins to abuse it cannot give it up. He cannot give it up.
But one who tries will give it up.
And one who refrains from abusing it will stop abusing it.
You see, back when they talked about the world ending, I was born in time to see those who talked about the world ending
Way back when they talked about a time of need, I was born in time to see those who talked about it.
And then, you see, now I always remember what that one person said.
And then as I always remember it now, I am wary of this world, afraid that it will end badly.
And it’s apparently not just me. Some are not wary of this world.
When I started becoming observant back then, I noticed that some old men and old women would walk by supporting themselves with their knees, yet some could not walk anymore.
When they had old women and old men [among them].
Some would take them, bring them out of the community house, and take fire baths.
And when they were done, they would bring in those who could not walk anymore.
Then when they spoke about the world ending, some of them said this:
"The oldest ones who had been alive under the earth, the place we heard about beneath,"
Those oldest ones said, "A person lives for a long time. He will not do so again."
They also said this:
"Back then, you see," when they spoke about the world ending way back then,
"You see, some of these great hunters,"
That old man who was just waking in the community house, I heard him toward the door by the wall
They said that one of them got up, "Ah, it should happen already during our good time."
Apparently, it was when the one who would get them was nigh.
Apparently, you know, they said that when people hoped for something. They said that people always hope for something.
They said that they would beg to be liberated when that time was nigh.
And back that, at that time, I also used to see those days.
It seemed they did it in one winter.
The daytime came to be, upriver where the dawn would come, going upriver toward the north.
From beautiful days, night would set.
Some of them men would say that there are not false days. They wouldn’t offer any explanation.
And one day, we were rowdy, playing until it got dark.
I entered a house that wasn’t the house of those who had raised me.
And right when I went in, a woman came in after me.
Then when she came in, she said before she sat, "There is day out there now."
And then the old man among the people of that house, the old man said
"When it’s time, nature does not keep its people in ignorance. Instead, you see, it gives them a sign."
He said, you see, that it gives them a sign of what it’s going to do. When it was time to teach them, looking at its people, because it’s time, looking at the people living here on the earth.
You see, he said that it is showing them what will happen to them through that.
And then he said, "You see, people will wait expectantly. You see, as they are waiting expectantly, they will wait no more, and no one left will be waiting expectantly.
"Also, you see, they will no longer hear anyone talking about the world ending."
Now, we are in the time that he talked about.
You see, he also said that there would be no snow anymore.
In other words, when [nature] puts it into one place.
Now, I always remember what he said.
I am not wary of this world
I actually don’t know to how far along this world is.
They also said this.
They only talked about fish roe.
They said that this fish row will appear every year on earth.
They said it would not change.
They said it would not be dangerous to humans though it comes every year. That’s all they would say about it.
And now, there are freezers.
But there are two kinds of these. There are two kinds of freezers.
But when I think about this salted fish, it will also keep every year if it is salted right.
Though it takes on years, that will not spoil either.
There are two kinds of freezers. We don’t know how far along they are.
And these days, our Caucasian counterparts are [qagret] out there in this day.
But as they go, we do not know what they do.
When I think about it, you see, I’ve started hearing since quite some time ago
The populous lands out there that I’ve never seen who do not know cold have started getting cold. It’s started getting snowy where they do not know snow.
That is causing harm to plants, and probably to young animals.
It is also causing harm to those that were able.
The people in those lands way over there that I do not see are in heavy consideration, considering how to grow plants.
When I imagine being there, they will not turn back from their lives and value Alaska’s people.
I was also told this, I was told about this untranslated topic from someone who was knowledgeable:
"Those who grow plants must grow plants. Those who food must go with their food."
And then he also said this: "You see, when that time is nigh, when that false day is covered
"You see, people will start fighting, acting crazy. They will no longer await anything."
You see how it is now, we are in that time during the current days out there.
They do not care about those around them anymore.
It is also clear these days. Their grandmother does not teach.
Neither are we pitiful ones, their grandfathers, teachers in random places here.
It truly seems that the people of the next generation, it seems like we are just watching them out of fun.
We have no sense of discipline these days.
And when I think about it, when the world is going to change, even if it’s heading to winter, it will not tell its people what it’s going to do.
It turns out, you see, that it would do any of them since it already showed and told its people that it would do that to them.
And then, that old man also said this:
"You see, when that time of starvation is close, these two, shee, Bering cisco, there will be a lot of those fish in the rivers.
"There will be a lot of those fish."
They said that if a person runs out of food, he will have one of those as a food source.
They said that he would eat one of those.
They said that despite that, he will become skinny, his flesh will deteriorate.
Those two fish are appropriate and good, and they are fatty.
"Those," he said, "Those two fish are the fish during famine."
I haven’t forgotten this.
Since I’ve been remembering it now, I’ve become wary of this world.
Then they also said this back then: "These fish, king salmon, chum salmon, silver salmon, those do not [?]."
That’s why, they said, the people back then passed on this traditional knowledge to the current people of our next generation:
While those are swimming, if a person is able, he should not be lazy, but take as much as he can from them.
They admonished them against [?] during the fall.
They said that type of winter is going to happen, everything that comes after them will be gone.
I always remember this now.
They said that when famine comes upon them, I was also told about this. It’s been a while.
It also touched my mind when the one who told me talked to me, and it also touched his mind when he said this:
He said that he dreamt that he was fishing with a drift net, drifting in the water like this. However we or you fish with drift nets.
Then when it was time, he rolled it. As he was rolling it, a fish appeared down there.
It was [?entirely] covered in bones, yet it was moving.
Then when it appeared, it said to the one who caught it, "Wait. I have two things to say."
Then it said to the one who caught it, "After a few years, a famine will come.
"Also, the spirit of theft will move."
You see, of all the people I grew up in time to see who have always spoke, this was the first time I heard about the spirit of theft.
Then after the person who told me that, it seems that every year, people are getting worse. They seem to get worse.
They’ve become reluctant to share with their families, even stealing food.
When I think about the people now, if their stomachs are deprived, how far will they go?
They will also steal from their families.
Or, people are not like how they were before. Some have no more social inhibitions, and some have become dangerous, and some will be killed because they have food.
It’s getting too long. That’s all for that.
I would watch them rejecting advice, and being disobedient.
I knew they weren’t good people.
They covet their peers.
They would covet those who worked and provided through their stomachs or their bodies [with ragged clothes]
Those who were unable to follow traditional wisdom, those who did not obey the wisdom passed down to them.
They lived in suffering, not living right.
You know, they were in need of things, were in need of everything.
They wouldn’t live long either.
They wouldn’t live long, those who followed their minds like that.
They wouldn’t live long. You see, that’s how true what the people back then talked about is.
They wouldn’t live long.
They would also pass away easily with minor sicknesses.
They said that I would do what [instructions] I heard.
If I live according to my loneliness, I will not be doing it to myself, but will cause suffering to those who have departed from me
If I live according to my suffering like this.
Since I would cause suffering to them, I should support myself to those who are good, who are mentally healthy, support myself with those who are healthy.
They say that I am like this now, though I have reached this age still standing.
Indeed, he said that he showed what a person is like.
"You are truly showing what a person is like."
They said that some people who live according to their loneliness too much
They say that a person who lives according to his loneliness too much goes through [life] quickly.
A child spoke truly about what a person is like.
He was a child to me since it hasn’t been long since he was a boy.
I looked at him and said, "You see me now. You may seem insignificant because you were born so late.
"You make me remember that traditional wisdom must not be misunderstood when you say this.
"You’re a good person.
"Also, never [?regret] the fact that you are standing alone, dear cousin."
I say to her, "To not [?regret] it. When we’re near the end, when we reach it, we will go after them."
Only those who doubt the traditional wisdom passed down to them are like that, being in need of things.
Things are scarce for them, and they have nothing. They are always without things.
Also, this mischievous behavior now, it’s like it steals what some people need.
It’s like they trade what they need to use for mischief.
They trade what they need to use, giving them to their mischevious behavior.
Poor things, they are now misbehaving with what they call alcohol, and this marijuana.
It truly seems that what they want to abuse is waging war against them.
It’s like they give their own spirits through that.
They pass by what they should do and forget it.
Now, people have become alcoholics, coupling it with what they call marijuana.
Those who continuously abuse mentally impairing things also take their own lives through that.
It’s like they take their own lives. It is very heartbreaking to part with the younger generation.
Also, I would apparently put myself down too much.
That’s why I don’t want young people do to that now, telling them not to think themselves incapable.
Instead, I tell them to treat themselves well, and to believe they are capable.
Also, when I was a girl like this, I would associate with my fellow girls.
It was because I thought I wouldn’t be as pretty among them.
Those are my memories.
I also didn’t join those who were mischievous.
I also didn’t join those who played outside in the dark.
But when we were in the wilderness, I would only slide and gather wood.
I would also hunt.
That why, young people, do not dislike yourselves, but treat yourselves well.
Also, if you remember them, even if you don’t do them, you may do bad things if you don’t go to them or take them.