Yes, okay Betty, you were a health aide long ago in Akiak.
You were part of the first health aides.
Please tell us what your work was like back then.
Now, I will tell the story of when it started, starting from when I began, even if it’s not complete.
I first started like this:
Back then, when the doctor would arrive, and the nurse would arrive
Since they chose me to speak for them, I’d start by speaking for them.
I started, and I was knowledgeable.
And when I didn’t understand what they said when I was going to pass on their words to a person.
I asked them about the meaning when I didn’t understand the doctor or the nurse.
When I understood its meaning a little in Yup’ik, I would pass it on to a person.
And when they gave them medicine, they would right them down, indicating them on their labels, and give it to that person.
That’s how I started.
And when the doctors or nurses planned to arrive
They started letting me know.
Because I wasn't knowledgeable
I wouldn’t follow my disinclination too much.
But I would always try to help them with my speech.
Then one day, I went to the teachers.
When a person came to get me
After putting their name, I’d write down what they say their problem was as best as I could
And how many days it started since some don’t say it right away.
I also didn’t know how to give them medicine by myself.
About those things I talked about, I’d wait for the teacher’s lunch.
When they had lunch, I’d bring that writing over, and give it to the teacher.
He would put me on the phone. After I read them, he’d go with me.
The only phones would be in the school at that time.
Those first very tall ones upriver when they were BIA schools.
The teacher would report to the doctor.
Then when the doctor spoke to that person over the phone, he would write them down since I would watch them.
The teacher would write what he said, including those medicine.
And if he doesn’t get better
If the medicine he took didn’t help him, they’d say to bring him to the hospital here. I wrote these down.
Since they would obey me, I wasn’t intimidated by the teachers anymore
Though it was clear I was taking up their time.
Then when he stopped speaking, that teacher brought me to the clinic.
He would instruct me on what that person should do.
I would do that with them.
Then in 1960
What I talked about was before 1960.
In 1960, the [tribal] council took me, meeting in December with me.
Then at that time
They said that they’ve taken me, and to help those that arrive like this.
Since I had no choice, I said I would do it if I were able.
And since 1960, it was like what was before had passed.
I didn’t quit in 1960, but I went to the teachers.
Then one day, that teacher, they would be replaced, replaced.
I went to one of them, whose name I haven’t forgotten.
But I won’t say their name. I know it clearly.
I went to them. I’d go to them in the past.
This one wasn’t like the others before them.
After going to them several times, they told me
[S]he said this to me: [s]he didn’t come to Kwethluk to be a nurse or a doctor.
[S]he said [s]he came to teach.
Then I said to them
"Since I do not know much about the English language, I also need you teachers’ help since way before you."
Then [s]he said that [s]he reads what I write.
[S]he said that there was nothing confusing.
[S]he said that I should report by myself, briefing them over there.
[S]he said that I should report on the radio by myself.
Then I said to them, "Hey you, since I was born, I have come from all the days before me to this day.
"Never once have I pressed the radio’s button."
"No, I will teach you. I will teach you if you come with me inland."
I said, "If you want to."
I took them out of their house, and we went inland since it was lunch time.
Then when we went in, when they used to do this, you know, with no clocks, we waited for the doctor to be open.
When they heard the first one speaking, I think they would then answer.
Then this teacher said to me, "Watch me. I will watch you and have you speak."
I agreed.
Then after making the call, [s]he called them.
Then [s]he said to them that it was my report.
Then, oh my, I didn’t learn right away from watching them.
But what they said, I didn’t know what they pressed.
When [s]he was finished, [s]he said to me
And after [s]he put the instructions for the medicine, when [s]he spoke to the doctor
[S]he said [s]he was going to have me repeat what [s]he said.
The doctor was fine with it. [S]he told them to do it. [S]he agreed.
Then when [s]he brought it to me
Since it was still going and [s]he gave it to me, [s]he said to me, "Now, talk about that," then that [s]he would listen to me.
[S]he was in front of me.
Then I said I heard what [s]he said.
And I said I heard what the patient needs to do, and their medicine.
"Did I hear you right?"
You know, I couldn’t say "over" either. I didn’t know how to say "over" at that time when they used to say "over."
Oh my, [s]he said it’s good. [S]he said it’s good. [S]he said I understood it well.
Then when I was done with it, that teacher said to me
[S]he said that from then on, I would call by myself.
I said, "I won’t call by myself tomorrow. You’ll go with me." [S]he said [s]he’d go with me.
Then when it was lunch time, I went to the, bringing with me that patient’s things
Because when they got me, I’d write them down as best as I could.
Then when I went to them, [s]he said to me, "Are you going to make the call?"
I said yes.
[S]he said that I should...
After the previous day, [s]he said that I should go inland and call the doctor.
I said to them, "Come with me. I didn’t learn what to press."
[S]he said it’s on there. You know, it’s there in big letters down there.
Then we went inland together.
Then [s]he said to me when we went in to press these and read these.
[S]he said to indicate Kwethluk since it’s put there.
Reading those, I looked at and read those here.
It wasn’t long. Though it was sudden, [s]he answered me without scolding too much.
I told them about that.
After telling them, after saying what [s]he said
[S]he said that they should take that medicine.
I also wrote them down though that teacher was watching me.
When I was done, I was done.
[S]he told me to look at the medicine by myself over there and set them out.
[S]he said that [s]he would look at them that evening. [S]he was at their house, at the doctor’s house.
However, the phone was inland at the school.
You see, it’s distressing when one doesn’t know like this.
It’s, you know, scary for people. It’s scary for people.
But since it’s like it takes getting used to, it seemed that it became more [?manageable].
And what used to make the heart pound doesn’t make it pound anymore.
It isn’t bothered anymore.
Then after [s]he went with me several times, [s]he gave me keys.
[S]he gave me keys for [the school] up there, and the clinic’s keys.
Even if I didn’t go to them when the school is locked, [s]he told me to open it, go in, and use the communication device.
Also, when they said to prepare medicine, [s]he told me to go down, open it without notifying anyone, and prepare the medicine.
I started doing that before I went to training.
Then just when I started doing that, I got into training.
When I started training, I would try to do what I had done like that.
But we became two as we were going back when we were going to train.
There were two of us like this.
But when the two of us started working, we would eat [lunch].
We wouldn’t have lunch.
It would open at 10:00, until when would it go? I think it would be until 5:00 back when we started.
We wouldn’t have lunch because the teacher sent students to us
All the way until it closed.
And after closing, when people came to get us, we would go there.
We would go there.
And when they came in at night while we were sleeping and woke us up, and I wasn’t the only one.
When they came to get us, we’d go to that person[’s house].
And after I trained then, it truly seemed that I was not reserved to even give them medicine [since] it they became clear.
But I would give out what I didn’t fully understand, including the names I didn’t fully understand.
I wouldn’t give them to a person without explaining them.
This is it for that [story].
There is a lot before what I just said.
Starting from what I first started to my training, I’ve spoken about this.
You just said that when you first started, that you did it without any training.
How does this pertain to instructions on how to make your own living
It’s in their traditional instructions, that a person must make their own living.
What can you instruct to us young poeple about how to work to make your own living like that?
You see, I told you this: "I didn’t choose to work hard with them on my own
"But I passed the doctor’s and nurse’s message, passed it on in my hard work that wasn’t my choice."
That’s what I did. I started back then without knowing how to take are of medicine.
But when I  went to training, I would do it according to what I had learned.
So, how did you learn to to speak English, or how did you learn to how understand English back before teachers came?
Did you go to school before then?
I went to school before that.
But back when I first learned writing
But when I became an adult, I think it was when I learned after becoming aware.
I don’t know what year.
I can’t say what it was to this day, yet I went to school when it was in a building.
It wasn’t a school, but in a house.
We started going to school from then, and they eventually built a school.
Then when they made schools, in our school, I stopped at the fifth grade.
Those was my education until the fifth grade.
Back when you first started learning, were you not asked to speak, or to speak in Yup’ik?
Oh my, they told us not to speak [Yup’ik]
Since we didn’t know English, we didn’t listen to them.
So did you start speaking English?
And as we went, when we started [speaking amongst] ourselves, and we started understand when the teacher spoke to us.
And we also started speaking to them.
Others, even the Catholics up on the Yukon, say this now
Back when they first went to school, they said they’d be punished when speaking Yup’ik.
What did they do to you?
They wouldn’t punish us even if we spoke Yup’ik to each other.
But you are speaking English as you go to school. You, all the school boys and girls, speak English, not Eskimo language.
Since it’s our language.
I still remember what that teacher said to this day.
Okay, thank you for telling us the stories.
You’re welcome.
They’re also related to [?] in Napaskiak downriver.
Paul Guy, the Guy family downriver in Napaskiak are my grandchildren.
But his father is my child.
And Andrew Guy is your grandchild?
Yes, he’s my grandchild.
I do know him.
I see.
And recently... so, you have eleven grandchildren.
Yes.
Phillip Guy’s children, and his older brother’s childre like this
There were 12. They both have six children each.
But one of the children of the older brother passed away last year.
Have you not gotten any great-grandchildren yet?
I did get great-grandchildren.
I have great-grandchildren. How many great-grandchildren do I have again?
You see, Kiarrngualuk
Then the younger one...