...when you [fist saw Caucasians], what did you think?
Well, we Yupiit were amazed by them.
Were you scared of them or what?
I had no sense of fear, but I was amazed by them.
I don’t know about the others.
I see.
When you were a little girl, you girls probably had traditional instructions.
Now, I also hear that those in their first year of menstruations have admonishments.
Please talk about their admonishments.
When a girl had her first menstruations, they wouldn’t let her travel.
They would have their children stay.
They would also keep her from getting too close to these unmarried boys.
They would watch them very carefully around those who were in the first year of menstruations.
They would speak to them, speak to that girl, instructing her about how she should be
And what it’s like when she’s started menstruating.
They used to very carefully watch over their young boys.
Now, they’re nothing like that these days.
They’re different now.
How would they carefully watch over them?
What admonishment did they have to do that?
They carefully watched over them, admonished against them.
They also told them not to breathe on these young boys.
They told the not to get too close to them.
Also, they always have messy hair now.
They also told them never to have messy hair.
They told them never to have messy hair.
And when they made food for a young man, they told them never to have messy hair.
And they said that only after washing their hands to work on fish.
That was how they carefully watched them. They’d carefully watch them then.
So, what’s the meaning behind not breathing on a boy? Or what’s the meaning because going downwind from him?
What did it mean?
They say that when that boy makes love to one in the first year of her menstruations, when something happens
A young man becomes bad, becomes abnormal, and lacks common sense.
That is what they feared about these girls within the first year of their menstruations.
What about when you started working on fish?
What traditional instructions were there about fish?
Everything had traditional isntructions back then.
What did they especially instruct about fish?
They would give a lot of traditional instructions about fish to these young girls, their children
To treat it with reverence and love.
Don’t make a mess of fish too much, or trample upon it.
When a little fish comes when they drift net
Even if it’s just one, cut it well, hang it to dry, and eat it when it’s time.
However, they said that if they leave it strewn, it’ll rot if it stays there.
And the bugs, maggots, will eat it, destroying it.
They told them not to do that out of great love for what fish they had.
When they dried, they’d store them, store them well.
They didn’t waste what fish they had.
And what they wouldn’t eat among them, they’d feed to the dogs, not leave them strewn about.
Also, they always dumped the food scraps somewhere.
Food scraps had dumping sites in the wilderness where people didn’t trod.
They wouldn’t dump them in the dumping sites for honey bucket, but there in the wilderness.
They treated fish with great love.
And since they didn’t eat Western food long ago, since it was their only food source
They instructed their youth to treath these fish with great love.
And they’d tell them not to dump them in random places, not to tread over them.
They didn’t waste what fish they had.
Now, you’re 80 years old.
Back when you started becoming observant
It’s clear that it wasn’t like our current day.
In our days, many things don’t need to be set out.
The changes you’ve seen in your observation, what are the biggest changes in your observation to this day?
You mean what things are like?
Yes, what things are like, and what a person is like, what we Yupiit are like.
What all of us are like has changed.
We’re nothing like long ago, having become bad.
And even when we speak to our youth, they don’t listen anymore.
They don’t obey anymore.
They only focus on the bad things they want to do.
These boys and girls can’t follow our commandments these days.
If they want to treat their parents as we were commanded to like that
They’d live well, and would not become pregnant without husbands, wouldn’t become pregnant.
There are now many of those.
They don’t respect their parents. Though they’re told, they don’t listen anymore.
I wonder what’s making many of us young people disobedient?
Why, in your observation also, why are we so disobedient now?
I also think like that too.
From what? Or is it because they follow their parents?
Or do they think their [parents] do it? I have no idea what makes them like that.
You see, though we try to make our youth good, they don’t tend to turn out good.
This alcohol also makes it worse for boys, the young ones.
When you first saw someone drunk, what did you do?
I was staring, not knowing what was going on with them acting insensibly.
Going from Bethel down there, they started doing that.
They acted senselessly and foolishly.
And we who’ve never had that didn’t know that they did.
But we would admonish them.
When they do it, though we admonish them, they don’t listen anymore
Though we tell them not to do that, that we don’t want them to do that.
What do you want to leave with the young people?
How do you want to be remembered by your descendants?
What do you mean?
If you have something you’d like to leave us with, leave with us, your descendants
What is something important you can think of that you want us to remember?
I want you young people to live well.
And when they get married, we’d want them, we want them to treat their spouses well and to love them.
Without treating them badly, also because some are abusive, we admonish our youth not to do that.
Also, if they gather food, we instruct them to take good care of what food they have.
We instruct them to do that.
We tell them to take care of those with great love so that they’ll be good.
Also, because they feed people, and give to those who have none
Through that, we tell them to always prepare their food, what food they have, well.
No matter what this fish is like, dry it, and prepare it well.
Dry it so that it won’t spoil or rot, and store them.
When they had caches, they’d put what fish they had into caches out of great love though they [seemed] bad.
Those were our traditional instructions.
I also tried to practice the ways and instructions of the first place I lived.
Eventually, I can’t do anything anymore and stay here now.
My body’s become weak, and I can’t work hard anymore.
Okay.
That’s it. I have no other questions. But if you want to say something to add to what you’ve said.
I think that’s it for me.
Well, I’m glad when we see each other.
Yes.
I also regularly watch you on the TV here. (I see.)
Okay.
I watch you.
I think that’s it.