Okay.
This is will be all for what I’ve just spoken about.
But also, in order to try to keep our bodies safe here on this earth
Yes, I’m also going to speak on how it wouldn’t get into misfortune.
Now, these days.
These rainproof clothese in the winter: rainpants, raincoat
Those should not be absent in the winter like this when traveling.
For this body to be good
Also through that, if we walk on this land, in the wilderness, these rainproof clothes shouldn’t be absent.
It’s so that this body will be good.
Then, should a person get into misfortune in the wilderness without rain gear
If the weather turns bad on them, they used to instruct us
They said that if we get lost, we shouldn’t keep going but stop.
Or if a blizzard hits us, they said that especially if we [have nothing but] what we’re standing in like this
If we travel without anything, and if we don’t have the supply tarpaulin
They used to instruct us like this:
They said if we come to misfortune, if a blizzard his us, to dig into the snow like this.
We should go in, but they’d also hold something small.
They said this walking staff would be salvation for this body.
Or, if [s]he has no staff in the winter, it [s]he holds on to a branch while going
Then when a blizzard hits and [s]he is lost, [s]he should dig and have the snow cover them.
But also, to those things, you know how we refer to those deep [hollows/depressions] as kanarvikneret.
If there’s a blizzard, and [the summit] up there is high, and this [depression] is deep
They said we shouldn’t have the snow cover us there.
Instead, they said that we should dig into a low hill
When we go in when we fit in there, we should close our entrance with snow.
But, they said not to get it too small.
Do this to the snow, and set this [staff] upright to pierce [the ceiling] up there.
If we get covered in snow, do this [to open it] up there.
They said if a person is airtight under snow, [s]he will suffocate.
Once, we almost suffocated inland.
There were three of us: my younger sibling, and that one who moved to Kwethluk, and me.
When we set up a tent in a deep [depression]
A blizzard started at night when we [set up] when it was windy like this. The weather turned bad.
I opened my eyes and felt very suffocated. I quickly got up and hit this [ceiling].
Apparently, the snow was weighing down on it like this.
We got out after much struggle then, and our things were wet.
And yet, the weather out there was very cold.
When it’s airtight under the snow like this, it’s evidently very hot and hard to breathe.
The snow kept melting like this and made our things, our beds, wet.
That’s why they would admonish us like this:
If the weather turns bad in us, we shouldn’t shelter in deep [depressions], shouldn’t let the snow cover us.
Instead, [shelter] on a low hill or where it will be thin despite snowing.
Also, pierce [the ceiling] up there like this, and even move it back and forth.
Then, if we also know that we’re not going to make it back home
They said we should stick soemthing in the land toward our destination and go in.
They said that if dawn comes with good weather
We will know and not be confused, and will go to our destination over there.
This, you see
Since noticing things is not demonstrated too much anymore, and since we don’t demonstrate it anymore
We’re starting not to know it like this.
We are ignorant these days.
That’s all for that [subject].
Then, what’s also been on my mind
Those who raised us back then didn’t keep us from knowing our relatives
Even if they’re in other villages somewhere.
You know, these days, they’re told those people are their [male to male] cross-cousins, maternal uncles, maternal aunts, [male to female] cross-cousins
Those do get pointed out.
These days, we don’t know anything like this.
Back when we were little boys like this, those who raised us back then would teach us.
And when they arrived from [other] villages like this, when these relatives arrived
They would point out to us.
They said we and that person are related somehow.
We’re [male to male] cross cousins, or we’re [male to female] niece/nephew, like that.
Through that, we’d suddenly figure out [how we’re related] when they’re pointed out.
These days, however, we don’t know how we’re related like that.
And through this, not knowing how we’re related, how we’re not shown [how we’re related]
These days, people are starting to fight each other.
And yet, though they’re related like this, they’ fight. They’ve started fighting these days.
People back then were peaceful.
There was no one fighting each other.
That’s the extent of my story of that.
These days, like this, yes, we’re no longer like our ancestors of old.
Now, it’s gotten better like this. We’ve gotten better. They said we’ve gotten better these days.
But we haven’t gotten better. We haven’t gotten better.
People back then were tight-knit.
We have gotten better without struggling for:
These Caucasians have provided us with our clothes, our vehicles, various things, our food, and our buildings
We stopped suffering, stopped being afflicted with great cold at night, started being hot all the time.
It had gotten better.
But they’ve gotten worse, we’ve gotten worse these days.
They’ve started fighting each other. They’ve started killing each other.
It went exactly as this Bible said it would.
Now, you boys and girls who are listening like this, remember what you just heard.
Those who raised us back then weren’t like this.
There weren’t a lot of accouterments in a home because their homes weren’t like this.
And when they slept at night in the extreme cold, these buckets filled with water would freeze.
And even if they were on the stove, even though those kettles had been warm, some would [end up] frozen.
Yes, this [is it]... (So, how...)
Now, your question, ask me.
You know, how to take care of men, women.
You know, men’s traditional wisdom about owmen, you know, how men, you know, their traditional wisdom, how married couples, you know, take care of their spouses.
Okay.
Now, married couples like this, this married couple
The priest asks them a question like that.
In front of God, [s]he asks them this:
"In your marriage, will you respect each other, obey each other, obey your husband?
"Or, you who is a husband, obey your wife."
That’s how this is done
But we’re instructed like this:
They said this married couple, if they’re married like this and want to do well
They must obey each other like this, not disobey each other.
[S]he must watch their husband, his stomach and his possessions, and his clothes.
And [s]he must watch over [the animals] he catches.
Then a husband also with his wife whom he takes care of
A woman takes care of the inside of a home, the things in the home that the man caught.
However, a husband also [works] out there, outside the house
Or [in] the wilderness, that’s his responsibility.
He must also watch over what he needs to take care of for his wife.
Water inside the house is a way to take care of a woman.
Then even if it’s like that, they must obey each other without being at odds with each other.
They’re admonished like this if they want to do well:
Couples don’t always treat each other with love.
But like this...
What do they tell them again?
They shouldn’t be at odds with each other.
If one’s spouse tells them something to make them upset
They said that for a husband, even if his wife says something to him like that
Even if it destroys his mindset, if he doesn’t do the same
If his wife has no opposition, she will stop things.
Then [if] the man [does the same] to the woman
If he’s not in a loving mindset or talks about her behavior
They said the woman shouldn’t misunderstand like that, and not make herself an opponent.
People in any relationship who are at odds cannoy stay together.
Or if siblings do not interact with each other well, they cannot stay together.
Then if this married couple is like that, if they are at odds with other, they won’t do well.
And especially when they bring forth a child
They said with that, that was something we were especially strongly admonished with.
They told us not to have them come to us when we upset if we have children.
They said that these children are not ignorant like this.
And the ones I watched back then weren’t like this.
You know, they didn’t, you know, they wouldn’t argue about their thoughts in our presence.
These days, however, what did they become?
And even if there’s a lot of people, if this married couple wants to speak badly, they will angrily argue.
These days, we know what causes too much destruction.
This, what they’re abusing these days, alcohol is what destroys a married couple.
And even if there’s a lot of people, when they start abusing that, they divorce.
It’s a source of great destruction.
And yet, our instructors here and our [Caucasian] counterparts are working on it.
Since it’s what they [brought], they’re working on it.
These days, this alcohol torments them.
People back then didn’t do this, the ones I just talked about.
They never killed their wives. They never raised their hands against their children.
These days, it’s the cause of destruction for married couples.
You just asked me what a married couple must be like.
They will live well if they don’t [abuse] anything.
They will live better if they don’t abuse this alcohol that’s admonished against.
Yes, what I just said...