He became my husband or had become my husband.
So after that one told me, 'ok now go up (place not said) and I'll bring your clothe later.'  We were at Kelliquciq located above Kegg'ukaq.
And so I walked up early morning because those people had moved at a time when stoves weren't used regularly and kettle water was boiled outside in a firepit.
Anyway, I walked up.  If those people looked at me, I would look away and speed up.  When I got in I was hot so I stripped my clothe.  The people there didn't do anything.
I stripped my clothe.  That mom of mine didn't do anything and say anything.  I stripped my clothe off and slept because I was sleepy.
There, so I didn't even know for a long time I had been engaged.  We even went home and arrived at our place.
So then it happened by chance because the man was leary someone would beat him. I was spoken for.  That's how I found out about it.
So, little did I know I had a husband and continued my life.  It was by fall time when they speared fish where I became aware at Chefornak.
Were you born there.  What?  I was not born in Chefornak.  Spring season I was born in May at Isriq spring camp.  That evening someone found eggs where I was born.
Where exactly is Isriq, where were the people of Isriq from Chefornak?
Below them.  Have you seen those two mountains.  I've seen them.  Below the two  mountains.  Across from Kipnuk there are those two mountains, across from them two.
Were they a village or a fall...They were a big village with lots of houses made of soil/mud for spring camping.
And not far over from there were people of Nuuteqerr with houses and they had qasgiqs (mens house).
Over from them were the people of Cevv'arneq and even more populated.
They were close together and you could hear their noise like dogs.
People walking were visible.  So, their spring camps were very close.
I grew up at Isriq spring camp not far over from other camps with Isriq people.
Oh my, they spring camped.  Around them were many little people.  There would be someone coming to a village carrying a gaff as a signal that he had caught a sea mammal but before reaching the village the person with the gaff would no longer be there.
After his disappearance there appeared several sleds heading down.  After they go down, those little people were doing things ahead of the spring campers.
They were doing things ahead of them.  The sleds would go down and return with sled full of red color and plum full of sea mammal.
So, it would be evening when those sleds came by and they would be going towards the two mountains.
So, that evening there appeared someone holding a gaff signaling catch who was a camper from this village.
And so there was a semi-subterranean house right next to us there, a semi-subterranean house, kinda big semi-subterranean house.
Our poor grandfather, he was Avnguq's father came over and sat above the ground entrance to semi-subterranean house.
He sang for the one holding a gaff/stick  coming up.
Us girls and boys were like a nest around him listening to him.
My, we even learned his song.  He sang like this with his eyes on that gaff holder.
(The young one holding the gaff needs help. Aiyiyaa Aiyiyaa All you young boys. Spotted Seal Spotted Seal Bearded Seal Aiyiyaa All you young boys.
We really wanted to learn as we listened to him.  The hunter after he carefully stood in front of him holding a gaff/stick, poked his stick aside and said a story.
Telling the ones who will retrieve his catch.  So, then
those little people presented ahead of them how many sleds were going down each day.  They showed that the same would happen as them.
Oh my, the same amount as those (little people sleds) traveled each day to go get the catch.  And, it was winter.
At that spring camp they filled the back wall and place more on the floor.
They filled up the large back wall/corner with sea mammal inside those spring houses full and some on the floor.
Oh my goodness, that's how they were the ones I saw.  Hold on, we're running out of battery power.
My grandchildren's children, my great grandchildren.  Pangall'aq's children oldest daughter, Nuraar, Qussauyaq, Arnaquq, Dick, and the last of them down river is Nanugaq.  Yes
And, there are Uyang'qulria's five children, sixth is growing in her belly.  Also, Miisaq's three children.
Downriver, Ciulluk's one child who had five siblings following him who weren't complete but miscarriaged.
They were going to be after Ciulluks child.
And over at Kwigillingok Akat'aq's children are also my great grandchildren.  Their oldest sister is hree.
The second is now in Chefornak with her in-laws.  She visits her parents.
They were seen back then.  There were many shaman in my time.  Okay, tell us those stories.  We hear now, there were good medicine man and not good medicine man.  I could be random but you know them so please converse to us about them.  Yes
When I started to notice some of the shamans, some people back then were upset about them.  Some about to die; upset or fussing about that medicine man.
Some about to die went through that; saying that one is doing something to them.  Upset that (medicine man) was doing something to them.  Fussing
There were some labeled as medicine man but there was absolutely nothing said about them living as shaman/medicine man.
They were like regular people and they conversed good things about them.  But, there were those that were bad (shaman) among them.
You see, my dear cousin I also was visited by a medicine man.  See
I was visited by a medicine man in my sleep.  So, I became aware.  Let me tell you about it.  I became aware being in the wilderness sitting alone on the tundra.
And then I heard something and looked back this way and saw a door.
There was an arm, right side touching the tundra moving towards me.
I immediately thought, oh gosh that doesn't look good coming my way.
Then, before it reached me because it's kind of far I prayed in my deep sleep for God to help me.  I also said that thing moving towards me was beyond my ability to fight it.  I knew that.
I didn't have the same skill to go against it.  But to give me strength.  Give me strength towards it.
It was getting creepy before it reached me, and done I woke up.  As I was sitting like this there was between my legs my big curved knife.
How did it get to me?  And, I was out in the wilderness.  I took it.  After taking it I saw it was almost getting to me.
Look, I turned my body to face it.  When I faced it, it was about to get to me I was on my knees here holding the curved knife by the handle with both hands.
At that time after I prayed I woke up not myself and felt strong.
Noticing the hands were here, like the right side, I put the curved knife and placed it like so.
I felt it grinding and I closed my eyes.  It was grinding.  While grinding for a bit it poked into the ground.
It made a calling noise again.  As in a metal wire making a calling noise.  And then it shrunk.
So, I looked back the arm was gone.  So, I thought and here was an uluaq poked into the ground up to its handle.
So, did I miss that one.  It seems I cut it though.  And so I got up and looked around me.  There were hands bouncing around me.
They didn't do anything but bounce up and jump.  I ran after them to chop them and soon they are still.  As they're still I cut them and threw them any which way.  There were fingers I was throwing separating them.
So, I was done doing that and stood up holding onto my curved knife.  I headed home to Kwigillingok.  I headed home.
I started having dreams like that of various kinds.  From this or that person Segg'aq because he had said to me when he was intoxicated.
"You there, let me treat you."
"I treated that one over there, Ayaginaar, who is living to this day."
"Let me treat you.  You will have to bathe yourself adding a little bit of salt water from down there to your wash water."
He was going to continue to add to his work of healing as his.
As he had to Ayaginaar.
In my mind, I didn't want to do that so I said to him looking at him it was okay for me to live the way I did, it was okay.  I didn't want to do it like that.
So he came into my dream starting from then when I didn't accept his healing medicine.
Ah, I stopped dreaming about him.  But, I started to dream of those things.
I went home and arrived.
Oh, at that instance I looked around after cutting up the hands.  It was early spring.  Christmas had just happened and it was not too long after Christmas.
The tundra had melted.  The ponds had melted.  But ice had not melted.
There was water in between the rivers ice.  I looked around.
The tundra was like that.  I went on home, and when I arrived and went in our house. I realized it was in my sleep and just about to wake up.  I opened my eyes.  When I opened my eyes, father asked how I was so I told him.
I told him what I dreamt of.  I said to him if my dream is true I will watch how the weather is all spring.  So, I said that to him even though I didn't tell the entire dream.
So, I kept watch of..you may not know where they pitched tents at the mouth of Kuigilnguq.
I think It was Tengmiarsuq's family who went there that I remember.  They were the last ones.  Yes
This side of Kwigillingok had tents, down river there were alot of tents.  And, above them there were a lot of tents.  Across from there, there were alot of tents, as well.
They use to go there to the mouth of the river.  So, oh my.  That was how.  We went downriver and we stayed across the tent of many people.  My cousin, first child of Avamaq were next door to each other.  He was healthy, long before he went.
As we stayed there not long they were catching sea mammal.  I was skinning seal limbs and trying to finish skinning those limbs of skinned ring seal.
As we were in our tent, the door opened from the entryway.  Our tent is a dark tent with light color in the middle to brighten inside.
That's what we were doing.  He said, coming in that person behind me and it was Qayuq's dad who was living then.
So, he said to Acill'aq's name, 'my cousin go see them across the way.'
So, I said, 'who are you referring to'.  He said, 'that one, Segg'aq has died.'  There was nothing happening to him.'  He was fine.
I said, 'how did he die?'  He was spitting blood as he does and died.  He started spitting.
Oh no, so the two went across together.  After they went across I didn't want to do anything so I put down my work, went outside and looked around the tundra.
I was remembering my dream from last winter.  It was exactly to the time he ceased seeing the water on the river bank between the ice.
It was exactly the same as my dream.
Oh, I was scared at that time.  I was scared.
Oh, that is how I was.  I just told you my story.
Ok, ok, what did the good quiet shamans work on?
They had a medicinal ritual/practice to heal people.  They healed the sick to the end, made them well again giving them more time to live.
In the qasgiq when they worked on people who were getting ill from bad shamans, some of them used their arms and make pulling motion holding nothing and a shaman while laying flat would sit up and down.  They were not holding a thing.
He was the one who made the ill, sick.
Oh, they couldn't deny when they had been caught.
The ones who sat up and down, sat and had no way of denying doing anything.
They couldn't say they didn't do anything to him/her.  That's how.
That's how alot of people talked about them.  The shamans said to be good at the time of ritual were pardoned but were transfered to a bad shaman with evil intention.
That's how they were.
They put it out to be seen and returned it to them unknowingly or invisibily what became their evil intention.  They or to them it came around back at them.
That's how they were.  I don't know all of it completely but that 's what I had heard briefly.
Since you became aware back then especially up to today what is a teaching you remember or sticks out in your mind you can share.
What are the teaching you heard long ago from your elder's when you were a giirl.
See, long ago in the beginning
our speakers spoke to us like they were scolding.
Poor us, we listened sitting very still, and begin to sweat.  Our hands begin to sweat.  We stood still as they spoke.
This is what my mom said to me, "when you hear a teacher look at your teachers mouth until they are finished talking.  Even it feels like they are addressing you watch him/her until they are done.
So, I followed her advice and did that.   Even it seems you're being scolded watch his/her mouth.  Look away only when they're done.
That's what I did.  Surely, anyone who took in knowledge like that doesn't forget it.
Then, we stood very still and listened and when the speaker was done, we could get up and leave.  Only when he's finished.
We stood and left when they're done talking to us.  It was like scolding us as we listened with emotional pain and they're like scolding.
They did that.  So, now I recall those teaching and recognize them when I reach it.  I recognize all of it or remember some of what the speaker repeated to us.
What were some of those wise words?
They told us the same thing over again.  Their wise words were knowledge passed on and were said more than once.
So, what they said were pretty accurate from those people back then.
So, now we have speakers of the good word (bible) who are our own people.
And when I hear that our first teachings are invalid to use
or that it cannot be used anymore, when I hear that, I think
of Jesus and what he said.
I am now here not to destroy teachings and the law but to finish the work.
He didn't say that any of our first teaching were forbidden but said he was here to complete a mission.
I always think of what Jesus said.  Always and see at my age now I remember everytime I reach it and when I recognize it in other people the sayings from those mouths I watched come to me.
They also had a premonition of someone's future and I remembered the statements at that juncture.
They described how they would turn out.  So, that's how they were.
And sometimes while a young girl my age walked away while they are speaking to us, he would say.
Oh my that one, why did she go out.  Perhaps she didn't want to listen and left.  So, she will only follow what is good for her life.
That's what they said about him/her.  When she likes something she will see it herself.  That's what they said of him/her.
Oh my goodness, those initial sayings for proper conduct were not bad.  That's why they lived long when they followed them.
When they moved them their fragile bones crackled.  They were out of position.  They used tuntu skin for carrying.  There bedding.  They crackled.  When they placed where they will rest you can hear bones make shooting noise.
They (joints) had apparently moved back in place.  See, that person had lived to the fullest.  Life to the fullest.
Some grew new teeth, which they called that stage, growth of new teeth.  They describe their teeth to be like mink's teeth.
They had new teeth growing.  I really wish I have new teeth come out because I've lost mine.
You mean they lost their teeth and those...they lost their teeth and were replaced by those.  Poor me, I'm not like my youthful stage now.  I have my tooth pulled when it's moving.
Right now, there are how many, three moving. They're moving.  So, the top has no teeth left.  Toothless except only one.  And this side has no teeth left.  Except these two.  Bottom has one teeth below.  And several left further back.  Bottom of the other side so far has not lost any teeth.
Those that lived a long life had crackling bones.  Did people cry about the pain or...They didn't cry...ven they looked hurt they didn't cry.
When they were placed down joints made noise indicating they had relocated from their dislocation.
Oh my, our dear grandmother, poor when we moved she was on a caribou skin to move her.  That's what happened, moving her, carrying her and they put something warm around and under her.  Her fragile bones would make the sound of getting back in place.  Goodness!
That one told us stories our Grandmother and how she was.  She got married to one of the men who was known as a medicine man.  She didn't watch her husband.  She didn't sleep by him.  When he came in at night, she left.
So, one day her husband left him.  He want her as a wife but he got ready to leave.  After he left her.  Out there, right out there next door.  You've heard of the people of Cakcaaq?  The end of the mountains coming this way.
At that time, she imagined she had a husband.  There was another man who came to her.  He was a handsome man and there was no other like him in Alaska.  She even liked this very nice young man.
Poor, one day she was getting ready to bring him things.  She had lots to bring him with a bowl at the bottom.  They were piled up to here.
So, carried them with care and delivered food.  So, she came up, handed the bowls and sat and waited then left.  She went out and one time after doing the same she went out and notice a bright light.
It was full moon and bright.
So, as she went from the Men's house door going back this way she saw...
That one who was her partner use to tell her he will get her and was going to get her soon.
Down below this place the lower side doesn't freeze all winter even it's frigid cold.  Oh, his kayak...a beautiful kayak was parked on the bank and a person down there.  When she saw him he raised his paddle and moved it waving her to come on down.
That's all she had in mind and began to run in the air as she ran or so it seemed.  As she was about to reach him, she heard a scream from above where she came from.
So, when her body slipped she realized she had fallen, backward and backward she slid.
She remembered the kayak, quickly looked over there.  Right before the iceless spot is where she fell but that kayak was gone.
So, it was gone, she stood up, cleaned herself up first.  She looked up to the village and there stood someone in front of her house.
She slowly went back up.  So, while she went up, she started to wonder about the bowls she had.  So, those many bowls I carried, where are they?
So, she didn't reach that person but because she saw the kayak in front of the Men's house she thought she put the bowls there and was going there.  That person asked, 'Hi, where are you going?  Come here."  "Hold on, I'm checking on the bowls."
So, when she got to the spot where she first saw the kayak, there were no bowls by the men's house.  So, she looked past and around there and saw black things behind and much further out.
She went to them and realized they were the bowls she had in her hands. And not a single clean bone in any of them.  (Laughter)
So, then she collected all of them until she finished.  She had thrown them out pretty far.
So, she finally went to that person who yelled at her and she took her in.  Once inside a house, the household members circled around the girl.
Asking her why she had ran towards the water?
She said she had seen a a kayak and that one who lifted, waved at her with his paddle had made her hurry down.
At that time, she got ready to do something like cutting trees out there and went out.  She would find a bunch of cut wood already done once outside.  She would carry them in though.
And when she was told to get food from the cache, she would go out to find the requested food all ready inside a container.
From that one who was coming to her.  He filled the container household wanted
They declared to heal her in the men's house.  The one doing his healing ritual (En'ariissuutem) said this of her, "pitiful, it's as if underneath the girls bedding was home to mice.  Many mice.
There were many trails from everywhere, man's trail.  That's how it was underneath the girls bedding.
Oh the girl often went to bed.  As she layed, with eyes closed waiting she smelled nice fresh air and he would come through the door.  When they had tunnel doorways. That young man would come in and take care of that girl.
Oh then they got ready to heal her medicinally using two miniature dolls, male and female taking over the men's house.  So the one who performed the healing practice sent a pretend female leave her toward that one who kept coming to her.  He made her leave.  And with her, a male doll was placed next to the girl being the dominant one to block off the man from reaching her.  When that male takes over.
That's how that one, our poor grandmother was on the road to recovery after the medicine men worked on her.  She was well and changed from there on.
So, that was getting well.