Those round [?], they called them tannin. They were good.
Yeah, we’re rolling, so thank you for your patience.
We can go ahead and start.
Now, you should talk about what you used to hear way back then.
Okay.
In my earliest memories, people weren’t like this with nothing to do.
They only ate from the wilderness. They didn’t eat too much Western food.
Now, boys are completely sedentary, and ask only of fathers.
Since I always had work, I never asked anything of my father, also because I tried to do things on my own.
I’d go get wood and had three dogs, and a sled.
And with those drift nets that would deteriorate easily that had wooden floats
And those old bullets.
I’d always try to set the lead line, thinking of how we might go hungry, go without flour, and I’d have no cigarettes
Though [s]he’s admonish me, I’d go, but when [s]he spoke to me, I’d listen.
You also just said that you always had job, and that you liked to work. Please talk about your workplace.
When I worked at a cannery, I’d always [?].
Then I’d owe my peers as I’d sleep at their places.
I liked to work.
And they’d always let me come first.
Sometimes, I’d feel ashamed.
And now, there are no more people in these churches. There are no more people. These TV’s are making them empty.
These things, and whatever they call them, they stay up late at night for them
Long ago when there were no TVs. There were only those portable stoves that would make rumbling sounds, none of these.
So what can you advise of us young people so that we will be good workers?
You see, the Caucasians like those who work well, one who doesn’t mess around but focuses on work..
Those are the ones they like.
One who is distracted when working cannot stay long.
And a worker who works at the co-op down there and messes around cannot stay long.
They fires them.
Do you still work at the cannery?
I stopped.
Instead, I started getting money from [?].
The ones who receive money give them to who’s responsible, including food.
You’ve probaby heard of traditional wisdom from your elders. Please talk about those.
My late father always said to me, :"Never be lazy. If I’m lazy, you know of the fish down there
"Even if I see them and don’t know how to set a lead line, I will be hungry."
I’ve never been hungry since then.
I’ve never been hungry.
And if you work well, they won’t fire you. You’ll be good.
Since I tried to work well, I stopped working.
And I wouldn’t go by boat, but always with a plane.
I became the first in the airport across there, and they’d always call me first.
When we were going to come, they’d call me first. And when we were going to disembark, they’d also call me.
You see, that’s why I’d be ashamed.
I was always first.
Look, you shouldn’t mess around either. I’m going to tell you.
You are a worker. If you work without messing around, they won’t fire you.
I also wanted to tell you that I’ve reached this age before I’ve been fired.
And my leg here is [?] starting from here. I have injured legs. And this one is plastic with two screws.
How much did flour cost back when things were inexpensive?
They were inexpensive, $3.
How much did they weigh?
A 50 lb. bag was very inexpensive, $3.
And tea was $2.
It was inexpensive.
Now, they’ve become difficult [to get]. They’ve become difficult.
What they took last year won’t be found.
I won’t speak of the old boat motors.
How expensive was gas?
Five dollars...
A drum was $25. It’s very inexpensive [compared to] now.
Now, they’re difficult [to get].
And [motor] oil was $2. Motor oil, $2.
I wish things were inexpensive now. I wish they were inexpensive.
Yes, they’re not difficult [to get], and things are expensive. They’ve gotten expensive.
If there’s a final thing you’d like to say, say the last thing now.
Let me pray. Do you want me to?
Yes, if you want to.
Okay.
Oh, Lord Jesus, God. God, our father, who art in Heaven, hallowed be thy name.
May your kingdom come. May your will be done on earth as it is in Heaven.
Give us this day our daily bread. And forgive us our trespasses as we forgive those who trespass against us.
Lead us not into temptation but deliver us from evil.
For yours is the kingdom, and the power, and the glory forever and ever, amen. Thank you Jesus, amen.
Thank you.
Now, try to always work well. (Okay.)
Now, you see, they fire those who don’t work well.
Caucasians like one who works well.
Now, before they fired me, [?].