...with this, [we would try to catch] wilderness animals...
With this, we’d try to catch wilderness animals, riverine animals, and fish.
We get them when we’d gather and subsist.
And one who doesn’t subsist has nothing, is poor, and has no food.
They say that’s what they call that one who doesn’t gather anything.
But they said that one who subsists obtains things.
Back in our time
Widows, and you know, whom we call the poor, and the orphans
Back then, there were those who had no financial care
Because there was no welfare back then.
But these people who were able by the themselves, those who could catch from the wilderness
Those who are good hunters gather food.
They say that that one who is to care [for the less fortunate] is given by God to catch many things
So that [s]he can give those to them.
So, our parents back then would always tell us this:
"Now, when you go, when you are able to provide for yourself
"For those people, if you have some, if you obtain what you can use to help
"Give as much food as you can to one without food
"Especially widows, the poor, and orphans.
"And not always just with food.
"If you have clothes for him, if you have extra, help him with clothes to wear if you have any.
"If you have anything to help that person, you must."
They’d also tell us this
Not always that
Some mornings, my mother would tell me back when I was young when I got up
"Now, go out there and check on the people.
"They won’t have water, won’t have wood, and won’t have something.
"Go and check on them, and the women with no providers."
As she requested
Since I knew those women and those without providers needed that
Those who couldn’t gather wood on their own
I would go to them and help them with my body even though it was food, if they didn’t have wood
Because they said wood was [to help with] a food source.
They said wood is like a food source. They said one cannot cook food without wood.
That was how I was supposed to share as the one who raised me told me to
"Now, go check on the people out there, and help them with whatever they lack.
"Also, if you have food any know of anyone
"Now, try to give that person food.
"You see, that person’s gratitude to you is very great."
Watch, they said, our caretaker, the Spirit of the Universe, will exchange his gratitude for more.
This is all for sharing
Helping each other, and giving depending on how much one is lacking.
This is all I’m saying about it.
Okay. I just wanted to...
Well, helping out is an ancient practice.
And people back then who helped out wouldn’t want to take payments.
Our ancestors back then wouldn’t take payments when helping out.
They used to help out without requiring payment.
And families, relatives, would live together in single houses.
Back at that time
Families, relatives, in one house, would live in one huge sod house with wooden accouterments.
Across there were those who subsisted, and here those with children, four families would live like that in the house.
I was also born at the cusp of that, when relatives lived in traditional sod houses like that.
People back then had good relations, loved each other.
And now, my ancestors are actually from Qinaq.
That one from Qinaq who stood up this morning and spoke is from the same village as I am
That boy who was the very first to open up our gathering.
My ancestors, my parents were from Qinaq.
Back in my earliest memories, that village had one resident Caucasian.
That village was my earliest memories, a village where they lived across the river from each other over there.
That village apparently had that one resident Caucasian.
It’s unfortunate that helping out these days is no longer practiced.
They can’t prepare for guests anymore. Though young people are able, they can’t do them on their own anymore.
And without payment, they can’t do it without a little payment.
Back then, those people evidently practiced love.
And those who couldn’t fish, and the unemployed who couldn’t drink Western tea
All winter, they’d eat of people’s gifts.
I also had my earliest memories.
I have early memories when my father passed away when I was very small.
And after that back then
From there where my earliest memories were
My maternal aunt’s husband brought us upriver to Lomavik.
I also stayed there downriver at Lomavik until I became aware, and from then on, I have always been aware.
People took care of us. My mother had no provider.
Gifts were a cause for great thanks.
Food, and clothing, clothing that covers this body
People’s gifts were very great to me, in my opinion.
I am extremely thankful for them.
I would covet those with fathers, families, large familes, many siblings.
People’s helping out, taking care of others, helping others
Those people back then who helped out gave me this to say right now.
I am very thankful for them.
You see, these days, you know how you say that people have changed?
We know how they’ve changed.
Families, close relatives do not act like relatives anymore.
And some don’t know their relatives, or their mothers’ relatives.
And they don’t know their fathers’ relatives these days.
It’s because people’s treating each other with love has changed now.
Then when I asked after that time, "How did those in the home live?"
My mother would tell me this:
Those people lived
This didn’t claim anything, and this didn’t speak of their food, and they didn’t say they’re low or gone.
Very tight-knit relatives had one house.
And no one was stingy.
She said those families helped their relatives a lot.
And they never refused them anything. Even if it was their only one, they’d have them use it without payment.
You see, these days, every little thing
What was to be for help, to be given, has turned profitable.
We also had a traditional instruction.
Though we’re women, just women, and can’t buy anything
That we can help people out.
I thought like this back when I heard this: "I wonder what I can use to help out?"
My mother said this to me:
"If you say something to a depressed person, if you say something good, you will help them."
Then she also said this to me:
"His tattered clothes with many holes without anyone to sew it
"If you sew the tears closed, you shall help him."
Those were how we helped others back in our lives without money to help others.
That’s how we helped
And because I used to practice mending these clothes.
You see, it also becomes a habit if anyone starts this.
And if they see something torn here, they’ll remember it, "Let me fix this now."
One can learn like that. Anything can become a habit.
When I practiced that, it became my habit.
Even if they’re these Caucasians, when I see them, I want to [mend] them.
And I would think that I want to mend that tear closed.
It’s because anything can become a habit.
In helping out, there are many ways to help a person.
We’ve understood part of the many ways to help others through food
Because we helped each other back in our time by giving to each other.
And since some who do not catch anything, fish, or are unable have great shortages of food in the spring
Since through that, we carry them through food scarcity until food comes.
But we’re going to move on to this: helping each other.
Helping each other as a community.
Helping each other with something, or sometimes, we practice that in villages.
Sometimes, one of us has a some big job to do
Or trying to build a house
Or because they had wooden homes back then, since they didn’t have wooden boards at that time
Also because there were none of this plywood back then.
But since people would get wood for houses from here on the Kuskokwim
Since they don’t use those much anymore.
Also, though they regularly used what they called mudhouses in my time
Since they used those at that time in spring camps, fish camps, and winter camps
Thye used those for a long time.
But in small villages like this, they ask for help when they work on something because they find them difficult
And since wood is not light, and we had no machines to pull them back then
But, because they took them by hand.
Also, since they spoke to each other
They notify us, they notify those around them when they work on this that needs help.
Then the people of that village prod us
That even if it’s not big and we won’t have to help, to go to them.
When those adults worked together
When they ordered us, we’d get something though it wasn’t important.
And when they asked for a tool or something, we’d get it.
We were like the arms for these adults when they worked on something.
And when they were going to make houses, since they brought them inland to where it’s going to be worked on, they’d bring them up from the water here.
Or also, a long time ago
These villages would ask for help with this.
And when they were going to build a community house, since making a community house is a big job
And since it needed huge logs of wood.
They’d invite, kelegluki, villages.
When they thought their people would be to few, they’d invite villages to their own.
They say that they were going to work on a community house, and asked for help.
Then those villages that they invited would arrive, they would arrive there since they were invited.
But the wood they were going to use was already ready down there.
Then several villages, even two they invited, would work together and help each other.
They’d help each other work on that huge sod house, the community house.
And since they covered community houses with sod back then
And since they covered them in sod after they spread grass to prevent crumbling down
When they finished setting the logs on their sides.
They would work on it like that until it was finished.
When they were finished, this host village would hold what we call today a potluck for the villages they invited.
Back then, they’d hold a feast like a small dance festival when that community house was finished.
Oh my, they would even Yup’ik dance like a reward for that to them.
They had them enjoy themselves.
And after they had a feast, when that was finished
They would end with that feast.
They had a potluck, and were very happy, even Yup’ik dancing.
They cooperated with them, helping each other out.
And like that with what one person was going to make, because they helped each other
With what they were going to do, they helped with that one person’s project.
They’d even tell us to help out and stay among them.
And those villages, even if they weren’t helped that one person
With their ways of helping, when this village brought up something that they wanted to do
They said long ago when there were settlements down there
And since there weren’t many villages
After the Moravion missions first started, the people really worked together.
These missions got a lot of wooden board [houses].
So, we made boardwalks going from the mission to what they called that big store upriver.
People back then didn’t do it to get payment.
Women [know] about how to love children
Especially because they take care of them as children starting from when they’re born.
That’s why, with some of what Lucy knows about how to love children
Using what she knows, she will tell us what she thinks.
Using what you know about loving children
Women care for them from when they’re born when they care for them when they’re born.
Talk about how much you know about their love for children.
About children long ago
Our caretakers back then took care of us, giving instruction about everything.
Starting from when we married, they’d always instruct us so we wouldn’t be ignorant of anything.
And when we had children, they’d instruct us on how to care for children.
Our caretakers back then, you see, were not like how they are now.
We didn’t see many Caucasians, and we didn’t see any money.
I didn’t first see money for a long time.
Because I grew up in scarcity, I woulnd’t get those things.
Also, I do not forget how my mother took care of me.
I clearly remember it.
This is how my mother took care of me:
This food, she didn’t let me squander food and water.
Instead, all she gave me [was all I ingested].
You see, my stomach is used to it now.
I’m going to tell you what I’m like.
My stomach is used to my eating habits since long ago.
Before noon, I will not fill it to this day.
Neither do I fill it before dinner.
It’s used to me not nibbling at random times.
You see, the ancestors long ago were not like this.
They don’t nibble at random between meals.
Becuase there were three meals:
They drank something hot in the morning.
Then during lunch at noon they would eat real food.
We would eat and be full then.
What we were given from our mothers wouldn’t be enough to fill. We’d want more.
And here in the evening, we’d have dinner.
Then after, we wouldn’t ingest anything else until the morning.
And at night, our stomachs were used to it, and we wouldn’t be thirsty at night.
Only when we awoke in the morning would we have a little something.
And when I didn’t have a little pancake, my mother would give me a little piece of fish
Because we didn’t have an abundance.
Then I wouldn’t have more than what she gave
And I wouldn’t try to have more.
Like this you see, a person can practice this.
If our descendants learn it, they can practice it.
With my stomach, I am going forth with with my eating habits to this day.
Some of them however, these things
It’s become different from how I’ve taken care of these things.
But, they never let us ingest anything walking around or standing.
They never let us eat while standing.
I also see this now, and I just watch you as I came in this morning
Drinking coffee, taking the cup, then walking around.
Listen, does it really settle well inside?
This is how it’s changed.
It’s how the instruction of the people back then has changed.
When I came in this morning, I watched you.
After this person fills their cup without asking permission from above
After filling a cup, they go, drink while walking, and goes into rooms.
You see, that’s how it’s changed.
You say that the lifestyle of people back then has changed.
This is one of the changes.
You see, when we had children
They never let them be soiled by their urine.
We didn’t take care of our children by putting them in diapers.
More recently, children have started wearing diapers because of increased Westernization.
We used to take care of children, getting up every time they moved at night.
We with children couldn’t afford to be lazy.
It’s because we loved children. We took care of them with great love.
We didn’t keep leaving them, and we wouldn’t babysit.
Now, I have borne 14 children.
Those ten
These ten, I gave birth to in my home without going to the hospital.
Then these other four after the ten
Only when my body here was not completely healthy
I’d come here and give birth to these four.
But three of these were not born in the maternity ward.
Only this very last youngest one was born in the maternity ward.
It’s because I wouldn’t suffer for a long time, not be in labor for long
Because I experienced the suffering of childbirth.
I’ve said what I know.
When I was first pregnant, my mother would instruct me
"If you want to give birth well, and if you want good labors without going for a long time
"At night and day, every time you think of it, go outside."
You see, we didn’t doubt what instructions we were given as we practiced them.
We’d practice them.
Then when the child was born, we took care of them.
We’d take care of the dear one with our mothers to instruct us.
When they stirred as they got up and night, we let the tiny newborn urinate.
Always doing that, we didn’t let it get wet, kept the bedding dry, never soiling it.
Then back when I did that and learned about clocks when clocks came
I learned the times when they defecated and urinated.
Then I started taking care of them.
You see, our caretakers, our mothers, would tell us
"When they grow up, don’t raise your voice at them.
"Admonish them without adding to your voice.
"If you do that, they will be obedient to you.
"However, if you add to your voice, speak loudly to them, and shout at them
"The child will not live well like that.
"They will be stubborn and disobedient."
You see, I’m speaking about what I know of what I was instructed.
About those, they say, and I’ve heard them say
They say the Yup’ik lifestyle has changed now.
Those are the changes.
Look, everything had traditional wisdom to us.
They had instructions.
Sometimes, when we disobey them
There is also regret about disobeying that traditional wisdom.
That is what I know about raising children, loving children.
If a person loves a child, then they must take care of them with love like that.
Also, let them know about what will bring them misfortune.
Let them know about what will bring them shame, get them incarcerated, what will put them in jail.
You see, the most important things for us parents with our children
When one of our relatives happens to be brought to jail
They parents cannot socialize well with their relatives because of those
Because they raised them, took care of them.
You see, this is how it’s changed.
You say that those people have changed, that the traditional ways of people back then have changed.
And we know that it’s changed now.
I first started what what you know about one of the changes.
They wouldn’t have us ingest anything walking around.
And though we were very thirsty after eating, they wouldn’t give us water right away.
Then our mouths would be dry because we were so thirsty.
And that saliva turned white.
Only when that happened did they give us a little water, then we drank that.
And though we really wanted more, we didn’t have more, they didn’t let us have more.
We waited for meals.
We were used to it. That is how I was taken care of by my mother.
My stomach only follows it, is used to it.
It got used to not being filled randomnly outside of meals.
I want to translate what you’ve said into English because [?] does not speak [Yup’ik].
And I just said that children didn’t have diapers.
We didn’t put them in those to take care of them.
Instead, we watched for when they urinated to keep them from doing it on the floor.
She said that...
My mom said the helped me my first time.
But after I gave birth
Giving birth once, my mother helped me with the eldest.
Then afterwards, when I was going to give birth to the second
Across there in the original Bethel over there around the airport
I gave birth to the second after the first.
I knew when [s]he was going to be born.
And since I knew, I prepared by getting bedding, a mattress for when I gave birth.
After I prepared bedding, since I did it in the summer in July
I gave birth a second time on July 6.
Then after I prepared, I took scissors
Since I watched my mother taking care of me in my first childbirth.
I set out scissors and thread to tie with.
Then when that child was born, I took care of it myself.
The belly button, umbilical cord, and the end over there.
When [s]he was born, tie it here, and tie it here, then I scissored the middle the cut it.
I took care of them myself.
But the four who were born inland after the ten, these ones after the ten
Since I did it fourteen times, I’m telling you this story.
[?] was the father ever involved in this?
Did you understand? Let me intrepret back for those that didn’t understand.
Since some women were frail back then
When there was no other woman in their village
When they were alone and helped each other
Her husband would tie those umbilical cords and cut them.
When there was a woman nearby, her spouse would invite her, saying that his spouse was [giving birth] and to be her midwife.
Another woman would help her from what I know of back then.
However, her spouse, when he didn’t have help, when they didn’t have help
When she couldn’t do it alone, her spouse would help her in childbirth.
This is what that’s like.
Then also, watching over children respectfully
Part of it is also like this:
When a child can’t get up [from sleep], they don’t know when they’re taught.
And though they’re told something, they don’t understand yet.
Then when they get up, when their bodies are strong as they get up, when they start sitting
Those things that are dangerous to them, the hot food on the table when they ate
Since that child doesn’t know about getting burned
Have that child touch that hot thing.
Then after doing that, try to let them touch that [again].
They already learn. That child knows that it’s hot.
They said that for getting accidentally burned, they know what is hot.
Because it’s like they become a little aware when they start sitting
And when fed when they start eating
They teach their child of those.
Then when they do something
Also admonish them when they try to grab things too much.
Don’t let them take it, don’t let them take it.
They say that when a child grows up grabbing things
Allowing them to grab these things
When they grow up a little, when they grow up and become able
They are no longer inhibited from taking things.
They can also take someone of another person if they want to.
A long time ago, they were not admonished, but were allowed to take whatever they wanted.
But if they admonish against those from the start
They will also learn more like that.
Also, when they start understanding, when a child starts understanding
When they understand what we say as they grow more
We have this wisdom from those who raised us:
They said if we have children like this
They said that when a child first wakes up on the morning, they are aware.
They get up without being wily, not shouting, not bursting out laughing, but quiet.
They say they’re aware.
They said that when they’re aware to then tell them a piece of traditional wisdom.
They said that as they are aware, if they pay attention to the wisdom passed down to them
Sometimes we say, "Look, they’re aware."
When these children start staying still, "They’re aware," looking at one thing.
They say they’re like that in the morning.
If that child is spoken to as if they were aware.
And they say they will not forget it, but remember it more clearly.
But they sit still later after they are given traditional wisdom.
And when we wake up, we start moving about and [?becoming actively awake].
Then after that child sits still
They start moving around as if they are not aware anymore.
Then when they grow up more, say to them
"Treat those around you with love, okay?"
Tell them about this.
Since you love them, tell them to treat those around them with love.
"Treat those around you with love today, okay?"
They say that because their mother or father loves them, they want them to go [through life] well with them
Also because it’s the most important traditional instruction, tell them to love those around them.
Then they said that a woman sometimes, though that person is not her own child
When she sees that child, another person’s child, just like her own child
She also tells them of traditional wisdom, loving them as much as her own child.
I don’t understand the meaning of why they do that.
We from the upper Nushagak River also do that.
When we catch those dangerous things upriver, including grizzly bears, and black bears
When we first catch those
Its blood
We open the mouth of our dangerous catch, reach into it, and take some saliva.
Then after putting it on our hands, we apply it on our faces.
They say that when that bear sees us
Through that, when they see us living as one of them
They will not come to us and do this, wanting to harm us.
They respect their saliva that we applied to our faces.
That’s what it’s like. (I see.)
They do that so that they will not fear [a bear].
Okay, we asked the original question about the ritual of getting the first seal.
It’s been discontinued for a long time because there are these priests.
It’s been discontinued since a long time.
I’m going to explain, talk about, the meaning of the time when they started doing that.
They said that long ago, they didn’t used to do that.
But when that child’s father had him sent to the bladders
When they had sent him
When he had stayed there for a year with the living beings, along with the seals, the bearded seals back then.
Only when he had come back home the next year after his stay was complete
That child had them start doing that.
He had them start giving those seals water like that.
After that time, they started doing that to [the seals].
When he was a child, he had gone over there where the living [seals] go and stayed.
And he only returned when a year had passed.
Only when it was time for him to go did he return.
He started that tradition.
When they caught those seals, they wouldn’t throw their bladders away, but inflate them.
They inflated the bladders of every seal down there, and kept them all summer.
Then only when fall set did they pop them, stuff them under the ice, and had them drift away.
They would do that with seals when they caught them.
Its spirit might be there in its bladder. I think they say it’s in the bladder.
They say they come the next year. They would say that.
They say that those that were caught, that blatter returns to be caught again by the one who had caught it.
That’s what they believed happened to them.
They would send the bladders away, asking them to come again, when they held the Bladder Festival.
Speaking of part of it, they said that that...
Later. Let me translate this first.
Kurt Bell...
The shaman, the child of that couple
The children of that couple wouldn’t live in the past, always dying.
Then one of their children, that shaman wanted to do that with their child.
He wanted to send him along with the bladders.
The shaman did that, [sending] him to the place of those living beings.
But he saw the place of those living beings as a house.
When he arrived to the place of these seals in the winter
They said some of them picked on him.
That one sent with the bladders [was picked on by] those seals and spotted seals.
They were different there.
However, they said some of them treated him with love.
They said that when after he went home and started hunting
He would recognize those spotted seals or ringed seals.
He recognized them like us people.
They said that when he started hunting, since he recognized them, he would shoot arrows at them with great force.
He would shoot arrows at them, or harpoon them, doing it with force since he recognized them.
That’s what that’s like.
He expanded on that one about the boy going out to the seals.
There was a man and a wife whose children did not make it, kept dying, kept dying.
And so, this one child, the shaman asked the man and wife to send that child with bladders out to the sea.
And so, that’s what he did.
And then, that boy lived...
That’s how he went to their place to do that.
Okay, he...
...[?] does it without doing it too hard.
But he would do that with those that picked on him.
I understand it.
What he’s saying is that those people that were, or, those seals that he recognized that were good to him
He made sure that he made a good, clean kill.
You know, he really made sure that he did that.
It seems like this was a really important ceremony to go through.
Why did they stop that after Western contact?
They stopped doing that when priests came.
When these priests came
With those legends, when these priests came, they relinquished that practice and stopped doing it.
I see, like this?
Which of these: out of shame, or did they tell you to stop?
Though they weren’t told to stop, they stopped practicing that.
The stopped practicing those practices they had with seals.
Okay, I’ll do one, and I hear something different over there.
But Kurt Bell says that after the missionaries came, they stopped on their own.
May I speak?
(Yes.) Okay.
About the faces of bears, black bears or brown bears
With the first catch, he evidently applies [saliva] from its mouth to his face.
When I was a boy...
(Who are you?) Edward Weiss.
They said this to me, my grandfather:
After shooting and killing a black bear, he’d then have me apply the salive from inside its mouth on my face and hands.
Then he told me this:
He said that when I grow up and start hunting
He said that should a black bear or one of those brown bears get injured and takes me
He said it’ll see my face covered in its saliva.
He said that that [bear] won’t breathe on me.
Black bears’ breath and saliva are very strong for people.
That’s why they can kill by breathing on them, making their faces swell.
He said it won’t do that to me.
Then afterwards
When I was some age, when I was 25
I missed my gunshot, and a black bear took me.
It took my gun like this, but it didn’t breath on my face.
Instead, it looked away from me as it breathed.
That’s what he instructed.
Even now, at least in our village upriver.
Okay, that’s Edward Weiss from Kuskokwim.
He said when his grandfather...
From her point of view of you older men
She thought that you would respect, qigcikluki, animals you hunted.
She asked if now, in your opinion
Your descendants, are they doing that like you now?
Or, she asked, are they not?
Or if they’re not, she asked this: do you think animals will deplete?
Now, I’m going to give some answer to her question.
These seals, I don’t think of how the animals down from the ocean will be depleted.
These instead, the birds, their chicks, and their eggs
I admonish my descendants, my children, like this when their young hatch:
Never to hunt.
And never to [hunt] them when they’re chicks, when they’re small.
Though their mothers bring forth a lot, when they have too few chicks, I admonish them against [hunting] them.
Those children, my children, are probably like those chicks.
They are the reason I admonish them.
Though those birds’ eggs aren’t my children, when their chicks hatch.
And when they’re bigger, if a person is chasing them to another place, I will admonish them
Its mother, never to kill both it and its mother.
The mothers, I tell them their chicks won’t have any caretakers.
I say these seagulls don’t need anything else.
I said their chicks would be pitiful without any mothers to take care of them.
That’s why I admonish them.
Well, he says that for him
He doesn’t think that there’s not much danger to the seals right now.
But he tells his children about the birds.
That when birds have, you know, when the eggs are hatching
And the mother, father birds have to take care of them...
And it’s no different.
We would hunt, then our mothers would honor our catch, be very thankful for it.
Then now, we who’ve become fathers, that mother also know them since she has sons
When her son catches a ptarmigan, she is very thankful and welcomes it.
She doesn’t think it’s too little.
She is thankful for and honors everything he catches.
She doesn’t leave them strewn, or where people have trod since they’re are our ancient admonishments.
He’s... these days...
[S]he will was their face. I don’t know that.
You see, we mothers who are younger than you have no instructors.
Would it be good if you here had them speak on KYUK News
Or, give them time to instruct us?
We have many children trying to provide for themselves. We don’t know.
I also leave my children in ignorance.
It’s because I don’t hear of them since it’s been a long time since I’ve lost my mother.
I like when these older people speak.
They’re true. They still are now, but they’re disappearing.
Western teachings that have appeared are eclipsing them.
It would be good of the Caucasians among us gave us time.
If an elder speaks on KYUK radio or on the news to teach our children, that will help us.
We would be thankful if they gave them time.
There’s much to learn.
Thank you, Eliza.
They instruct us when we’re going to hunt black bears...
...that we should get a wooden staff.
They said that that staff
You know how a staff is useful in the fall for thin ice or for dangerous areas.
That is a traditional instruction up north
If we go to hunt a black bear in the mountains or travel anywhere, to always keep that staff on hand.
Then when we travel for long enough, a black bear will attack us.
They said that these black bears are like people. They grab like this like our hands.
They said that before it takes our gun, that we should give it a staff right away.
They said that that will save us.
Give it to [the bear], it will take it, and we’ll shoot it.
We had shamans. We evidently had shamans.
We refer to those things back then as superstitions.
They're superstitions. They're from shamans.
Wait, wait, I don't understand that. "Piciruiq?"
You know, it’s not true, but is from shamans.
A shaman is of the devil, by what we call it.
Those things
When we got faith in God, many of those things, including medicine, have been given up.
They’re given up now.
Then in our village now down on the coast
We don’t give up hunting for seals.
Now, even if one is not young, ever year in the spring, when he catches the first seal
Also having caught one the year before
When the first man who goes spring seal hunting makes the first catch
As we call it now, they distribute it.