I just have the one that I just loaded.
Okay, I'm rolling.
Back when you were a teenager and you traveled
to other villages or when you went hunting,
did you ever see anything very strange
or did you ever hear of anything strange or scary?
Yes, I did back when I had taken a wife.
I didn't experience that when I was teenager.
My late older brother and my older sister inland, my full sister. taught me.
When I began to travel to learn, my father would take me with them every time, take me even if I wouldn't be helpful.
They really taught me well. They taught me well out of great love.
And that is how I lived growing up. Eventually when I grew older, my brother an I [traveled] by ourselves because we were the only men since many would die.
My brother would take me with him and I started going every time he traveled. I wasn’t helpful with anything.
But I worked for him and started cooking and starting the fire to cook. That’s how I grew up.
And when I became competent, I was born. (??)
I would then think this, would say this, "I won't get wife."
It turned out, you see, that my relatives here would say to me that I would get a wife.
I would say that I wouldn’t get a wife. I didn’t care about women.
It turned out that taking a wife makes one entrenched in having a wife.
When I had taken a wife, I would go to the wilderness more because I started regularly traveling.
It turned out I was fated to do this.
And then when I lay down here on the ground
I wouold fall asleep, also when I lay among the grass.
I pitched a tent over me.
Oh my, I sang a song that I started hearing, ii-yii ii-yaa
It turned out that I was supposed to sing.
Then when I would hunt seals in the spring, in the lakes, you know the [?kevneret], when we hunt muskrats in the spring.
While I was spring seal hunting, it called out to me like this, "Apaqutaq!"
I was started and loaded my gun thinking that I was going to see something.
That’s how I did it. I’ve gone through that twice.
Twice something called out to me.
It turned out that obeying those that taught me
It’s very good. And now, I have not destroyed a person’s mindset.
According to my admonishment.
For a person’s mindset, they told me not to speak harshly to him.
That is how people are.
That is how the people back then were.
They have a custom like that.
They lived in accordance and treating each other with love. They treated each other with love.
My iluraq, cousin, down there from Tununak and I
[?We were always together as boys]. I wonder who’s older? I think I’m older.
We grew up always with each other, and started going hunting with each other.
Yes.
Then the first time, the very first time you saw a Caucasian, a real Caucasian
What did you think?
I was scared of the real Caucasian in Kayalivik
They were scarcly any Caucasians here in Alaska.
The Caucasians coming to Kayalivik, the would arrive in the winter once in a while.
They would give the people fitting names, and give them fitting names from their parkas.
They’d also give them fitting names by their heads/hair.
People named Qiivcugpak [Curly], Nayilek [One with Sealskin]
They even called Neqiacaagalek by that name. They used to call Waskie, Neqiacak.
That person, Itertaalleq [One who Brought in a Lot]
When there was an epidemic back then, he traveled by sled, and he even traveled by sled in the summer. He was a soldier then.
And this, you know
You know that school over there?
The owner, yes, I see the picture of the one I used to hear about. I used to see it when I was a teacher over there.
Kilbuk School.
That Kilbuk [School] is of the [Bureau of] Indian [Affairs].
This is how he first went to war.
Among those who recorded over in Kilbuck School.
His picture over there.
Then back when you first saw a Caucasian, what did you think?
And you saw a Caucasian for the first time.
That Caucasian, it turned out that these Caucasians were like this.
I saw one. Also, when Caucasians came after that, that Caucasian
He slept at Kayalivik. They only [slept] in community houses. And Caucasians arrivered there to the community house where they only slept in the community house.
Their things
They would eat their provisions of [caribou skin].
Caucasians would catch them. They would also bring in grass for matting.
They would spread out grass for matting, and he would spread some out in his sleeping area.
The people back then used to do that.
The men wouldn’t be afrais, and when Caucasians came on sleds, a sled like this
They had various things, tobacco, tea. [I used to see] teapots, [and tea. They would use pitchers like this.]
They would trade a mink skin like this.
Two pitchers [of tea].
They would raise that white one.
And the other here, the other like this.
That was how much it was worth.
They would trade that mink skin like that.
They say this now: "Caucasians back then
"They used to pay a lot of money to people here from Alaska."
They took his money, would have their money
When they bring them out of states.
They would be committed to doing that.
I have a great many stories to tell. And Alaska here
Now, I have gone everywhere in Alaska.
Now, I work in Alaska by traveling.
Then to you, why don’t you want young people to forget their way of life?
It’s because of this
Because of our land
Our land here.
If they forget it,
Even if he wants to be Western, he cannot be without money.
However, if he is traditionally Yup’ik even without money
Neither will he be hungry.
Yet if he has no money, he can’t do anything and can’t eat.
We don’t want them to forget that because it is a promise. Because it’s a Yup’ik way of life.
Like that.
Is the tape still recording what I’ve been saying?
Okay.
So, when they used to have dancing festivals long ago, what were they like?
The people back then would have dance festivals by sending what they called an invitor to that village
To their competing [village]. Then when it’s time, they would get them, two boys with a sled like this.
Then when they arrived, they danced. Those guests would bring various things to give during dances.
Since I grew up just when Caucasians first came
During dances, they would give out cloth, and a lot of animal skins, seal skins.
They also gave caribout hides during dances.
Whatever that host village wanted
We’re a [host settlement here in Bethel.
That’s what they did.
They would ask those people like that to give those things.
Then they would give through dancing. The guests would dance and give what was requested.
They would dance and give various things that they had said, guns, dancing and giving various things, smokehole covers, pots.
It was fun. It was fun.
Then when they were done, the host village would dance.
They did the same when they danced.
Then when they were done, they had what they called a feast.
The guests would bring in [food], at least since I grew up down in Kayalivik.
They would bring in seal oil, various cooked food, walrus, beluga.
Various things, including cooked fish.
They would let the guests go back home with absolutely nothing in need.
People used to do that.
They helped each other a lot.
You know, it was like trading like this
They would trade their things.
They helped each other like this.
You see, I have a lot of stories to tell about everything.
But what are masks? Why do some wear masks today when they dance?
They used to make masks, those magic things.
They said they were depictions of things, depictions of seals or fish.
You know, they have various things around them, even it’garuat [certain plants].
That’s how they made them.
Then when they fishing wearind them in dancing, the people from here would hold Itruka’ar [Inviting Feast]. They also called it Keggnaqurluteng [Wearing Masks] down [on the coast].
They called it Kegginaqurluteng [Wearing Masks] down there.
And here they [called] it It’ruka’ar.
Then when they were finished, they discarded them.
And they would, you know, give those masks to the children they loved.
Like that. People back then had strange customs.
From what I’ve seen of these young people
They’ve become lazy and sedentary.
The youth I saw were active.
They also had strength competitions.
They held strength competitions outside. They held strength competitions to tease each other. That’s what people did back then.
They always competed.
They would run too, even by themselves, and with their peers, what friends they had.
Then they would compete by twisting [something]. They had [?speed] competitions. The young people did various things.
And they wouldn’t let them sleep in the morning. Every one I see wouldn’t sleept for long in the community house back then.
They were very active. When they were told to do something, they would obey.
Then if a person, old man, or man, asked for something to be done
He would run out trying to go before his peers.
You see, the ones I saw were very active.
What about those Yup’ik songs?
Now, you work with Yup’ik songs and you drum.
Where did you learn them from?
It’s because I grew up with those who always danced.
Since I grew up [like that], I also apparently started singing when I was small.
So,
I can write a song if I want to write a song and sing.
Then, those old songs too.
These days, I try to sing a lot as I am doing now.
The baby inland
He’s, you know
You know, the old [songs] he’s heard, since he’s not fluent
The ones I saw would get tired of hearing songs that are always sung every year.
They would always replace their songs with new ones.
They would try to write songs every year. That’s what people used to do.
They keep singing only new songs.
They would always have new songs for the year.
Please sing us a short song.
They said that long ago
My late father would tell me, "The people of Kayalivik had two community houses, two gargantuan community houses."
He said one was called [?Qukutnguq], and the other was Qasgirpak.
And the other was dug out like a mudhouse.
The two ends submerged toward the water, here inland from Kayalivigmiut
Touching the edge of the village.
The hole was like this.
The two ends were submerged, and the middle here was visible.
The one further inland, however, became infested with grass like this with nothing [left].
They said it was back when there was a lot of people in Kayalivik.
My father always told us stories back when we were young.
Now for Qasgirpagmiut?
Noy, you see, I know the songs from a long time ago [and can sing] some of them anytime, a few of them.
"Angaa-yii-yaa agiyaa-ii-yaa." Then their dance movements.
Look how the real dance movements are like this [?upriver].
Mengyaq here is going to go, he’s going to go [dance] in Qasgirpagmiut
Are the people of Qasgirpak curling their tails yii-ya-ya,
You see, when he would sing for people, he started talking about it when he had grandchildren.
He said that the people of Kayalivik back then
Those two community houses would compete with each other in the Kevgiq [Messengar Feast], dancing like this.
The people down in Kayalivik apparently loved to dance.
Yes, that’s what it’s like.
We also used to accompany that with dancing before the host village.
When they would dance for the host village, they would dance with arm movements like this.
How does the verse go again?
Oh, I sang their song, you know, that they sung for a certain purpose.
I made a mistake.
I forgot it. You see, I know some of their songs that I heard very well.
I see.
I can talk about anything from long ago.
Okay.
The [recoding] is full now.
I see.
Thank you very much.
Yes.
We’ll use them. I’ll notify you when we’re going to use them.
Yes, okay, okay.
Okay. Oh my.
Their Ilurapak [Big Cousin], your Ilurapak out there, Louie, is your Ilurapak.
He’s from Cuukvagtuli. The man out there and I are from Kayalivigmiut.
I see.
Yes.