Is it going?
Now, please say your name in English and in Yup’ik.
My name is Martha Sarah, and I’m Uliggaq in Yup’ik.
How old are you?
Seventy-nine.
Please talk about your children, grandchildren, and if you have any great-grandchildren.
I have four children, and 17 grandchildren, [and] 11 great-grandchildren.
First of all, February is nearing its end now
How did they prepare to go to their spring camps back then?
When they were going to go to spring camps, they would start preparing in April.
They also prepared their food supplies for the spring ahead of time.
And they went to go set their tents.
And… I’ll slip into English, you see.
And, you know, they would bring their boats and canoes.
They would bring what they would need to their spring camps.
And then after the middle of April, we would move.
We would arrive to our settlements.
It was very nice and wonderful.
Have you heard about how they gauged whether it would flood?
The people back then would look at the snow when there was a lot.
And the ice when there was a lot.
When it was a little frozen between the snow
There were repeated warm periods.
They said that when there was lot of snow, and a lot of snow upriver from us, there is a lot of water.
They would say that there was a lot of water.
Did you see the snowiest time?
There was a lot of snow back when we were small; there used to be so much snow.
And those mission houses down there were the only ones most elevated.
[The snow] would reach their roofs [sloping] down.
We would go up there and slide.
And when the entrance porches were shoveled, it would be like an animal den to the doors.
Were they wary of floods when that happened?
Yes, they would be worried that it would flood.
But sometimes when it melted slowly, they said that the water went away.
It probably evaporated and drained.
There wouldn’t be a lot of water when it [melted] slowly.
Then how did women prepare to go to spring camp?
Women back then prepared by making waterproof skin boots, putting soles on waterproof boots
Also because they didn’t use shoe packs.
They made waterproof boots out of various things.
They made waterproof footwear for the men when they were going to move.
And even the women wore waterproof skin boots.
It was because the women back then used to sew to prepare what they would need.
They weren’t like us; they weren’t lazy.
Is the snow not like how it was back then?
It seems that now, [un]like back then
Well, when I first started school back then, there used to be a lot of snow.
Very big snow banks; it was quite wonderful.
We also dug tunnels, and made houses in big snow hills.
Now, you see, that doesn’t happen anymore.
It seems like there’s a lot of snow now, but it’s not like that.
The snow hasn’t reached the roofs either.
How far… and then after spring camp, would they go to their summer camps right away?
They would go back depending on how green the plants became in June.
They would go home when they became green in June.
And sometimes, they would be weatherbound by the late melting of the ice
Unable to travel by crossing rivers and oxbow lakes.
They only returned when it melted
And they would portage to the Kuskokwim.
And when the ice broke up on the Kuskokwim, it was noticable even in the Akula region.
It was audible when it happened.
At this time of year, what did they do, including Yup’ik dance festivals?
What did they call it? They said that they used to have the Sharing Festival [Avgarutaaryaraq].
After they held Yup’ik dance festivals, villages would invite others
Villages downriver and upriver from Bethel would compete.
They called that Avgarutaarluteng.
Even if it was just the people from here, yes.
They would compete against each other, inviting the village at the end and [giving] them things.
They would bring various things to the community house, traps and all kinds of things.
Is there anything else to add?
That’s all they did in my presence.
They would stop when they started moving.
It was fun watching them compete.
The last ones to finish would win.
What kinds of contests did they have? How [did they go]?
The last one to invite like that, and they would bring things to the community house.
And then their competitors over there would stop without reciprocating.
That [inviting] village would win.
Did they have prizes?
No. No, they just… (They just had fun.)
They were fun.
Well, that’s enough. (Yes.)
Okay, like Martha just now, please say your name in English and Yup’ik.
Okay, they called me Kumangulria in Yup’ik, and Matthew in English.
Please talk about your children [and] grandchildren.
I have nine children of my own
And only six grandchildren, and no great-grandchildren.
Where did you grow up? (Wait, wait.)
Ready?
Where did you grow up? [Please] talk about how you grew up.
I grew up on the Yukon [in Acacaryun]
But I went to school in Holy Cross back when I was small.
After I stayed for 11 years, qula ataucimek allrakunek, after going home I went again to Mt. Edgecumbe.
After I was there for ten years going to school
And after getting a job there, I came here to Bethel.
I moved and worked inland at the hospital.
I worked for 17 years.
When I got tired of working at the hospital and moved to the BIA [school]
When they told me I couldn’t work anymore after working for six years
The doctors had me quit working because I got an ailment in my midsection.
What did you see when you grew up on the Yukon?
Like, what did they do when [the season] became like this?
In the spring on the Yukon these days, various fish including these blackfish become scarce.
That’s why what you call Kanruyauciq [February] here is called Unguurvik [Time of Driving Game] up on the Yukon.
In this month back then, they only subsisted by driving hares.
Did you observe a lot of snow on the Yukon or somewhere else?
Yes, there used to be a lot of snow back in the 1930s when I was a boy.
Sometimes when there was a lot of southern winds and snowing, they would say the the marsh cirmiggluni.
They said it froze.
Even though there’s a lot of snow now, the tundra here is not frozen.
Sometimes, though there’s a lot of snow like this, it doesn’t flood even with a lot of water.
But the ice [?melts in the region] late.
They say that it repeatedly freezes and depletes its [flood] water.
Only when it’s frozen and can’t do that, there is flooding.
Also, when these rivers have a lot of snow, the ice isn’t thick.
Because it’s not as thick as it usually is even with a lot of water, I don’t think it’ll flood because of that.
Did the people back when it used to be extremely cold
You know that it’s not like now.
Did you hear about people freezing to death?
We didn’t hear about anyone freezing to death because we had warm fur clothes.
And even though it’s cold now, it doesn’t reach the cold it used to.
Because we don’t have appropriate clothes anymore now
When it’s a little chilly we like to say it’s cold.
Did you used to hear about how they gauged whether it would flood or not?
Well, I just told you about the marsh here…
What did they look at to find out?
Did they watch the area upriver or downriver?
Even though there’s a lot of snow like this now, it only gets foreseeable in the spring.
When it gets cold at night after being warm like this, they call that repeated freezing.
Until when would it be cold?
Sometimes when summer was late
When summer came late up on the Yukon, the ice melted on the 10th of February.
When that happened, summer started to set past the middle of May.
I think it was about 1936.
Now, Easter is also late. And now…
Summer will set later than it usually does.
These days, they also use Easter to gauge the seasons.
When it’s later [than Easter], they would say summer will set late.
When it’s before Easter, they also say summer will set early.
So we don’t observe groundhogs?
We don’t know about those.
From what you saw growing up, what would they do this time of year? How would they do them?
They didn’t do too much back then.
I grew up mostly in the wilderness; we didn’t live in settlements.
We only tried to gather these various things.
And at that time, there was no fish in the Yukon.
My late father also told me back then
When he was a boy also, there was [a time of] no fish too.
When the Yukon has no fish, it apparently has no fish for four years.
The fish wouldn’t suddenly disappear; the fish declined every year.
When that happened at the time, because my earliest memories are when there was no fish
We stayed mostly in the wilderness, not in settlements
Including my blood siblings.
Our peers Yup’ik dance, but we siblings never Yup’ik danced.
Neither did our mother and father Yup’ik dance.
But they didn’t explain why we didn’t do that.
How did youpl prepare to go to spring camps?
Right after Easter back then, we would prepare by moving our boats, even setting up tents.
And fish traps, they [made] fish traps in the spring.
What about the women?
And back then, women would make grass packs to store the meat they dried
Because they dried blackfish, even pike, and dried these birds.
Those dried meats in the summer
Because fish might be our only food, they dried birds also because we didn’t have freezers here.
How did they use like freezers?
You know, my older brother made one out of the land by digging the side of a cliff.
In the winter, however, he would fill them with ice
Lining them with grass that he sawed there.
When the things that needed to be stored in the spring were stored there, they wouldn’t spoil too much.
But, that’s how they lived without freezers like we have here now.
Have you ever seen an extreme flood that was very high?
That happened once.
Also, when I moved here, it was [over]full here once.
The bridges, qeraryarat, down and over there
It almost made the bridges on Kepenkuq float.
When it was going to flood like that here, we escaped to the Yukon because [Acacaryun] there is on the mountains.
When we went north, it turned out that all of the marsh here had water
Because the [ice] apparently choked downriver from Mountain Village.
Hills were the only land [above the water].
It seemed like the ocean around us.
When it started getting [over]full up north, we came toward here again when the tide was going out.
It was also extremely [over]full here.
Before they elevated these bridges and roads, it almost [flooded] over them when it was [over]full then.
I saw the Kuskokwim get that full.
Also, I think it was in 1937 when the Yukson was [over]full too
And because we wouldn’t travel with planes through there, the marsh there was completely covered with water.
And when we went hunting for muskrats, because my older brother and I always went together then
When the water level was increasing, we went to our family whom we found because the land was completely covered with water.
But our ancestors would apparently have spring camps in places the land wouldn’t be covered [with water] even when it was [over]full.
Because they had known that since time immemorial
As they hunted in the aftermath of [the land] being covered
They established settlements like that because they might be in dire situations if the water reached them.
Is that all? (Yes, thank you.)
What’s your age, date of birth?
I’ve turned 65. I’m going to be 66 this year.
I’m still a boy. (When? When?)
March 22nd.