I will ask you about that.
I wonder how I'll do it? I don't know. I don't know too much about it.
Your answers are good.
Oh, okay.
I understand you.
I see.
The story you just told
What you just said to us,
How we should treat others with love though they are bad. What would be the reward for our hearts?
The reward for our hearts will be good in the future.
It seems that our reward will be that we will live in peace. You know, a person...
They said that people long ago, there is also traditional wisdom that all people
Some of them probably do not live right.
That is how one shouldn't disparage their husband.
So that we will be able to live peacefully in the future.
I see.
You've said the important thing. Do you have anything else?
Personally, you know
Looking at how we were back then, and how we are now
Many times, I pity young people.
You know, they act in socially unacceptable ways, or they are leading bad lives.
They focus on misbehavior.
I pity those, you know?
Because I didn't grow up mischievous. I didn't grow up mischievous.
And being bad, even though I was bad sometimes,
I treat being a mother to my children with respect.
Because I only have my mind on wanting to live well.
These days, I pity young people
Those that do now know traditional wisdom because they are not spoken about.
But with your work with KYUK like this, if they show Yupiit speaking [about traditional teachings]
You will do good work.
And not doing this only in Yup’ik
In English, if you translate it into English so that the young people who only speak English will understand, you will do good work.
That’s the important thing I want to say.
Our Yup’ik ways, since we are being mixed today.
Married couples are not all Yup’ik. They have Caucasian spouses.
Their Caucasian spouses also need to understand how we Yupiit
How we would be good married couples. Caucasians can learn it too.
Show the traditional wisdom without delay.
Through KYUK or TV, since there are a lot of married couples now, young people, who are not gathered right.
Yes. I am curious about that, you know
Why are children more attached to mothers, not fathers?
Mothers stay in the house, and the fathers go out to travel, hunt, and work.
Our children are more attached to us mothers
Because we stay at home.
We prepare food, wash their clothes, take care of our families. We mothers are important in the home.
That’s why if children are obedient to their parents,
And if they’re especially obedient to their mothers, it will be good.
Those who are disobedeint to their mothers, their mothers get hurt.
Mother work hard on a lot of things in the home.
They take care of all of their children, and love them all.
However, a child who [disobeys] their parents
If he keeps disobeying them, their poor mother
Her heart will be hurt. That’s not good.
Their mother would not cry in front of her children, but cry without their knowledge, hurting in her heart.
If their children keeps disobeying their parents, they will make their mother suffer through that.
Being a mother is extremely important.
And being a mother
Many people, even among these Caucasians, these young people need to know it.
If they respect their mothers without destorying their mental health, they will live well.
Yet if they do not respect them, they will lead bad lives
Misbehaving, doing the things she admonishes against.
These children without mothers or fathers who, you know, want do not have teachers, who can they go to?
Who can they go to if they want to learn them?
Well, these orphans without mothers and fathers
Since I was an orphan, an elder, an elder lady, or
When an old woman or man taught me, I would be very thankful.
And so, these orphans
If they want to grow up well, they should go to their Yup’ik elders
They can ask them something. We can tell them how they would do well.
Thank you.
You’re welcome.
If I have any other questions
If I listen, you know, some of them now
You know, some of them had a commotion, or
You did well. You didn’t make sudden movements.
Yes, since I didn’t want to do that, I wanted to see your questions.
Yes, that’s good.
I didn’t want to waste time.
It would be good if Caucasians also listened to our conversation.
Because there are a lot of Caucasians, married couples who are half [Yup’ik] and half [Caucasian].
Rusty, don’t move around.
You might disturb her.
Sorry, I didn’t mean to be so, you know.
But since I told him to be quiet when he was talking, I told him to be quiet.
It’s okay. He’s my foster kid.
Really? He’s so adorably well-behaved.
I have two. The other is in school.
How is he your foster kid?
Through the state?
Yes.They had me do it last year.
And he’s good now?
No, she’s going to [interview] me again.
This is just cutaways.
I see.
I need her to talk at length.
For a long time?
How?
Speak about random things.
Tell me stories about your children.
How?
How many children and grandchildren do you have?
What your children used to do.
I have ten children.
I have seven grandchildren. They are few, seven.
And they’ve all become adults, but only one, the youngest, is in high school alone.
And all of them, some of them are on their own now.
They’re doing well, trying to take care of themselves.
What’s going on?
No, I gave him something.
Oh, if you want to push it more, it can go further back still.