Oh my, I was like that. I just told you the story.
Are we going? Is it better?
So now, how did these good shamans that didn’t needed to be scolded work?
They would use their shamanistic powers on people to heal them
And when they use their shamanistic powers on the sick to heal them without side effects.
They heal them so there was nothing left wrong with them.
And when they exercised their shamanistic powers in the community house on a person whom [others] had [attacked] with malice
Some shamans, when they were faced with something invisible that they could take, when they did this with their arms and pulled what was invisible
Yet they had nothing [physical] to pull.
As one of the shamans kept pulling, they’d get pulled up as they lay there.
They said that what had been making that sick person sick
The ones that they did that to couldn’t deny it happened as they were there.
Those that were pulled up like that would stay without being able to deny that it had happened.
And they couldn’t say that nothing had happened.
There you have it.
Many of those people would experience delirium before death like that.
When some shamans who did not need apprehending exercised their shamanistic powers on them
They’d forgive them, confess them to those malicious shamans.
That’s what they were like.
They would confess unto them
Without their knowledge, or with some unknown force, they’d experience their own malicious intent.
Their malicious intent would fall upon them.
That’s what they were like.
I haven’t covered the entirety [about] I don’t know
But I used to hear about some of them like this.
Okay, so when you were growing up back then, especially up to this day
Traditional wisdom that you remember, please talk about one that is still clear in your mind
The traditional wisdom you used to hear back from your elders back when you were a girl.
You see, a long time ago
Our instructors back then would instruct us, and it seemed they were scolding.
We poor people would listen, unable to move as we sat, getting hot, and our hands would get wet.
We couldn’t move anymore when they instructed us.
This is what my mother used to say to me:
"Now, when you hear someone instructing you, watch you instructor’s mouth until [s]he stops.
"And though he seems to be directing at you, don’t look away from them, and watch their mouth until they’re done."
I’d also follow what my instructor said and do that.
"Though [s]he seems to scold you, watch their mouth. Only when [s]he’s done, look away."
I would do that.
Truly, a person who was there should not forget the traditional wisdom passed down to them.
We'd listen without being able to move.
Only when they they were done, that instructor, would we stand and leave them.
Only when [s]he finished with us, we’d stand away from them, only when [s]he finished with us.
We’d listen as they seemed to scold us. They’d seem to offend us, scold us.
Oh my, I wish their traditional instructions would come. When I come upon them, I recognize them.
I’d recognize everything.
I’d so recognize what some instructors would speak of.
What are some of those pieces of traditional wisdom?
They’d also tell us repeatedly
They’d also repeatedly tell that piece of traditional wisdom
Repeatedly, not letting them hear it once, but having them hear it repeatedly.
Oh my, the first people back then would speak of true things.
That’s why when some of these people, when these Yupiit speak on the Bible
And when I hear that the first doesnt need to be anymore
Or when I hear people say the first shouldn’t be done, I think like this
I think of the fact that Jesus said this:
"I didn’t come to destroy the Law, but to complete it.
"I didn’t come to destroy a single part of it, but to complete it." That’s what he said.
I always remember this, that Jesus said.
So now, as I’m now this age
When I come across that traditional wisdom, and when I recognize people
I would recognize what those instructrs would say.
And when that person that they said would end up a certain way, when the time time, I'd remember what they said about what they'd be like.
They were like that.
Then as they're speaking and instructing them, when one person, and when one of my fellow girls went out, they'd [?decry] her.
"Oh my goodness that one. Why did they go out?
"They probably went out since they didn’t want to listen in order to live with whatever whims they have.
"When they come across what they liked, they’ll examine it for themselves."
They’d talk about them like that.
When they see what they liked, they’ll see themself.
They’d say this about them.
Those first traditional instructions are absolutely not bad.
That’s why the people who practiced them long ago lived long lives.
And when they moved them, their old bones would pop. They said they went out of [socket].
Or, they also carried them on caribou antlers.
They’d pop. Then when they put them where they were going to be, their old bones would be like shooting guns.
They said they went back into place.
You see?
From being so [?tightly clung] to life, [?tightly clung] to being alive.
And they said some grew a new set of teeth.
They’d call them "those with small new teeth." They said they looked like mink teeth.
They said those were "those with small new teeth."
Well, I wish I could get small new teeth since I have no more.
Were those after they lost their teeth...
After they lost their teeth, they’d be replaced by those.
Oh poor me, I’ve become like when I was young
I’d have my tooth removed when it gets loose.
Or, several of these, three, are starting to get loose.
Then here on the top has no tooth, one without a tooth has a false tooth here, then this part has no more teeh, and two teeth here.
And the bottom here, there’s one tooth down in the middle, and several teeth out from there.
The other side, however, on the bottom hasn’t lost any.
Those people who lived long, you just said their bones would pop.
(Would they complain of aches?) They wouldn’t complain.
Though they seemed in pain, they wouldn’t complain.
They wouldn’t go "ouch" though they seemed in pain.
Their bones would pop like guns firing.
And when they put them down, they’d make loud noises.
They said their joints would go back in from where they came out.
Oh my, and our dear grandmother, poor thing, when we were going to move and they moved her from her mat with caribou antlers, she would do that.
And when they carried her and put her where she was going to be with a warm bed
Her old bones would pop in what they said they were going back in place.
Our grandmother would also tell us stories of what she was like.
She said she had taken one of the men as a husband, and he was called a shaman.
She said she didn’t pay attention to her husband.
She said she wouldn’t sleep by him, and would go out when he came in at night.
One day, her husband left her.
She said though he wanted her as a wife, he was preparing to leave her.
After he left.
Do you hear about Cakcaarmiut out there on this side of Qaluyaat?
Cakcaarmiut, at this end of the mountains.
You see, she found a lover there.
She found a lover when another man came upon her.
She said he was a very handsome man with no equal in Alaska.
And since she liked him, she was with that person in his prime.
Poor thing, she said that one day, one day she was bringing food gifts to people.
She said that since she had many food gifts, she held the bottom bowl, and these were on each other up to here.
She said she tried not to let them fall as she gave food gifts.
Then she came up, after giving them out to the owners of the bowls, after sitting and waiting, went out.
She went out. She said that after doing that, she went out, oh my, it seemed the world was so bright.
The moon was shining and it was very bright.
Oh my, she said that when she turned from the door of the community house, she realized
She said her old partner would tell her that he was going to get her.
He said he was about to get there.
She said that the area downriver down there doesn’t freeze though it’s so cold it crunches.
Oh my, his kayak, a nice kayak down there was docked.
When she saw him, he waved his oar to signal for her to come.
She said he was all that was in her mind when she ran.
She said it seemed her feet touched the ground in slow motion as she ran.
Then as she was going to reach him, there was the sound of someone screaming behind.
My goodness, she said when she came to her senses, she realized that she had fallen on her back.
When she fell on her back, she was on her back.
She said she realized as she remembered the kayak and looked over there
She said that she fell on her back [?right before] the iceless area. The kayak was gone.
Since it was gone, she stood up, after shaking herself to her senses, she look up and saw a person outside their house.
That was when she went up.
Oh my, she said as she was going up that she remembered the bowls she was holding.
"Oh my, I wonder where I put those many bowls I was holding?"
Oh my, she said that she didn’t go to that person, but since she say the kayak outside the community house, she thought she’d put them there.
She went them, then that person said to her, "What’s wrong? Where’re you going? Come here."
"Wait, I’m going to check on those bowls."
Oh my, she said that she reached the place where she saw the kayak and there was no bowls outside the community house.
Oh me, she said she looked around them to see some black things far inland out there.
She said that she went to them to find the bowls she was holding, and they had not a scrap in them.
Oh my, she said she gathered, and only stopped when they were all there.
She said she’d apparently threw them far away.
Oh my, she said she went to that person and they brought her in.
When she brought them in, when the people of that house brought them in, they had that girl [?check]
Why someone ran toward the water without ice.
"Because someone on a kayak was waving his oar as a signal to come, she went down."
At the time, she said that she would go out to do things, including cut trees because there’s a lot of trees out there.
She said she went out to find cut [branches] already finished.
However, she said she hauled water.
Then since they told her to store things into an underground ice cache
She said she’d go out and it would be filled with what they asked for.
She said it turned out that it was the who’d come to her who’d fill them with what the people of the house asked for before she got them.
Oh my.
They mentioned that they were going to perform a shamanistic ritual on someone at the community house.
She said that when the one called An’arissuun performed the ritual, he talked about it.
"Poor thing, the girls’ bedding truly looks like a vole nest."
She said that the path from where that man would appear
She said that path was like that on her bedding, that girl’s bedding.
Oh my, she said that girl lay down.
Then as she stay laying with her eyes clothes, she had her [?], and he appeared through the door.
She said it was when they had "doors" of tunnels that you go down.
She said that man that used to take care of that girl came.
In the community house, the one who was going to perform the shamanistic ritual held a meeting at the community house with two [?] who were brothers.
She said that the one who was going to perform the ritual sent a decoy woman.
He sent one to the one that would appear to her.
And she said that he had a decoy man replace as the one who would appear [to her].
He had that decoy man stay around that girl.
He did it so that there was no way that man could reach her though he went to her if that decoy man, the doll, replaced him.
Like that, you see, our poor grandmother was getting after she had that shamanistic ritual performed on her.
She got better. There was nothing wrong with her anymore.