Now, Junior has three children.
Greet me with a handshake.
It’s been so long since I’ve seen you.
By your estimation, how many great-grandchildren would you have?
There are five now, five. Five [?].
When will some of them [have children]?
How old were you when you became a pastor, serve as a pastor?
When did we first move here again?
Nineteen-sixty-nine here.
I became a pastor.
As a lay pastor, your, you know, reverend...
Now, with your observation of Nanvarnarrlak
Tell us a story about what the people of Nanvarnarrlak was like looking at your guardian.
Without stopping? (Yes, without stopping.)
Do I start now? (Yes.)
Okay, thank you. So, I’ll do what I want.
Yes, you’ll do what you want.
In Nanvarnarrlak, but I can’t say what year when I was very young at that time
And since I wasn’t a student, I only learned by watching them
When we got that pastor, Neck, Uyaquq [in Yup’ik].
He was Lloyd Nick.
I first saw him preaching in Nanvarnarrlak in a house.
But afterwards, I’d watch him preach in the community house.
People would gather. Since they had no bell, they’d [personally] invite people.
Those who were able would gather people from villages.
And with Uyaquq’s orthography...
How I wish I could show you.
Uyaquq would read the Bible in his own orthography.
That was the first I heard of the Bible, and there was no one before him.
And those who raised and my grandmothers had no Bibles.
And I hadn’t heard anyone reading the Bible.
Before I saw him reading, his pupil arrived at night.
My grandmother told me to turn clockwise this way in what she called looking for a story [forecast].
I would have to go tell her about the weather that I saw.
And she told me to know where the wind was blowing from.
When I was in a hurry, I said
"When I went out, I looked out to the right like this.
"Then when I looked toward the river, and there was a small tent at night.
"It had two drapes."
Then since I was barefoot, I didn’t make a sound as I went down to see the small tent’s entrance.
When it came into my view, it was closed, the flaps crossing like this.
Then right when I saw it, I stood in front of it from a distance.
When I stood still, the person inside started like this, and it was the first time I heard the Bible:
"Respect for the Lord will be the beginning of knowledge.
"But those without sense do not care for knowledge and teaching.
"My child, obey your father’s instruction
"And do not leave your mother’s command
"Because they will be writing in your head that will bring you joy, and they will be a necklace around your neck."
As soon as I became a priest, I found it in Proverbs chapter 1, verses 7-9.
What I’d heard was there.
Then when he was done in there, I ran right home.
Since I was barefoot, I didn’t make a sound. You see, he probably didn’t hear me.
And when I went inland through the path past our house, I stopped when I reached a deeper area.
"Well now, let me try what I heard down there."
I faced the tundra, while the graves inland were visible, I faced it and tried it.
"Respect for the Lord will be the beginning of knowledge.
"But those without sense do not care for knowledge and teaching.
"My child, obey your father’s instruction
"And do not leave your mother’s command
"Because they will be writing in your head that will bring you joy, and they will be a necklace around your neck."
I apparently learned the Bible outside by that door, watching that door and listening to the person inside.
I can’t forget it as I’m alive here.
Also because I found it in Proverbs chapter 1, verses 7-9.
I also learned what I [later] found without paper.
Now, when I became a priest, they had me move a lot over many years.
Before that, they’d also sent me as a pastor.
But I would use that verse more than once because it was the first one I learned.
The first [?pektesta] I saw was Robert from Akiak.
I forgot his Yup’ik name. I did know it.
He arrived, saying that my father invited him to eat when he was at Uyaquq’s house.
Puciinaaq, Puciinaaq said because [s]he speaks up that [s]he will go with him.
Then my father said to him, "You’ll be embarrassing when he eats. I’m going to have him eat frozen aged whitefish."
Then Aalaaq shook his head. He said he’ll follow. He said he wants to see our house.
It was a sod house from the land sicne we had the first houses, with no wooden houses.
Then he came in and sat down.
Then when he ate further in from him, he was speaking because Puciinaaq spoke Yup’ik.
He could manage to speak, speak in Yup’ik.
Then when he was done drinking something ate after Robert ate
When he was done, he took and opened his book bag and said, "I’m going to teach you."
Without mentioning the chapter, he held and opened the book used for Easter. He was looking at, but I wasn’t looking at it.
Then he said that he’s now going to teach me something that I shouldn’t forget.
And he told me to stand. So I stood and faced him.
But, I’d never forgotten what I’d seen as a little boy.
Then across there, he said that he’s now going to begin teaching me.
He didn’t mention the chapter and verse.
Then he started like this:
"Jesus proclaimed, "One who believes in me does not believe in me, but to the one who sent me.
"’And one who sees me sees the father.
"’I came to this land as a light so that one who believes in me will not be in darkness.
"’And one who hears my word and does not believe then, [s]he will be tried.
"’The word will try that person in the last day.
"’That’s why when I speak, I speak like that as my father told me to.’"
And that was end of his lesson.
I learned all of it.
I became able to preach without a paper.
And I first learned a song written in Uyaquq’s orthography.
These were the words, and without them teaching me, I learned it by listening:
"We are thankful for you, they are thankful [in Heaven] up there
"Because you can manage anything, and because you are compassionate."
Apparently, I’d learned the writing then.
I started reading this book used for Easter.
I also learned Uyaquq’s orthography, and could even read them.
It turned out that when I would become a priest, I could do my work without papers.
Uyaquq wrote an intention saying this:
"God said, ’Do not falter. Open your ears and listen.
"’Everything comes from above.
"’Even a tiny insect on the land is created from above.
"’Oh Christian, be slow to speak, and be slow to anger.
"’First, test what you are going to say three times.
"’If a person will not take offense from them, speak them."
I [learned] these without paper.
I wasn’t a student, but the Lord had me learn this much without papers.
He let me learn that song, these [songs] that the Moravians translated, and even let me learn them.
Also, when I was getting checked at the hospital, I read the Catholic Bible, their Revelations.
Those were written in the new orthography that they spoke of.
It turned out that when I saw them, because they were written by the next generation of translators, I would also read them.
I learned [how to read] them when I read Revelations.
I learned the ones written by the Catholics. And since it’s updated now, I wasn’t shocked, but could read them.
Because I learned them then.
It turned out that the Lord had me [learn] these things I needed to for my work.
Now, when we had the first books before the changed the first ones
Without any books, I would go baptize and lead communions using those first ones.
Though I can recite them now, I started reading from the later ones.
I’m thankful for all I did.
Also, I would know nothing, being able to cry having become a reindeer herder.
They said I was now a reindeer herder and had me put on a brand here.
When the lower authority put the brand on me, he said this:
"Everywhere you go, take this brand with you. It’s a fish."
What’s a miluqutaq?
A rope for reindeer herding.
When they take reindeer, they would brand it with a mark to indicate who it belongs to.
So that you will recognize it, let me say one thing.
The moravians had a mark by removed the tips of reindeer ears so that they would recognize it if it acts strangley from afar.
They also gave me a mark for me to learn.
They didn’t let me forget it.
Then a knife, he gave me a belt and hung it here.
That belt was made of hide and had straps to tie it with.
Then the one who put it on my measured my waist.
He told me my waist length.
He said that if a blizzard sets or the weather turns bad on me, that I must travel wearing the belt.
And if there’s a blizzard, the blowing snow wouldn’t go in my [clothes] here. I would have to do that.
Then when he let go of that belt, he said this when he put the knife here:
"Take it everywhere you go.
"If you leave it somewhere and go, if you forget it and go
"It will, you know, you will have misfortune, and have nothing to gather grass for matting."
Then I would always bring those three things that I owned.
That’s why had I not herded reindeer, I would be lost when taking care of God’s sheep.
Back then, I apparently learned how I could take care of God’s sheep.
The lower authority admonished; let me say this last thing
He said I shouldn’t hurt the reindeer. He said it has a spirit.
Or, I should not shoot it, or I should not somehow hurt it.
He said it has a spirit. He said it’s spirit is watching me, will watch me.
It turned out that when we took care of God’s sheep, I remembered that.
I eve respected them, and feared speaking to them wrong
Because God’s sheep have spirits.
I think it’s gotten long, so this is all I want to say.
Yes, okay.
Many times, if you listen to me, it will be beneficial to you since I did it when I was very young.
I experienced these without forgetting them, but knowing them.
Thank you very much. (Yes, thank you.)
Back when you heard Uyaquq reading Proverbs, how old did you seem back then?
When I stood to the reindeer, I cried.